We will begin, so we are entering a last lecture
of our introduction part. And I do not
know whether, you can read the names on the
slides. These are the people we have met
so far. Starting with Nicolaus Copernicus
are even before that Ramon Lull. And host
are
people including Galileo and Hobbes and Descartes,
Pascal. Pascal who said that
perception is in our minds. And if is smell,
the smell of a rose, then that is a reaction
to
though partials that are in . upon our nose.
And we are set of
pursuing based on that essentially.
So, we saw that there was a stand of listening.
Now, this is you can say the pre-history of
AI. And you can see, from this diagram that
it is about more than 500 years of history.
And their two stands to this. And one is said
the physical side of trying to make, talking
heads, walking statues. And statues, which
can you know not their heads and that kind
of
stuff. The engineering all the physical all
the contraction site of it. Because, they
was the
.believes an it can move autonomously. It
must be able to think also essentially.
So, there leap of faith, that one is to make.
The others stand was the emergence of the
motion of the mind. At some point you know,
teachers like us for simply live in a world
and see the world. And believe that what we
see is what the world is like. But, then along
cames somebody like Copernicus. And he said
that, you thing at the sun is going around
the earth during the day, but that is not
what is happening. What is happening is at
the
earth is rotating. And it creates and elution
of the sun going around the earth.
So, the fact it what you see is not necessarily
what is out there had already started
coming out. And gradually then that the distinction
between what we see and what we
think started happening. And that some point
they cart said there two world out there.
One is the world of a mind. And other is the
world of the body. And he had this idea of
mind what is dualism. Then as we moved along
we saw cant for example.
Immanuel Kant one of the most influential
philosophers a from Europe, who said that
we
perceive the world. In terms of a priory knowledge
that we have in our heads. And we
mold the world at we see into those a priory
knowledge structures that we have. Of
course, he did not use the term knowledge
structure, which we used now a days concepts
at we have essentially. And at the same time
the mechanical contraptions of becoming
more and more sophisticated. They was just
duct in trance or a vacancies.
So, some of you saw, BBC every Sunday if you
see BBC you get something for this
course. So, this last Sunday, BBC showed a
news item, in which in the south of France.
They have open the museum of all these talking,
walking mechanical creatures
essentially, which apparently very popular.
And you should keep them in shop window
to attracts shoppers, then thinks like that.
And I could see there, this vacancies duct
also
amongst the displease. So, they were getting
sophisticated.
And we see that from, so these two stands
the merging together. You know this moving
creatures and thinking futures in some sense.
So, Pascal for example, we will so those
can recognize him here for the fact that he
was the first person to invent a calculating
machine. Of course, it could only do addition.
But, nevertheless it was a calculating
.machine, which was set of improve later by
lightness into something, which could do
more than addition, it could do multiplication
and so on.
And it became more and more sophisticated,
tell we came to Chales Babbage, who
invented a machine which could store of a
program. And run the instructions in that
program, which is the notion of computers,
that we are still working with essentially.
We
also met Alan Turing, who sort of try to put
down this debate on, what is intelligence
scan machine things. And that can he propose
a Turing test that we saw earlier. He did
many other things and we will just have a
brief mention on of him later essentially.
So, let me remind you of this definition by
hogiland. AI is the quest for building,
machines with minds of your own. And we are
ask this question, towards the end of the
last lectures. So, what are minds, we will
come to that question later today, but a little
bit
later. Before that with less complete the
histories. So, we have seen the pre-digital
computer hire so far, the mechanical contraptions
are people use the bill. How they AI
progress after the digital computer came into
b, which is just along the time an Alan
during was around.
.
So, let us first begin with this piece of
information is tells us, how did he get this
name
.artificial intelligence essentially. And
the name was devise by John McCarthy. I think
you all know John McCarthy for some form of
another. Among other things invent
language lisp, which became very popular in
AI for many years. So, the name is credited
John McCarthy and Marvin Minsky, along with
Claude Shannon. Who organized this
conference called the Dartmouth confidence
in Dartmouth college in 1956; where
McCarthy is credited with the having devices
name artificially intelligence.
Now, many people have said that, it is name
is not a nice name. You should used
something like heuristic programming or machine
intelligence or something else. But,
some of the name as stuck since that time.
And we all know this area artificial
intelligence. So, hogiland for example, suggest
that you could call it synthetic
intelligence. So, artificially and he makes
with comparison with pearls for example.
Now, you have real pearls we have artificial
pearls, which have kind of fake essentially.
But, you also have synthetic pearls, which
have not fake, but which are pearls in sort
of
made by humans. So, the conference was organized
and it is charter was that if you two
months, ten mans study of artificial intelligence.
So, name was point there. On the basis
of the conjecture that every aspect of learning
was or any other future of intelligence can
in principle be so precisely described. That
a machine can we made to simulated. So, the
focus all the emphasis is that when we are
talking about intelligent behavior.
.It is something, which we can describe up
to the Manutius detail. And if you can do
that,
we can make a machine do with essentially.
That was the idea behind that. So, who are
the people, who organized this feels see them
in the moment. So, for those of you hand
residing history. So, we should look at this
two books, which I have mention earlier. And
this one book all machines for think, that
is shown here by . which
describes the full chapter on the Dartmouth
conference. And the other book is John
hogiland, which is AI the very idea which
is the most philosophical side of things.
Essentially will come back to that bit later.
.
So, who are the organizes of this conference,
we have already said that they were John
McCarthy, he was then and assistant professor
at Dartmouth. And he has done many,
many, so these people who have contributed
so much to AI in one way or the other that
is not easy to list there. What all they are
very active people. McCarthy inventor lisp
he
invented something called situational calculus,
which we will may or may not see in this
course.
He is also credited with having invented the
alpha beta algorithm, which we will see a
bit
later in this course. And he did lot of work
on logic commonsense listening essentially,
which will see if you can come to that later.
Marvin Minsky the only person of these
.whose still alive was a junior fellow at
Howard he and McCarthy towards set of the
MIT
lab AI lab in MIT. And as you will see in
the history parts today most of these work
in A
I was concentrated in a few places in the
US and few places in Europe.
And it is not as a everybody everywhere was
working on AI. So, MIT lab was on CMU
was another place, stand for another place.
And you know a couple of places in Europe
essentially. So, Minskye is very well known
for his idea on frames, which is a way of
structuring knowledge into interconnected
components. And it is basically, the for 1
hour
for three college object one day programming
nowadays essentially. He also wrote a
very Influential book also society of mind.
And more recently book all the emotion machine
essentially. The somebody have once
pointed out dealing over machine, lectures
that machines cannot display emotions. So,
maybe it should look at that book. Another
person there was what is turn, who was the
inventor of release at the designer of this
IBM 701, which was the best machine around
the that time, in work the first assembly
of for that machine.
He supervised arsis into writing of program
for playing the game of checkers, which you
will talk about little bit, which was one
of the early successive of AI essentially.
Now, I
turns out that this Samuels program was a
learning program. And Samuels goals for
actually learning, he wanted to see how computers
could learn. And his program was the
program, which became better and better as
it late more and more essentially.
And this kind of a generated, a kind of a
fear amongst a people that is machines will
become smarter than us. More powerful than
us and thinks like that, will come back to
that point little bit later. When we talk
over is checkers program. And finally, Claude
Shannon everybody knows Claude Shannon, because
of is in information to the end
there. He was the person who had hired Minsky
and the McCarthy as in terns when they
were graduate students. And it is they are
that they got this idea of floating together
this
conference, which would talk about this new
feel which was coming of call artificial
intelligence.
..
But, they was couple of guys, who were in
some senses are shows dealers that
confidence essentially. So, let us first see,
who there were the names we have might have
mention before, Herbert Simon and Allen Newell
and . corded says
are they that about them the two vaguely known
persons working at Carnegie Tech. At
that time . university it later on became
CMU.
At that point it was Carnegie Tech and grand,
who are also in mighty to the Dartmouth
conference . as an afterthought. And it is
these to people, who really
creative then big impact at the conference.
Because, they had along with J. C. Shaw, who
also was that rand, build this return this
program call the logic list. It was a logical
listening machine, a theorem proving machine.
It put prove theorems in mathematics. LT
as short it was.
So, this say about this, it was a first program
deliberately engineer to mimic the problem
solving the skills of a human being essentially.
So, Simon and Newell for greatly
inference by the way human being solve problem.
Because, after all we are sort of
existential examples of smart creatures. You
know, we set of are thinking creatures if
you do not want to call us machines, who operate
very effectively in the world. You
know, solving problems and getting along and
so on.
.And he wrote a book, they wrote a book call
human problem solving, which became very
influential later essentially. Now, this program
logic theories, went on to proves several
theorems on from .. See, . had embargoed
upon this land exercise of formalizing all
knowledge. And this had you know everything
that you can do mathematics will put it down
piece of paper. There great dream or
shattered and 1931 by Kurt Godel, when he
came and proved that you cannot become
powerful.
You cannot construct powerful enough systems
listening system, which are consistence
at the same time. So, either you can be very
powerful in the sense very expressive, that
you can talk about all kinds of things. All
you can be consistence, but not both at the
same time any should that this is something,
which will always followed if you try to
will power systems. And as some of might know,
his arguments are basically scented
around, self-reference and self-negating sentences.
So, sentences like I am lying or the story
about this barber, which resilient resolve
so
worried about that if there is the village,
in which the rule is that everywhere, who
does
not shave himself shaved other barber. Then
the question is who shaves the barber
essentially. Because, the barber if you shaves
himself then he shaving himself and
therefore, he cannot shave himself. Also this
kind of conundrums comes to selfreferentially
a sentences and curd ..
That any formals system, which is expressive
enough, will and a become in consistent,
which means in our the kind of things of day.
And that however, do logics are never
going to be consistent. And complete at the
same time will come to this versions as some
letter point of time. But, the simpler logic
or first order logic are predicate logic is
good
enough for us. And first order logic can be
seen into capture everything appear doing
in
programming essentially.
So, our programs can whatever, we can express
in programs we can do consistently in
some sense. Now, this program LT produce some
shorter and more elegant proves that
were present in this principia mathematical.
This is a book barbers Russell and
Whitehead’s. And apparently, so this story
goes I do not know well it is true or not.
But,
.apparently the journal of symbolic logic
or journal of logic or something, refuse except
people.
Because, it is the authored by computer program,
co authored by computer program. I do
not know whether, stories true a not, but
you can find it in some places essentially.
.
So, let us first talk a little bit about Simon
and Newell. A Simon was a multi faceted
person as you can see, from this court from
Wikipedia. He was a political scientist
economist, sociologist, psychologist and a
professor mostly at CMU who’s research
range across all these fields cognitive psychology,
cognitive science, computer science
public administration economics and so on
and so forth. He went on get a Nobel Prize
in
economics.
And his long time associate was Allen Newell
about 10 years is junior. And they did a
lot of collaborative work together essential.
So, Allen Newell created this language for
IPL, in which LT was implemented.
..
Some little bit more on them, because they
give us something which we base our work
on. So, they became reading figures at CMU.
And they wrote this program for general
problems, which is based on even problem solving.
And how human beings use
heuristics solve problem. And we will visit
this general problem solve a idea, this idea
of
means on analysis, which is the heuristic
that views. We will see that sometime needs
in
the courts essentially.
Their work also brought to focus a information
processing approach to A I, which means
at you are talking about, that if you all
the create intelligence system. It is enough
to do
information processing. As approach to this
others stand of effort, which was to say that
will bill system form bottom of will put together
components, which make intelligence
systems and so on and eventually they will
come intelligence. He said not we do not
have to do that.
You can work are they information level was
A I some people call as a knowledge level;
and bell in the legend systems essentially.
And one of things which came out of CMU,
one of the many things which came out CMU
was this cognitive architecture call so or
which you can even or download and use to
bill a good application. So, one all the things
a talked about was this architecture for AI
what you neat for AI.
..
So, you have this idea of the physical symbol
systems. And a symbol is something for as
we I concern, a perceptible something which
stand for something else. So, a symbol
stand for something else. If you write the
numeral seven, it stand for the number seven.
Of course, it is not the number 7, it just
stands for the number 7. We could have in
different script, we could have written it
differently. A symbol system is a collection
of
symbols.
So, for example, a data structure or English
language would or he one musical tune
essentially. So, you put them together you
have a symbol system. So, you have alphabet,
which is made of symbols and then you put
together things of alphabet and he have a
symbol system. And physical symbol is something
which obeys laws which have like the
laws of physics. So, in some sense, if you
can men ably if then using well define laws,
how rules then they are physical in that sense
they are physical.
In the sense they can be manipulating apparently
this law. So, anything you can use
algorithms or so the procedure for long division
for example and so on and so forth.
..
The important statement that they maid is
known as the physical symbol system
hypothesis. It says there the physical symbol
system as a necessary and sufficient means
to generate intelligent action. So, what they
are saying, that earlier need in our
terminology, earlier need to bill intelligent
systems is the ability to create did the
structures. And right algorithm which will
operator from the data structures. You deal
nothing else essentially. That is the basic
infrastructure you need.
So, unlike for example, roger pen was who
feels set the human mind, a human brain has
some kind of physics, which is going on which
we cannot replicate reset nothing of the
slot. If you can do information processing
which means, if you can operate on symbol
systems using well define algorithms you can
create intelligent behavior. So, this is
known as the ability symbolic AI of classical
AI. Classical AI follows this principle that,
it is a top down design approach to build
in intelligence system.
So, that you will create your data structure
and you would like algorithm and you will
producer intelligence systems. Ours Haugeland
calls it good faction AI essentially. So,
as
a first symbolic classical AI, we have a sometimes
he call a sub symbolic systems or
signal level systems. Systems like human brain,
which operate settle level where
information is not and coded into symbol.
So, if you look at a neural network for
.example. It is made of many nods and many
edges collecting nodes.
And edges have values, which are numbers essentially
all weights as we call them. And
everything, that the Newell is encoded in
terms of those weight essentially. For the
weight itself does not stands for anything.
It was a mean anything to us. In that sense,
it
is not a symbol. A symbol should stand for
a something, where as if a writer a let us
say,
program in which variable call x, which stands
for let us say the distance from plays a to
plays b.
Then it is some it is a symbol. Because, it
is stamp for something. So, symbolic AI or
classical AI concern with explicit representation.
And I will go with them for working on
representations.
.
And that is what we a perusing here. So, we
have mention this Samuel’s Checkers
program he was also one of the participant
in this Dartmouth conference. And he is
contribution was this program to play checkers.
And he wrote it in this IBM 701
perusing. And as a bit earlier his goal was
so explode learning for computers. His idea
was at if computers could learn. Then they
would be known need to do all this pain
trekking programming.
.And when he says programming in the pain
trekking passion, he really means that.
Because, in those days be did not have this
whole set of high level language is that you
are so comfortable, which nowadays a you had
somely language. And maybe you, I am
not sure whether even four time was devise
at the time. List was devise a little bit
later
then the dark mouth conference. So, programming
was very pain sticking in those days.
And Samuel said that, if you can make the
machines learn then below have you program
them essentially. And you know that so fascinating.
So, the active idea, that you will
some system and little learn and become efficient.
And of course, we have a thriving
machine learning community .. So, his checkers
program Samuel
was not great checkers clear. He was a computer
scientist. But, story goes that he wrote
this program the program became better and
better and better.
And eventually beep it is own creators as
be sick. You know this around the time. when
Babbage was constructing is machine. And we
have mention the his collaborator either
contuse of loveless, who was the daughter
of Lord Byron. And Lord Byron have this
. peter shell end. And peter shell is a may
be wife was may be shell
he, who wrote this novel call Frankenstein.
And this novel I do not know . it is about
a artificial creature, you
know people were fractionated the artificial
creatures. So, this novel about this artificial
future creature call vector Frankenstein who
was made by doctor. And eventually,
became like a monster, who would you known
destroy is the doctors essentially. So, that
whole idea, that this machine would becomes
smart and you know whole power us and
kill us have always been around for a long
time. So, you have seen the movie matrix.
So, that is one of the films and will come
to matrix again later for different reason,
so
quite an interesting film. But, one of the
I thinks in matrix is that this machines have
Clint to control human spices essentially.
So, you do not always realize it when you
was
things it film.
..
So, in 1940 sometime, I Isaac as Asimov who
was the science fiction writers. He
introduce the so called laws of robotics,
which we can many popular. It took the fancy
of
all the people around. He wrote it as part
of a slot story called run around, which he
wrote in 1942. So, they are the three laws
that Isaac of Asimov said. So, lose in the
sense
that, not like Newton’s laws, which we discover
that the physical world is the obeying.
But, mould like a laws at human beings make
you know, well legislation by the
parliament and so on essentially. So, for
example, our parliament is necking a law that.
They cannot come under RTI essentially, so
this kind of laws essentially. So, his law
was
basically this three laws that the lowert
will not injure a human being. That is the
first
law. You know protecting the human spices.
Do a robot must always we built in such a
fashion that never harm human being essentially.
Secondly, if will obey human beings at all
times. Unless it voyages rule 1, so if I build
the robot an I tell it to harm another person
then the robot should not obey too. And
thirdly, it must protect this old existence,
as long it does not by late the first two
laws.
So, it is you know all this is they in the
popular imagination, because people are worried
about machines over taking human beings. Already
for 4 500 years we looking at talking
moving heads, which they think are thinking.
.So, chess as we know, for many reasons has
been fractionation for computer scientist
for
ever since a computers go invented.
.
So, let us look at the quick history of chess
first. And then we look at a History of the
rest of the computing world. Before, we come
back to the question of what a minds and
so on. So, you see all these name safe. And
all this materials been taking by taking from
Wikipedia. So, you just at ago to Wikipedia
at computer chess in you will see this time
line or part of this time line. So, clot channel
first wrote a paper called programming a
computer for playing chess.
To will in developed up on paper and algorithm
for doing it. McCarthy invented the
alpha beta I will go with them that we will
study. But, other people also set a have
invented a including a Samuel essentially.
Bernstein Alex once and who work then IBM
was the person to who wrote the first actual
program, which could play chess. Complete
program a, who could which could play a complete
game of chess.
Then program for Mack hack 6 by beam let was
first program should defeat a person in
tournament plays essentially. And we are already
mention David levy, who made this bet
in 1968 that no machine can him in 10 years.
And it 2008 the wrote this book call love
.and sex with robot essentiality. I when he
is swan from one end of capability of machine
intelligent to the other end. That they could
be like human companions to us.
In 1970 the American computer chess championship
started. In 1974 a program call case
of from somewhere in the USS of won the first
. chess
championships and the small micro computers
subject playing chess in 1977.
.
So, that was a initial years then in the latest
70 is the started making progress. So,
program call chess 4.6 well in the major chest
tournament. 1978 David levy one his that
defending a program call 4.7. In 1980 of Fred
kin price was institute it 100, 000 dollar
in
1980 was quiet the bit of women if a beating
of reigning world champion, program call
create it is. Now, creave was the you know
super computer, which of deal by same
..
And they was the fastest for seems for a very
long period of time the best and the fastest
machine for create a machines. And create
blitz all the program running on those
machine. So, it when is the championship with
the score of 5-0, which means it one all
the games. If the performance rating for those
of your family with chess rating 2258,
which is the quite good. And it was a first
program to be the human master. Along that
.time people certain it investing in special
purpose hardware to play chess essentially.
So, for example, a high tech mutual also developed
on this time in 1988
had 64 processors. One processer dedicated
for each where of the chess board.
And that, kind of think. So, Ken Thomson had
a hardware chess. So, people where
investing more and more hardware. And the
same time, so then a program call deep
thought. Share the first place with Tony Miles
a head of the former was champion, not
the reigning world champion Mikhail Tal. So,
deep thought is a name, which does it ring
the bell for anyone.
. .
He . to the galaxy. So, when as been taken
from there, it lost two
games to galicasple of 1989.
.
And after that, the years of tram for the
machine. In 1992 a micro computers program
one a computer chess championship playing
against mean free in some super computers.
A program call chess Genius actually, defeated
cast . game. In 1996
are program call deep loop, which was also
developed at IBM lost to cast Kasparov of
at
.a 1997 it beet Kasparov when a 16 match.
And it is creators a inventors or actually
awarded the Fred kin Price at . mention sometime
ago.
Then after was it was a series of losses for
the human players Kramnik do an 8 games of
program call deep flits. Then program call
hydra beet Adams 5.5 is to 0.5 which means
Adams could only do one game. Then Kramnik
lost two deep fritz later. And nowadays,
it is routine for the human players including
Vishwanathan Anandh from India to
contently take help from machines, while preparing
their own chest playing strategies.
So, here we have a mention in 2010 Topalov
prepares by sparring against super
computer Blue Gene essentially.
.
So, let us move on to general AI and look
at what is happened since the dark mouth
conference. Before we come back to the main
question again essentially. So, just quickly
done through some of these things. We already
mention the general problems solved by a
Simon and Newell. Then known book on syntactic
structure, which was very influential
in natural languages .. McCarthy introduces
list ((Refer Time:
32:47)) wrote a program for . theorems in
geometry.
This was a part of PhD .. So, you will see
a list of people whose
.PhD works appears in land marks in A I. So,
which is a kind of a motivation for some of
the PhD students setting here essentially.
So, Minsky and McCarthy set of A I lab in
. build us percept on. The percept was the
single layout Newell
network, which had this learning capacity.
So, that Newell networks was program, which
have basically pursuing this idea of learning.
You are training as he call it.
You show system of sequence of pattern a little
learn to recognize that pattern. Samuels
programs beat the best players. People also
started talking about machine translation
along that time. But, one of the early . set
that machine translation is
not something that we can do so easily, which
is actually quite rule. In this early 60’s
the
first industrial lower started coming indica
wrote his influential book on knowledge and
belief, which talks about how can you formal
the reason about what people you know.
So, I know that, you know that something you
know this kind of kripke. ((Refer Time:
34:08)) introduced a formal model for this
kind of reasoning call kripke structures.
There
was progress in a cad so other land million
wrote the program semantic nets. You knows
parcel on MIT was tested with this very well
known sentence time flies like an arrow
essentially. So, I would earlier to look at
this sentence and try to parse it. Now, the
thing
about our summons is that we always . to one
parts of this sentence.
Because, we are like and said pre dispose
to certain ideas award this world essentially.
So, well we here a sentence like time files
like an arrow. We do not even thing that it
could have any other meaning then that time
is going fast very quickly essentially. But,
for a machines, which is not biased by h p
dispose ideas there could be other meaning
as
well. So, this is the an ambiguous sentence.
If you look at it from the fundamental point
of view, it could have other meanings and
worlds could have a other meanings.
So, one of the problems in natural language
processing is that our language is so rich.
That we can say, the same thing in many different
ways. But, also conversely something
we say can have many different meaning essentially
you know. With you of course, were
useful for politicians, because a say something
and then they say that this, what a meant
out of corteges store something like that
essentially. So, this sentence time flies
like an
arrow. I would early to look at other meanings.
.So, a look up the web and a try to see, what
other past structures. So, when he say passed
we mean you know subject, object and you know
known face work frees and this kind of
essentially. So, it is time adjective is it
a verb. You can look at some of those option
essentially. A very influential book all computers
and thought by .
around that time. They were programs to do
in a we saw program for geometry.
Then we saw program for algebra by . a program
to answer
questions for people. You can put all this
things together and build the system, which
can
you know.
(.)
Teeth somebody let us algebra or geometry
or something like that. In 65 Allen Robinson
introduce is varies this facets call the resolution
method for theorem proving which
revolutionize is whole idea of theorem proving.
By theorem proving we mean the kind of
seen that LT was doing logic theories was
doing. That given a set of axioms. So, given
a
set of flimsies what are the things that you
can proved from their essentially.
And there was other developments Herbert Simon
predicted in 1965 that by 1985
machines will do any work that man can do
essentially. You optimistic people, we have
seen then Allen Turing also said that by 2000
the during test would be past essentially.
.None of that has really happen. So, at the
same time Herbert refers argues against,
. we have seen Eliza earlier in 1967 refers
to a beaten by a chess
program at chess.
Also there was this program call Dendron which
was one of the early successive of A I
we could do chemical analysis for us. So,
we will not going to the details now, but
later
on in the course we will see what Dendron
died. But, it was it officiate as the level
often
expert came is. Then mosses it is work on
symbolic reasoning in A I, which is also
common essentially. That everybody uses some
symbolic integration passages you know
mat lab, maxima and all these kind of packages.
Shaky the first robot appear then SRI’s
stand for research instituted. Minsky and
paper
wrote this book on perceptions. We mention
perceptions they have single they have
neutron. What minsky and paper should in 1969
was that perception was limited to
recognizing only certain kinds of patterns
essentially. And a kind of patterns at a person
from problem could recognized was pattern
at for linearly separable, which means that
if
you what the plot them in some space.
Let us a two dimensional of three dimensional
space, a let us a two dimensional space.
Then you goes draw straight line, which would
say a one side of the line is class a and
the other side of the line is class b. So,
such patterns have call linearly separable
patterns.
And what minsky and papered show would was
a that is all perception could do. And it
is said, that this skilled the research in
Newell quite a wild. It was not a till the
mid 80’s.
The people started getting interested in Newell
network again.
That is when they realize at multi laid Newell
networks. Have do not have this limitation.
That they are not limit it to finding only
linier separates. So, about that is what happen
in
69 essentially. So, shrank talked about is
contextual dependency theory. McCarthy talked
about the frame problem essentially. The frame
problem says, the refiar representing
about of wall. And if you a reasoning about
change in the world. How do you figure out
what is not change essentially.
So, if something was true, if may I watch
laying on the table here. And I look that
side
.for a few minutes. And then a look at this
again is a watch still there of course, I
can see
it is still there. But, in the reason system
after sometime after 2 hours will the watch
still
be there. Of course, they have a different
example log out a loaded gun, if you will
not
get into right now. So, let me say, what was
other staff so Nilsson and fikes demonstrated
this planning system call strips. We will
see, a strips later in this course.
And wino grad wrote the program call ., which
could do lateral
language conversation in a well limited domain,
the domain of blocks world. So, it could
converse with a person taking instructions
and do things. So, he should look of on the
net. And you probably get a sample conversation.
So, you can say things like pickup the
green block and put it down talk of the red
one. And it could do that. Understand what
you saying and do that.
In the sense, it would generate a plan for
doing that essentially quite interesting.
Along
that time this language for log was device
by is French pan .. And
some more work on planning for example, apps
strips essentially.
.
So, here the picture of shakey. This was the
first autonomous robot that was built, which
could take it is own decisions. So, it could
one the a one coli does of SRI, which as stand
.for research institute. And do some limited
things like a open dose and plug itself or
getting charge then things like that essentially.
And so standard was another hotspot of a
activity people like Nilsson and many others
there. And some of the name set we
associate with a shakeys lisp came by McCarthy.
But, as go with them like is a star and strips
and visibility graph and collision detection
they were all discussed at time put.
.
So, let us move on, so and early 70’s. Schank
and Abelson introduce idea of a script.
This is if you on to understand remember this
cant says that we perceive the world in
terms of predefined a priory that is he call
them. What are those a priories. Schank and
Abelson say, that these are like script. So,
it is like a movie script. That, you always
follow a script when you have acting. So,
if you so that the standard example that the
used was rest a gone essentially.
If you go to a rest around you a essentially
following a script. That this is how typically
things are so if you here so the about somebody
going to rest around. Then you can
understand the story, if you have the script
in your head essentially. So, that is the
idea of
scripts. We already . Dendron another success
was mission. It was
.the rule based what people called as expert
systems. And the 80’s was the time and
people wanted to bill lots of expert systems.
By expert systems they meant a system, which
will capture the knowledge of an expert
typically, in a roof form we will see this
later in the course. And performer to expert
level essentially. So, minimal the program,
which this medical diagnose. Minsky wrote
about this names a advance version of Dendron
called . had some
learning capabilities. There were some more
planning systems. There is more work on
visual representation.
The power of metal level reasoning for example,
Randall Davis we see a another PhD
. program call A M, A M stood for applied
mathematician. Created
quite it staff, when it was first published
essentially. So, if you look at some those
papers, which talk about A M. It was the program,
which len it claimed was doing
mathematical discovery. That you give it basic
concepts and little learn you thinks. So,
concepts like prime numbers, the concept of
prime number.
Not in algorithm to find prime or something.
What is the notion that some there
something call prime numbers len at claimed
his program could learn. And essentiality,
his thing was at it forward the heuristic
that go towards the extremes of certain kind.
And
one extreme is that number of devices pattern
number can have. So, one extreme is two
essentially. You cannot have less than two
devices except you know one and itself
counting one and itself. So, the smallest
number is 2, so those numbers are interesting.
So, len it claimed that his program was doing
that, but has it often happens, if will
discover that the lot of things for set of
encoded into his learning program itself
essentially. So, that something that we have
to be very about essentially. Now, we write
a
program and we put in our knowledge some of
which in embedded into the program.
And then we say this system is discovered
that knowledge.
So, it talking about experts systems the system
called prospector, which was built at the
SRI for prospecting the natural world. Found
some unknown deposits of ((Refer Time:
45:39)) in Washington state. So, Mitchell
events the concept of version spaces and so
on
.and so forth, which scripts some of these
things.
.
And so you can them from the slides often
the Wikipedia page essentially. I want to
point out the some of this, newer things,
which were happening. So, one new thing we
was happening around this time was autonomous
vocals essentially. Can you have a car
which will drive it selves. So, arise earlier
1980’s people were building car it should
navigate themselves on the road so in unique.
The first car was done, then experts system
self started appearing in a market.
Another expert system call expand for configuring
vat system so was developed. The
triple A I conference that A I conference
started series started. In this design the
connection machine, which was maid suppose
to be machine of thousands of processes
connected together little bit like our own
brains are simple processing units connected
together. So, one interesting thing was this
program call Aaron develop by professor
Harold Cohen whose still around, which could
make drawing.
So, this drawing it is see there, painting
that we see there is been created by a program.
And when you say created, you mean visualized
and drawn. It is not somebody has told
the program draw man or something. The system
has drawn this whole thing itself. And
.if you look up Aaron on the web you will
see a whole gallery of his spin, it is paintings
so essentially. As she had try to get Allen
to draw the cover for my book. But, professor
co inside that know it not active any longer.
.
So, some of work and 1990 this program called
TD gammon, which played the game of
bargeman using this technique call wean forcemeat
learning, in the course learning right
now in the department. Beat the became the
world champion in wage man essentially.
So, what tells is, so way these to robot cars
in 94, 95, if you look at 94, 95 we have
descriptions of robot, robotic cars which
can navigate themselves. So, here this car,
which one men from munic to coo pen Hagen
and came back all by itself essentially.
You driving, breaking, accelerating, avoiding
vehicles and so on and so forth. And this
already seen that 97 deep blue beat kasparov.
The Robocop to an aments started is a
football tournament for robots. Robotic toys
like this furby that you see there. The tiger
electronics came into picture. So, these a
toys, which could furby apparently could learn
your language, you could teach it how to speak
this thing. Sony introduced this AIBO,
AIBO is that small dog like robot that you
can see in the picture on the bottom right.
So, there these to small dog like futures.
They are these Sony AIBO robots, which
.became very powerful of. In this picture
they are participating the Robocop football
tournament. So, you can see an orange colored
boll. They and you can see some different
proof humanity robots hanging around in the
side line.
.
So, you see this picture, it is robot call
kismet. Another PhD dissertation from MIT.
A
robot that expresses emotion. So, again if
you go the web and look for kismachivels see
videos of Sethia talking to this robot and
robots smiling and you know, making all kind
of human express human like expressions in
the system. The language ((Refer Time:
49:55)) web ontology language was standardized.
A darpa introduce the grand challenge
in prize money.
Honda produce this robot call asimo is you
can see, the small nee length robot which
could work around at human piece. So, it is
not the easy problem to make up two legged
creature walk keep it is balance and walk
and thinks like that. And that became very
popular.
Recommendation
systems
started
coming
into
play
like
amazons
recommendations if you go to Amazon or flip
kart. And you look at the book, little all
immediately make some recommendation see you
the people bought this as well thinks
like that.
.Collaborative filtering for those of you
attendant none stoke yesterday. He talked
about
collaborate of filtering recommendation systems.
When they was another dark mouth
conference in 2006 with said what is A I going
to be the next 50 years essentially.
Checkers the game of checkers was slot. What
do you mean by slot? Just as by solved
mean that if both the place are playing perfectly
we can tell you what the outcome will
be essentially.
So, we can do that for things like, smaller
games like cross and notes. A ticktack to
as it
is called. But, for checkers it was done quite
recently using expensive computing
essentially. So, we know that checkers is
the drawn game. Or maybe it is a wind
provided do not know. Then much more recently
ideas program call Watson, which
participated in this game call jeopardy, which
look upon the wave deeds the world
champions at this game essentially.
So, jeopardy is the program, which in which
we need lot of general knowledge,
geographic knowledge and thinks like that.
So, this program add axis to all this
knowledge and it could . game better than
human beings essentially.
And we mentioned last week this could this
robot call kerobo, which is a David levy was
talking about human companions to human being
essentially. So, this robot was saying
him to space last week by the Japanese space
agency.
And it is man it has a human companion to
a human astronaut, which will follow in
November essentially. So, this a very brief
history of what has been happening in the
last
50 years, will stop here.
..
And the next that we will followed is come
back to this question about, what are minds.
So, that will be the last segment of our introduction
today’s essentially.
.