We are looking at problem decomposition with
goal trees, and we want to look at an
algorithm, which will solve it.
So, what should algorithm do?
Break it down
into simpler
problems
and we keep doing this, till the problems
are severely small or primitives, that
you have access to in some systems, especially.
So, we will use, of course, one thing is to
search the entire tree, but we do not want
to do that.
We will use the heuristic function,
which is estimated cost
solving node n.
We will use the heuristic function to guide
our
search.
..
Let us say that we have some problem, which
we are trying to solve.
We compute the
heuristic value, and let us say, it is 50,
essentially, just to start with.
When we start
solving the problem, our estimate is that
it is going to cost us 50 units of whatever.
Let us
assume for the sake of illustration here,
that every edge has a cost associated with
it,
which is 10, essentially.
Let us say that I get something like this;
out of this.
I get 2 edges
out of it.
One of them is, you might say, hyper edge
or an edge; and the other one is
simple edge.
So, this is a tree like this.
Let us say the cost associated with this is
15, and
this is 20, and let us say this is 40, essentially.
Now, in this example, I have mixed up the
kind of edges, emulating from a node and if
you think about this, it does not really cause
a problem to see it like this.
We can think of it as two choices from the
top level, and these choices already being
broken down into two parts, essentially.
You could have easily transformed this into
a
node, which says that 50 and then, some node
x, and this is 40 and this x has got 2 nodes
of cost 15 and 20.
These two are equal in nature, and if necessary,
we can always
transform such a problem into that.
Of course, you have to keep in mind, the cost
of the
edges.
So, we have to take care of that somehow.
But for the illustration purposes here,
we will assume the cost of every edge is 10.
So, if you have generated, if we have
expanded, we will use the same term expanded
a node.
Here, expanded the node of this
.thing and we have got these three nodes which
is the next node that one should pick.
So,
let me call them A, B and C.
This is the start node S. We will use similar
term only.
Between A, B and C, which is the next one
I should expand?
.A; why is it?
Yes.
So, the cost of solving the original problem,
if I take this option, would be the cost
or solving this plus the edge cost which is,
I can write this here; 50.
And the cost of
solving it from the other side is 15 plus
20, 35 plus 20, which is 55.
So, obviously, this is
better.
So, I must choose this side, essentially.
Then, let us say I get this, some values,
and this is
n node; this is an n node.
Then, I can compute the cost of solving; revise
the
cost of solving A or estimated cost of solving
A. So, instead of 40, this has become 30
plus 250 here, and this has become 40 plus
260, plus 20; 60.
So, 20 plus 20 plus 10
plus10; that 60, and likewise, this is 15
plus 15 plus 10 for each hour; 60.
So, I have to
revise this cost now.
This becomes 60, because this is 50, and this
is 60; 50 plus 10; 60.
So, at this moment, my algorithm was shifted
tension to the other side.
You can see, it
has a best first nature about it.
We are using a heuristic function to guide
search.
The
heuristic function is estimating cost of solving
a node.
It is just that, because this is an
end of graph or end of tree; we cannot make
a decision, based simply on value of a node;
we have to look at the cost of the full solution
of which, this node is a part, essentially.
Now, you can see this is consistent with what
you were doing earlier.
We said that, for example, when you are looking
at the travelling salesmen problem, and
the branch and bound algorithm, we are saying
the estimate is a estimate of full tour,
essentially, and not just one, that edges
we have found and so on, essentially.
So, now,
my attention must shift here, and maybe, I
will expand one of these two nodes.
Let us
say, I expand this.
Let us say for argument sake, this can be
solved like this, or it can be
solved by another node, which is of cost,
let us say 25.
This is 20, this is 25; this is an
odd node.
So, this cost is, I have to revise this cost
to 25 now, which means I have to
revise this cost to 65 and then again, my
attention must shift this side, essentially.
So,
basically, what we need to do is to formulize
this process, and sort of make this little
bit
clearer and put it down as n algorithm.
So, let us now write this algorithm.
This
algorithm is called AO star and it essentially,
finds an optimal solution for a problem like
.this.
When do we terminate this process?
.
Let us say, see, what has happened?
This has now, gone up to 65.
So, we will shift our
attention to this 60, and we will come down
here.
If I note, if I pick up, if I just name
them, let us say D, E, F, G and H; what is
the next node I should expand?
So, I have to
pick a leaf.
C is a leaf; H is a leaf; G, F, D, E; these
I have already expanded.
So, D, E, F,
G, H and C; which one should be the next node
I should expand?
Looking at the
heuristic values; just think about this, I
will come back to this question in a moment.
Let
us write this.
So, A star wolves with a graph, graph G, which
is initialized to S, which is
a single node S, essentially.
Then, it says compute h of s and initialize.
Now, at any stage of the algorithm, I will
have a graph which looks like that, essentially.
I will go into some sort of a loop while;
we have this lotion of the solved node and
node, which is not completely solved.
For
example, in the integration example, something
like, integral DW is the solved node, or
in the chemistry example, we saw that once
you know that complete structure of all the
atoms, we are talking about, it is a solved
node.
We will use a label called solved, while.
As long as, and eventually, we want to say
that we have solved the original problem,
which is a root S, essentially.
As and when, we find the solution; we want
to percolate
.this label of solved, up, essentially.
So, this is a problem decomposition process,
and there is going to be a secondary process
in which, some labels will travel upwards,
and one of the labels will be the solved label.
Once a solved label reaches a root node, we
can say, we have solved the root node.
So,
while, S is not solved, means it does not
have a label solved.
If you look at for example,
rich and night, the book which describes this
algorithm, that I am describing here; we use
that some value call futility, which says
that basically, we do not want solution which
is
more expensive than this value.
So, we are going to explore for a solution
or look for a
solution, whose value is less than this number
called futility.
That is just an additional
thing that we are using.
Do the following.
We have to pick a node to expand.
Of course,
in an initial stage, the graph is only one
node, but at something like this stage, the
graph
has evolved.
So, let me get back to this question.
I started by expanding this root node s; I
got these three nodes then, because this was
cheaper than these two combined.
I expanded this next; I got this option and
this option.
So, let us call them DE option and FG option.
The DE option costs 50; the FG option
costs 60; and add another 10 for this option.
So, this becomes 50 plus 10; 60, which was
worse than 55.
So, I came down to this option.
Now, here, I choose between B and C;
one 50.
This B expanded so that, I got this 20 and
25.
When I back up these values, I got
25 here, and that became 65.
So, I have to now shift my attention to this
one, again.
Because going down, that pass is estimated
to cost 65, along this, I can cost 60.
So, I
must come down here.
At this point, I must choose this option,
because this estimated
cost is 50 and this, here, the estimated cost
is 60.
So, I must choose one of these two
nodes for expansion next, essentially.
How do I do that?
In the graph, I maintained at every choice
point, a marker, which
marks the best choice at that point, essentially,
or at that stage of the graph.
So, for this
graph, at this stage, I would have a marker
here.
Here, I would have marker here.
Because, here this is a better choice, here,
this is a better choice and here, I would
have a
marker here.
So, this algorithm is going to be a two stage
process.
In the first stage, I will
identify the nodes to be expanded, and that
I will do by starting from the root every
time.
In every cycle, in this while loop, we will
start from the root, follow the markers, and
a
.marker will take us to a set of nodes.
We have to pick a set of nodes.
So, the forward face
is as follows.
Then, follow the markers to a set of nodes.
Let us call them N and then,
pick some n belonging to N.
So, we have picked a node.
In this example, I have to pick
either D or E. Does it matter which one I
pick next; whether, I should D or whether,
I
should pick E?
In this example, of course, both the costs
are 15 so, obviously, there is no
way of telling, which one I should pick.
But let us say, for some other example, this
cost was 90 and this cost was 20.
Let us say
that D had a cost of 20, and E had a cost
of 90.
Then, of course, they look different.
Will
it matter if I pick D or if I pick E?
You have to think of it from the perspective
of
reaching a solution, and the perspective of
saving on some amount, of course.
If in an
OR graph, you are searching something, like
A star, if you have to choose between two
nodes and you chose one and then, you are
committed to having a solution to that nodes;
I mean, that if that happened to be the cheapest,
essentially.
In a AO graph; AND OR
graph, if you are at an AND choice like this,
if you have to, if the solution is along this
selection, you will have to eventually solve
D, and you will have to solve E also.
So, you
will have to solve both of them, essentially.
From that point of view, it does not matter
whether, you pick D or whether, you pick E.
Because, you have to solve both if you have
to solve, if the solution lies, if the sub
tree lies somewhere here, that is one perspective,
but supposing, this are the values 20 and
90; is there some other reason for trying
to
solve one of them?
Now, you can think of this as if you are solving
C and F kind of a
formula, then you are exploring whether, a
sub formula.
Let us say f1 and f2; you have to try to solve
both.
If you have to solve for this formula,
which has f1 and f2; you have to solve f1
and you have to solve f2.
It is not necessarily C
and F; it is some formula and, of course,
f 1 and f 2 are themselves compound formulaes.
If by looking at the size of those formulaes,
does it make sense to choose something,
which looks harder or something, which looks
cheaper, essentially?
So, this is the same
problem here.
Here, D looks cheap.
E looks expensive.
Does the estimated cost; should it
influence my choice having said that, I have
to solve both anyways, essentially.
How will
it help?
No, No, No.
You are not listening to what I am saying.
If you solve D, you have
to also solve E; why because this is an AND
node here.
.Then, you do not have to solve E. Then, which
one is not likely to give a solution?
E; the
more expensive one, I think, or if you keep
in mind, the fact, that we have some bound
on the cost of the solution, that we are looking
for.
So, if you have to do two things any
way, and your success depends on doing both
the things.
If one of them is harder, then
you should see whether, you can do that harder
thing first, because then, you hope of
help solving easier thing later, essentially.
The idea being that if you solve for D and
then, if you solve for E, then the solution
cost shoots up then, we will anyway, have
to
shift attention to another side, essentially.
So, that extra work could be waste, whereas,
if
you try to solve the more expensive thing
first, then you will get to know early whether,
it is too expensive or not.
So, that is the only idea, but if you have
to solve for both you
have to solve for both.
We will just assume; pick some nodes n from
N; generate children C of n.
We have
something like the move gen function, which
is not like the old move gen function, but
something, which defines the problems into
different sub problems; gives you the set,
essentially.
If none, if I do not have; if this node n
does not have any children, my system
is not giving a child, which means, it means
my system is not telling me, that I can
decompose it in some way.
What should I do?
Let us have picked this node n.
Let us say
this is my node n that I have picked for illustration
purposes.
Now, I am saying; generate
the children of n, which means, it has further
solutions expanded, essentially.
What if
there are no children?
What if it cannot be expanded?
What if it is a dead end of some
sort?
What should my search do?
If I cannot expand this, I do not find any
solution.
What should my search do?
You have to speak up a bit.
I cannot hear.
What does back
tracking mean here?
Should I go and look at E then; no.
Then, I should somehow
abandon this whole solution of which, this
is a part, because if I cannot solve D, then
I
cannot compose the solution, which has D and
E as their parts.
So, I should abandon the
whole thing; how do I do that?
I simply say that cost of solving n is futility,
because my algorithm is looking for
something which is less than futility, which
means, this will never be considered
henceforth, essentially.
So, generate children C of n, if none; then
you do this.
Then, you
remove loops.
What do I mean by this; remove loops?
I am talking in the perspective of
AND OR graph.
In the OR graph, of course, we have the social
of loop, looping that.
.You could just go round the same path.
Here, what does looping mean?
Remember that
AND OR problem is, decomposing the problem
into simpler problems.
If you think of,
for example, symbolic integration that we
looked at; can we have looping?
How can we
have?
What do you mean by looping?
Can we have looping when we are decomposing
the problem?
You said; you nodded your head.
.Integration, it could happen like, when we
apply that formula, we will get the
same integral part again.
So, it is possible that you to do one transformation;
you take sin by 4, by cost by 4; sin
rise to 4, divide by cost rise to 4, and you
get tan rise to 4 and then, you apply another
transformation, which will, let us say, take
you back to the same thing.
So, it is possible.
Looping is possible, because transformations
are not one way; transformations can be
two way in many situations.
So, you want to avoid that extra transformation.
Therefore,
we move by mean by loops, essentially.
Then, otherwise add for each child c belonging
to this C; compute h of c.
This is a forward phase of the algorithm,
that in this situation, I
follow the markers.
I will come to a set of nodes; n.
So, in this example, n is these two
nodes; D and E. Then, I say, pick some node
n from this set.
I have picked D from there.
Then, I say, generate the children of this
c; this is my set c, and this is the values.
So, let
us say, I have two choices for solving D.
Let us, for argument sake, that each of them
is
10 and this is 5 and 5; let us say for argument
sake.
So, what I am saying is that for each child,
c belonging to this set of children c; this
set is
c.
For each child in this, compute the h values.
So, this completes the forward face,
essentially.
Now, in the backward face, I have to propagate
the new cost up, essentially,
and I have to readjust the pointers, the markers
as I go along.
So, that is the second face.
Forward face goes from the root to the leaves;
the backward face goes from this set c,
subset of the leaves, to the root.
So, what do I want to do?
I want to; I found this heuristic
values 10, 10 and 5, 5.
Now, I want to first change the heuristic
value of n, essentially.
So, this is 10 and 10, 20
plus another 20; this becomes 40, and this
is 5 and 5, 10 and plus 20; this becomes 30.
I
have to now, say that the revised value of
this node D is 30, and this is the best part
to
.follow, if you are solving this node D. So,
I have to put this marker here, and I have
to
revise it to 30.
So, this is the new value.
These two things I have to do, correct.
This was
my node n; I expanded this; I got these children;
I evaluated the heuristic values, and
now, I have to propagate this value up.
Till what?
Till what stage, this propagation goes?
It should go till, as long as this node changes?
If this node changes then, I must
propagate its value to its parents as well.
So, let me take another situation, or this
one.
Let us say, this is a node that I have.
Let us say, this is 10, 5 or let us say, this
is 30, 5, 5,
and this is 5, and this is 10.
Let us say this was my node n.
I just want to illustrate this idea.
If this was my node n,
and these are the two children; I will evaluate
this children, and what is the best way of
solving this n?
I will mark with the pointer and compute the
cost, as 5 plus 10; 15, and
this is 10 plus 10; 20.
So, that is not the best one; this is the
best one.
Because, this has
changed from 5 to 15; I will add its parent
here.
So, this will become 5 plus 5, sorry, 15
plus 5, 20 plus 20, which is 40.
This was originally, also 40, because this
30 plus 10; 40.
Let us say, this was 80, to start with; otherwise,
I would not have gone there at all.
So, if
this was 80; this was, this is on 90.
Now, after I revise this, I must revise its
parent,
because its parent is getting affected; it
has got from 20 to 40.
Because, I am revising
this, I must revise both the parents.
I must, because I know that the cost of this
has
changed; this cost must be propagated to this,
as well.
Whether, I came from this path or
whether, I came from this path; it does not
matter.
I must revise both the parents.
So, the
process of propagation is basically, to go
up to all the parents.
If you have got a feel of
that, just write it down.
Let M be the set of nodes, that has changed.
This is just a comment.
So, initialize M. The
node that I expanded, I put this into the
set M, essentially.
Essentially, M is going to be
the nodes, whose value has changed, essentially.
So, I could have done the next step
before this, but it does not matter.
Let me write it here.
It says that compute
the best cost of n.
Pick some; let us say this node p or something
like that, or just a way consistent, let me
use n; I do not know which is better.
Let me use
n, because I will just only put n into this
m, initially.
So, I just use the same name, but of
course, as m grows, it may have more elements.
How will it grow; because parents will
.get added to this set m, essentially.
But initially, of course, there is only m
inside n, and I
am just simply, saying, using the same name,
saying, and pick some node m from n.
Compute best cost for n.
How do I compute best cost for n?
For example, if this was n,
then I can see that from this side, the cost
is 40, and from this side, the cost is 30.
So, the
best cost for n is 30, essentially.
I should have checked that, you know, anyway,
you are
going to revise the cost, irrespective of
whether, it improves or not.
So, compute the best
cost for n.
I must do another thing here, before that.
For each child c, compute h of c; I
must have another step, which says that if
c is primitive, label c solved.
If the child, that I
have just generated, is the terminal node
of the primitive or trivial or whatever, you
want
to call it, are solved; then put a label solved
for this node c.
For example, if this was
solved, then I could just put a label, saying
solved.
If I knew this was solved, the others
may still have to be expanded and all.
So, for every child, you compute the h value,
and
if it is a solved node or primitive node;
you label it as solved.
Then, n is the node that we
just expanded, and we have added this to the
set m.
We are picking some node from m.
In this case, it is only n to start with.
Compute the
best cost for n, which has changed.
If a solution below is labeled, solved; label
n solved
where, I should not say, a solution; is the
best solution, say, if the best solution below
it
is labeled solved, you label it solved.
If I take this example again, the other side,
supposing, this was n; this is a better node.
If this is solved; I will use double circle
to
denote a solved node.
If this is solved, what do I need to do?
I need to update n from 5 to
15, that is the new cost; that is the best
cost for solving n.
Initially, I thought of it is going
to cost 5, but after I expanded it, I know
that either, I have a choice of 15 or choice
of 20.
The best cost is 15, but this is labeled solved.
So, I must label this also, solved.
That is
the step here.
If the best solution below is label solved,
then label that node; solved.
If I have to label
this node solved, then the better solution,
which is this side; both of them must be labeled
solved.
If both of them are labeled solved, then I
can push the solved label here.
In this
fashion, the solved label will percolate up,
and I want to keep doing this, till solved
does
not reach the root node, essentially.
This is the mechanism for the backward phase.
So,
this is the best solution below n is solved.
.Then, you put label as solved.
So, we have done two things; compute best,
and possibly
labeled it solved.
If any of these things happened, we will say
that node n has changed,
which means, it was 15 originally.
It has either changed to 30, in this case.
In this
example, it has changed from 5 to 15, and
also, it has got a label solved, essentially.
So,
either a change of heuristic value, or the
application of solved label means that the
node
has changed.
If a node has changed; I am using this as
a kind of technical term, which
you have to have a test for doing it.
If n has changed, then add all parents of
n to m.
So, all parents; that is what I was trying
to illustrate here, is that if this has changed,
then
this will change.
If this is changed, not only must you propagate
the change of cost, from
the direction you came; but also, to any other
parents that this may help because in the
future date, that parent might become, essentially...
So, I must put this, of course, in the
loop, while m is not equal to empty; I have
this full loop.
Pick some node form m.
Compute its revised value, which is the best
value from all the sub solutions, it has.
If the best solution below it, is labeled
solved; label that node solved.
If the node is
changed, add its parent to m.
What will happen?
Initially, I will add only this node n to
m, because it has changed; I will add to this
parent, and because this has changed; I will
add this parent.
In this way, the revised value will propagate
up.
In this example, if this
has changed, I will get a new label solved.
So, I will add this to m, but this cannot
be
labeled solved, because you know, that branch
still is unsolved.
So, I will not label this
solved, but I will change its value.
Because now, it was originally, 20 and this
has
become 15 plus 5; 20 plus 20; 40.
So, from 20, it has got to 40.
So, it is changed.
So, I
must add both its parents to solve; they will
change to m, sorry, they will change and I
will add root to m.
After I change m, I will add nothing to m
and eventually, all these ms will get revised.
All these loops will terminate, which means
the backward phase will terminate.
So, the
algorithm works in two phases; in the forward
phase, you move forward following the
markers.
I have missed out one step here, somewhere
here; I must have this thing marked
as best sub solution, or I should say, hyper
edge, because each of these are the two hyper
edges; just mark the best ones.
So, whenever you are looking at the node m,
node in this
m, you must recompute its value, which will
get from its children.
You must mark the
.best path, because next time, you are going
in the forward phase; you must know which
direction to go, and you must also percolate
this solved label back, if possible,
essentially.
It is possible, if all the sub solution; if
this entire hyper edge has nodes,
which has label solved, essentially.
Just to repeat, if this was to be labeled
solved, and
this was to be labeled solved, then this will
get labeled solved.
If this was to be labeled
solved, and this was to be labeled solved,
then this will get labeled solved.
The moment
it gets labeled solved, and if this is the
best one, if the arrow still pointing to this;
that
will get labeled solved and then, you will
stop.
In this example, this has got labeled
solved; this will get labeled solved, but
this will not get labeled solved, unless that
gets
labeled solved, and this is the better choice.
So, I must have a marker here, and a marker
here.
Once this gets slipped, if this has to get
labeled solved, and the marker was still here,
then I can label this solved and so on, essentially.
So, in the forward phase, you follow
the markers, end up with some unsolved set
of nodes, which we have called as this n.
You pick some node from n, may be, the most
expensive as we discussed, a little bit
earlier.
So, that is not really so important.
We pick some node from n, generate its
children.
If none, we call it futility.
We assign the cost futility of that.
Then, we remove
loops and for each child, we compute the h
values, that are this set of nodes here, or
it
could be this set of nodes here, depending
on what is n.
There, the forward phase ends.
Then, you add this node n, that you just expanded
to this set m; initialize m to this set n.
Then, one by one, you pick.
So, this is not correct; this sum is not correct.
I should pick
the lowest.
So, you can construct examples to show that
you have to make this right.
If m
is the collection of nodes, pick the one which
is lowest in terms of the graph.
Pick the
lowest node; compute its best cost below that.
If the best cost leads to label to solved
nodes, then label these nodes solved, and
if either, it is not labeled solved or if
its cost
has changed, you must add its parents to m.
This loop here, this whole loop here, works
under the condition as long as, m is not equal
to empty.
You pick some node and do this process, essentially.
This process is
essentially, backing up the values from the
leads, towards the root node, essentially.
Once this ends, the algorithm will go back
to the forward node; again, follow the mark
.path; again, expand some node.
Then it will go into the backward phase, backing
up the
values from there.
These forward and backward phases will keep
happening, till either,
one of the two things happens; that either,
the value solved is percolated to the root,
or
the value futility is percolated to the root.
So, in which case, either, it will give you
a
solution; solution would be a sub graph or
a sub tree, or it will say that we cannot
find
the solution of this cost.
So, there is only one more point left.
For this algorithm to be called AO star, for
it to
deserve the suffix of star, we need a condition
on the heuristic function.
Can you guess
what the condition is?
So, let me, Sorry?
.(( ))
What does it mean?
This is the optimal cost solution and algorithm
is designed to find
the optimal cost solution and what here; saying
here is that as long as the heuristic
function under estimate the optimal cost,
then it is going to be, give you an optimal
solution.
So, as an exercise, I will ask you to construct
a small problem like this, with
some leaf nodes, solved nodes and so on.
You can basically, manipulate the edge cost
to
make it of under estimating or over estimating,
and first work with a over estimating
function, and you will see, that it gives
you some solution, which may not necessarily
be
the optimal solution.
Then, try out with an under estimating function,
and all you could
go up and look up the past test papers, you
will see one such, one of such problems there,
where an AND OR graph is given, and you have
been asked to find it solution.
So, do try
it out at home.
In the next class, we will take a diversion
from here.
We will move to games primarily,
because I want to give the games assignment
in early October, so that, you can finish
it
by the end of October, essentially.
Then, we will come back to this idea of expert
systems, tool based systems.
I mentioned things like, R1 is called an expert
system or
prospective.
How are they implemented, and what is a rule
based system, and how does
it work?
So, we will come back to that after, we finish
with games.
So, we will stop here.
.