So, let us continue with a study of game playing,
and we saw in the last class the notion
of a strategy, and a strategies constructed
by making one choice for max, considering
all
choices for min, and then one choice for max,
and then all choices for min. So, you can
say that solving a game tree, means discovering
an optimal strategy we said, that the
value of a strategy, is minimum of value of
leaves. Assuming that, we are talking in this
minus 1 0 1 valuation, where 1 stands for
win for max, 0 stands for draw, and minus
stands for loss for max. And if once maxes
shows on the strategy, then the value of the
strategy is the lowest value, from the leaves
in the strategy, remember the strategy is
a
sub tree, and what are the value that the
leaves are to minimum of those is what the
value
of the game will be. And assuming that the
opponent is perfect and we assuming that the
opponent is perfect, my feel look at and and
over graph.
We viewed our solution and and over graph,
if you look at what on solution is, at all
level you have to choose one, we have to make
one choice, and at end level we have to
make all choices. So, if for example, if they
you had three choices here, then at all level
.you will choose one choice, to solution would
be like this, and if this was an hand node,
you would have to solve for all three, and
then if this was an all node, when you would
again make a one choice essentially.
So, we can see a similarity between and over
trees and game trees, in and in and over
trees, if you added and node, you had to solve
all the three, all the sub problems
emanating from there. If you had an all choice,
you could choose any one of them
essentially. So, a max node is like an all
choice, because max can choose anyone
essentially. But max has to en counter for
all of min choices, so a min node is like
an and
node essentially, the differences that the
value of the solution, is in this case a some
of
the values of cost of these three nodes, solving
this nodes.
In this case, it is the minimum of the cost
of these nodes essentially, where it is a
min
nodes sitting here, if this was minus 1, this
was 0, this was minus 1, and this was 1, then
min with select minus 1, so it is a minimum
of these value essentially. You can see that,
so also consistent with our logical notion
of, and always choose is the minimum. So,
a
and b, if a (s) falls and the whole thing
becomes falls essentially, so and also in
some
sense chooses the minimum value or chooses
the maximum value essentially.
So, there is clearly an analogy, between and
over trees and game trees; of course, game
trees have a very well defined layer structure,
which we can always impose on some and
over problems, but we have an algorithm for
solving and over trees, which is the A O
star algorithm. So, my question is can we
use the A O star algorithm to solve the game
tree, what do you want, we want a strategy
of optimal value, in this case a roundly three
possible values 1 0 minus 1, so if there is
a winning strategy we want it. Otherwise we
want the strategy it will draw the game, otherwise
we are force to accept a loosing
strategy.
So, can we use the A O star algorithm here,
there is also there is analogy, in the and
over
graph the solve nodes are nodes which have
a label attached to them, and leaves also
have a label attached to them. In some sense,
the similar back up procedure is taking
place in A O star, if you remember algorithm
essentially, in the forward phase. We
expand the search a little bit, and the backward
phase we backup the values, which is
.very similar to the backup values that we
using here. Except the of course, here we
I
choosing min and max, there we I just summing
up the values essentially. So, the answer
to this is actually yes, we can use the A
O star algorithm, provide it we have access
to the
complete game tree.
.
And why is that not always a feasible thing,
let us look at the game of chess, which is
been the game, which has fascinated most programmers
or computer scientist essentially.
Now, if you count the size of a tree, as the
number of leaves, which means, each leaf is
a
different game that you can play. Every pass
that you can take in the game tree is a
game, and the leaf is outcome of the game
essentially. So, the number of leaves is in
some sense a measure of, the size of the game
tree essentially.
So, let us try an estimate, how could the
tic tac to ((Refer Time.) not is a simple
computationally a simple game, because at
one level you have 9 choices, assuming that
you could you cannot, distinguish between
symmetric situations let see, you have 9
choices, you have then 8 choices, at the next
level 7 choices and so on. It is a very, not
a
very large game tree essentially, which is
not surprising, because we have figure out
by
now, that it is the value of the tree is a
draw essentially, what about the chess game
tree?
.As I said, at a max first level, there are
20 choices, those of you know chess will agree
with me, eight pawns eight pawn moves with
one step, another eight pawn moves with
two steps, and four knight moves for the two
knight essentially. So, 20 at the first level
and as you start playing the game, the game
board opens up, and more moves are
possible. So, for example, bishops can start
moving, cooks can start moving, the queen
can start moving, and the number of the balancing
factor in some sense increases, as you
go towards a middle game essentially.
So, chess players tend to categorize the game
into opening, middle and the end game. So,
towards a middle game, it is a most complex
part of the game. So, people say that on the
average b is equal to 35, that on the average,
a chess game has 35 moves, that a player
has a choose from essentially. And on the
average, a typical game is 50 moves long,
so
average game of course, some games get over
earlier some games can long last and so
on. But just to get an idea of the size of
this game tree, so we can say that, you can
one
big estimate is set the number of games possible
is 35 raise to 50.
So, if the punching factor was concert 25,
then you can 35, then you can see, the top
level 35 moves and another 35 moves for each
of these moves and so on. So, since it is
50 moves long 35 raise to 50, which is equal
to what 10 raise to 120, which means of
course, just to remind the point, if I started
writing this, and I label the zeros, this
is the
first 0, this is the second 0, this is the
third 0, and I will have to keep writing to
the end of
the board, till I write the one twentieth
0 essentially.
We have already discussed this kind of numbers
before, that this is not the number, you
can refill with, there is no hope ever of
solving the game tree completely, chess tree
completely. And in fact, we do not we have
an been able to solve it, still now even
though people, putting massive computing power
towards solving game trees, and they
are using very sophisticated techniques like,
analyzing the end games, and creating of
look up tables for them and then using those
to, so all the games trees and that kind of
stuff.
Checkers incidentally I do not know, if you
remember when you went through this
progress in computer science, at some time
in this century 2005 or something, I do not
.remember exactly, the game of checkers was
solved. So, it was known, what the
outcome of the game is, and this was done
through use of massive amount of computing
power, and checkers as the much smaller game,
because the choices available for each
piece are very limited essentially.
So, if you know the game, you can only move
in one or two directions, one step or
sometimes you can jump over other than so
on, is a much smaller game in terms of the
size of the game tree. And that we have just
minus to ((Refer Time.) chess is
practically impossible, if you remember the
kind of numbers you are talking about, 10
raise to 75 is the number of fundamental particles
in the universe. And then, if the each
of them was a super computer, so we can do
that argument again, and you can see that
you can, any fact not solves the game at all.
So, we do not know, where a why it will always
been in chess or not, which is by the
game is still interesting, as oppose to cross
and nodes, which we do not want to play
because we know that it is always a drawn
game essentially. So, if we do not have access
to the leaf then how can we use this algorithm,
we cannot use the algorithm. So, we have
to do some other approximation, and which
is what we will look at, essentially is that
kind of variations of ((Refer Time.)
While I am talking about games, the most complex
game, in terms of size of the game
tree, is the game called go, I do not how
many of you are heard about it, it is a game
which is extremely popular in Japan, and size
of the... and a feeling of the complexity
of
the game, can be got by the fact that it is
plays on a ninteen by ninteen board, and you
can plays, it is a game in which you plays
coins, on one on top of the, not one. So,
their
specified locations at cells you can place
coins, and you can imagine that in the first
move, we can place it an any those ninteen
by ninteen locations and then so on, so it
is a
huge game in that terms.
Go is something that we have not been able
to program well, by view in the whole
computing community, has not been able to
produce good go playing programs. And the
people who talk about go; they say that no
you have to use other techniques like pattern
recognition. By pattern recognition, I mean
you know, trying to make out which both
.positions are good, and which both positions
are not good essentially. Some people use
the word zen with go and so on. So, games
can be quite come, so go is much more
complex then chess in terms of, the size of
the game tree which and be can really not
too
much with that essentially.
.
One game that, is of interest to us, is a
game call othello, also called as reversi,
and we
have been using that for the last few years,
for the game competition and will do so this
year also. So, maybe you should go and look
up the game, the idea of the game is that,
it
is played on a chess board, like board, except
that it is a single color board, and we start
of by playing, two kinds of coins. So, which
let me say, I am representing by knots and
crosses like that game, but it practices like,
red coin and white coin, and things like that.
So, let say cross stands for red coin, and
this stands for white coin, this is the initial
position of the game, in the center of the
board and a move, you a move is made by
capturing opponent pieces, which means that,
if I have a piece coin here, I can place the
coin here. And in the process, I will capture
this piece essentially, which means this
piece becomes actually mike piece. So, I have
made one move, and this is a game, then it
is opponents turn, so opponent can also do
something similar. So, opponent can for
example, put a coin here, and then this is
captured back, in some sense, then I can place
a
.coin here, and capture this back again and
again, and the game sort of goes on.
So, if I, if the opponent were to put a coin
here, then I then you would simultaneously
capture this and this essentially. So, both
will get captured, because by placing a coin
here, you are enclosing one end you have this,
and this end you have this, and this end
you have this. So, both in both directions
you can... so in all... So, you can captured
in
four directions, and if you can make multiple
captures in one move, but you can, you
allow to place only one coin on the board.
And essentially, the game ends, when either
one side cannot make a move or every or all
the coins have been place on the board. So,
it is not uncommon for the board to be
almost completely fill them, and you win the
game, if you have more coins in the board
at the end of it, but we have will be also
give you a score has to how many points we
have, one by essentially. So, if it is a massive
win. So, let say eight by eight board, you
have sixty point coins, and opponent is four
coins, then you have a big win essentially.
Whereas, if you have 30 and opponent has 34,
then he has a smaller win. So, that is the
game that we will use for the competition,
you will have to write a program, which will
compete against other peoples programs. So,
how do we play a game, whose search
whose tree we cannot access essentially? So,
we do what. What humans do is that we do
a partial look ahead.
..
So, in most game playing programs, you do
a limited look ahead, which means, that if
my tree looks like this, this is max, then
instead of search, so I have drawn with this
as a
practically, and infinite tree growing exponentially,
we cannot explore this threes. So,
what do we do we, cut off at some level, this
some people called as a horizon, we cannot
see beyond that, and this is called a number
of plies. So, this is k ply, if the
So, instead of searching the entire game tree,
I mean if you have the complete
game tree, then you could have just pack up
the values, and you would have found the
minimax value, and the best move for max in
the process.
But we do not; we cannot search the game tree,
because we have seen that they can be
really huge. So, we decide that we will low
or limited look ahead, and try to decide what
is the move. Now, incidentally, that is how
human beings also tend to play, at least the
beginners, that is how they tend to play,
they do a limited look ahead, may be two moves
ahead or three moves ahead, but they do not
do a complete look ahead, in the sense they
do not look at all possibilities.
So, most chess players for example, would
not even consider all the twenty moves that
you can make at the starting point, they would
have a fancy for two or three different
possible moves. So, either this pawn opening,
or that pawn opening, or something like
.that, and they would only explore that. So,
we do a limited search, in the sense that
we
do not look at the complete branching factor,
we only look at the few possible moves,
and a few possible replies by the opponent,
and a few possible moves that I can make
the, and in some sense of a search is incomplete
essentially.
Of course, expert chess players tend to do
more exhaustive search, they also tend to
be
able to judge positions. So, let us, let me
introduce that idea at this movement, then
if
you are doing a limited look ahead, what is
the use, because the nodes that you are going
to look at this level. They are not completed
games they are sort of half way plate games,
but you have made a few moves, opponent as
made a few moves, and based on this look
ahead, you want to decide, what you want to
play essentially. So, what do we do, we
have to write algorithms, to go values to
this nodes essentially, so what do we do,
we
apply evaluation function.
So, again those of you might have played chess,
sometimes or watch other people play
chess, then you can hear comments like, this
is the good position for white or something
like that or white is winning. So, white is
not yet one, but you look at it in say it
looks
like white is winning, instead of making such
qualitative statements, we want to give
quantitative values. So, we want to define
a function which is an evaluation function,
which will give us a value for the board position.
Now, what do we do instead of this, 1 0
minus 1 those three values, which are available
to us, when the game ends, instead of
that we break it up into a larger range.
So, typically it is, let say minus 1000 to
plus 1000, so the evaluation function returns
as a
value in this range, which the understanding
that plus 1000 is equal to the original one,
minus thousand is equal to the original minus,
one and all values in 0 is equal to the
original 0, which means both sides are roughly
equal, but the actual number tells you,
how good it is for max or how bad it is for
max. So, if it is plus seventy, it is a little
good
for max, if it is plus 700, it is much better
for a max, and if it is minus 600, it is quite
bad
for max. So, we try to look at a board position,
and give it a value, give it a number.
Now; obviously, this means, different kind
of reasoning, and in some science it involves
the use of knowledge, about the game essentially.
So, you should be able to look at a
.game, board position and give a number essentially.
So, if we can now apply the
evaluation function to each of these nodes,
on the horizon, which is wherever search
ends; then we can apply the same minimax back
up rule, to evaluate the value of this
game.
So, the backup rule let we said, that at min
level, choose the lowest value from it is
successive, and at max level, choose the highest
value from it successive. So, we can
back up these values, and determine what is
the value for that, and in the process also
decide what is the best move to make essentially.
Now, clearly the performance of this
algorithm will depend upon how good your evaluation
function is, essentially, because if
your evaluation function is good, then it
will tell you which of the board positions
are
better.
.
Now, ideally we would like to have a perfect
evaluation function, which in a game like
GO people have try to do, is that you look
at all the choices, and apply the evaluation
function here. So, we will call this function
e, and let say e of J, were J is a node. So,
we
apply e of J here, ideally we say just look
at the all the options and see which one leads
to a better move essentially.
.And then make them, but in practice, evaluation
functions are never perfect, they are like
heuristic functions, you know you are making
some judgment, and arriving at some
number that may not be accurate. So, in practice,
it has been observed that a combination
of evaluation and look ahead does reasonably
well for games. So, this is the situation
where a there is no look ahead, except that
at this level, you just look at the choices,
we
have and picking the bests base on a evaluation
function.
.
Here, you are saying, I will look at my choices,
first and I will look at what the opponent
can place, in that position and so on. And
I will keep doing that, to some k ply,
depending on how much computing power I have,
go up to the k (s) ply, apply the
evaluation function there, and then back up
the values essentially. So, in some sense,
what will happen is that, that is something
will get captured in the look ahead.
So, again if I use a analogy of chess, then
if you are doing, you are capturing the
opponents look, and the opponents is capturing
you bishops or something than at least
those things are known, that this, this is
are going away essentially. So, the absence
of an
evaluation function is compensated by doing
more look ahead essentially, typical chess
playing programs that you get, on laptops
for example, would do something like eight
ply or something like that. And generally,
you can imagine that with this kind of
.branching factor, the number of games that
you have to look at is growing exponentially.
And people have surmised, that if you do sixteen
ply look ahead for chess, with risibly
good evaluation function, then you can play
the grandmaster level essentially. So, it
is
a... so nice in practice of course, we do
not do such simple searches, we will see,
that
sometimes we do a little bit more search in
some areas and so on and so far. So, what
is
the game playing algorithm, we want to write,
see we want to still win the game; we do
not want to make some move and say it is a
good move essentially. So, the game playing
algorithm that we will use is. So, let us
just call this k ply search.
.
We will have an do in which will say, do k
ply search, and then make a move, and then
get opponents move, and we will put this into
a loop, till the game ends. So, what are we
doing now? If the game tree was something
that we can explore completely, we would
have analyze the whole game tree once for
all, and said this is the strategy, and it
is a
winning strategy. And then, you just play
it according to that strategy, but the game
tree,
we are not able to access and
what we are doing now, in this algorithm,
is that at every
move you are doing a search, every time you
have to make a move, you do some search,
limited search k ply search, and then decide
based on that.
.So, what does this amount to? This amount
to saying that if you make a choice here,
let
say this is your game tree, and you do a search,
let say up to this ply depth, which means
you make a move based on this much search.
So, this is your move; then you wait for
opponent move, so opponent makes a move, let
say opponent makes this move, so here.
Somewhere inside that original search that
you did, now I this stage, you do another
search, limited search, again k ply search,
and then make your second move. So, let say
this is your second move; then opponent makes
a move; then again you do a search.
So, in this manner, you can see that for every
move that you are making, you are doing a
limited search essentially, what is a advantage
of that, is that there is a game and force
you are looking at those part of the three,
which you are not seen originally. Originally
you have seen only till this part of the tree,
and then after two moves, you can see two
plies deeper. Because you are made one move
and opponent is made one move, then
your search will now look a little bit deeper,
then again here, another two plies deeper
and so on. So, as it goes along, you are looking
at different, so all that remains to do is
to
write this k ply search algorithm that is
the simplest of game playing algorithms.
.
We will see, how to improve upon that in that
following classes, so let we first write the
algorithm, it is a very simple algorithm minimax,
it is call minimax, and it takes a node J
.as an argument, and it returns the minimax
value essentially. So, let us say, this
algorithm only computes a minimax value, and
on the process, we can put in a small
routine, which will tell you what is the best
move, that is the secondary thing, which
comes out of it essentially. And rough you
the algorithm we just follows, to let us
assume that you have a way of testing, whether
you are on the horizon or not essentially.
So, you can have some kind of count, as you
go searching into the tree essentially.
So, I am assuming that you will some of figure
out how to do that, and then we do the
following, if J is terminal, so J is a node,
and by terminal we mean a test, which tells
you
whether you on the horizon or not. If you
are on the horizon, then we get V J is equal
to e
J. So, you simply apply the evaluation function,
and you get the value for that note, else
it is not terminal for i is equal to 1 to
b, where b is the branching factor, generate
the J i
the i th child of J, then if i equal to 1,
which means if you are looking at the first
child,
then V J or let we uses slightly simpler is
this.
Let say something called val is the minimax
value of V J, if J, if i is equal to 1, then
V J
gets val thus the first node, first child
that you have looked at. Otherwise you will
update
to a better child, else if J is max, then
V J get max, so I just use this devised, because
I do
not want write this, this is a recursive call
notice, it is a recursive call, with an next
node,
I just do not know to write it again and again.
So, I am just writing in once, so once I
making a recursive call, and then if the first
one of course that gets the value, V J gets
that value, if it is not the first child,
then you compare with the current value, and
this
new value that you are getting.
So, if it is max, it means that, you have
got some value here, which is V J, and you
have
looking at this child, and your getting a
value V J, let say k, which is return by this.
So,
you have, you going to return V J, which is
the minimax value of this node J, and so this
recursive call will return the minimax value
of V J. And then as I scan from left to right,
going, I go going from 1 to b, I will keep
seeing, if I am getting a better value, from
the
next call and so on. And wherever I get the
better value I will store that.
So, it is a very simple algorithm, which will
look ahead k ply deep, and compute the
minimax value of that game, based on the evaluation
function, because you have at
.terminal level, you have applying the evaluation
function. And I am assuming that you
will augment this with, be able to select,
what is the move that max should make,
because that is really the task that you have
doing, that you do this much search. And this
algorithm is basically doing this search here
in this area, but you want to make the move
also. So, you must keep track a what, where
the best move came from essentially.
So, you must keep track of that then you will
make the move, wait for opponents move,
and then again make a call to V J to decide
what is the next move? ((Refer Time.)
So, this is the simplest of all algorithms
essentially, what is the nature of this search
can
you tell you what kind of search is this doing.
Student: First depth.
It searching this part of the tree, game tree
or in if you look at this diagram, it searching
this part of the game tree, would in what
manner is searching.
Student: Depth bounder, depth first, depth
burst.
Depth bounder yes, because we have doing k
ply, but within that bound, how is it
searching in.
Student: Depth first search
It doing depth first search, so you should
figure out, this is really doing depth first
search,
which of course, give us ((Refer Time.) just
may not be the best way of looking at
things essentially. So, in the next class;
of course, we will trying to improve upon
this,
next may be one or two classes, but the, in
the remaining time, today which is about five
minutes are so. I want to just spend a little
bit of time on this evaluation function, how
do
you write in evaluation function for a board
position.
Because it is the performance of the algorithm
really depends on how good the
evaluation function is, if it can judge, accurately
the value of a board, and by accurately
.you mean, whether it is you know how close
to winning it is essentially. Then just one
play search would be enough essentially, if
you have very good evaluation function, but
other side in practice it not so easy to get
very good evaluation function.
.
So, what goes into an evaluation, so essentially
you want to look at a board position, let
say we are talking about chess, but in practice
of course, when you do you will be doing
othello, when you look at a goal port position,
you want to give it a value between minus
1000 and plus 1000 essentially or minus large
and plus large let us see, any ideas how
you could give this number.
Student: Any games practice from, wherever
it means back tracken keep asign((Refer
Time.) keep it.
But you see, the whole point of this exercise,
is that we are trying to our search problem
is so huge, that we cannot search the game
tree.
Student: ((Refer Time.)
How do you play many games?
.Student: May be initially begin with random
assignment and you will ((Refer Time:
37:48)) and based on once you reach the end,
go back track and ((Refer Time.)
So, I get a point, you are trying to say that,
so you are a machine learning enthusiasts
and
you are saying that, I want to learn the evaluation
function, that is that will come. In fact,
Samuel Sekars playing program, improved it
is game, because it improved it is valuation
function on the way, but that comes after
word essentially, before that what are the
components of the evaluation, I mean.
Student: ((Refer Time.)
Oil all in machinery terms, what is the structure
of a evaluation function, what I am
learning, am I learning parameters or weights,
weights of what essentially. So, if you
look at Tom Michaels book the first chapter,
he actually describes, how game playing
program can learn evaluation function, but
then he gives it a linear combination of,
I
thing is document checkers, of number of pieces
I have, and number of pieces opponent
have, number of things I have, number of things
opponent has, and a linear combination
of them is this thing. So, my question is
more fundamental, that if you are to write
the
evaluation function, just for. Let say you
are a chess expert and All right, let say
you
have Viswanathan Anand sitting next to you,
and you say help me write this evaluation
function, what could he say.
Student: The answers piece of the pieces will
have particular value and then ((Refer
Time.), and there would be additional advantages,
piece advantage.
So, typically an evaluation function will
have two components, one is call material
and
other is called positional. So, chess players
will say, white is winning, because white
as
material advantage, which means you know,
white is got let say, one row can one bishop
extra. And then any good chess player will
say, if you have that much more fighting
power, I am not going to play against you
or rather you would resigned essentially.
So,
one thing is material, number of pieces, you
can say, some of now beginning chess
players might say, that you know a queen as
value 9, and bishop has value 5 or 3 or 4
or
whatever I do not know, look as value 5.
.And then you count, how many pieces, do I
have, what is there values, and let say you
give negative value to opponents pieces, and
from that I sub track how many pieces
opponent has. So, if I have more pieces or
more valuable pieces, than the opponent, than
this, some will become positive essentially.
Initially as you can guess, both sides of
the
same number of pieces a value of material
value is 0, both are the same number of
pieces, but as you capture some pieces, your
material value goes up essentially.
Now, in practice; of course, chess playing
people have much final gradation of values.
So, they compute in 100, for example, let
say bishop is 200, and knight is 220 or
something like that, it really depends on
your prospective of the game essentially.
So,
one is the material value, how many pieces
I have, and how many pieces opponent has,
rather is positional, we says, how are the
pieces arranged. Now, this is of course, the
trickier part essentially, this is the more
difficult part, because it is not looking
a
structure, and not it is not just a method
of counting, how many pieces I have, how are
they arranged essentially.
So, chess players, what say things like, if
there are two rooks in the same. So, if this
is
the chess board for example, then if I have
a rook here, and if I have a another rook
here,
in the same column, then chess player say
that, it stronger position, two rooks in the
same column are very powerful, and you know,
you should try to arrive at such a
position essentially. All they might say,
that you know some pawn structures, linked
pawn structures, if pawns are supporting each
other, it is better than pawns, if their
scattered around the place, and not putting
each other essentially.
Then you know that if there is a knight, if
n stands for a knight, and if it is the opponent
has a queen here, and a rook here. Then you
can see that knight is attacking both the
queen and the rook at the same time. So, chess
plays called is a fork, and a fork is;
obviously, a good thing to have essentially,
because it among to saying that in the next
move, I am going to either capture a queen
or a rook. So, you are going to use lose
material in the process essentially, because
queen and rook are important then knight is
not so important in ((Refer time.) material
value essentially. And there are other
things like controlling the center, and attacking
the center, and think like that.
.Now this program deep blue, and when I read
about this is so in 2002 or something like
that, it had a 1000 components to positional
evaluation. So, just as we said you know,
rooks in the same column or connected pawns,
a protected king or mobile pieces, so you
know bishop is slap then it not very useful,
hence things like that. It has a 1000 different
component, which were use to evaluate the
board position, in the positional part. So,
that
obviously is the key to the whole thing, if
you can look at a board position, and give
a
value, and this is just an attempt to give
an accurate value, it is looking at it piece
say this pattern is good, this pattern is
good, this pattern is good,
And of course, if the opponent has that pattern
you are going to subtract it from
essentially. So, really the secret is in devising
a good evaluation function, if you have
good evaluation function, then you do not
have to search very much deep in the game,
and you evaluation function itself will tell
you what is the good position or not
essentially. So, what you will need to do,
for your othello game is to, look at the game,
on the web or read about, what it in try to
device an evaluation function, because that
is
going to be critical part of your program
essentially.
So today, we have seen this, that we cannot
search the entire game tree, we have to do
a
limited look up, look ahead, and we have a
program to do k ply search. And we will
repeatedly call this program, for the first
move, for the second move, for the third move,
for every move that we make we will call the
program. And this simple version of k ply
look ahead is essentially doing depth first
search, left to right and we want to improve
upon that essentially. So, we will do that
in the next class.
.