We are looking at game playing
and in the last class, we saw the minimax
algorithm. If
you remember, what the algorithm basically,
does or what the game playing algorithm
does is that there are two kinds of players;
one is max, and the other is min. Max is trying
to maximize the board value and min is trying
to minimize the board value. The game
tree consist of alternate layers of max and
min. To starting with max node, there are
some min children, and then, there are max
children, and so on. This is the tree which
minimax algorithm explores, and we saw that
this explore, minimax algorithm does, is
depth first search, left to right.
Now, today we want to look at improvement
upon minimax, which does not inspect this
entire tree, up to this cape lie. So, this
is cape lie search that we are doing. Can
we do
without looking at the entire tree? What minimax
is doing is going down all the way, to
this level and at this level, the evaluation
function e of j is applied, and then, the
values
of these leaf nodes are backed up using the
minimax rule. The minimax rule says that if
.you are backing up to a min level, you back
up the smallest of the values of all the
children. If you are backing up to a max level,
you back up the largest of the values of all
the children. So, at alternate level, we choose
the minimum, the maximum, the
minimum, the maximum, and so on. That is why,
the algorithm is called minimax
algorithm, but the question is that do we
have to really inspect the entire tree, essentially.
To consider that, Let us first look at a small
example. Let us say you are playing this
game of Tick Tack Toe, and for some reason,
this is how the game proceeds. Let us say
you play this and we are not drawing the game
tree; we will just draw the board. The
opponent plays this; Let us say. So, the opponent
is mirroring your moves. You play this
and then, the opponent plays this. Now, Let
us say you are doing some search from his
point; one ply search. If you want to, now,
consider this move. So, you play this move
here, or you are looking at this move. Then,
you can see at this moment that if you are
considering this move, then there is no need
to look at all these other children. Why
because this is a winning move position, and
you have won the game. So, why consider
the other moves at all, essentially. So, this
is the idea that we will explore, up to a
greater
depth, essentially, and the algorithm that
we want to look at today, is called Alpha
Beta .
A little bit of nomenclature, before we continue;
max nodes are also called alpha nodes,
and min nodes are also called beta nodes.
Max nodes store alpha values, and min nodes
store beta values. What are these alpha and
beta values? These are the values of partially
computed node, essentially. Let us see how
these happen.
..
.
Let us say this is the route node, which is
the max node. We always play the game for
max, and at some point of the game, Let us
say max is trying to evaluate this particular
min child, which is not the first min child,
because it has already seen; remember, that
we are going from left to right; it has already
seen some min children, and the sub trees
below that. So, it has the already explored
the sub trees this side. It is trying to,
now,
evaluate this min child. What will it do?
If the value supplied by this min child is
higher
than the values supplied by all these children,
then this would be adopted; otherwise,
those values would be adopted. Let us say
this value is 10, to begin with. So, we say
that
alpha becomes 10, after this node is completely
evaluated; it means that sub tree below
that is completely searched; alpha becomes
10, because that is a value, this beta node
is
giving to this.
Let us say then, we evaluate the second sub
tree below that, and this happens to be 15.
Now, we change this alpha to 15. So, this
alpha value for this max node is the value
it
has seen so far, and the value comes from
the left hand side of the tree, essentially.
Let us
look at an example of slightly, deeper example
of this Tick Tack Toe game.
..
Let us assume that we are using this following
evaluation function, that e of j is equal
to
count of the number of rows, or columns, or
diagonals; available to max, minus the
number of the same thing, available to min.
So, essentially we will evaluate a board
position by saying that how many are available
to each side. For example, if this is the
board position that we are looking at; let
us say this is the board position we are looking
at. Then, we can see that max has this row,
one, two, three and four; two rows and two
columns are accessible to max. For min, it
is this column, this diagonal, and this row;
so,
3 to min, essentially. So, the value of this
board position would be 4 minus 3 is min,
essentially. So, we will use this evaluation
function to illustrate this idea of cut offs,
essentially.
..
Let us say we are starting the game from the
beginning, and then, first we explore max,
playing at this corner, here. Now, remember,
the game playing algorithm are used as
combination of search or look ahead and evaluation
function. So, they do not evaluate
this board position at all. They would look
ahead a little bit for evaluating the board
position at this, and then, back up the value
essentially. So, let us say about, we are
doing
two searches that is easy to defect here.
So, we look at one more level. So, at this
level,
let us assume that we are looking at this
move for, when we are going look at all the
moves for min. Let us say we look at this
move for min.
We evaluate this board position. Now, if you
look at this board position and count them
carefully, you will see that there are six
rows or columns or diagonals available for
max.
So, 1,2,3,4,5 and 6. So, 1,2,3 sorry, 1,2,3,4,5,6,
and if we look at min then, they are 5;
they happen to be 6 minus 5. So, the board
position of this is 1, essentially. Now, this
is a
max node. So, we are going to compute alpha
values for this. So, let me draw this as the
max node, and this is the min node, because
it is min play here, and these on max nodes,
but it does not matter. At this point, you
can see that beta will become 1.
The moment we evaluate this position and this
node knows that this beta is 1. Now, what
are beta values? Beta values are values of
min nodes, and they are upper bounds on the
.values that they can take. So, beta values
are upper bounds, and likewise, alpha values
are lower bounds. What do we mean by this?
We mean that once, this node has seen one
value from a left child, which is 1, it is
not going to accept any value, which higher
than
this value. From the remaining children, it
is only looking for lower value. So, this
beta
value, which is the partial value, it has
got from here, is an upper bound on the value
of
this node. It can only be 1 or less, essentially,
less, if one of the children evaluate to less,
essentially. So far, we do not have an alpha
value, because none of its children is
completely evaluated. So, we look at the second
child. Let us say this is the second
option, we are looking at. This, we can see,
is symmetric in nature, that both are at two
corners. So, the number must be equal to 0.
So, I will leave that for you to verify, and
let
us see this one and this one. Now, if we count
this, you will see that max has 1, 2, 3, 4,
5,
and min has 1, 2, 3, 4, 5. So, let me know
if it is wrong; 5 minus 5 is equal to 0.
One thing, we should have done. The moment
we saw this 0, we should have changed
this value to 0, because beta has gone down
to 0. Now, 0 is the upper bound on this
value. Then, we look at this or may be this
one is 1. 6 minus 5 is equal to 1. This one
is
again, symmetric. So, it must be 0, whatever,
the count is. Finally, we look at one more
move for win, which is this. Now, this turns
out is max as 1, 2, 3 and 4; only 4 available,
and min has 1, 2, 3, 4 and 5, minus 5 is equal
to minus 1. Now, we have a new value for
beta. So, beta becomes minus 1 and now, this
node is, of course, completely evaluated,
which means, it can say we can think of these
as suppliers.
So, beta nodes are suppliers to alpha nodes
and below them, alpha nodes are suppliers
to
beta nodes and so on and so forth. So, beta
nodes always choose the smallest value, and
alpha node will always choose the highest
value from what its suppliers have given.
So,
here we can see that alpha is equal to minus
1; that is the value this first beta node
is
supplying to it, which we can read as saying
that alpha is going to be greater than equal
to minus 1, which is the characteristics of
an alpha node, essentially. So, from the other
children that we going to look at for max,
it is only going to be interested in a node,
if its
value is going to be greater than minus 1.
Let us try the second option. Let us say max
try this option, and we try the first option
for
min, and see this is the first option, which
I have for min. We always begin from the top
.left hand corner, let us say. Now, we can
see that, we have already seen this position.
This is the opposite of this position, and
the value of this is 5 minus 6 equal to minus
1.
The moment we see this, we know that this
is minus 1, and by this, you remember that
beta is less than equal to minus 1. Now, here
we have alpha is already equal to minus 1
and this beta says, that I am going to be
minus 1 or less. Though this alpha, in some
sense, will tell this beta that we do not,
I would not be interested in you any more;
that
you do not need to value it yourself any further;
which means all these other children that
beta was considering, like this five children
we had here; there also, we would have five
children. It would not be evaluated.
So, this is the cut off which takes place,
and this is called an alpha cut off. So, an
alpha
cut off appears at a beta node, which is a
descendant or in this case, a child of alpha
node. It happens when the beta node promises
to be worst than or lower than or not
higher than, rather, than what alpha already
seen, essentially. So, after alpha has seen
one
side, it will now do this in a very control
fashion, which is only, as long as we have
better than minus 1, I am going to be interested
in you; otherwise, do not explore the sub
tree below that, essentially. So, this will
get cut off and then, alpha will try; this
is a third
option. So, if we ignore symmetries, I mean,
if we take into account symmetries, then
you can see that max has only three moves
to start with, either corner, or on a side,
or on
this. This small move, I will leave as an
exercise for you to explore. The idea is basically,
that a cut off takes place, when there is
enough information, essentially. If we were
doing
10 ply search, for example, then the entire
trees; 8 ply trees below this, would be cut
off.
So, the saving would be considerable in amount,
essentially.
The algorithm that we are looking at today;
this alpha beta algorithm, essentially, is
like
minimax, in the sense that its searches from
left to right, but it does cut offs along
the
way. We have illustrated one cut off, which
is alpha cut off, which you can also think
of
as alpha induced cut off, and it happens at
the beta node. So, beta node stops evaluating
itself, if the parent alpha node tells it
to stop evaluating itself. Then, it is an
alpha cut off.
In a similar fashion, beta cut off will take
place at an alpha node, or it could be thought
of a beta induced cut off, essentially. Now,
these cut offs do not necessarily, have to
be at
the immediate level, essentially. They can
happen at a much deeper level. So, let me
illustrate that with a diagram. Let us say
that you are evaluating this deep game tree.
..
This is the route node, alpha node and we
are, this diagram, I am basically, repeating
it
here. We are evaluating this beta node and
you have evaluated some part of the tree;
so,
always the left side of the tree, you have
finished evaluating. So, we have got some
value
from here; alpha 1; from this side of the
tree and essentially, what this node is trying
to
do is to see, if it can get a better value,
better than this alpha 1 value. What is this
alpha
1? Alpha 1 is the best amongst these here,
and it is time to see, if this node will supply
it
a better value, essentially. Likewise, this
node may be looking at a alpha child, and
it
may have got some value, which we will call
beta 1, from the left tree, that it has
explored on the left side, essentially. So,
this process continues. This has got some
value
alpha 2 from here.
Then, this has got some value beta 2 from
here. Then, let us say this is a node. Let
us say
that this is a beta node that we are about,
we are trying to evaluate, essentially. Now,
if
this node we will call j, which means, we
are evaluating this slowly, by looking at
its
children. The question we want; so, this has
alpha 2 here. So, I hope this diagram is
clear. Just imagine, this that depth first
search, sweeping from left to right, and all
these
values are coming from the left side of the
tree; alpha 1 coming from the left children
of
this, when it is trying to evaluate this.
This, in turn, is trying to evaluate this.
It has got
some partial values beta 1. This one is trying
to evaluate this. This has got some partial
.value alpha 2 and this has got some partial
values beta 2. This has got some alpha 3 and
this j is what we are trying to evaluate.
The question we want to ask is; when will
this j
value reach the route, or in other words,
when will this j value influence the game,
essentially? Is it the node worth exploring?
You can see that this j value will influence
this node, only if it is better than alpha
3. So, that means, let us call it v j, that
is the value
of this node j, because we may be searching
deeper, must be greater than alpha 3;
otherwise, this node will take alpha 3 from
here. Likewise, it must be better than alpha
as well, because otherwise, this will take
alpha 2 and also, alpha 1.
Only if it is better than this alpha 3 value,
because these are max nodes, remember, and
they are looking higher values. Only if this
node supplies the value, which is higher than
alpha 3 and higher than alpha 2 and higher
than alpha 1; will it influence the route
node,
essentially. Likewise, it must be less than
this beta 2, because this is the beta node,
and it
is going to only take lower values and also,
beta 1. So, we can generalize this and say
that we need to evaluate this node j, only
if v j is less than beta and is greater than
alpha
where, alpha is equal to max of alpha 1, alpha
2, alpha 3 or in general, all the ancestors
of this node; all the alpha ancestors of this
node. So, alpha must be higher than all these
ones, and this value must be higher than that
max of that. Beta is min of beta 1, beta 2
and all the beta ancestors of the node, essentially.
I just repeat, this node is worth
evaluating only, if it is higher than this
alpha 3, and this alpha 2, and this alpha
1, and at
the same time, lower than this beta 2, and
this beta 1, and all the beta ancestors,
essentially. So, this alpha and beta can be
seen as the bounce, within which, we want
the
algorithm to search; otherwise, it should
abort the search or prune that below that,
essentially.
Let me write the algorithm first, and then,
we will look at a slightly, more detailed
example, essentially. So, I hope this is clear.
So, we can think of this alpha beta as the
window. If these are the values of the game
three, then this alpha beta is a window. Beta
is an upper limit and alpha is a lower limit.
The absolute possible is plus large and
absolute minimum is minus large. So, remember,
we had said that the evaluation
function can be something, like in a range
of minus 1000 to plus 1000 or something like
that; instead of 1000, I am writing plus large,
some suitably large number.
.What the alpha beta algorithm does is that
for evaluating any node, it passes a window
and says, only if you can get me a value inside
this window, I am going to be interested
in that. So, again, look at this node. The
window is defined by this alpha and this beta
where, alpha is a maximum of all the ancestors,
and beta is the minimum of all the
ancestors. What will the node try to do, because
this example here, it is a beta node; it is
going to try to pull down this beta and say,
I want a value slightly, lower than this beta.
If
it, alpha node try to raise the value. So,
as we sweep this from left to right, this
window
gets smaller and smaller, and search progresses
only inside this window; otherwise, the
tree is pruned off. Let us write this algorithm,
or at least, I will write a part of it, and
you
can write the rest.
.
Alpha, beta; it takes an argument j, which
is the node, and a value; alpha, and a value;
beta, which are parameters, essentially. These
parameters are basically, the window sizes
that are passed on to the node, essentially.
Let me first ask you what should be the value
alpha and beta, when we call the game playing
algorithm at the root, essentially? So,
alpha should be minus large and beta should
be plus large, when the first time we call
it;
that means, windows completely opened. Then,
the algorithm is simpler. It is basically,
a
small variation of the minimax algorithm that
we have seen. So, if we assumed that we
have a function, which tells us, weather j
is on the horizon or not. You can do this
by
.keeping some kind of a counter as you search
deeper, so that, every time you make a
recursive call, you also decrement the counter
by 1. Let us say you are doing eight ply
search. When you make this call, they count
as 8; when you make this call, they count
as
7 and so on. When the counter becomes 0 that
means, it is a terminal node on the
horizon. The implication of being a terminal
is that you have to apply the evaluation
function stop searching further, essentially.
So, if it is terminal, then we can say that
v j is
e j where, e j is the evaluation function
that we are using in the game. Else, we have
to
evaluate still then, which means you looking
at a node; it is not a terminal node.
So, you have to evaluate all the children,
essentially, one by one. So, for j, let us
say i
going from one to b. So, Let us assume that
b is a bouncing factor, or every node has
b
children. We are going to evaluate them from
left to right, essentially. If j is a max
node,
what do we want to do here? If it is a max
node, like this one, for example, or this
max
node; it has got some alpha and beta bounce,
given to it, and we want to evaluate this
from left to right. So, this is j 1; this
is j 2 and so on, up to j t; we want to evaluate
from
left to right, and we want to see, if we can
get a higher value than what alpha has.
Remember, it has to operate within this window,
and seek a higher value, essentially. I
will write the part for the max, and you write
the part for min. So, if j is a max node,
then
what you do is; alpha gets maximum of alpha,
and a recursive call for j i, the highest
child, with the bounce alpha and beta; the
bounce keep getting propagated. So, what does
this step say? We are doing from; i going
from 1 to b. So, for every i, we will evaluate
the highest child, and if its providing the
better value, which means a higher value,
because we are using the max function here,
then alpha. Then, we will update alpha to
that, essentially.
If alpha becomes greater than beta, then we
say, return beta. What does this mean? Look
at this alpha value here. It has got this
beta bound coming from the top, which is beta
and beta 2. If the value that we are trying
to compute for this alpha becomes higher than
this beta or this beta, it does not matter.
Then, they are going to say that no need to
value
it anything here. So, we are making a return
statement there, and say, return whatever
beta bound is and that is the best you can
do with this. So, this amounts to a beta cut
off,
because it is happening in an alpha node;
it is dictated by the beta value; it is a
beta cut
off; otherwise, if j equal to b, sorry, i
equal to b, which means you who have looked
at
.the last child and evaluated it, and you
already done this, choosing the best of this
values.
You can return alpha. So, this takes care
of the alpha side of thing. The other option
is l
s, which means j is min; I will not write
this completely, but you can fill it up yourself;
this would be similar if i equal to b, return
beta. This would be analogous, which says
beta is min of beta and the recursive call.
This test will remain the same; alpha greater
than beta, because this test signifies that
this window has closed in some sense. This
alpha value has gone above the beta value.
So, there is nothing left to explore, but
the
return value would be alpha, essentially.
So, you can fill up those details, essentially.
Let
us now look at a slightly more detailed example
of this algorithm.
.
Let us assume that we have binary search tree,
and it is 4 ply deep. Let us draw the tree
first. We will have 16 leaf nodes
and since, a binary tree; there would be beta
nodes
sitting here, and then, alpha nodes sitting
here, and beta nodes here. This is the root.
This
is the alpha node. So, I have just drawn the
space that is going to be searched; the space
of nodes; we have not drawn the tree. What
we want to see is how will alpha beta
algorithm explore this tree, essentially.
Now, observe that the minimax algorithm will
explore this entire tree from left to right,
and back up the value. So, these beta nodes
will
take the minimum of what they get from here.
Then, alpha nodes will take the maximum
of beta children. This beta will take the
minimum of these alpha children, and so on.
So,
.you want to see what alpha beta does; we
will fill in some random values, just to explore
the algorithm here. So, it is during depth
first search; left to right. So, it first
goes and
evaluates the first left most node in the
tree. Let us, for argument sake, say that
this value
is 50, some random value, essentially. Then,
it evaluates its next child. Let us say that
is
40. So, at this point, this beta is completely
evaluated. Its value is 40 and since, this
is
completely evaluated, this alpha is equal
to 40, which, remember, you must read as
saying that alpha is greater than equal to
40, essentially. Then, it starts the next
round. It
looks at this, and looks at this. Let us say
this happens to be 30, which means this beta
is
equal to 30. Now, you can see this relation
between this beta and this alpha node. This
alpha is saying, I am at least, 40. This beta
is saying, I am at most, 30. So, this alpha
node is not going to be in this beta node.
So, we have an alpha cut off. I will just
write
alpha here, to signify, it is an alpha cut
off.
So, we are not going to look at this node,
essentially. Then, we continue the depth first
fashion; go here, go here, go here, and let
us say that this is 70. So, this beta becomes
at this moment. Then, explore this, and this
is 60. So, this beta is 60, now, and this
alpha
is also 60. This beta is 40, because it is
getting this 40 value from here, and it is
essentially, asserting that I am 40 or less.
This one is getting 60 from here, and we say,
it
is 60 or more, essentially. So, which means,
this beta will induce a cutoff here. So, this
will be cutoff, and this is the beta cut off,
or beta induced cut off, essentially. So,
we are
not looked at those two nodes, those two leaf
nodes. In fact, we have not looked at the
entrie sub tree there, essentially. At this
point, this alpha is equal to 40 and again,
we do
depth first search, and let us say then, this
value is 30.
Now, you remember this; a node is influenced
or the bound that node gets, is influenced
by all the ancestors. In this case, then,
only one ancestor, which has a value, which
is this
root for this value is 40. Look at this beta
node. This beta node is saying it is 30. Of
course, it could go lower than 30, but at
the moment it is 30. So, this now induced
the cut
off, what we call as a deep cut off. That,
because this is upper bounded by 30, this
node
is never going to be interested in what is
going to happen here; so, might as well, cut
it
off, and this is an alpha cut off. So, the
alpha cut off does not have to be induced
by a
parent node. It can be induced by some ancestor,
of course, which is what, we have said
here, explicitly. When you have said that
this alpha bound is actually, the maximum
of
.all the alpha bounds, essentially.
So, this alpha is 30. It is saying, I am going
to be 30 or more. Let us say we come here;
we come here. Let us say this happens to be
70, and this happens to be 80. Now, this
becomes 70, and this value of also becomes
70, and this beta is 70. So, what is
happening? Now, when we explore this child,
it is getting the bound of, beta is 70 and
alpha is 40. It still has the window opened,
so, we must explore this tree below here.
So,
we do that in the depth first fashion. Let
us say that this is also 30, then again, we
introduce a cutoff here, very similar to these
same values. So, this is now, 30 or Let us
say now, this is 80. So, we do not get this
cut off. We do investigate this node. Let
us say
this happens to be 90, and this happens to
be now, 80. This says alpha is equal to 80.
Now, look at this beta and this alpha. This
beta says, I am at most, 70. This beta is
saying, I am at least, 80. So, we have a cut
off here.
We can see that we did not look at this node;
we do not look at this node, and we did a
fair amount of cut off. So, out of the 16
nodes, this alpha bit algorithm has not seen
nodes; it has seen only 10 nodes, essentially.
As an exercise, I will ask you to fill in
values, so that, the number of cut offs are
maximum. At the same time, as a different
exercise, fill in the values, so that, there
are no cut offs at all. Now, it is possible
that the
values are such, that there are no cut offs,
essentially. That happens, because the
algorithm is searching from left to right.
What does left and right mean? It basically,
means in what order you are generating the
moves, essentially. This is some game in
which, you have two moves; let us call them,
a and b. You are generating a first, and
then, b, essentially.
Now, what this exercise will reveal to you
is now, what is a mini max value of this game
tree? This is 70, this is 40, and this is
an alpha node. So, this value is actually,
70 where
is it coming from? It is coming from this
node here. This 70 is coming here. This 70
is
going here. This 70 is coming here; which
means that the game that will be played, if
only on this analysis; would be that max would
make this move; min would make this
move, because that is what min can do best;
it is getting 70 here, and 80 there; max
would make this move, and min would make this
move.
.If you go and flip this tree left to right,
which means, this game value would come on
the
left part of the tree. Then, you would notice
that the number of cut offs are moved,
essentially. In other words, if somehow, the
best moves are made earlier, if they are
made in the left part of the three, then the
number of cut offs will be more. This, you
can,
sort of, understand by constructing an example
in which, the best moves are on the left
hand side. In fact, if you try to construct
a tree in which, you fill in values, so that,
the
number of cut offs are maximum, you will see
that the game value will come from this
left side of the tree, essentially. Now, that
has an implication for game playing programs.
If you are writing a game playing program,
you would like to generate your moves. For
example, you are doing the Othello program,
and you have some set of moves to
generate. You would like to generate the moves
as far as possible, in such a manner that
the best moves are considered first, and then,
the worst moves, essentially. So, the
question is; how can you order moves, essentially?
Remember, we are discussing this in
domain independent fashion. Of course, you
can apply some domain knowledge to saym
these moves are to be considered, and so on,
but in a domain independent passion. Any
suggestions?
Student: Heuristically
Heuristically, but how do you choose that
heuristically?
Student: Evaluation.
So, here is what many people do. Remember,
that when we are playing a game playing
program, you are doing some search up to some
Cape lie, deep search, here.
..
Let us say up to this level or whatever, and
you decide to make. Let us say this happens
to be the move that you are making, essentially.
This is a move that you made, after you
have done this whole game play search, essentially.
Then, what happens? Then, its
opponent turns to make the move, because opponent
is going to play the next move. You
have made a move, and opponent will play a
move, but what you have access to, is your
search tree, and has to below this max node.
Now, you will have to your next move at
this, assuming that this happens to be the
best move for min, which will be the case,
because your analysis search that you are
considering the best moves for min. Min is
taking the minimum value from all these. Let
us assume that this is the minimum value
that min can get. Next time, when your turn
comes, you will have to play from here,
which means, you will be searching the tree,
starting from here, and going down,
essentially.
Now, you can exploit the search that you did
in the previous round, below this node,
because you are getting values from the all
the children. You order the children, so that,
the higher order min children come first,
and below that, the lower order max children
come first. You can order the sub tree, so
that, the best nodes are coming to the left
side.
If we do that you are likely to get more cut
off, which in the real tournament
environment, will mean that your move would
be faster, and you would have more time
.for the subsequent moves, essentially. You
can also do some amount of analysis in
opponent’s time. This is opponent’s time,
here. What do the mean by opponent’s time?
It
is when opponent is thinking. So, you have
made a move, and opponent is thinking; what
to move? That time, in the real world is available
to you. You can also think of what
opponent might move, and what you would respond;
you could do this analysis in
opponent’s time.
The only thing is, of course, in the game
playing assignment that we are going to give
you; you will not get this opponent’s time,
because you will have a separate thread
running. We should be invoked, only after
opponent has made their moves, but in the
real world game playing situation where, you
take your own computer to play. Again,
you do have this time to do some further analysis.
One analysis that we can do is to try to
order the moves in such a way, that the best
moves comes first, essentially
.
Now, this algorithm suffers from this common
trade that we have been observing
throughout this course, which is that it is
a blind or uninformed algorithm. It searches
from left to right. Of course, this desire
to order the moves is, in some sense, the
desire
the give it a direction, but given a fixed
order of moves; can we have an algorithm,
which
will have a sense of direction, which is,
which will be like a best first search algorithm?
.Indeed, there is such an algorithm called
sss star algorithm, but we will take that
up in
the next class.
We will stop here now, with alpha beta.
.