We are looking at planning. In the last class
we saw two approaches; one was a forward
state space planning, and the other was backward
state space planning. The forward state
space search; forward state space planning;
thus, forward state space search, it starts
from the start state and keeps applying actions,
till it finds a goal state, considers actions
in forward direction. This one considers actions
in a backward direction. It constructs
plan also, in the forward direction, and this
one, constructs the plan in backward
direction. So, in that sense, the two processes
of looking for actions and constructing a
plan, happens very in a closely coupled fashion.
In forward state space search, we start
looking for the first action and then, as
soon as we pick a first action, we say this
is the
first action of our plan.
In this manner, we construct the plan also,
in a forward direction. In backward state
space search, in the likewise manner, we start
looking at the last action, looking for the
last action; what could be my last action,
and then, also construct the plan in a backward
.fashion, by saying that will be my last action
of the plan, essentially. Now, if you
remember, we had this notion of relevant action
here, and the action was said to be
relevant, if the effect of a; intersection
goal was not empty, and if it has no negative
effects, which kind of, distracted the goal.
We had the notion of a relevant action and
we
had a notion of regression. We could regress
a goal over an action. So, we would get a
sub goal, g prime, if which is obtained as
g minus the effects of a, because we expect
that
the actions will; actionable, produce the
effects. The whole thing union p conditions
of a.
In the similar manner, we had for forward
state space search; the notion of an
applicability of an action and the notion
of progress. So, a state could progress over
another state. So, you could progress over
it.
This regression progress and the notion of
applicability and relevance was used basically,
to do both these stars, that looking for actions
and building the plan at the same time. So,
the process of building the plan is that you
move from one state to the next, and then,
look for an applicable action; then, move
to the next state, and look for an applicable
action; move to the next state. Here, you
are looking at a relevant action. So, you
look at
a goal, find a relevant action, regress to
a goal g prime, and try to find a new action
at
that point. So, what we had observed then,
was that this was a sound process that, when
you progress from one state to another; what
you get is a legal state, essentially. So,
this
was sound, but this was not sound.
We had seen that you could regress to a set
of predicates, which could not have been part
of a state. So, for example, you might have
something, like holding a and holding b, at
the same time. That, of course, not possible
in a state in which, because we are
considering one arm robot. So, you could;
this process of regression was not sound,
in
the sense, it was not closed under the set
of states. You could start with a possible
state
and you could end up with something, which
is not a state, whereas, this was sound and
you would always end up in states, which is
why, when we did backward state space
planning, we said one of things to do is that
after you found a sequence of actions, check,
whether it is a valid plan or not, before
accepting it. So, this was a plus point of
forward
state space planning, and this was corresponding
negative point of backward state space
planning. On the other hand, in forward state
space planning, we had large branching
factor.
.Because the state was a complete description;
it may have hundreds of facts. There may
be hundreds of applicable actions. Forward
state space planning would consider all those
hundreds actions, and choose one of them,
essentially. Backward direction search had
low branching, and the reason for that was
that we were focusing on the goal; we are
trying to see, what we need do to get the
goal, predicates into our state, essentially.
So,
this was a plus point for backward state space
search. Today, we want to look at an
algorithm, which combines both these features.
So, what do we mean by this? We want
to look at an algorithm, which will consider
actions from the goal point of view, in a
goal
directed fashion, but it will construct plans
from the starting state to the goal state,
essentially, which means that we will be benefiting
from the low branching factor of
doing goal directed search, and also, the
soundness of constructing a plan in a forward
manner, essentially.
You should ponder by little bit over this,
as to why is the progress action sound, and
the
regress action not sound, essentially. So,
the actions are not symmetric in that sense,
essentially; you cannot prove both ways. These
are sort of an arrow of time, which says
this is a precondition, and this is a post
condition. So, you can only construct plans
by
looking at pre conditions and making post
conditions.
.
.The algorithm that you want to look at today
is called goal stack planning. It is actually,
one of the earliest planning algorithms devised,
and was in fact, used in the skips
program, which was used to control the robot
in Stanford that we have spoken about,
essentially. The general idea of goal stack
planning is the following. What I will do
is I
will give a high level description of the
planner, and then, we will look at an example
in
a little bit more detailed, essentially. So,
as the name suggests, this uses a stack to
do the
reasoning, and we do the following that; let
us also consider an example, along the same,
at the same time. So, let us say that this
is an example. Again, we have resorting to
the
blocks while, because we are familiar with
it, but you must keep in mind that these are
general domain independent algorithms that
we are considering. This is a starting state
and I am not drawing anything, which is relevant.
You can imagine that there are 50
blocks, which I have not drawn here, which
will not interfere with our plan. So, we just
want to focus on the planning actions today.
.
The goal state is that; let us say is that
you want a on b, and you want b on d, essentially.
You actually, do not care what else is true,
essentially. So, the goal is on a b, and on
b d.
As long as these two predicate are there in
my state description, I would call that a
goal
state, essentially, which means, as long as
a is on b, and b is on d, that whichever state
it
is, is a goal state. You can think of this
as a set of states in which, this part is
common.
.Everything else can be in some manner, essentially.
So, this is basically, a set, and the
algorithm that we are looking at, will do
the following.
.
It pushes; you start of a pushing the goals
that you want to achieve on the stack. So,
the
top of the stack will always, contain the
goals that you want to achieve, essentially.
When I say goals, I basically, mean the predicates
of the goal, essentially. Now, let me
do this here, and let me write the algorithm,
here. So, goal stack planning; push goals
on
to stack; then, you pop the stack. There are
various things that can come out of the stack.
If it is a predicate; I will use very loose
language here. When I say, if predicate, I
mean a
statement like; on a b, or on b c; or holding
a; or some such things. Then, there are two
possibilities; one if true, which means, it
already holds in the world; then do nothing.
Else, it is not true; push an action on to
the stack. So, this is a basic process that
this
algorithm follows. The stack has, you are
pushing these goal predicates on to the stack.
In our example, we push these two things on
to the stack; then, you pop. So, it is the
alternates between push and pop; you pop the
stack. If it is a predicate that comes out,
then you check, whether the predicate is true.
If it is true, then you do not have to do
anything. If it is not true, you push an action
on to the stack, essentially. What action?
You should say the element action; here, define
the notion of relevant action.
.If it is not a predicate, it must be an action
there. Only two kinds of objects in a domain,
either predicates or actions; if it is an
action; I forgot one thing. You push the action
on
to the stack and push. So, let us say this
action is a; push pre conditions
on to stack. You
first, push the action. Then, you push the
pre conditions of the action, and you can
get
some intuition here, that you are pushing
an action. Then you are pushing the pre
conditions, and then, you will look at the
top of the stack, and there will be the pre
conditions of the actions. If they are true,
then this thing will happen; you will not
do
anything; you just remove them. Eventually,
if the action comes to the top, then you will
say, yes, I have found one action, essentially.
There is an extra step, which is, push each
predicate
on to the stack, essentially. So, this
part is that, if then part, then for this
if, we have these else, pop, action, or we
have
already done the pop. So, add action to the
plan, and by this, we mean that a plan
becomes plan followed by dot where, the dot
operator is a concordinate operator, which
says that you take the plan and add the action
at the end of it. So, you found the next
action, essentially. So, this part, that you
are talking about, it constructs plan in a
forward
direction, is taken care of by this operator,
essentially. The new plan is an old plan with
the action at the end. Initially, of course,
old plan will be empty. The moment you find
the first action that will go into it, and
then you find the next action that will go
into it,
and so on and so forth. So, this is a high
level algorithm for goal stack planning. Let
us
see how it actually, executes this. We will,
sort of, try to simulate for this small problem;
what goal stack planning does? Before I do
the simulation, let us make an observation
as
to what this is really, doing. It is taking
a set of goals; the pre conditions. Every
action
has a few pre conditions. So, it is a set
of goals, or set of sub goals, you might want
to
say, and push it on to the stack.
Then, it pushes each predicate of the pre
conditions on to the stack. We should do the
same thing here, essentially; push each predicate.
We will see the usefulness of this step
in the example that we see, but the important
thing to note here, is that it is taking a
set of
goals, or a set of sub goals; we use the term
goals and sub goals, interchangeably. The
initial goal is the only final goal. Everything
else is a sub goal, but we tend to use the
term goals, also for that, essentially. When
we have a set of goals to solve, for example,
in the pre conditions of an action, we put
them one by one into the stack, which means
.we have serializing the goals, sub goals,
essentially. So, this is saying; serializing
the sub
goals. In effect, we are saying, we will first
achieve one sub goal. Then, we will achieve
the next sub goal. Then, we will achieve the
next sub goal, and in that fashion,
essentially. So, we have, in some sense, if
you look at what A star did, it also said,
I am
breaking up a goal into sub goals, and I will
solve each of them independently. This is
doing that, but it is also imposing an order
in which, you will solve them. So, that is
why
we use a term; it is serializing the sub goals,
essentially.
.
So, our initial sub goals are those two, on
a b. I will just use, I will not use brackets,
just
to make it short; and on b d, and I will go
by stack downwards, and I hope that you get
used to that idea. When we pop stack, the
stack we will just put a line across, to say,
that
element has been popped. So, you must visualize
this stack going down. Let us say that
we put these in this order that we say, you
achieve on b d, and you achieve on a b. So,
this is the bottom of my stack, and my stack
is going like this. So, whatever done, I have
pushed the two, I have pushed the goal, which
is these two elements on to my stack, and
then, I pushed each predicate in some order.
So, we are not saying in what order; we
saying in some order; push them in to this
stack. This is a place where, you can, sort
of,
try to think of heuristics; what is the good
order of pushing things. So, this is a goal
given to us.
.I want to emphasize again, that considering
of actions is done in a backward fashion.
So,
we are now, only trying to see what actions
will achieve these goals, which is exactly
like, what backward state space does; except
for that backward state space says that
moment, for example, if you look at on a b,
it will say the last action must be stack
a b;
stack a on b. It starts constructing the plan
also, in a backward fashion. We will not do
that here; we will wait a little bit more
patiently, till we are sure that whenever,
we add
an action to a plan, its pre conditions are
true. Backward state space planning does not
look at pre conditions at all. It only looks
at the relevance of an action. It says if
an action
is relevant, it could be the last action,
and we saw that this leads to the trouble
that the
plan construction process is not sound. So,
we have on a b, now, and we go to the pop
cycle.
So, we push this out. This is gone and then,
we have this condition. It is a predicate
and it
also, happens to be true, in my given state;
you look at the value in a given state. It
is true
so, you do not do anything. Then, you pop
the next thing out on b d. Remember, this
was
popped out first, and now, we are talking
about on b d. So, let me, sort of, use an
arrow
to denote that we are considering this; just
for our sake. That is not true; on b d is
not true
in my, this state, and therefore, I push and
action, which will make this true. So, the
action that makes on b d true is stack BD.
So, let us say we use this arrow to depict
the
fact that we have pushing an action, essentially.
So, you push an action and we push the pre
conditions of the action. What are the pre
conditions of stack? I will you short forms;
h for holding; holding b, and clear d,
anything else; you remember these preconditions
for stack. You must be holding b, and d
must be clear, I think that is about it. Then,
I have pushed the individual actions. While,
we are doing this example, we will use a simple
heuristic, we will assume that the
holding action is the last action we want
to do; last goal we want to achieve. Remember,
these are two goals. If you can, just to recall,
this is a, let me put brackets here; that
we
want holding b to be true, and we want to
check, whether d is clear to be true, and
we
will push each individual action.
So, the first action, the first predicate
we push, will be the last predicate we will
check,
and let us use this heuristic between ourselves.
In practice, of course, an algorithm may
.have to back track and try the other option
or something like that. That we will check
for
holding b later. First, worry about; let us
worry about clear d, essentially. So, this
is a
push space. In a push space, everything gets
pushed; the action and its pre conditions,
and individual goals in the pre conditions.
We will refer to them also, as goals, because
this is a goal stack now, essentially. So,
we know push, we know pop this c d out.
That clear d is not true, but we must insert;
we must push an action, which will make
clear d true. So, this is a situation; c is
on d. So, we can use an action unstack. So
far, we
are doing backward search c d, and then, the
preconditions of unstack c d, which are that;
on c d must be true; and arm empty must be
true; and one more, clear c must be true.
Then, these individually, again, in some order,
let me choose arm empty as the last
predicate. Intuitively, I just want to reduce
some amount of extra work we want to do
here, but this is a matter of choosing heuristics.
So, everything is pushed here, like this.
Basically, this is a cycle; I have not mentioned
it here, but this whole thing is in to a
cycle here. Then, you go and pop this clear
c; now, clear c happens to be true in our
world. So, we do not do anything. On c d also,
happens to be true; on a also, happens
true, and it is not a surprise in particular
case; that the conjunct of all three on CD,
an
AE, an CC happens to be true.
So, we remove this from the stack, and now,
in the next pop, an action comes out, which
is this last part of the algorithm, which
says, if it is not predicate, it must be an
action,
and add action to the plan. So, this becomes
our first action; unstack c from d. The world
has changed now. The world is, I am holding
d. Whenever, I look at a predicate, I must
look at this world. Now, you will notice that
when I am talking about actions, I am going
in the forward direction. This was the given
start state, and this is the first action
that will
be there; part of my plan. The first action
will be unstack c from d, essentially. So,
everything that we do here will be sound,
essentially.
That also, does not lose sight of the fact,
that we are considering the actions in a goal
directed fashion. We started off by saying
that what is necessary for making on a b,
on a
b true, on b d true, and then, we said to
make on b d true, you must do stack b d, and
then, we discovered that to do stack b d,
we need to do clear d, and to do clear d,
we can
do unstack c d, and we find that we are able
to unstack cd, and so, we put that as a first
.action. So, this signifies the plan. So,
that is gone now, from the stack. Then, it
has got
holding b as a next action. Holding b is not
true in this world; you are holding c,
essentially. Let me grow the stack from here,
that when I pop holding b out, I am forced
to insert an action. So, I have a choice here.
Notice that to make holding b true, I can
use
an action; unstack b from something, or I
can use the action; pick up b, essentially.
We
will assume that we have some non determinism
going on here, or you could look at the
state and try to decide, which of those two
actions is a relevant action? So, we will
assume that somehow, we are used pick up b.
So, the stack is now going like that, and
along with pick up b, the actions, which are
arm
empty, and on table b, and clear b. So, let
us say I look at them in this order or in
the
same order; on table b and clear b. So, I
have pushed this action and it is preconditions.
Then, I pop the top of the stack. Remember,
the top of the stack is actually, at the lower
end of our list; I have popped this. Clear
b is not true in the world that I have here.
So, I
must insert an action, which is unstack something
from b, but we will assume that we
have figured out that it has got to be a from
b, and the preconditions for that are on a
b,
and arm empty and clear a. So, let us say
arm empty, on a b and clear a; clear a is
true.
So, I can remove it from the, pop it from
the stack. On a b is also true. So, I can
pop that
from the stack, but arm empty is not true,
because this is the world that I am looking
at. I
am moving forward from here. I am holding
c.
So, I must make arm empty to make arm empty,
I insert an action, put down c and the
preconditions for that are holding c, and
that is all. So, you pop this and you pop
this, and
this becomes a second action; that you have
put down c. So, now, the world looks like
a,
which is the world. I have done two actions.
One action I have done is unstack c from d,
and then, I was in this state. Then, I have
put down c, then I am in this state; that
is a
second action. Then comes this conjunct, on
a b is true here, arm empty is true here,
clear
a is true here. So, I can remove this, and
then, I can pop this; this becomes the third
action. Now, the world looks like, you are
holding a. The rest is all on
the table. So, this
is that.
Let me label these states. This is a state
after action one. This is a state after action
two.
This is a state after action three, which
is unstacked a b. Then, the next thing on
top of
.stack is, on table b. I pop that and I see
that is true in this state. Then, arm empty
is not
true. So, I have to achieve arm empty. Let
me start here. I need, I remove arm empty
of
course, and then, say put down. So, I am holding
a. I need put down a. Again, there is a
choice, which I am, sort of, skinning over
here. The choice is really, that either, I
put a
down, or I put it on b, or put it on c, or
put it on d, essentially. May be, you can
do a little
bit more sophisticated reasoning here, but
I am, sort of, just to illustrate this, I
am just
saying that we have something, like a nondeterministic
choice happening, which means
magically, we are making the correct choice;
this is to put down.
For which, you must be holding a. So, you
can do this, and this becomes the fourth
action. After the fourth action, everything
is on the table
and the arm empty. So, I must
go back by a stack I have; I find this conjunct
here; arm is empty, on table t b, and clear
b; everything is true. So, I pop that, then
this becomes my fifth action; pickup b. So,
at
the end of fifth action, I am holding b, and
a c d are on the table. So, this is gone from
my stack, and this is where, we had taken
off. Now, you are holding b and clear d. You
can see that in that fifth state, both are
true; you are holding b and clear d is true.
This
goes off. Now, we have the sixth action coming
out. The moment an action comes out of
the stack, we know that it is applicable.
Why, because we have just popped their
preconditions; pre conditions must be true,
essentially. So, it must be applicable. So,
this
is the sixth action; stack b on d. So, this
is how it looks
and arm is empty.
Now, observe that in a manner of speaking,
we started off with two sub goals; on b d
and
on a b. We decided to do on a b first, and
in this case, it was already true in this
state. So,
we do not have to do anything, but as you
can see that was a right choice, essentially.
If I
have to achieve, if we look at the goal state,
which is that a must be on b, b must be on
d;
you can see that the way to achieve the goal
is to first, achieve on b d, and then, put
a on
top of the stack that you have, tower that
have constructed, essentially. We choose an
opposite order, and we ended up finding a
plan, which is the six step plan, which says
that you unstack c from d. So, this is the
state. Then, you put down c. Then, you unstack
a from b. Then, put down a. Then, you pick
up b, and stack it on to d, which is what,
this
did, essentially.
So, on the surface, it looks like we have
achieved both these goals, but if you look
at this
.state, when we achieved the second goal,
which is on b d, which is what we were doing
all this while, and as a result of which,
on b d is true here. We have undone the first
goal
that we had done, essentially. My first goal
was that a should be on b. We started off
with a on b, but by the time, we finished
on b d that, a now, lying on the table. So,
you
can see this is the reason why, we have added
both the conjunct of the goals as well as
individual goals. So, we are saying we want
achieve this conjunct, but we will do it
individually, will serialize the sub goals;
we did this; then, we did this. Then, we found
that in this sequence, we, somehow ended up,
undoing some of the goals. So, when I
popped this out, I will find that this is
not true.
So, I will insert both the goals again, into
the stack. So, let us say if we inserted in
the
same order here; that I insert on b d and
on a b first; first, on b d, then on a b,
which
means I am first doing on a b and then, I
am doing on b d, as I did in the last time,
essentially, but now my starting state has
changed. That is my starting state. So, I
will
not go into the stack, because we do not have
a space left on the board, but you can
imagine that to achieve on a b, we will do
the same thing; stack a on b. To stack a on
b,
you must be holding a. To be holding a, you
must pick up a. So, you pick up a and stack
a on b; these two actions, you will end up
doing. So, you will achieve on a b.
Once you achieved on b, you will go back to
on b d, but this time, on b d is already true,
because in that state, as you can see, it
is already true. Only thing you are doing
is in the
seventh and the eight step, you are picking
up a from here, and stacking it on to b. So,
this is a final state that you are looking
at; a is on b and b is on d, essentially.
So, both the
sub goals are true, and then, I am finally,
able to pop the goal, and that is a terminating
criteria. If I can pop the goal and come up
an empty stack; that means, I found a plan
for
solving my problem, essentially. To emphasize
what goal stack planning does, it does, it
considers plans in a backward fashion. It
looks for actions in a backward fashion by
putting the goals that you want achieve, on
to the top of stack, starting with an empty
stack of push, and it always, looks at the
goals set on the top of the stack, which means,
it
is doing backward reasoning, but when it comes
to constructing a plan, when it comes to
saying that this is my first, these are my
actions; it starts off by choosing the first
action
first.
.So, if you look at this plan, this is a first
action. Even, when you want to actually,
implement the plan, you want to first, unstack
a from b, sorry, unstack c from d; put it
down on the table. So, it is doing, it is
constructing the plan like a forward state
space
planner. It is looking for a plan like a backward
state space planner. So, it is taking the
advantage of both the things. It is only focusing
on the goal by looking for a plan, or it is
making sure that when it is construct a sequence
of actions, it is a valid plan, because it
is
doing it in the forward fashion. In the process,
it ends up serializing the goals, but we
have to be extra sure that we do not disturb
the goal; so that, we add this whole thing
or
doing this extra thing, all over again, essentially.
Now, it turns out, and I will leave this as
a small excise for you, is that if I had
considered them in the opposite order, which
says that first, do on b d, then, on a b,
which inside inverted the order in which,
I push up in to the stack. First, I would
have
done on b d, which amounts to everything that
we have done here, and I would have
ended up in that state. Then, I would have
done on a b, and I would have just picked
up
the a; this a, and put it on to b. So, there
is an order I can choose in which, I am not
undoing the work done for the solving the
previous goal. This particular order, I am
undoing the work. Of course, I did not have
to do any work to achieve on ab, because it
was already true, but imagine that, a was
on the table here, or something like this,
and
then, I picked up a, and put on to b. Now,
I would have undone the work that I have,
I
am doing, essentially. So, there is an order
in some cases, essentially.
..
Now, interestingly, it was shown by a guy,
called Sussman, that it is not always possible
that such an order may be found. What order
am I talking about? I am talking about an
order of serializing sub goals; so that, there
is no disruption of previously achieved sub
goals, essentially. So, this particular example
is known as Sussman’s anomaly. If you
just search on web, you will find this example.
The interesting thing about this is that he
shows that, this kind of planning will not
always work; well, work in the sense, without
doing this extra work, essentially; because
we are serializing the sub goals, we also
call this as linear planning. I will achieve
one
goal, then I will achieve the second goal,
then I will achieve the third goal, and so
on; I
will solve goals in a linear fashion, essentially.
So, I serialize the goals, essentially. What
Sussman showed was that there are examples
where, you just cannot serialize the sub
goals. The example is quite a simple one.
This is a start state; c is on a and a is
on b. The
goal state is a on b on c, which is very similar
to that, essentially. Let me just, for the
sake of illustration, call this d, to make
it identical to the goal state that we just
looked at,
which means, this whole exercise that we did,
will also hold for this. Of course, except
for the start state is different, but the
main point is that I cannot think of two goals,
achieve on a b, and achieve on b d. Goal stack
planning is forcing me to serialize the sub
goals in some order, and what sussmans showed
was that you cannot serialize the sub
.goals.
Let us see what happens. So, let us say you
first, achieved on a b. I am not going to
the
process, but we are just. To achieve on a
b, what will you have to do? You will have
to
pick up unstack this d from a, put it down
somewhere, then we will have pick up a, and
stack it on to b; these four actions will
achieve on a b, and goal stack planning will
do
that. You should try it as an exercise. So,
a will be on b, and d will be on the; and
arm is
empty, and then; that means, you have first,
done on a b, then you have to do on b d.
Now, if you do achieve on b d, you can see
something very similarly, happening. You
will unstack a from a; unstack a from this
stack, put it down from the table, pickup
b and
stack it on to d.
So, what would you get is d.
What we have shown in this example? As an
exercise, you
should fill in the details and show how block,
this goal stack planning will actually, do
this? When you first, achieve this, then you
achieved this. So, when you achieved this,
this is true. When you achieved this, this
is true, but this is a goal, and this is not
a goal
state, which means, to achieve this goal on
a b and on b d, I cannot, at least, this order
is
not correct of doing things. Of course, I
can do extra work; pick up this a and put
it on d,
but that means, I am somehow missing the correct
order, if there is one. What Sussman
shows was that there is no correct order.
So, let us try the other order.
You can achieve on b d first, which is very
simple. You just pick up b and stack on to
d.
So, you have achieved on b d. Then, you achieve
on a b.
What happens; you have to
unstack b, put it down; unstack d, put it
down; pick up a, put it on to b. So, you would
get a b d. Again, you can see the other order
also, does not do the task. None of these
two
paths leads to the goal, essentially. Of course,
you can do extra work; that is a different
matter, but we cannot take these two goals
individually, and say, I will solve the first
one, then I will solve the second one, and
my task is done. I could do it here, if I
change
the order of this goal. If I have done on
b d first, and then, on a b, then I would
have
solved the task in a serial order, essentially.
What Sussman showed was that there are
these non-serializable sub goals, essentially.
That in many problems, goals are not
serialized with.
.So, that is a problem with this kind of planning,
which we will also, call linear planning,
because we are serializing the goals and saying,
I will do this first; and I will do this first;
and so on. Of course, this is something that
we have observed earlier, in other situations.
For example, when we talk about solving the
rubrics cube, then if you say I will do the
top surface first, and then, the middle layer
and then, the lower surface and then, by the
time you finished the top surface and while,
you are doing the middle layer, in the
middle, you upset the top layer.
Of course, those who know the solution know,
how to get it back, but that is like doing
an extra work, essentially. So, rubrics cube
is the typical example of a goal, which is
fundamentally, not serializable, like this
problem, which means that there is no way
that
you can achieve the first goal, and not have
to achieve it later again, essentially. Such
problems are called non serializable sub goals,
essentially. So, in the next class, we will
look at an approach, which some people call
as non-linear planning, which allows us the
possibility of solving this kind of a problem,
optimally. What do I mean by that? That, if
you just think about this problem, this Sussman’s
anomaly; the best way to solve it
follows.
You unstack d, put it on the table; that is
two actions. Then you pick up b, put it, stack
it
on to d; that is two more actions. Then, you
pick up a, stack it on to b; that is six actions,
but neither of these paths is going to give
a plan with six actions. Of course, they will
even eventually, achieve the goal, but this
will have to do two more actions here, and
this
will have to do at least four more actions
here, essentially. So, I cannot find optimal
plan,
essentially. In the next class, we will look
at an approach where, the possibility of
finding a optimal plan is kept open, essentially.
You can see that; to find an optimal plan,
you have switch between goals, in some sense,
that when you start by putting d on top of
a b. For example, when you start to do this,
then when you put d; what you do? You
unstack d, and put it on the table, and you
want to achieve a on ab. Then, you want to
certainly, realize that if you stack a on
to b, you would not be able stack b on to
d. So,
you abandon that goal of achieving on a b,
and switched to the other goal of achieving
on
b d, in which case, of course, you will find
optimal plan, but goal stack planning, because
it serializes the sub goals. It says, I will
completely solve my first goal and then, go
to the
second goal, is not able to do that, essentially.
.So, we will stop here, and in the next class,
we will take up this non-linear planning.
.