So, we are looking at rule based systems power
changing systems, and now we want to
look at the inference engine.
.
So, the inference engine is basically a program
which works in three phases. The first
phase is called match, and what it takes as
input is a set of rules and some data and
produces a set of matching rules which in
their terminology is called the conflict set.
It
produces the data. So, let us first see what
is match is doing.
..
So, if you have these rules. Mainly notice
that we have written this two rules in the
last
class. This rule has three conditions 1, 2,
3. This rule has four conditions, this is
1, this is
2, and 3, and 4. One of them is in negative
condition. So, essentially a rule is a collection
of patterns and actions. As far as matching
is concerned, we are only interested in
patterns. So, we can think of this as P 11,
P 12, P 13. So, that is for the first rule.
Then, P
21, P 22, P 23, P 24. So, for this rule for
example and then, so on.
So, P K R or whatever, depending on how many
rules you have and how many patterns
each rules has essentially. So, that is rule
memory and when Simon annual for talking
about this kind of problems. They would associates
it is a long term memory. So, they,
so, basically rules capture the problem solving
solver knowledge essentially, which is
always there with the problem solver so, you
can think of it is long term memory.
Whereas the actual problem that you have trying
to solve sets in a memory which we call
as working memory or WM which is also ordered.
So, you have this data elements which
we call working M E 1. So, this is the data
item 1 then 2 and so on essentially.
Now, remember that the actions on the right
hand side of rules, I allow to delete data
which means they might delete some working
memory element. So, some things might
vanish from the way. But initially let us
assume that we have some capital N number
of
working memory elements. Now, this can be
thought of as a time stamp, which says
.when was this working memory element created
and as far as we are concerned time is
just an ordering. So, this is the first element,
second element, third element.
We will see that this plays a role in the
control of the execution essentially. So,
we can
also think of these as short term memory.
If you want to think of this as how we solve
problems essentially. So, we have these two
memories, one is the working memory
which contains is working memory elements,
and we saw examples of that. The other is
the set of rules where each rule consists
of a set of patterns. So, this rule has 3
patterns,
this rules has 4 patterns and so on and so
forth. And these are the examples of such
rules
essentially.
Now, for a rule to match, now the first task
is to match which means look at all the rules,
look at all the data and compute which rule
matches with which data. So, if you look at
this first rule for example, it says that
to play any card it does not specify which
card to
play. Now, if you a just starting the game
and let us assume that this rule here. So,
let us
say this is, this one of the working memory
element is this here. So, let a say this one
is
turn to play S. So, let us say S is a name
of a player. So, it is S turn to play. So,
there is a
piece of data, here there is a pattern which
says turn to some variable name. So, this
will
match with this, which with this data essentially.
And let us say, this element is suit to play,
let us say club. So, this is a working memory
element which will match that pattern, second
pattern that suit in play, in play. This is
a
constant. The data will only have constants,
variables are only in the patterns and if
a
pattern has a variable it means it can match
anything essentially. Whether this was clubs
or diamonds or hearts that rule would still
match essentially. And then look at this third
element that player P, in this case P is S
has some cards of, let us say this player
has 6
cards of clubs. So, there would be 6 card,
this player is S and suit is clubs.
Let us say name is 3. So, let us say he has
3 of clubs and he has a 7 of clubs and the
9 of
clubs and the 8 of clubs and jack of clubs
and the queen of clubs. So, let us say this
player has got 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6 cards of clubs
essentially. That is effective and 6 working
memory element in which says and each memory
element is saying that there is 3 of
clubs it is held by S. So, let us say S stand
for south essentially. Now, you can see that
this rule, the first rule will have 6 instances,
for each of these 6 cards 1 instance of that
rule will fire will match.
.So, 1 instance will says yes it is south’s
turn to play, the suit in play is clubs and
he has
got the 3 of clubs. Another instance of that
rule will say yes it is south turns to play,
suit
in plays clubs and he has got a 7 of clubs.
So, like this for each of this cards, 1 instance
of the rule will fire and they may be of course
many rules in the system and each will
have some instances, it should ready to fire
essentially.
So, the task of match this first part of the
inference engine is to compute this set of
instances of rules and the corresponding matching
data and put it into this set which they
call is a complex set. So, this is rule. So,
let us say I call this rule 1 and this is
rule 2 then,
my conflict set will have something like.
.
Rule 1 matches with first, second and third
working memory element. first, second, third.
Let us say this is rule 1 another entry into
my working memory element into my conflicts
at would be rule 2 matches with 1, 2 and let
us say 4. Another one would be rule sorry
the rule 1, rule 1 matches with 1, 2 and 5.
Let us say where 3, 4 and 5 are those these
element.
So, this is the third one, the fourth one,
and the fifth one. This is saying that this
is an
instance of rule 1 which is. So, these are
the times stamps we are using from that
working memory. It is matching working memory
number 1 and 2 and 3. This one is
matching the same rule in matching 1 and 2
and 4. This one is matching 1 and 2 and 5.
And likewise for rule 2 and rule 3 and whatever
rules we have this set is called the
.conflict set and the objective of the first
phase of the algorithm which is the match
phase
is to compute this conflict set. Why do you
call it conflict set?
It is like each rules clambering to say I
will, I will execute, I will execute and so
on. So,
there is a conflict between all these rules.
But you can execute only one rule at a time
assuming that you are talking of sequential
system here. So, people talk of parallel
systems in which parallel rule firing takes
place, but you will not get into that here.
What
is the complexity of these task? How difficult
is it to compute this conflict set in terms
of
how many operations, how many comparison you
have to do?
So, the brute force algorithm would take the
first pattern which is P 1 1 which means the
first pattern of the first rule and try matching
it again solve these things. Then, it will
take
the second pattern of the first rule and try
matching it with all these things, then the
third
pattern of the first rule try matching it
with all of this then it will go to the second
rule. I
mean here it you do not have to distinguish
between rules. We have just a set of patterns.
So, each pattern in this it will try to match
with each of this and at the end of it, it
will
compute the conflicts set let us keep this
in mind.
So, this conflicts set is a set of rules which
is ready to execute. So, we use a term execute
or fire. So, rule is ready to fire essentially.
We keep this conflict set to step which is
called resolve
and it work it does is it select a rule. So,
there is another program, another
module to the program which looks at this
conflict set and picks one of them to fire
essentially. Now obviously, what this resolve
needs is strategy. What is your problem
solving strategy given that many rules of
ready to execute which rule should be select
to
execute actually essentially.
..
Now, there are different kinds of strategies.
So, one strategy which is called lax in
((Refer Time. terminologies or lexicon graphic
strategy. It says that choose a rule
that matches or that makes a maximum number
of test and what do I mean by test. By
test I mean each individual these things.
.
So, for example, I will match the class name
with the working memory element that is
one tests. Then, I will match the value of
this attribute to play which the working
memory element that is the second test. Third,
fourth, fifth, sixth, seventh, eighth. So,
.this rule has eight tests that it is doing,
this rules has a little bit more tests than
it is doing.
So, the lax strategy says that choose a rule
that makes the maximum number of tests
essentially. So, what is the strategy essentially
doing?
.
It is saying specificity. In other words,
it is saying choose the most specific rule
which
matches. Now, if you look at this two examples
that we have.
.
In these two rules, one rule is saying that,
if you have to play a card of suit S and if
you
have a card of suite S play that. This rule
is saying, if you have to play a card of suite
S
.and if you have many cards of suite S, then
pick the one which is the highest or highest
rank card and play that card. Now, obviously
given any data that I have so, for example,
I said that we have these 6 cards. So, this
will have rank 3, this will have rank 4, and
so
on and so forth. Both rules are matching,
both rules 6 instances of this rule will match
and 1 instance of this rule will match.
So, there are 7 rules which are trying to
tell me which card to play essentially. So,
6 rules
are saying any of these cards and the seventh
rule is specifically saying this card queen,
which is of highest rank why because we have
said that the rank of this card is r then
there is no card held by this player whose
rank is higher or higher than r which means
the
the number is lower than r. So, this rule
is more specific than this rule. So, this
conflicts
resolution strategy at as it is called which
is specificity will choose the second rule
essentially or if the second rule matches
little.
So, you can see that this strategy allows
you to implement what we sometimes call as
default reasoning which is you like many rules
essentially. So, it is like saying one rule
says if you are hungry go to the mess and
eat essentially. The other rule says if you
are
hungry and you have lots of money and you
do not have any exam tomorrow then go out
to a restaurant an eat essentially. Now, the
first rule is less specific than the second
rule.
The second rule requires many conditions to
be true that you should have money you
should be free and that kind of stuff. If
both rule matches than the second rule would
be
selected, if only if the second rule does
not match that means you do not have money,
or
you have an exam tomorrow then that will not
match and then only the first rule will
match and that will execute. So, you can see
that the more specific the rule the greater
we
would like it to reselected and specificity
say exactly that choose a rule, which is making
more number of tests out of the competing
set of rules essentially.
..
Another strategy is looking at the time stamp
which is called recency. It says choose a
rule that matches a most recent data
and what do you mean by most recent data?
Is
basically this time stamp that we have said
which has the highest time stamping. So, if
every rule will match certain number of elements
remember for example, this is my thing
1, 2 and 3, this is my thing 1, 2 and 4 and
so on and so forth.
Whichever rule is matching the latest data
choose that essentially. What is the intention
behind this strategy? It is to kind of maintain
of flow of reasoning essentially. So, just
imagine you are doing theorem proving, you
are proving something, you have proved
some lambda 1 then, you want to use lambda
1 to prove lambda 2 and this rule will allow
you to do that because lambda 1 which is whatever
that lambda is could be the latest
entry into a database and if a rule is matching
that, that will automatic get selected. So,
it
sort of helps in maintain chain of reasoning.
..
There is a first strategy which is called
mea, which stands for may be at some point
we
will a discuss this, means ends which is due
to a Simon and Noel and it essentially
combines these two by saying recency of pattern
one and if there is still a conflict then
specificity. So, I should write else. So,
by this I mean that you are only looking at
the
recency of the pattern one and pattern one
is the first pattern in a every rule essentially.
So, this is the first pattern, this is the
first pattern, this is the first pattern and
so on.
So, the first element which follows after
the rule, look at the recency of that and
as you
can see all these are same, but some of the
rule may have higher recency and use that
essentially. If there is still conflict that
is more than one rule which is in contention
then
use specificity to choose between them essentially.
So, that is why I have written else
specificity. So, what is the intention behind
this? Essentially, you can partition your
rule
sets into, set into groups which will solve
particular problems essentially. So, let us
say
you are making dinner essentially. Then, you
might have a set of rules let say to how to
make sambar and another set of rules how to
make subjee and so on and so forth.
Now, if you in each of this rules, if you
have the first element which says something
like
making sambar or making subjee or making chapati
or making rice, then the moment you
create a context for saying, okay now I am
making rice then you will add that data
element saying making rice that will become
the most recent and all the rules which are
concern with making rice they will get priority
essentially.
.And that is done by the fact that recency
of the first pattern. The first pattern setting
the
context, making rice, making tea or whatever
essentially. The moment you said this is
my task I am doing only those rules which
have that as the first pattern will be in
contention the rest will not come into play.
So, you can see it is a combination of these
two things. It helps you keep focus to what
you are doing, but it also tries to see which
rules are best and so on.
.
Now, one more thing is refractoriness, this
simply says that a same rule cannot fire with
the same data again essentially. So, this
comes from some neurobiological studies which
says that, you know when neurons are firing
then once a neuron gets certain set of input
they can only fire once with that input and
then there is a period of refractoriness in
which they do not, they are not active at
all essentially. But from our point of view,
we
can see that we do not want the same rule
to fire again and again and again essentially.
So, let us say you are doing a classification
task or let us say now the task is to classify
students into grades essentially. So, you
have said if a student has got more than 95
and
he has done all the assignments then give
an a grade. And this let us say, this rule
get
selected and it fires. So, you have already
done with the task of giving the a grade or
classifying the student in as a student. You
do not want that rule to fire again essentially
with the same piece of data.
.And that is what refractoriness says that
every rule can only fire once with that piece
of
data. Which means of course, with the same
time stamps in the working memory if you
were to delete some data and add the same
data again with a new time stamp then it
could fire, that is a different story.
.
And then so, its selects a rule and gives
it to a module call execute and what is execute
does is to applies the actions
of selected rule. So, remember that this resolve
module
resolves the conflicts between all these rules
and it says this is the rule that is going
to
execute and this execute module basically
takes a rule and takes its right hand side
which
is the actions and in and sort of execute
to those actions.
So, remember what was, what was the actions
thinks like make or delete and so on
essentially. So, what is this doing? It changes
the working memory. The effect of execute
is to change the working memory. It may add
some new data and it will deletes some old
data from the working memory.
So, now you have a new working memory and
now you have to go back all the way and
do the match all over again. So, this is the
algorithm which the, this in some sense a
high
level algorithm. Actually, you do implement
it like this. We will see how it is done,
but
you can think of it as doing like this. That
first is a match phase, which looks at all
the
rules and all the data and by that mean everything
in the working memory and creates
.this set or this list of rules and the corresponding
times stamps of the data elements they
are matching.
Then resolve looks at this set and picks one
element out of that and says this is the rule
that we will execute and then when execution
happens, the right hand of the side of the
rule may make some changes in the working
memory. So, some elements are deleted,
some may be added and then we go back to matching
again and selecting a rule and so.
So, we keep doing this till some termination
criteria which could be that either the
conflict sets becomes empty at some point,
which means no rules are matching all we
have an explicit halt statement somewhere
in the program which says if you see a certain
pattern that then you halt and execute.
So, let us now discuss the complexity of this
whole process. What can we do to improve
this essentially? Now, empirically people
have found which is the hardest part of this,
in
terms of complexity, which one will take the
most amount of computing time match or
resolve or execute. which one will take the
most amount of time? Look at the complexity
of each of the task, look at these tasks,
execute what is it doing? So, in this example
the
right hand side has only one action which
is to add one working memory element with
this particular this one. So, you can see
it is a little bit of work.
What does resolve have to do? Resolve has
to look at this entire set of matching rules
of
the conflict set and applied a chosen strategy
whichever the strategy we have chosen, to
select one of these from this and what does
match have to do? Match has to look at the
entire set of rules or the entire set of patterns
we have compare it with the entire working
memory and try to find out what is the conflict
set it is. So obviously, this is a largest
task, the number of comparison we have to
do if you have k rules and each rule as let
us
say p patterns. So, k into p patterns totally
and each pattern may have a certain number
of
tests essentially and then, all these working
memory elements. So, with each you have to
find.
Remember that you want to find every rule
that can possibly execute or every rule that
matches. It is not that you are if you find
one or two rules match you are done. All the
rules with match, the complete set must be,
this conflict set must be exhaustive. It must
consist all possible rules which are matching.
So, this is really the most time consuming
part of the algorithm and people have observed
that match takes up something like 80
.percent of computation time. So, just like
you know they say in an industry that most
of
the time of computing is spent in sorting
for example, most of the time in power
changing inference engine is spent in matching
essentially.
You could have other strategies which I have
not mentioned here. If you know how
prolog works. Prolog will take the first rule
with matches. So, it sort of goes down the
program and the first rule which matches it
applies essentially. It does not compute all
possible matches and then selects one. So,
that is a different strategy that is the,
something like order of rules or something
like that. Here we are considering rules to
be
floating in some space and there is no order
and any rule is as good as any other rule.
So,
what Charles Forgy. So, if you look up some
of these terms either ((Refer Time.)
Charles Forgy or this algorithm which he developed
which is called the rete algorithm.
.
Which is what you want to study, but I think
you do not have enough time today so, we
will do it in the next class. Charles Forgy
device the rate algorithm in 1979, his phd
theses at a you and subsequently it became
a commercial product. It is available in any
these business rule management engine you
talk about, it uses some variation of rate
for
matching rules because it is really the hardest
part of doing that essentially. So, this is
off
course available to us that we have a paper
written by Charles Forgy and you can find
it
on the net which talks about this is rete
algorithm.
.And then he went on to develop algorithm
called rete 2 and from there onwards they
stop
disclosing their algorithm to the public because
they have commercial interest. They had
this company which was selling that algorithm
and did not want to diverse this create
secret that this say.
.
And eventually he wrote on algorithm call
rete NT. For those of you who are familiar
with windows will see the influence of windows,
so just around that time windows NT
came, it was a new thing, and so, this rete
NT was new thing. This rete NT is suppose
to
be 500 times faster than these original rete
algorithm, which means it takes 500 times
less time to the same match essentially. And
you can see that the great improvement
instead of having to wait of few minutes,
you might have to just wait a second for your
match to be done essentially. Unfortunately
we do not know the algorithm, we will only
look at the rete algorithm.
Rete itself, the word rete is a latin word
which means the net essentially. And what
this
rete algorithm does is to, it compiles the
rules into a network which we will see in
the
next class to improve upon the efficiency
of match. So, what we want to do today now
is
to observe where does the inefficiency come
from in matching these things. There are
two sources of inefficiency and can you think
about then. See one is the following, that
we have many rules and each rule has some
number of patterns and those patterns have
to be match with data. Now, if you look at
that two rules that I have written.
..
We have these pattern, we have these pattern
turn to play p. So, it was match a working
memory element whose class name is turn and
whose to play attribute must match
something, there must be something in the
these thing. It could be south, north, east,
west
to use the terminology from which. This rule
also has a same pattern so, this one could
be here for example, and this one could be
here. Likewise as you can see the second
pattern is also the same suit in play S, suit
in play S. So, this and this are the same.
Why should we spend computation time doing
this match separately? Why not once and
for all save as the this is match, then we
can tell this rule there is matching also
tell this
rule that is pattern is matching. So, if you
can reduce that there will say sometime
essentially. Not only that in this third pattern
certain things are common. So, card, suit,
play these things. These also has card, player,
suit, name. It has a additional thing called
rank, but at least for those 3 tests or 4
tests, we can share those 4 tests.
So, the first thing that we would like to
do is to share the tests the different rules
are
doing and different patterns are doing. So,
that as far as possible each test we make
only
ones or each pattern will match only ones.
So, if you match this pattern ones and then
both the rules come to know about it, then
we are saving time essentially. So, that is
one.
So, this is one source of inefficiency or
one avenue for increasing the efficiency of
your
match algorithm.
.But there is another which will occur to
you if you look at what this execute is doing.
What is this execute doing? It is making some
new working memory elements or it is
deleting of you working memory elements. So,
in a large working memory of this kind.
.
Let me rub this out. So, what execute my do?
It might send a signal that this is to be
deleted, so I will use minus sign for deletion
here. It might say this to be deleted and
it
might say new one to be added. So, typically
a rule when it executes it will delete may
be
a couple of element from the working memory,
at may add a couple of elements to the
working memory.
Now, what is it doing? After it executes its
goes back to the match and at least if you
look at it from the brute force point of view,
it is going to match all the rules with all
the
data all over again. Does it need to do that?
Now, if you look at this first rule here,
which
says play any card, it is adding one working
memory element essentially. And let us say
I had a 100 rules for playing cards and all
of them I have done the match in the previous
cycle and all of the above matching that say
2, 3 instances. So I have 3 or 400 instances
of rules which I match in the last cycle.
What I have done when I executed this rule.
Let us say this was executive for some reason
or this one is executive for some reason,
yeah I have added 1 working memory element
to my these thing. So, why should I match
those other 99 rules again. In this particular
example, I am only adding 1 working
memory element and assuming that those 99
rules do not have negative clauses. Even if
.they have why should I do that match all
over again essentially. Rule number 2, rule
number 3, rule number 7 they were matching
with some data which is nothing to do with
this 4 data elements that we are talking about.
May be some, may be the some rule was matching
a data here and data here and data
here. If it was matching in the last cycle,
it will match in the, this cycle as well.
So,
essentially what the rete net does. So, what
is the match doing? Match is taking rules
and
data which is working memory and producing
the conflicts set.
.
The rete net is an algorithm or the rete algorithm
is a algorithm which uses a structure
call the rate net or let me just a use algorithm
here, takes as input changes in working
memory which is what this execute action is
doing. This change is in working memory,
its changing, is deleting a few elements and
adding a few elements. This algorithm rete
algorithm takes changes in working memory
and gives you changes in the conflicts set.
So, compare this with this thing this match
here. What match is doing is taking the full
working memory, taking all the rules and producing
the complex set and it is doing this
every time we are going through this cycle.
Every time a rule fires it go the does match
all over again or the area algorithm does
is says tell me what are the changes in the
working memory element and it computes that
as a result what are the changes in the
complex set. So obviously, as you can imagine
this is must less work as compare to
.doing the full match all over again essentially.
We only have to see the effect of these
changes into the conflict set.
May be, if I have because of adding this may
be because of deleting this some rule which
was firing matching earlier will not match
now. So, I should able to know that
essentially. Likewise if I have add this some
new rules may come into the conflict set
and may be some rules might even go out of
the conflict set, if there was a negative
clause here. I should be able to capture that
essentially.
So, in the next class we will look at this
rete net, which is basically a sort of a
discrimination net or you can some people
are use other terms like many sorted network
or it is a generalization of a trice structure,
but basically it is a network which
discriminates between different kinds of data
essentially. You might even think of it as
a
extension of binary search tree, which this
discriminates between only one kind of data
which is numbers. So, its sends you down one
branch or the other.
So, same principle holds except that this
is of multifaceted data and we have different
kind of test which are being. So, we even
have a test which says that the rank is less
than
r or rank not equal to r or something like,
things like that essentially. So, all those
tests
should be will together. So, will take this
up in the next class which is on Friday and
complete this part of the this unit.
.