So, we are looking at logic and listening
and we are looking at propositional logic,
so
just to do a quick recap.
.
.We first look at the language
and the language is made up set of propositional
symbols I
do not remember what the symbol we use anyways.
So, something like this accountably,
if a set of atomics symbols and each of these
symbols stands for a sentence and we do
not particularly care about its stands for
essentially. Associated with this set of symbols
is a function v which map p this symbols to
set let say true and false basically a two
value set which as far as we are concerns
will stands for true sentences and false
sentences. Then, we have connectives
and or not imply and so on, which gives lies
to a
set of sentences, so we will call them a set
of formulas.
Let us call set f, so we could construct compound
sentences from the atomic using the
logic connectives and associated with this
set of formulas is a function with maps f
to the
same set true or false. So, this side is the
syntax and that side some sentence semantics
of
this thing and what the semantics captures
here is that how do this logical connectives
connect the or influence the meaning of compound
sentences essentially and that is given
by this. So, if you remember for example,
a sentence like p and q would map to true
if
both p map to true and q map to true and so
on. So, now, given a sentence f belonging
to
f or formula f belonging to f, so for example,
you might say something like p and q
implies r or not.
Then, p implies some such formula re arbitrary
formula, which can be constructed using
this logical connectives p q r and s are the
atomic symptoms and implies of or not
implies other connectives. Essentially, we
can find a valuation for this if you know
what
the valuation for p q r and s is, so if you
know for example, the p is true, let us say
every
p q r s everything is true and this true implies
true or false implies true. So, this whole
thing will evaluated to true essentially,
so this was the notion of truth this is the
notion of
truth. It says that given a sentence f belonging
to this set of synthesis there we can
compute whether the sentences true or not
given a sentence and given a valuation v.
For all the atomic sentences, we can compute
whether the given sentence match to true
or false essentially and I do not remember
whether we discussed this, but in general
a
formula can fall into three categories one
is a valid formula. So, we say f is valid
if for
every valuation we that we can think of Val
f is equal to true, so you are familiar with
this notion I just repeating this. So, when
you say for every valuation v essentially
we are
talking about the truths table for the formula.
So, this formula for example, we can
construct the truth table which will have
16 rows because there are 4 propositional
.atomic sentences, which means p can be true
or false q can be true or false, r can be
true
or false or and s can be true or false.
For each of these 16 valuations or each of
the sixteen rows in the truth table if the
last
column is label with true then we label then
we say the sentence is valid. So, a sentences
is valid if is true for all possible valuations
a trivial sentence which is valid is for
example, p or not p this is of course there
is only one variable, but this is a valid
sentence
also known as the tautology always true.
.
We say that the sentence is satisfiable or
the formula satisfiable if for some valuation
v
this is true the same thing accept that instead
of every v use term some. If you can find
at
least one valuation which will make this true
then that sentence is satisfiable for
example, I might say p implies q 1 simple
sentence not always true for example, if p
true
and q false this is false. I can find valuations
of p and q usually make this true if there
are
3 valuations which will make this true such
sentences is also sometimes call contingent
sentences. So, one is valid the second is
satisfiable or contingent and a third is
unsatisfiable.
Here, we replace this with no if there is
no valuation which makes this sentence true,
then it is unsatisfiable example as you can
this something like p and not p essentially.
So,
in general there are three kind of sentences
valid satisfiable and unsatisfiable. All are
seen notions are used somewhere or the other
as we will see later essentially, so when
we
.talk about truth we also say we sue this
symbol to say that a formula is valid, you
can use
say using this essentially.
.
Then, there is a notion of entailment if now
this is an interesting notion because in when
we study logic the reason we study logic is
to we are able to capture valid forms of
argument. Essentially, we are not so much
interested in saying can we find the valuation
which will make the sentence true or not we
are more interested in saying that if
somebody has given you a set of premises or
a set of axioms. Then, does some other
sentence follow that essentially, so given
set of s sentences we say that a formula f
is
entailed by s, which we write as f entails
s if the following is true if for every
that makes
s true and when we say a set of sentences
is true essentially.
What we mean is that every sentence in that
set is true, so you can think of it either
bigger sentence with the sign in between their
essentially. So, we are more interested in
the notion of entailment that somebody give
us the set of premises let us call them s
then
we want to ask whether a given formula f is
true or not essentially. That is notion of
entailment essentially, so these concepts
are kind of semantics concepts.
..
On the other hand we have the notion of provability,
so if you recall we did a small proof
in the last class notion of provability is
tied up with the rules of inference. For example,
most commonly used tool of inference call
modus ponens and we express it follows like
if you have alpha and if you have alpha implies
beta then entails beta. So, last time we
wrote with as three separate lines alpha and
then alpha implies beta below and then beta,
but this is just another way of writing it.
Essentially, you are saying that if you are
given
the alpha and if you are given alpha implies
beta, then you can derive beta or in some
signs you can add beta to your set of sentences.
So, notion of provability is a or the notion
of proof is the entirely syntactic concept
if
simply says that given set of formulas, you
can keep adding new formulas to the system
and this particular rules says that is you
have a formula which matches alpha. If you
have
another formula which matches alpha implies
beta, then you can add the formula which
matches beta to the set essentially this alpha
and beta could be arbitrarily compound
from. They do not have to be atomic form,
essentially it is just s it is just a pattern
that a
pattern the same thing must be here of course
alpha can be any formula. If that formula
implies beta is present in the data base or
nor it be a set of sentences, then you can
add
this.
So, the proof finding algorithm is basically
a simple algorithm which keeps which does
the following select a rule of inference select
some data to which you will apply it to and
.add some new formula to your database. You
keep doing this repeatedly till you have
proved the in formula that you are interested
in essentially. So, another rule of inference
is for example, Modustollans, which says that
if you have not beta and alpha implies beta
then you can add not alpha in this set I will
show.
You are familiar with this kind of formulas,
so the next question I want to ask is what
makes a rule of inference a suitable rule
of inference essentially. So, if you recall
we had
this notions of soundness we say that a logical
system is sound which says that if s
in
other words if you can derive a formula alpha
from a given set of sentences then if their
logic system is sound. Then, this alpha will
also be entail by the set of sentence s which
can be re express as the following if your
set of premises are true then the conclusion
will necessarily be true that is the notion
of entailment.
Thus, the right hand side this notion of entailment
we say that the rule of a logic system
is sound if anything that can be derive is
entailed as well. On the other hand, a logical
system is complete if anything that is entailed
can be derived observe this also look likes
sentences in a logic. This is a slightly different
logic in which we can talk about
sentences like s derives alpha or s entails
alpha which of course has to be in some
different logic essentially, not in proportional
logic. So, the question we want to ask is
when the rule of inference is sound essentially,
so soundness is tide up to valid rule, so
rule is valid if it entails right hand side.
So, rule like this is valid if this and this
actually entail beta, so look at an example
of a
rule which is not valid if I say alpha implies
beta and beta, I am just writing in the old
which is its similar thing this is not really
a valid rule. So, we do not have a name for
it
this rule s says that if alpha implies beta
is given to you and beta is given to you infer
that alpha is true. I do not know whether
we discuss in the last class this is actually
the
process of abduction, so it is like this for
example, you might say that if somebody is
drunk then that person staggers while walking.
So, that could be alpha could stands for somebody
is drunk and beta will stands for
person stagger while walking essentially,
then you say somebody staggering while
walking essentially.
You come to the conclusion that the person
is drunk essentially, now this is not a valid
rule of inference because it possible that
the person may be drowsy or sleepy or tired
or
.hurt it could be anything, but it is not
necessarily follow that that. If you have
this fact
you assume that to be true that people who
are drunk will stagger, it does not mean that
anybody who staggers is drunk essentially,
whereas if we you were to use that formula
here if some you say that somebody is drunk.
If you have that somebody is people who
are drunk stagger then you can info the other
person who is stagger because the rule that
actually says that essentially.
In other example, that we might have discusses
this problem this process of diagnosis in
medical diagnosis a disease causes symptoms.
So, disease implies symptoms if you see
the symptom then you infer the disease essentially
now that is not necessarily a valid
inference. It is possible that the symptom
could have been due to some other disease
as
well essentially because there are many diseases
for example, cause fever. Then, if you
simply say that just because it is fever it
is this particular disease not a valid rule
of
inference. So, how do we distinguish between
valid rules, and rules which are not valid
rules are based on tantological implications,
which means that corresponding to every
rule of inference.
There must be tantology which is an imp there
must be an implication statement which is
a tantology and corresponding to modus phonons
for example, the tantology is alpha and
alpha implies beta implies beta. So, notice
the similarity between that pattern and this
pattern here this is one sentence one sentence
in my language of logic. There, I am using
an additional symbol which stands for derives
or something like that which is and extra
logical symbol in sense it is not a part of
language that I am using, but this is a sentence
in my logic and what we are saying now is
that rule of inference is valid. If it is
based on
a tontological implication by this, we mean
we should we should have a corresponding
sentence here and a sentence must be a tautology.
So, is this sentence are tautology you can
construct a truth table to find out and show
that
this is tautology or you can try and show
that this is a tautology by trying to show
that it
is not a tautology which is kind of proof
that you often do proof by contradiction.
This
would say let say that can we make that sentence
false or if you remember the truth table
for implication you can make it false only
if you make it this part true.
If you make this part false now you can make
this part true only if you make this true
and
if you make this true to make this true you
have to either make alpha false or beta true,
.but if you have made alpha is true here.
So, this mean that alpha is true, so now,
alpha is
become true and beta is become false, so this
part becomes true implies false which is
actually false, once this becomes false this
and this becomes false and once this and this
become false, this becomes true. So, we can
make this sentence false sorry we cannot
make this sentence false because to make that
sentence false we have to make this part
true. We have to make this part true, but
we are unable to make this part true because
you have to make this true and this part false.
That is the only row in the implication to
table where this implication formula becomes
false. So, this has to be false, so that means,
this beta has to be false now to make this
whole part true this has to be true. So, to
make this part true implies false has to be
true,
but true implies false is not true it is false.
So, we are not able to make this false, so
we
are not able to make this whole sentence false.
So, this sentence is a tautology, so as a
small exercise, maybe you should just construct
the truth table for this and see that this
is
tautology. Now, there are other kinds of rule
of inference which are based on tautological
equivalences and they give rise to rules of
substitution.
This rules of inference have a sense of direction
in the sense that you have to be given
the on the left hand side and then you can
produce the formula on the right hand side.
So,
it has a sense of direction you can go from
left to right essentially in rules of substitution.
You say that two formulas are logically equivalent
and therefore, you can substitute one
for other at any point of time essentially.
So, an example of a rule of substitution is
and
you must be familiar with many rules like
De Morgan’s law and so on, but one rule
is for
example, alpha implies beta is equivalent
to not alpha not beta. So, you must have looked
at it at some point that if you have not done
this, tries to construct a truth table for
this.
You will see that this tautology and if it
is a tautology we can base a rule of substitution
on this, which means that whenever we see
a pattern of kind alpha implies beta. We can
replace it which the pattern of kind not alpha
or the beta and vice versa and we do not
have to replace it in the sense we do not
have to substitute it we can even add it,
but it
same thing. So, De Morgan’s law for example,
you must have studied, so there are many
tautological equivalences and you can convert
each of them in to rule of substitution you
can also see a rule of substitution as a bidirectional
rule of inference.
It says that this implies this and that implies
that because if you might remember you can
.say something like alpha is to beta is equivalent
to alpha implies beta and beta implies.
So, you can think of a rule of substitution
s to rules of implies essentially going in
both
the direction essentially. So, what you have
in your to construct a logic machine is a
set
of rules of inference a set of rules of substitution
and you have to ask is now to pick one
of this rules and keep producing new formulas
till the formula you were that looking for
is generated. So, till this formula f we are
interested is generated, so if you look if
you
remember the example we did last time we had
something like this.
It was given to us to that p and q were p
was something like allies like maps and like
music or something like that. Then, p implies
r, then r and s implies t, then not q or s
and
from this you have to show t that was the
problem that we looked at last time or
something very close to this. So, these are
the four premises given to us the set of
sentences s and from this we have to show
the t is derived essentially. So, we write
this s
as this it says that this and this and this
and this let say this is s 1 s 2 s 3 s 4 then
s 1
comma s 2 comma s 3 comma s 4 and t entails
this or derives this we can only use the
truth term terms interchangeably entailment
and derivation if the logic is both sound
and
completes.
If it is sound, then whatever is derived is
true is entail if it is complete whatever
is entail
has been derive. So, we come to the completeness
in a moment, but so far we have
address the issue of soundness when my logic
machine sound is provided I use valid
rules of inference. Valid rules of inference
are characterized by the tautological
implication or tautological equivalence and
corresponding to each tautological
implication we can construct a rule of inference.
So, for example, if somebody says p
implies p is a tautological implication which
is trivially true. You can have a trivial
rule
for this which says that if you have p you
can add p to that essentially, but of course
that
is trivial for any tautological implication.
You can add a rule of inference for any tautological
equivalence you can have a rule of
substitution. So, before you move on i want
to mention one theorem, which is quite well
known. So, let me write me here its call deduction
theorem
this theorem says that if I
have a set of sentences s and a sentence alpha
and I want to derive the sentence beta if
I
can do that. So, remember that this most notation
stands for this idea of generating a
proof that you keep apply in rules of inference
till you generate beta essentially.
.The deduction theorem says that if you can
do that then always the case that you can
do
this, you can take s to the right hand side
sorry you can take alpha to the right hand
side
and instead of deriving beta you can derive
alpha implies beta. Now, this s could be an
empty set, which means that if you want to
show that beta can be derive from alpha, then
you can equivalently show that this formula
alpha implies beta is true essentially. So,
in
other words if you want to show that this
is true, this implies this amount is showing
that
this and this and this and this implies this
if I construct the large formula then that
is true
or tautology. So, you can see that all valid
derivation amount to proving this large
tautology essentially.
So, let me ask the question what is a relation
between these three sentences can you think
of a relation if f is valid, then if f is
satisfiable or if f is unsatisfiable is there
a relation
between them, we will come to this, so, just
think about that a little bit. So, I want
to
spend a little bit of time talking about completeness
when is a logic system complete. So,
you can see that by definition a logic machine
or a logic system is complete if it can
derive every true formula. In other words,
every formula that is entailed a given set
of
axioms essentially and in the last a couple
of hundred years ago, there were lot of people
trying to build logic systems and show that
they are complete essentially.
.
So, this are known as axiomatic systems
axiomatic system said there is set of statements
you must true to be you must accept to be
true without asking them asking about them.
.You know just accept them to be true on faith
and some rules of inference of choice
made is essentially. So, one of these earliest
systems, in fact probably the first one which
is given by Frege who is also credited with
inventing first order logic was the modern
form of first order logic that we use. He
had six axioms, which were as follows this
is a
name of the axioms then one it says alpha
implies beta implies alpha. Then, if you just
look up for Frege axiomatic system, you will
find a very nice page on Wikipedia which
describes this six axioms and the things which
we follow from there.
Essentially, you do not have to write them
here, so
this Frege gave this axiomatic system
which have this six axiom first axiom says
alpha implies beta implies alpha second
axiom says alpha implies beta implies gamma.
The whole thing implies alpha implies
beta implies alpha implies gamma the third
one says alpha implies beta implies gamma
is
also the same as beta implies alpha implies
gamma. Then, there are three axioms says
which use negation sign alpha implies beta
implies not beta implies not alpha. So, you
can see for example, this one Frege one has
connection with this two rules, essentially
this tool says that alpha implies beta and
if you see that not beta implies not alpha
is
implied.
Then, if you have to replace this to with
not beta, not alpha, then you have something
like this. So, you can see the modus Tollens
can derive using Frg one essentially and
substitute this with not beta implies not
alpha and that then it becomes like modus
ponens because not beta is given not beta
implies not alpha is given and not alpha is
given. This from many of us is trivial negation
alpha implies alpha is a axiom in Frege
system essentially and here one rule of inference
which is modus ponens, which we are
familiar with this rule here. So, Frege’s
axiomatic system says that all tautologies
of
propositional logic can be derived from this
set of axioms and this rule of inference.
So, it is a complete system because we are
not go into going to proof of this year, but
we
just take it for granted that here is a definition
of a complete logical. After Frege, there
were many people who devised different axiomatic
systems using different sets of rules
of inference and other things essentially
now as a small exercise. I will ask you to
prove
this formula using Frege’s axiomatic systems
observe that this is not taken for granted
in
Frege system, when you say an axiomatic system.
These are the only six sentences that you
take for granted this are pattern, which means
.alpha can be substituted with anything essentially
and only one rule of inference allow.
Using this, can you come up with a derivation
of this sentence p implies p, you can try
it
a little bit while. Then, if you cannot succeed
you can go to the Wikipedia site and you
will find the proof there. So, I am not going
to do it in the board here, but you can find
a
proof essentially, but the whole idea of developing
axiomatic systems was to choose a set
of axioms in the given language. This is now
a case professional calculus or professional
logic a rule of infer some rule of inference
and say that this set which is complete, which
means all tautologies can be derived in this
including this tautology which stands for
this.
This implies if you look at the deduction
theorem that if I can show that to be a tautology
then I can this t follows from those four
sentences is equivalent. So, if I can show
this
then I can show that beta follows from alpha
essentially and Frege system can derive all
possibilities of course that does not mean
that it is a trivial task. So, as you know
people
have been struggling to find proof of things
for example, Fermat’s last theorem to a
few
hundred years before it was accepted as being
solved essentially. So, finding the proof
is
not the trivial task it is because there is
a lot of choice available to you what to use
and so
on.
One of the kind of proof that we did in the
last class is called natural deduction which
says you take a rule of inference applied
to some premises and add a new one to the
set
and then again take another rule and apply
it and so on. So, we had if you remember we
had set that from this we can first derive
p and then from p and p and r we can derive
r
and then from p and q we can derive q then
from q and not q or s. We can derive s there
is a rule which I am not may be not stated.
So, from r and s, we can derive r and s and
from this we can derive t. So, there you can
start like this derive all this things then
derive t, this process is called natural deduction
essentially.
..
Very often, we can generate rules of inference
by showing something like this
supposing
I want to show that this is a tautology then
one way of doing things is to assume the left
hand side. So, I assume p and q implies r
and in some sense put it in a box, so everything
that follow within the box is based on this
assumption. Then I make another assumption
p, I open another box and third assumption
q which I open, another box and now I can
say. So, I have assume this three formulas
I have assume this I have assume this I have
assume this, now I can say p and q then I
can use p and q and this and apply modus
ponens and assume r or infer r rather.
Then, I can close this box and say I made
this assumption of q and so it is a little
bit like
this application of this deduction theorem
that I am closing this box and I am saying.
Now, q implies r because r is what I reduced
from here then I am saying I will close this
box and I will get let me write I t here p
implies q implies r. Then, finally when I
close
this box then I have this implies this, so
you see to prove this formula. So, you must
be
familiar with this kind of proof which you
have done quite often assume that this is
a
case then show that something in this true.
So, to show that this is a tautology we said
let
us assume the left hand side, then we said
let us assume q, so we have three assumptions
that picked by this three boxes.
So, anything that is entailed by these assumptions
are inside the boxes, so p and q is true
inside this box because p has been assume
q has been assume and because this has been
.assume r can be inferred because p and q
implies r modus ponens. We can apply then
we
close this box we get q implies r because
the only assumption we made in here was q,
then we close this box then we get p implies
q implies r because the assumption we made
was p here. Then, we close this box we get
this formula essentially, so that is another
way of another rule of inference essentially.
So, the process of finding proof is not a
straight forward process and lot of peoples
spent
a lot of time trying to devise strategy for
finding proofs. In 1965 along came a logistician
by the name of Robinson who devises the Skema,
which you will look at in the next
class in which only one rule was of inference
was enough for driving all kind of things
essentially. Now, observe that when we talk
of axiomatic systems we are daily talking
of
proving all tautology essentially. In the
real world we are often more interested in
showing that given a set of premises that
something else is true. Before we go on to
this
Robinsons method, there is another observation
that we must make which is about the
choice of connectives.
Now, if you observe this Frege system, it
uses only two connectives the implication
and
the negation essentially and yet they can
made a claim that system is complete which
means any true statement that can express
in proportional logic can be derive essentially.
So, where do the other connectives come from
well you cannot derive statements in
those exact form, but we have this rules of
substitution essentially. So, for example,
we
have this rule of substitution which says
that not alpha or beta is equal to alpha implies
beta. So, Frege saying that not that he can
derive this form of the sentence, but then
equivalent form of sentence here, but logically
they are the same they are saying the
same thing essentially.
So, there is a notion of a set of connectives
also which is complete I am sure you are
familiar with this set. So, I am not going
to spent too much of time here for example,
you
must say that this set. So, Frege set this
set is complete just use the implication sign
and
the negation sign and you can express everything
can that can be expressed in
proportional logic using this connectives.
We have all this rules of substitution and
you
can derive everything that is a tautology
in proportional logic using this system of
derivation which is those six axioms plus
the modus ponens rule.
Essentially, there are other systems which
are complete for example, a commonly used
.system is uses these three signs negation.
We will see that Robinson’s method using
this
set of connectives you can even just work
with and or you can even just work with or
and negation sign. There are other combination
which are possible and some that you
must be familiar with the NAND and NOR. So,
you must see familiar with the fact that
these two connectives NOT and AND, NOT or
NAND and NOR. This one single
connective enough to express everything you
can express in proportional logic which
means you choose any set of connectives that
we have here and or implies equivalence
and so on.
So, express anything using those connective
use can device a language in which there is
only one connective NAND or only one connective
nor or you can express the same
thing in this logic with only one connective.
What do you mean by you can express the
same thing you mean that they are logically
equivalent which mean that any valuation
which makes any sentence true in the first
one will also make the second sentence. The
same sentence true in this in this second
formulation, in other words if alpha implies
beta
is true here not alpha or beta will be true
here or if this sentence is true, then this
sentences that is a meaning of equivalence.
So, anything that can be set in proportional
logic can be set with set of complete
sentences complete connectives and then you
can choose a set of axioms and a rule some
rules of inference and you can have a logically
complete system. The beauty about
Robinson system was that he did not need any
axioms he just needed one rule of
inference and that was the complete system
you could derive everything all tautologies
in
that essentially. So, as a last thing it is
nice to define a complete system which is
minimal
stance in some sense small set of axiom and
small one rule of inference. As you will see
if you try to show that p implies p it involves
a lot of steps in showing that p implies see
because you have to start with some axiom
substitute something for there.
Then, you know keep laying with the axiom
it is a nice exercise you must try in practice
you would not want a minimal as the system
you would want a system in which
inferences can be made very quickly. This
means you can derive sort of complex rules
of
inference, so you can say for example that
and this side in fact this is a rule of inference
that is alpha implies beta and beta implies
gamma, then alpha implies gamma, you can
have a rule of inference like this.
.So, you can see its like transivity and f
alpha implies beta implies gamma, then you
have
rules says that alpha implies gamma if you
have such a rule in your system then you have
to showed alpha implies gamma or something
like that. If somebody have given you
alpha and asked you to show gamma then you
can just take this rule here and this
conclusion here and then use modus ponens
can derive gamma essentially. So, it makes
sense to introduce more rules of inference
which would make you inferences shorter, so
there is some wage analogy which defining
a language here.
So, when people define the instruction sets
for machines, they work with more
instructions or less instructions and each
ahs his advantage essentially. So, theoretically
of course it is nice show that a small set
is good and complete, but in practice you
guy
need something bigger unless you come up with
something like Robinsons method
which was small and yet very efficient essentially.
So, we look at Robinson’s resolutions
method in a next class essentially.
.