So, today we want to look at propositional
logic. So, to keep things into prospective
our
motivation for studying logic is to be able
to make inferences. So, in general if he given
a
set of facts and if he ask a statement about
which is not in this set some statement. And
we are ask the question is this statement
true or not true then we should be able to
answer
that question. And you want to build the mechanism
or a machinery to do this
automatically or mechanically if not necessarily
automatically. By mechanically we
mean by applying a set of rules which can
be then by human as well. So, whenever we
talk about logic, we have first talk about
the language part which like any formal
language is a set of sentences that belongs
to this language. So, what is the language
of
propositional logic? It has 2 components;
one is called the logical part and it essentially
contains the alphabet of these operators or
operator symbols. So, you must keep in mind
that we want to distinguish between the syntax
of the language and the semantics of the
language and do you not do you.
.So, a very pedantically in this lectures,
but we need to distinguish between the fact
thus
the syntax part which says that these are
some symbols that we use. But off course,
the
meaning of this symbols calms from this semantics
and which as you are familiar with is
given by the through tables at we can construct
for each of these operators. So, at one
level other syntactic level we just treat
them as symbols but when we talk about the
semantics of sentences. Then we will sort
of reverts to the idea which comes on the
proof
table essentially. So, for the movement we
have focusing only on the syntax part just
think of them only a symbols essentially.
Then there are other things like brackets
that
we can use then there is a non logical part
by thus we mean it varies from problem to
problem essentially let us as assume that
be since here. So, we have symbols which is
set
of proposition symbols. So, this is the alphabet
with which we construct the language we
have a concern at which we use and all progression
logics. And we have a varying set
which may be in principle and infinite or
at least countable infinite or it could be
fine at
as well essentially.
We just talking about the 5 statements speak
you are a steep then this set will be simple
set of statement. So, this is a countable
set of propositional symbols a we have 2 more
symbols here one is I will use this notation.
But you could also use f was 0 and the other
is this, but you could also used t or 1 or
even true and falls the full letters. It does
not
matter basically they are these 2 symbols
which are they are in all logics this you
often
read as bottom. And this we read as top essentially
bottom are falls or 0 are equivalent.
Basically it is a set of 2 symbols it is a
2 valued logic that we have talking about.
And
when we talk about semantics then every sentence
in our language will be map to one of
these symbols. And that is how the semantics
will be defined month we would implicitly
between us
say that it is stands for true sentences.
And the other stands for fall sentences
I mean this is fall sentences and this is
true sentences for that is only for us our
sake. As
far as the logic itself is concerned the machine
in self is concerned they are just 2
symbols to which sentences are mat on true
essentially. But a travelers helps to keeping
mind the semantics which is that we are talking
about false or true statements. What is
this machinery that we have talking about?
This machine is we want to built is essentially
a machinery which first defines this
language. And then tries to reach to sentences
in this language essentially and a mapping
.for to this anywhere will come to that in
the movement. So, the set of sentences let
us
call it s p where p stands for propositional
logic is defined as follows that this belongs
to
this his set top belongs to this set. So,
that of course, you know they stand for something
which is always true or and something which
is the always false. So, this is the set of
propositional symbols let us call this set
p. Then we say that if alpha belongs to p
then
alpha belongs to s p. So, every propositional
symbol is the sentence and then we say that
if alpha beta belong to p. So, alpha beta
these symbols we will use as variables to
stands
for any sentence essentially alpha and beta
belong to s p and a, these are finally, operator
symbol. So, of these symbols we will distinguish
between binary and unary and we will
not talk about higher or operators and we
do not need to a. So, this one is unary we
often
of always you also use the this sign for this
a for this sign. We also use sometimes an
arrow for this we sometimes use 2 arrows and
there are the symbols which we I have not
mentioned here, but we can build the language
using other symbols.
So, I So, is your familiar that there are
sixteen possible binary operates that you
can
device and these are only one 2 3 4 of them
and there are 12 more which so if alpha beta
belongs to the set of sentences. And so instead
of using this particular symbol let me here
use some abstract symbol if says the, this
is the binary operators symbol then alpha
well I
am. So, set I just defending the language
here. So, for example, a if p and q are to
propositional symbols then p and q belongs
to this set and once this belongs to the set
we
can also say p and q or q belongs to the set.
So, essentially we can combined this any number
of time and we can create sentences
which are which are really long. So, and which
infinites so the sentences in fact, we can
create even if the set of propositional symbols
is finite essentially likewise we have for
the unary symbol. If alpha belongs to s p
and we just use this symbol in a unary operator
then so essentially now we have defined we
started with the central propositional
symbols. And we have augmented this with more
sentences and the sentences are using
the operators. So, the or the connective essentially
and the bracket symbols and so we
can get in infinite set of symbol essentially.
So, this is the syntax, what is the meaning
of
these sentences propositional logic is not
concern with meaning. So the meaning is given
by us essentially.
..
So, I can say that a if have set of sentences
like Alice likes a math and physics and I
call
this sentence p. That is only for my own sake
essentially I want to let say reason about
Alice and I create a set of sentences is about
Alice. So, I say I like math’s and physics
a
Alice likes music. If Alice likes math then
Alice likes algebra if Alice likes algebra
and
music. So, I should really say I will just
likes music
then Alice goes to college that is say
I have this set of sentences. So, always thank
to give you flavor of anyway familiar with
this the kind of things we can do with professional
logic and from this we want to ask the
question that is this sentence. So is this
sentence can be cannot be informed not
essentially. So, I can now encode this problem
in propositional logic and I can say a that
Alice like math’s is p and Alice likes physics
is q.
Then I can call the sentences p and q because
Alice like math’s and Alice likes physics
this I can call as m. And then I have a statement
if Alice like math then Alice likes
algebra. So, this sentence I can call as a
let us say and this hole sentence I will represents
and implies a. And this sentence says Alice
like algebra Alice like music o implies a
if
Alice likes music and then Alice goes to college
So, this let us call it is c So, this
sentence I can write as a and m implies c
why did I put brackets around here? But I
am
not doing it, because when if clear then we
do not often put brackets and this is the
sentence c and we are asking with the this
sentences true or not. So, I am saying here
that
.m means that Alice likes music but that is
only between us as for as the logical
machinery is concerned it is not concern with
this at all. So, like we set logic as formal
essentially.
.
We say logic is it only depends upon the from
so essentially what we have going to ask
is a if a assume this is true; this is true;
this is true; this is true. Then is this necessarily
true number we said logic talks about for
deduction essentially, but suddenly you have
started talking about true statements for
let us talk about truth first when we says
semantics. We essentially have to kinds of
well should I safely worst do it values it
is a,
what does the sentence meant? What does p
mean? What does q mean? What does n
mean? Now, we are saying that logic is not
concern with that essentially. The other thing
is truth; truth values or some people in the
tram truth functional semantics. And what
we
have saying here is that there is a mapping
can which goes from this site of sentence
sp
to in site. We want to define this mapping
and that those 2 symbols we set that between
us will assume this stand for false and truth
essentially. So, what are what is the mapping
a looking for we are looking for a mapping
which takes an import any sentence in my
language. And maps it to one of those 2 symbols
which means it tells me, but that is
again between us where there the sentences
true or false essentially.
.So, we have to a define this mapping. So,
we start with the function v which maps this
at
p to the set of essentially lets external
what do mean by this? Somebody is telling
me
what is true and what is not true that I am
saying that Alice likes music’s. So, I am
give
mapping and to clue and mapping p to true
q to true. And so in general given the
mapping of the professional sentences we can
derive a mapping or so this is general
version we will come to specifics later sometimes
you have uncertain solid.
So, I am I it is say p is true or r it is
true in which a off course, a do not I am
not given
the mapping, but I am given the mapping for
pm also. We will come to that a bit later
first you all the defined that if you are
given the mapping a which we call we which
takes
you from the set of propositional symbols
to this. Then can be defined this value function
and that we can do as follows. If help a belongs
to p then val alpha is equal to, because
somebody is given a started it maps to he
are very talking about to tables from this
point
onwards. Then we always define val is equal
to this thing and val they will little bit
of
over loading happening here ideally at at
should use different symbols essentially.
So, I so let the say we defined it to 2 now,
what and really saying is that this bottom
always bottom symbol always maps to the truth
fell you false. So, let us call this is the
set of truth values and here working with
the binary true valued logics. So, that this
truth
values which one we call false and one we
call true and bottom always must be false
and
top always maps toT with stands for true essentially.
And then if val alpha is equal to
true then val not alpha is equal to form.
So, I right rules like this if alpha maps
true, and
alpha is the sentence in my language there.
Then the another sentence in which I prefix
alpha with this or unary operator for we will
off course, between us read as not alpha
then not alpha maps to f essentially and like
this you can right other rules. So, for
example, we can say if well alpha you control
true and val beta is equal to false then val
alpha implies beta is equal to false. So,
we are familiar with this. So, we will not
spend
our time righting this essentially you can
convert these kind of statements into a table.
So, for example, a alpha beta alpha and and
place beet.
So, false false true false true well I do
not know where there you can make out between
my maybe I should out chosen 0 and one that
anyway you not the truth table for
implication. So, this is the truth table for
implication these are the simplification if
I can
.like this for each low I can write a sentence
like this. So, this is this stands for the
a third
row here this statement call this third row.
So, I considered the 2 table or I can rights
statement like distance so on, but we are
familiar with this as to how to defined this
semantics of how to lift the semantics of
smile sentences to compound sentences when
they are made of using operators. And we have
this logic rules that we all familiar with
essentially. So, what have it done? We offset
that we have define the language
of
professional logic, we have define what is
the set of sentences which make up this
proportional logic. And then we have define
the mapping which tells us that if he knew
the truth values of the constituent sentences.
How can we lift those truth values to more
compounds in this is and we have rules for
doing that which means somebody gives us this
valuation which a that these are the 5
atomic sentences a proportional’s symbols.
And they map to true false true false
respectively then for this entire set of infinite
formalize. I have a mechanism for
determining for there they map to true of
where there they false and that I can do by
using true tables or something like that.
So, where, there the logic machinery come
and
here. So, logic machinery comes in the logic
machinery as we set is deals only with the
form it does not deal with content. It does
not with semantics it is it does not deal
with
meaning what we have interested in is can
we table of a syntactic machinery which will
do that mapping for us essentially. Instead
of having to apply these rules repeatedly
you
can keep applying the rules if some formula
l for and some formula beta for what is the
truthfully of this. It depends if both of
them a truth then this compel formula is true
and
you can breakdown essentially. Instead of
doing that in staff having to construct the
true
table can we have an alternate mechanism for
doing that?
So, to come to that let a say that somebody
as given a this function. We with basically
saves which professions of true and which
are falls from that we can come compute this
function val which says the something for
compound sentences. And from that we can
defined this said t is the set of 5 sentences.
So, of all the sentences which I can construct
did my language I the semantics tells me which
have true and which have falls, but I
have own and either waves of reaching those
sentences. I do not know to apply these
schools I do not want to construct to tables
quite, because the side of the 2 tables then
grow to be very large is essentially I have
2 constituent here alpha beta. And I have
4 set
.4 rose it may true table if I have a sentence
like alpha and beta implies or delta implies
theta and I have 5 variables and I have 2
rest of 5 rose in may true table. So, the
side of
the truth table goes exponentially with the
number propositional variables set I use in
my
sentence essentially. So, I do not know want
to construct a true table what do we do we
defined in set the notion of a rule of inference.
So, let me of this part out. So, what are
we interested it we I interested it we a interested
in reaching those wet set of true
sentences this.
.
And what do I mean by that if I somebody else
given with the promises which is this set
p that at talked about the semantics defines
is set t devises I assume to be true. So,
these
assume to be true but from if I assume these
to be true then there where hole set which
is
true. So, for example, I can say a and or
not q is this true or not this is the hole
they there
infinite. So, the sentences I can construct
using these symbols and I can ask the question
of the self them were there that is true or
not from that I can collect the true sentences.
And I have this set true essentially now a
are seen that he say the mechanism of reaching
this set again truth true or different means
now you talking about the logic machines.
Or
you can say and inference this use is something
call rules of inference. So, what does the
rule of inference? Rule of inference is a
pattern and the most popular on that no thought
the a familiar with is called nodes ponens
and modus ponens says that if he can see a
.sentence alpha. And the sentence belongs
to the set of sentences at we have and if
you
can see a sentences alpha implies beta.
Then we can add in sentence beta what do I
mean by this that if I have a set of sentences
given to me to set of premises. For example,
our data base of sentences if you want to
use at a then I can keep adding new sentences
to the data base essentially. And how do I
do that? I do it by this pattern matching
mechanism which says that if I have alpha
and if
I have alpha implied beta then I can add beta
essentially. So, this is rule of inference
there have many others you must see familiar
with. So, one rule is call simplification
we
should will need for this it say if you can
see a sentence of this kind then you can right
the sentence of this kind essentially alpha.
So, notice that once you have rules like
simplification we do not feel complete for
somebody to us the set of all atomic
valuations for all atomic proposition. Somebody
is given a of p and q from this by
applying this we can always add q to or p
to the. Then you say we can add this say
sentence beta or we can add this new sentence
alpha to our data base. We also use the
turn that we can derive beta essentially or
we also use the turn prove beta. So, if alpha
is
given to us and alpha implies beta is given
to us when we can say we can derive beta or
we can prove that beta is true essentially.
So, the notion of a proof is distinct from
the notion of truth that we have talking about
there the notion of truth is base on the semantics
of the operators that we have defined
what does it? What does and mean? What does
all mean? what does the implication
mean? What does negation mean? And when he
say mean basically we are talking about
the truth table essentially how does and combine
the truth values of it is component to
give you truth value. That is the meaning
of those operator and truth the notion of
truth is
based on the notion of semantics are those
operator essentially. So, notion of proof
or
derivation resent purely syntactic notion
it is purely base on pattern matching. It
says if
you can see is such a pattern and if you can
see is such a pattern. Then you can derive
this pattern it is nothing to do at least
on the surface which the notion of prove essentially
ideally. Of course, we would not been in a
machine like this a syntactic machine like
this
which is producing something which a not interested.
And we I interested in true
statement we want to know what is true even
some premises not else is true. So, theory
on proving is the name that we use. So, this
is essentially So, let us see what happening
.here before we look at the machine if further
what is been given to us says p and q for
lets label number this now true is am.
And you are familiar with this process p implies
a or a and m implies c here the fourth
facts is a terms sometime we used given to
us that this 4 sentences at true. Then a
conclusion that we have see is see true or
not will Alice go to college or not essentially,
but we have not looking at the meaning of
this sentences. Any more we have not even
looking at the truth values of the sentences.
We are asking that will this machinery that
we have we have talked about tools of inferences.
There are more rules that we can
talked about and if necessary he will introduce
the can we have this machinery produce
this formula c or derive this formula c a
prove this formula c. So, what is this machinery?
This logic machine
essentially says pick our rule
and corresponding data
by data had be
mean the sentences which are already there.
So, for example, these sentences are already
given to us essentially and if some rule is
applicable data take that rule. And take that
data and add consequent of rule of a there
as the matching component at am stating
explicitly here what is the consequent? The
consequent is return below the line here
return below the line here we also use another
way of signifying this rule.
We say alpha implies beta there is another
way of righting this rule it is say that given
alpha and given alpha beta you can derive
beta. So, this symbol is used for proving
or
deriving thing and this is stating a rule
of inference modus porous is say that if I
give this
to you can add that
corresponding to this is corresponding is
also the notion of truth.
Then we are asking if this is true and this
is this is true this is true then is it necessary
that
c is true. We would like this as follows p
and q and n and p implies a and this one a
and n
implies c
we have. So, corresponding of sentences we
have the social of truth value and
correspondence notion of a truth value. We
have saying that these 4 sentence entail c.
So,
the premises is what are the premises is 4
things even to us premises entail the sentence
c
and that more formally we like this these
first premise, second premise, third premise,
fourth premise. And that this similar symbol,
but it 2 lines is for entailment an entailment
says that if these are true than that is necessarily
true that you cannot the that true that is
notion of entailment. So, that is set of truths
2 sentence that we talk about an entailments
basically asked the question thus is see belong
to the set of 2 sentence or not those this
premises entail c the question. We are asking
here is can you derive see from the
.premises could derive we see are use this
rules of inference for entailment; we have
to
use the truth stable for the operators they
are quite this things.
So, I am so fact that they are different.
So, logic machinery basically says packable
and
corresponding data and add consequent of the
rule. And we put this essentially and what
this will produce is another set of formulize
which we will call is what is the call this
that
is let me, because I use the symbol p earlier.
Let us say this is p r something some
symbol what is the set? This is a set of I
should write it here set of provable formulas.
So,
I have in adamantly sort of switch to the
terminology of formulas but essentially a
formula is a sentence in my language essentially
a well form formula sp. It is a short for
well form formula anything that I can construct
using the sentence that I have defines is
a
formula. And this set p r is a set of all
those formulas which are provable given the
set of
premises and the set of rules of influences
that are given to me essentially. So, the
question we are asking is the c belong to
this set or not and instead of writing this
loop
which will keep going indefinitely, because
the set is actually infinite. We can put a
the
termination criteria that if c if the consequent
equal to c then stop essentially we can just
put in the condition that.
So, that means we are writing the program
to generate a proof for only c and not
worrying about other provable formulas essentially.
So, there a small variation
essentially so how do we go about this? This
is given to us we can add p here why
because there is a role called simplification
which says if you have alpha and beta and
alpha matches p and beta matches q. Therefore,
I can produce p here by simplification
there another rule. So, I can use now modus
ponens because I have p and I have p
implies a I can add a remember modus ponens
say if you have alpha, alpha is p and alpha
implies beta is p implies. Therefore, I can
beta becomes a and I can add a there is a
another rule which says that if I have 2 things.
Then the conjunction of those 2 things can
be added which is called addition, but I can
write a m, because I have a and I have m I
can write a and m I can add this is another
rule of influence which I have not written
here
explicitly and then again I can use modus
ponens. So, ideally I should say how would
I
get this? I got it from one and simplification
how did I get this? I got this from 5 and
and modus ponens hence so on essentially.
So, you are familiar with this process having
studied geometry and algebra in school.
.So, now I have got a m I got this by addition
of a and m and then the last thing is c,
because I have this a a and m a and m matches
alpha and a and m implies c matches
alpha implies beta. So, c matches beta. So,
I can using modus ponens. So, this is a
syntactic machinery of of arriving at proof
of c which does not look at the meaning of
the
operators. It does not understand what does
m stands for? What does implication stand
for know all it has is set of rules of influence
which says if you see this pattern. And you
see this pattern you can add a new formula
to your data base and we can put this to a
cycle and say can we add c. So, at this point
we have added c. So, we can say yes c is
provable in to. So, that is a notion of proof
notion of provability that is syntactic
machinery we are after, because it is easy
to write pattern matching algorithms and in
this case the patterns are exact. So, you
know matching is not even hard and you can
keep looking for rules and matching data and
keep producing new data.
So, you can imagine the forwards search algorithm
which says this is what is given to me
this is a rule available to me from this.
And this I can for this from this and this
I can
infer this from this and something else I
can infer this So, I can mo moving forward
and
that c is somewhere. So, if I can reach this
formula c then I have stopped. So, the power
state space search that we talked about is
essentially being done here in. So, notice
that
we have said pick a rule we have not said
which rule that of course, is a very tricky
question you can go off in some direction
and infer meaningless things. So, that is
obviously the thing that we need to tackle
next essentially. So, what have we done? We
have defined the language of propositional
logic this in fact then the semantics the
truth
function semantics which says that given a
sentence. We can arrive at it is truth value
using the truth table approach then we talked
about this machinery of making inferences
which which does not look at semantics. But
it only looks at the syntax, it is a syntactic
machinery and basically adds new formulas
to that we can sort of bill a machinery to
produce the formula.
So, is this machinery, good machinery or not?
This is this is the question which is asked
by all logicians. So, what do we have? We
have a logic machinery is this logic
machinery doing what we want us want it to
do? So, there are 2 notions that we use here
one is the notion of soundness. The notion
of soundness says that my machinery will
only produce true formulas we can express
this as follows if. So, let say l is a language
.give to us or set of premises given to us
if l entail alpha then l sorry if l l derives
alpha
then n l entails alpha notion, so soundness
is that my logic machinery will produce only
true formula if it produces a formula then
that formula must be true. Of course, trivially
if your logic machinery does not produce any
formulas that will be a sound machine. But
that of course, is not a very good machinery
as a properties completeness
that we have
already spoken about is that if l entails
alpha. Then l completeness says that if a
formula
is true then there is a derivation for that
formula in my logic machinery that if I had
a non
deterministic machine which knew which role
to pick and which data to apply to it will
produce a derivation essentially.
Of course, in the absence of having non determinism
we have to use search and we will
sort of focus on that as we go along tie to
soundness is a notion which is basically is
derived from soundness. But it is useful to
talk about is it is consistency, consistency
says theta logic is consistent if you can
derive either alpha or negation of alpha but
never
both essentially. So, says that l derives
alpha and I must use the exclusive or l derives
negation of alpha. So, this stands for exclusive
which is not a symbol I have defined here
but we can define it in terms of this. So,
consistency is basically de tied up to soundness
is if you just think about this a little bit
only one of those things will be true and
soundness says that I can prove only those
true 2 things essentially if I prove something
it must be true. So, you cannot have alpha
and not alpha being derived. So, which is
basically the other side of soundness, but
very often we talk about consistency
soundness, completeness and consistency essentially.
So when we begin the next class,
we will talk about these properties. We will
ask the question when is my system going to
be sound why is this rule sound how do I say
that this rule is sound.
So, we will ask this question, we will also
talk about completeness a little bit, but
we will
not prove it is completeness properties the
profs are simply little bit longer. And then
we
will move on to higher order logics essentially
may I will give you an example of logical
systems which were know as axiomatic systems.
So, last 200 years mathematician have
been talking about building axiomatic system.
So, they have been saying if you use this
set of operators and this rule of then your
logic machinery is complete essentially. So,
I
will just give you an example you would not
prove their completeness but we can talk
about it essentially. So, in the next class,
we will begin with soundness and completeness
.and then move on to logic.
Eventually we will also focus on this machinery
what really this algorithm should be
essentially this seems to wage and it needs
all this power of non determinism to work.
We need something more efficient to be able
to derive the proofs essentially observe that
you know of course, we are not talking about
first sort of logic yes. But in first sort
of
logic you would have this problem you could
say if a number is odd then it is successor
is even essentially. And if somebody tells
you 5 is odd then you will say go into a
direction saying 6 is even, 7 is odd, 8 is
of course, you have to have the other rule
also
that if a number is even and it is successor
is odd. Then you will just keep making
statements 5 is odd, 6 is even, 7 is odd,
8 is even, 9 is odd and you will never come
out
that loop essentially. So, obviously that
is like depth first search going into an infinite
branch that is danger lucks even in this algorithm
here and we have to look at some of
those algorithm issues. So, we will stop here.
.