So, today we want look at different approach
to problem solving and this approach is
called constraint satisfactions or some people
called it constraint processing. And we talk
of constraint satisfaction problems
and we call them CSP essentially. So, this
constraint
satisfaction approach to solving problems
is unified way of representing problems as
constraint satisfaction problems as we will
see today. And then solving the CSP
essentially so essentially what this says.
So, for example, in state space search we
talked
about states end, moves end and going to new
states and so on. And then we looked at
solution space search and these method in
constraint satisfaction problems everything
is
expressed in the following way. There is set
of variables x, x one, x two, a finite set,
a set
of domains d which you will denote by d 1
d 2 and so on. And the meaning of this
domain says that variable x 1 can take values
from domain d 1 variable x 2 can take
value from domain d 2 and so on. So, each
variable has it is own domain it does not
have
to be the same set of values.
.So, one can be numbers another can be colors
another can be day of the week; another
can be name of the students; another can be
the grade that the student has got anything
in
the variable. And each variable has a domain
from the third thing is a set of constraints
c
which you will say c 1 c 2 let us say up to
c k I will come to constraints in a moment
first
let us talk about variables. So, we will assume
that there is final set of variables which
is
always the case so x n which means d n. And
we will also assume far as for as we are
concern that this domains are discrete domains
essentially and not only discrete. But we
will assume that they are finainic essentially
which means that the set of values that
available can take we will assume it is finite
essentially. Because of the particular kind
of
sub problems that you want to look at and
the solutions to those problems essentially
now obviously many problems can be posed as
variations of finite discrete domain. So,
let us first discuss the constraint.
So, each constraint c i is a pair S i and
R i where S i is called scope of the constraint.
And
it is basically a subset of x which means
that a constraint is defined over a subset
of the
variables and that subset that particular
sub set was for the i t h constraint is called
the
scope of that constraint c i and R i. So,
this subset let us say this sub set is made
up of
variables x i 1 x i 2 x i p. Let us say that
there are p variables each of them has a
corresponding domain and the relation R i
is basically defined over those variables.
So, it
is a sub set of d i 1 cross d i 2 cross d
i p that is the most generate way of defining
a
constraint satisfaction problems a set of
variables a set of domains for each variable.
And
a set of constraint defined over subsets of
variable. And we have just using the generic
definition of a relation here simply saying
that is the subset of the gross product of
all the
domains in practice this could be explicit
or implicit.
So, we will assume that the relations are
explicit as for as we are concern for this
discussion. So, for example, if you say that
there is a number between 1 and 5 or the days
of the week can be numbered from let say 1
to 7 when you will simply list this set as
comma 2 comma 3 up to 7. We could have said
it in some implicit way like greater than
0 and less than 8. But we will not go into
those things here and in many case it does
not
really matter. So, we will assume that the
domain the relations are available to us as
explicit pairs of tuples which is the subset
of this cross product of the domains. Now,
you
will you must have for example, solved set
of linear equation they can also be seen as
a
.constraint satisfaction problems except that
the domains may be continues in linear
programming. Whereas, domains are discrete
in integer programming and they have their
own so specialized kind of constraint satisfaction
problems have their own methods for
solving them essentially
So, for example, you know how to solve set
of linear e Q inequalities or a set of linear
equations. We will not going to specialize
methods they eve those specialized methods
obviously more efficient than the general
methods that we want to look at that. We want
to explode is that for general kind of constraint
satisfaction problems. And we will be
interested in those problems where the relations
are explicit and the domains are finite
and discrete. We will called this a finite
constraint satisfaction problems and we want
to
look at ways of solving those problems what
is the solution a solution to a CSP. So, we
often say that a CSP is denoted often by R
as this triple x d and c. An very often we
use
the term constraint network it is the standard
term which the community uses. So, we
will also stick to that but when you say as
a CSP or constraint network basically mean
the same thing this is triple of set of variables
set of domains for the variables. And
constraints was this variables solution to
a CSP is an assignment
to each variable
obviously from their domains such that each
constraint is satisfied.
So, they will define what we mean by constraint
in a moment essentially. But that is a
general idea of a constraint satisfaction
problem again to repeat we have a set of
variables we have set of domains for 1 domain
for each variable from which can take
values. And we have a set of constraints defined
over a subset of those variables without
loss of generality will assume that for each
possible scope there is only 1 constraint
define. So, for example, if I take variable
x 1 and x 2 i define only 1 constraint on
that I
will not define 2 separate constraints, because
you can always combine the 2 constraints
into 1. So, we are assume that there is 1
and the solution to CSP is an assignment to
each
variable such that each constraint is satisfied
essentially. Now, this is very generate way
of looking a things but it is very useful,
because it turns out that a lot of problems
can be
as constraint satisfaction problems.
And we can now subscribe to this strategy
of saying that if you solving a new problem
just as a CSP then takes an of the self CSP
solver and use it to solve the CSP essentially.
.So, we can capitalize upon the expertise
of people who have worked on constraint
satisfaction problems and use their solutions
directly. So, only thing when you need to
do
is so to pose it has a CSP and he turns out
many, many problems can be pose as finite
discrete C S P’s for which we can use the
methods that have discussed in the committee.
We will not have time to discuss those methods
again as I said this is just giving you an
exposure to this particular field and for
those of you who are interested you should
come
to the planning and constraint satisfaction
course like semester in which you been look
at
all the defined methods which we will not
have time to discuss here.
So, as in a side you should also observe that
is the problem is a special case of a CSP
and
what is what kind of CSP it is? It is the
CSP in which the domains each domain has 2
values 0 or 1 or true or false or whatever.
And the constraints are defined in terms of
the
logical operators that we talk about and or
and not and so on. And if you have such a
problem where you have this then you have
a sat problem essentially. So, the sat problem
is special kind of a CSP and again of course
sat has its own specialize approaches to
solving them. So, there are approaches to
sat and all kinds of things. So, again we
will
not going to the special ways of solving things
essentially but we just observe that that
is
also a CSP.
.
.Now, our favorite problem one of our favorite
problem small problems is this n queen
problems. So, if you look at this problem
let say we are looking 4 queen and how can
we
represent this? We can say that there are
4 variables let say x 1 one for this column
x 2
for this column x 3 for this column x 4 for
this column. And let us say the values the
that
can take a ne 2 3 4 4 numbers
then we can express this as a CSP there equine
problems
by
specifying the constraint So, I will use the
short form R 1 2 to stand for constraint
number 1 which has the scope of variables
x 1 and x 2. So, will uses directly in a relation
here so it sort of clear between us. Then
we are talking about a constraint which is
over
the first 2 variables what us those constraints
we can simply specify it as saying that
these pairs are allowed. So, for example,
you have placed the queen on first row the
first
queen on the first row second queen I can
only place on the third row.
So, 1 comma 3 is allowed or 1 comma 4 is allowed
or 2 comma 4 is allowed or 3 comma
1 is allowed or 4 comma 1 and 4 comma 2. So,
this is what I meant by saying that we
have it available to us explicitly it does
not have to be implemented like this. As far
as it
is only for our discussion that we are assuming
that this constraint between the first
queen and the second queen i e expressed available
to us as a pair of values that is 2
variables can take. So, each variable can
take 4 on of this 4 values the domains are
all the
same and this constraint is expressed like
this likewise you will have to express R 2
3 R
1 3 R 1 4 R 2 4 and R 3 4. So, there are 6
constraints, because you can choose 2 variables
in 6 place and all those 6 which I am leave
as a small exercise for you is to be can be
expressed as a solution essentially. And then
of course the problem is to find the set of
values for this variables such that the values
satisfy all this constrain which means if
I
taken a value for variable 1 and some value
for variable 2 let us call it i and j. Then
that
pair i j must occur in set of topples here
then that essentially.
..
So, we have some definitions we say that a
constraint or we say that assignment. We will
use a bar as an assignment which will be a
short form for a set of so a over scope s.
So,
basically this means that this scope as says
on which variables this assignment is done
and this assignment selects 1 value for each
variable from their respective domain
essentially. So, explicitly I would say something
like ah x 1 is equal to some value a then
x 2 is equal to some value b and so on. But
implicitly we will just assume that we will
as
a vector of a b and so on. And we assume that
somehow we are able to specify what the
variables are essentially it does not really
matter the only important thing is that
assignment is over a scope S. The scope S
basically says that these are the variables
to be
giving value essentially. So, an assignment
a a over a scope S satisfies a constraint
ci if
the following wholes that the scope of this
constrain which you will call S i is a subset
of
this scope S which means every variable in
the constraint has a value and we will use
the
term pie to talk of a projection.
So, I am sure you are familiar with a notion
of a projection here of a bar over this set
S i.
So, why by this we mean that from this assignment
a which is over some set of variables
which you called S select only those values
which correspond to those variables which
belong to S i. And this is projection of a
bar onto the subset of variable is a subset
of R i
so an assignment satisfies. So, if I given
assignment here for example, i put a queen
here
.and i put the queen let say here and i put
queen here So, this assignment says a is equal
to
1 for the first queen 4 for the second queen
and 2 for the third queen that is an a bar
for
this particular assignment and I can say that
this assignment a satisfies the solution R
1 2
why because if I take the projection of the
of the these variables on the first and the
second variable which is 1 and 4 I can find
that 1 4 of course in my relation R.
So, it satisfy the relation R then we say
that an assignment a bar is consistent. If
it
satisfies all
constraints in its scope I will not expand
upon this. Basically we are saying
this a bar has a scope S and for whichever
constraint that scope of that constraint is
a
subset of S. It must satisfy that constraints
which means projection over those variables
must be belong to that particular triples
essentially. So, you can see that this particular
assignment which I have here where first queen
is here the fourth queen second queen is
here and the third queen is here is consistent.
So, I have not written those constraints,
but
you can see that between 1 and 2. It is satisfying
the expected constraints what is the
constraints that the queen must know the attack
another queen which here express
explicitly here you could have express. It
has a relation which says x if that is the
array
then xi not equal to y i or something like
that essentially if x 1 xi why location of
the
queen that they are not on the diagonal. They
are not on the same row they are not on the
same column you could have express it something
like that essentially but we have
expressed explicit here.
So, we can see that the first 2 queens are
not attacking each other .So, they and be
that
shown by this the second and the third also
not attacking. So, if you are written R 2
3 you
could have seen that and the first and the
third also not attacking and they would have
been present in this essentially. So, we say
that this assignment a bar is consistent
essentially sometime you use the term partial
assignment which means that if an
assignment only 2 a subset of the variables.
But we will use the time term
interchangeably or a partial solution some
time we say. So, an assignment is consistent
if
it satisfies all the constraints which call
within the scope in this case there are 3
constraints between queen 1, queen 2, queen
1, queen 3 and queen 2, queen 3 and all the
3 are satisfied. So, this assignment is consistent
now observe that just because it is
consistent it does not mean it can be a part
of a solution. Because you can you surely
know that this cannot be extended to a complete
solution essentially you cannot put a
.value and you this thing you put it here
it will attack these 2. If you put it here
it will
attack these 2 if you put it here it will
attack this if you put here it will attack
these 2. So,
you cannot place a variable.
So, this a consistent partial solution but
it is not a consistent full solution. A full
solution
is a consistent assignment to all the variables
which is another way of saying that what
you are said here that a CSP solution to a
CSP assignment to each variable which
satisfies all the constrain essentially which
is the same thing that is saying that if you
assign all the variables and it is consistent
it is a solution essentially. So, how do we
solve? So, again we want to look at general
purpose methods of solving CS P's just like
with it for state space or we did not care
what the state was and where the moves end
came from as long as we had move zen function
and as long as we had a goal test
function. We said we will use the search algorithm
that are used likewise we have just
made an observation that many problems can
be posed as C S P’s I have mentioned
sometime during planning. That planning can
be posed as a CSP which we will not have
time to going here but it can be planning
can be also posed as sat which is the special
case of C S P.
Both are slightly different formulation and
we will look at in due course couple of more
problems which can be posed as CSP but we
want to look at general purpose ways of
solvency C S P’s essentially. So, let me
discuss 1 more problem before we go just to
to
highlight what are the issues involved. So,
let say we are doing this map coloring map
coloring can also be posed as CSP before we
come to map coloring we are not said
anything about the scopes of this constraints
essentially do we have any constraints on
the scope of this constraints. I have posed
this problem where the scope was 2 variables
between queen 1 queen 2 or queen 1 queen 3
or between queen 1 and queen 4 and so on
and so forth why not between 3 variables between
4 variables in this. You can express
constraints and in more variables for example,
if I had express the constraints as a
constraint of 4 variables I would actually
be expressing the solution itself, because
I
would have just basically the set of solutions
in that essentially. So, in fact, this kind
of
illustrates the idea that we pursue in constraint
satisfaction problems that you do not have
to specify the problem completely as long
as you give some specification of the set
of
constraints it is a task of the solver to
elicit a solution out of that essentially.
.So, what is the solution to this? You know
that solution to the CSP there in fact only
solution 1 is 3 1 2 4 and the other is 2 3
1 4 2 3 1 4 2. And the other 1 is if I start
with 2
and 4 1 and 3 I have only these 3 now this
particular relation is a relation on the set
of 4
variables this is called a solution relation
where R refers to this constraint satisfaction
problem. So, correspondent to a constraint
satisfaction problem there is a solution
relation and it is task of the solver to elicit
the this solution from the CSP I have only
specify binary constraints here between 2
variables. And the solver will eventually
tell
me the these are the 2 possible solutions
it may not express in this form but it gave
me an
assignment of all possible variables and we
will do that. So, without again loss of
generality we will assume that we are working
with binary relations.
A binary C S P’s and a binary C S P’s
we mean that C S P’s which have scopes of
size
either 1 or 2 essentially scope of size 1
basically says that I am defining subset of
domain
scope of size to subset of the cross product
of 2 domains. So, binary CSP has scopes 1
or
2 and such a CSP is called binary CSP and
it has been shown that any higher order CSP
can be converted to a binary CSP by adding
more variable essentially. So, I will leave
this as a small thought exercise for you to
work on how can I converted into how can I
convert this. For example, into a binary CSP
if this was my original CSP which is the
solution itself how can converted into a binary
CSP. So, we will stick to binary C S P’s
because we know the there is a whole lot of
methods which obtain those problems and
other problems can be express as a binary
C S P's. So, this map coloring problem is
naturally pose as a binary CSP ao.
..
Let say I have 3 countries will not name them
and let us say my formulation of C S P’s
that I have a relation between this, this,
and this. So, let us just called this x 1
x 2 and x 3
and let us say they have the same domains
which is let say just 2 colors are allowed
red
and blue. So, I think that I think the domains
inside this circles and the relation is not
equal to now we can see that this problem
has 2 solutions. You can color these 2 red
and
this 1 blue or you can color these 2 blue
and this 1 red essentially which means implicitly
there is a constraint between these 2 variables.
But that constraint is not explicit it has
not
been mentioned in the CSP the CSP only says
that I have a constrain between x 1 and x
and between x 1 and x 3. I do not say anything
about x 2 and x 3 but eventually off
course, this can be again elicit ate through
a process of solving the constraint. And we
will try and see whether we get some insight
into how we acquire new relations in the in
some manner essentially. So, how so let us
look at these 2 problems. So, we have now
you know in those case 4 variables in this
case 3 variables and we have some domains
and so on. How can we solve a C S P?
The simplest approach you can go back to state
space search. You try you sign a value
for the first variable; you have sign a value
for the second variable; you assign a value
for third variable assign a value for fourth
variable and so on. Finish an assignment in
state space search we would have finish the
assignment and then check whether it is goal
.state or not in constraint satisfaction problems.
We can backtrack earlier why because the
moment you know that some constraint is not
being satisfied or some we have defined
the lotion of consistent assignment or consistent
partial solution. The moment we know
that the assignment is not consistent we can
backtrack from their essentially. So, you
do
not have to assign values to all variables.
So, in other words you do not have to assign
values to all variables. So, in other words
you do not have to as in this case of course
you
will backtrack only when you see the fourth
when you try to put the fourth queen. But
if
you let us try a 6 queen problem, you will
see that there is some kind of processing
you
can do when you can back track only or you
might be able to backtrack only.
.
So, the simplest algorithm for solving a CSP
is called backtracking it is a official name
of name of this algorithm essentially. So,
everybody uses this term essentially. So,
what
do we have? We have constraint satisfaction
problems given x given d and given c
essentially. So, let us this outline this
algorithm So, 1 issue that keep in mind is
that let
say you have assigned some value to x 2 and
then you are trying for values of e c. And
let say you assigned the third value to x
2 let us say in a set of domain you are trying
the
third value 2 x 2. Then you go forward to
x 3 and you find that there is no values to
x 3
and you need to back track to the fourth value
of x 2 and then try all values of x 3 again.
So, the fact that you every time you go back
and forth you have to keep track of what
.values left for you to try this algorithm
does takes a very approach it makes a copy
of the
domain every time.
So, it start up by saying i gets the value
1 di is a copy of di in this case d 1 and
while i is
in this range n it does the following
it calls off function call select value. So,
let say x
gets a value from a function called select
value I should also initialize a equal to
empty
initially I do not have a value for the partial
solution given a select value for this x i
x i d
i c. So, what this select value function will
do is it will give me the next value for xi
from
its domain d i; d i prime actually with this
consistent
by this you mean it is consistent
with all the previous variables that have
been given values. So, if xi is equal to 4
let us
say then if there is a constraint between
1 3 and 4. Then this value for the first variable
must be consistent with those first and third
value since essentially the way that you have
just defined there essentially. So, it will
written 2 things it will either it something
called
null which means it cannot find a value then
we say i goes to i minus 1 D i prime hence
i
goes to i plus 1 you have got some value for
x 1. You got some value for x 2 you got
some value for x 3 or let me try and draw
more elaborate diagram let say x 1 has theses
values x 2 has or d 1.
So, let us say you are looking at x 4 now
and let say you have always progressing from
let say your select value function always
fix the value from left to right, because
they are
in some list and it has selected this value
for d 1 and this value for d 2 and this value
for
d 3. And now we are trying to find if any
of these values for d 4 is consistent with
this
assignment we have here essentially. So their
2 thing that can happen either it can it will
say that no nothing is possible here which
means I was go and look for a new value for
d
3 here, because we are tried this. So, we
are doing simple that first search over this
3 of
possibilities where you start with the first
1 here then the first 1 here then the first
1 here
and then keep back trap. If you cannot find
a variable value here you must go back to
this
1 and try the next value for this essentially
which means you must set i is equal to i
minus 1. So, I do not need to change this
right.
So, let see what select value is going to
do
essentially what it will do? So, let say you
are
looking at xi from di and c it will say let
us say a gets head of di if it is a list it
takes a
first value and it says di di before that
it must have check which says that if di is
equal to
.empty then return null. So, if any point
di becomes empty it must return null otherwise
it
it should go into the this loops looking for
consistent value if a i if a sorry let us
call this
a a i if a comma a i. It means the whole solution
that has been constructed so far which
we will as a. So, this 3 values in this examples
plus this fourth value that we are we are
just picked from its domain we put them all
together and that is a new partial solution
if
this is consistent
then return a i. Well I called it x here you
could have called it x it does
not matter. So, it is in a loop inside taking
out values from the domain taking out and
showing them to speak essentially. So, when
it was doing d 3 that d 3 prime had thrown
away these two values from the domain.
So, they were not there in d 3 prime anymore.
So, when it backtrack it must try the next
value essentially then it must try the next
value then the next value. And if you cannot
find there is must backtrack that is the standard.
Therefore search chronological
backtracking that we have been talking about
this other form of backtracking that we had
mentioned dependency directed backtracking
was actually invented for solving for
improving this algorithm backtrackings. So,
that instead of if you cannot find a value
for
d 4 just to give an example that let say only
constraint that d 4 participate it is in let
us
call it R 1 2 4 which means this variables
1 and 2 and 4 essentially or if you want to
work
with binary constraints and let us say R 1
4 and R 2 4. So, let say the only constraints
d 4
participates as in with variable 1 and variable
2 with variable 2 then if you cannot find
the value for d 4. What is the point of looking
for new value for d 3? Because d 3
anyway not influencing the consistency of
the choice of d 4 essentially the only thing
that d 4 is getting influences by this relation
R 1 4 or by R 2 4.
And the fact that you cannot find value for
d 4 means that one of this relations you
cannot satisfy which means actually you should
really jump back here. But of course we
will not get into that here, because it needs
a little bit more formulization. So, that
is the
general idea of dependency directed backtracking
that if you can keep track of which
constraint is being evaluated. Then you can
jump back to one of the variables in that
constraint in this case they have binary here
essentially. But in our example we just to
i is
equal to i minus 1 which is like doing chronological
backtracking if you cannot find a
value for d 4 try a new value for d 3 and
so on essentially. So, that is a i mean I
have
written may be it is not quite correct something
is missing here. But you can work that
.out work out the details, but the basic idea
is to go down this set of choices looking
for a
new value for the is variable. If you cannot
find it if you can find it go to the next
variable which is what we have doing here
i is equal to i plus 1 di copied the domain
and
solution that we have made and then keep going
forward in that session if you cannot
find it backtrack. So, it is simple depth
first search being done over this structure
of the
now this algorithm is actually the simplest
the starting point for constraint satisfaction
problem algorithms.
The other algorithm which improve upon that
do the following is that for example, some
algorithms when they are doing select value
though look head to see whether or given
choice will in future conflicts with some
vary variable essentially. So, that is one
kind of
you know improvement which is called look
ahead algorithm then we have this kind of
intelligent backtracking algorithm. So, dependency
directed backtracking algorithm that
we are talking about essentially and there
are some other things that we will discuss.
So,
that you get a flavor of that essentially,
but this by and large is a the simple algorithm.
Now observe that backtracking happens the
moment of partial solution is what is a
partial solution we are talking about here
it is a value for a 1 for a 2 and up to a
i minus
1. And we cannot find we cannot extend this
to a i or the is value for the is variable
or 2
x i. Let say we cannot find a value for this
is variable and we backtrack at this point
itself
we do not go further to see you know, because
at this point as you can see no by
definition not right no a solution is a consistent
assignment to all the variables. Or in
other words a solution is an assignment to
all the variables.
So, that every constraint is satisfied and
a partial solution or a or a partial assignment
is
consistent. If it satisfies all the constrain
for whom values have been selected or who's
scope fall within this essentially here. So,
we say that constraint ci assignment a bar
satisfies ci if the scope of the ci is has
a value which means it is already in the
assignment. And the projection of this assignment
over this scope of S i is a subset of
this which means it which actually I should
say belongs to this belongs word here belong
to this and in. So, that is only for with
respect to 1 constraint ci and assignment
is
consistent if it is satisfies the all the
constrain with satisfy this property which
means to
scope are contained in this and who's projection
is contained in that correspondent
essentially. So, it can only be that it can
never be the case that a that assignment which
is
.a partial solution which is not consistent
can never consistency. So, when I was talking
about beginning on CSP one of the thing. So,
I had said was that CSP is very interesting
because it allows you to combine search with
reasoning now that reasoning part web
have not seemed. Let me just give you a motivation
for that and then in the next class,
we will see how that is done. So, one of the
another problem which is pose as a CSP you
know if you solving a crossword puzzle. Or
if you are solving sudoku or something you
do a lot of reasoning in fact you are supposed
to do more reasoning than search.
.
So, they these problems are similar they are
called some of you must have looked at such
problem and if you just search on the web
you will find examples. So, for example, you
might say send plus more. So, these are sort
of arithmetic problems in which we the
digits have not been revealed, but they have
been replaced by letters and your task is
to
find out what digit does each letter stand
for. So, we assume that each assignment is
distinct that that 1 letter stands for exactly
1 digit and so on. So, how would you solve
such a problem essentially? So, if you want
solve this or let me take another example.
So, here is a another example. So, this plus
this should give you apple essentially. So,
if
you wanted to solve something like this then
what you would do is you would create a
variable for each a place for each letter
of course the number of variables are number
of
distinct letters in this problem, but you
want to find vales for them. So, these boxes
that
.an creating are boxes for values this a plus
and obviously you must create some more
boxes which are for carry over.
So, 4 boxes for carry over and you can define
the domains of so these variables so the
domain of this is 0 slash 1, because we adding
2 numbers we can never have carry over
moves and 1 and the domains of these are 0
to 9 essentially. So, the kind of reasoning
that Sangeetha was talking about we can do
here essentially. So, for example, you can
observe that this must be 1, because you can
never be get a value of more than 1 which
means this carry over must of course we are
not interested on this. But never the less
the
what the moment we have said this a a equal
to 1 we know that this is equal to 1 and this
equal to 1. We can fill in the value there
t is 9, why t 9? And it must be distinct this
a p
and t are distinct they cannot stand for same
digit. So, which means this p cannot be 1
and in any case p cannot be 1 So, if t is
nine then what is p is 0 this must be 1 we
have 0
here also know and we have nine for t here
we have nine here nine here So, this must
be
eight this must be 1 So, we know this must
be 3.
So this is 0, now, we need to fill in this
is 8. So, this leaves only 2 for this. So,
we have
off course, solved in this problem now, and
we are solved it through a process of
reasoning certain some rezoning with it you
know this can only be 1 and know this kind
of stuff. Now, if you off course, were not
should I say smart enough to do this kind
of
reasoning you could still have try this algorithm
backtracking here you could have said
try a value for a try a value for b and so
on and so forth. Off course, we have to express
the constraint, how do we express the constraints
that this plus this must be either this
must be either equal to this plus this or
this plus this this plus carry over 1 and
modulo
10. So, we have to express that carefully
essentially, but the point is that we a try
to make
here is that solving constraint satisfaction
problems not necessarily have to be done
through a search method like backtracking.
They can be done through other processes
like reasoning in some way now can this reasoning
be done in general purposely
essentially.
Of course, here we are exploding the rules
of arithmetic and it turns out that yes indeed
you can do a certain amount of. So, this process
is called constraint propagation. So, we
are saying that if this is 1 this must be
0; this is 0; this must be 9 and this must
we are
.propagating the constraint. So, what are
we doing here basically reducing the domains
of
the variable we have reduce this from 0 to
9 to just 1 value 1 and just to 0 and so on
so
forth. And the moment we reduce the value
of some domain some variable we can
propagate a reduction to another domain. This
idea of propagation is of course very
common in reasoning. And we will see in the
next class little bit about how this can be
generalized. And we will look at another interesting
problem that propagation demands
that quite effectively. So, we will stop here
with this.
.