So, we have been looking at reasoning in proportional
logic. And today we want to look
at recent method known as the resolution method.
This is given by Alan Robinson in
nineteen sixty five. So, it is a fairly recent
method if you compare it with for example,
free gaze axiomatic system which is more than
2 years old. This is by recent and it is
motivated by the fact that you want to write
a computer program to generate proofs
which means you have to find proofs automatically.
Now, if you look at the high level
algorithm for finding proof it basically says
picks some rule of inference, pick some
applicable data and produce some new data
add it to the system. So, it is basically
a
search algorithm which is searching in this
phase of sentences which can be produce and
trying to produce the sentences that you are
interested in.
..
So, to motivate this resolution method let
us go back to the problem that we have started
with the example that we looking at which
said that P and R or something like that R
replies Q. P and S implies T and not using
the same symbols, but anyway it is a same
problem
and from this we have to show T. Now, if you
if you go back over the proof we
did for this and this was to be shown. So,
this is 1 2 3 4 then we derive it for example,
P
from this thing and there was a rule called
1 called simplification. So, we use 1 rule
for
inference called simplification. And then
we derived R by the same rule then from R
and
R and Q with a derived Q. So, 6 2 the second
rule of inherency use there and then from
R
and not R or S we derived S. So, this is from
6 and 4 and the rule called differential
syllogism. So, I just used ds there then from
this we get from 5 and 8 we get P and S.
And then finally, we get T from 9 3 and so
this proof required us to use 3 rules of
inference simplification 4 rules of differential
syllogism and the addition. And then of
course, we have to choose which ruled to pick
and what to apply.
So, and so it look nice and simple when you
look at just these 4 sentences and the
conclusion that you want to draw. But in practice
the set of facts that available to a
reasoning system would be hundreds of may
be 1000s of facts and you may want to ask
whether certain formula is true or not. So,
it is it is not that only relevant things
are given
to you there may be many irrelevant other
formulas and there may be 100s of rule which
may be applicable. So, if you look at the
power safety search example like we are
looking at in planning. It generates a huge
launching factor and the number of possible
.things we can do is very large essentially.
We have not use any axioms here so by and
large we try to systems were axioms are not
needed. It essentially they just add put
enough rules of inference which will work,
but as a motivator for this method say some
other example we have given a simple formula
S and you are asked to derive P or not T
we asked to derive.
So, you must distinguish between this in tactic
process of deriving formulas as suppose
to the semantic process of looking at the
truth value. And saying this formula is true
if
you look at P or not P you can obviously say
it is true it is and it is quite trivial,
but the
question is can you derive it in the system.
So, just say that it is not straight forward
to
the write P implies P system if not. So, in
fact, you cannot derive if you are given only
S
and you have given all kinds of rule of inference
simplification and differential
syllogism. There are so many of them it is
not going to help you can never derive this
from this equation that Robinson’s method.
Resolution method is a complete method if
you use only 1 rule of inference and it does
not need any extra axiom system for that is
why so very attractive it makes the task of
programming. It is simpler to simpler you
take
that rule all need to decide on which data
to apply here that is of true still not a
straight
forward problem.
.
So, what is the resolution rule as it is called?
So, will look at the simple form there is
a
more general form which we will may or may
not look at it later if you are given P or
Q
.and if you are given
not P or S. We can derive Q or S this is the
resolution rule in the
simplest form it could be P and Q or R also
does not matter. It does not have to be just
thing, but in the simplest form it has just
2 proposition here 2 propositions here. So,
in
the language of resolution method we call
each of these elements are literal and
resolution effect resolution method works
formulas in what is known as clause form.
And we are concerned in proposition logic
clause form is the same as conjunctive normal
form. So, we have to first construct your
formulas in clause form or conjunctive normal
form which means that you cannot use things
like P imply Q. And so if you have a
situation like P implies Q you should convert
it into not P or Q essentially. So, I will
take
it for granted that you can convert any given
formula into clause form clause form or C
n
f is basically a formula of the kind C 1 and
C 2 and C k where C I is of the form d 1 or
d
2 or d r.
Let us say and each d I is either a proposition
or negation of proposition. So, it is a very
simple structures form at the outer most level
it is a conjunction of clauses. So, C 1 and
C 2 and C k each clause is a disjunction of
literals d 1 d 2 or d R each literal is either
a
proposition or it is negation. The negation
sign is some sense occurs in the inner most
package if you imagine brackets all over the
places essentially. So, for example, you
could start up by converting this problem
into clause form saying P is the clause Q
is the
sorry R is the clause. Then not R or Q is
a clause then not P or not S or T is a clause
this
corresponds to that this is not R or S. So,
I converted this 4 sentences into clause form
here. So, each one of there is a clause and
I can think of it as a P and R and this thing
and
this thing and this thing have a larger formula.
Now, first of all we must ask ourselves is
this rule a sound rule or a valid rule of
inference and its validity is based on a validity
of
this equivalence P or Q. Or so I can keep
writing this, this should be consistence
we need
this larger equivalence to argue about what
we are doing. But in practice the only think
we need this and this implies this which means
P or Q and not P or S implies Q or S,
So, for the rule to be sound so this implication
is a total logic it is a rule of inference
that
we have if you this and if you see this. Then
you can produce this and remember that
unlike the rule that that we talked about
earlier these are not patterns in the sense
that you
cannot plug in any arbitrary formula here.
This is the clause; this is the clause and
this is
the clause which means the consistence or
proposition or negation of propositions it
is
not a arbitrary formulas but it take any such
2 clauses. So, if you want to describe this
.rule if you get 1 clause C 1 another clause
C 2 and one of them has literal and one of
them has a negation of that literal. We can
produce a clause to add up all the literals
here
and remove the, what is cancelling each other
in some says. So, we are talked about
clause form also instead of writing it C 1
and C 2 we often write it as C 1 comma C 2
comma C k. So, we think as it is a set likewise
this 1 d 1 comma d 2 d R where the
comma is interpreted appropriately and in
this outer level and in this outer level and
or in
the inner level sorry the joined by the and…
So, the rule of inference required by this
implication be true, but we are going to be
in
trusted in this as you will see in this moment
why that is the case. So, this is called the
resolvent this is called resolvent I always
keep getting let us call this resolvent whenever
you add that resolvent to the set of clauses.
Then 2 set of clauses are equal in other words
what we are saying is that we can keep adding
clauses to the set. So, the resolution
method works as follows that is start with
a set of initial clauses let us called them
C 1 C
2 C 3 C k. And then you replace or you add
1 more clause to this which is the first
resolvent which means you are saying that
this set of clause. I am using a comma here
and you should not confuse this comma’s
equivalent to and here or you can write and
that is to be safe I added 1 more clause here
then I can add one more. So, what I am
saying is there I keep adding this resolvents
to my set of clauses and what I get is an
equivalent set of clause. This set is equivalent
logically equivalent to this, this set is
logically equivalent to this.
So, you must prove that this is indeed the
cases once you prove this it is easy to prove
this, because from the right hand side to
the left hand side. It is trivial from the
left hand
side to the right hand side is based on this
that you are adding this extra clause Q or
S.
And then you can basically show this is the
topology and I keep doing this till I get
a
clause which looks like till I get the formula
which looks like this
this is called the empty
clause till I generate an empty clause. So,
what am I doing? I am starting with set of
clauses C 1 C 2 up to C k and I added with
a first resolvent R 1 then to this added R
then R 3 R 4 and so on till R l. And at some
point I was able to generate the empty clause
and I added the empty clause to this set and
that is actually the algorithm terminates.
So,
what is the algorithm? Algorithm says take
any 2 clauses which are which can be
resolved which means one of them has a literal.
And other one has a negation of that
literal resolve them produce a new clause
and added to this set. And then pick any 2
.clauses apply the resolution rule keep applying
the resolution rule keep, adding clauses
till at some point you generate the empty
clause. How do you get the empty clause? If
you see clause like this P if you see clause
like not P you can see P or nothing not P
or
also nothing.
So, when you apply this same rule here there
is no Q and there is no S. So, all you left
with this empty clause we sometime write with
a box sometime we write with this.
Basically it is an empty clause empty clause
stands for false or it always false. So, I
have
jumped a little bit ahead from the national
deduction of style of proof in the national
deduction style of proof. We said that we
keep adding new formulas and we terminate
when we find the formula that we interested
in here I already jumped ahead. And said
that the resolution method keeps adding new
formulas and it terminates when you
generate the empty clause when you find 2
clauses like this. And so this box is also
used
to denote an empty clause this bottom also
can be used to denote an empty clause.
Basically an empty clause stands for something
which is false in the resolution method
terminates with an empty clause. And we will
see a moment why or I will tell you in the
moment wise, but what the implication of this?
What is the implication of the fact that
you have added empty clause to your set of
clauses?
We have to go back and see what were we are
saying here, we are saying that this set of
clauses logically equivalent to this set of
clauses which is logically equivalent to this
set
of clauses and so on which is logically equivalent
to this clause. Now, what is the truth
value of this clause? It is false, because
it is something and something and something
and
something and something and false. So, this
whole formula is evaluated to false which
means this is false which means this is false
and this is false I could have use the
resolution method to say terminate for the
example. In that example we are doing
terminate when generate T essentially, but
we are not doing that we are saying that
terminate when you generate in an empty clause
which means we are trying to show that
this formulas are unsatisfiable. That is why
this method is called reputation method it
is
used to show that a formula is unsatisfiable.
A formula when I say this is the large
formula right this got many clauses inside
it and it used to show that the formula is
unsatisfiable.
And the reason why the resolution method is
implemented in this manner is, because it
has been shown that the method is complete.
If you want to derive null clause it is not
.necessarily complete if you want to derive
any arbitrary clause which may be an tail
by
the system. So, remember completeness means
whatever can be derived basically
resolution method is complete for showing
that a formula is unsatisfiable. If you give
with an unsatisfiable formula it will there
will a derivation which will derive the null
clause from the set of unsatisfiable formula
is it going to help us. We are not interested
in
unsatisfiable formulas or are we could we
interested in unsatisfiable formula. So, let
us a
question I asked you earlier in the last class
we have 3 kinds of formulas; one is valid
formulas which are always true on the all
valuations there are satisfiable formula which
are true under some valuations. So, for example,
P implies Q is true in under certain
valuations then there are unsatisfiable formulas
which have which are true for any
valuation which are false for all valuations.
And essentially what we are saying is that
if we have unsatisfiable formulas then you
can
test it using syntactic procedure of this
resolution method which means keep applying
the
resolution method and you will be able to
derive null clause. And so first of all you
have
to convince that deriving the null clause
is indeed showing the unsatisfiable. Because
of
this equivalence this whole formula is equivalent
to the 1 before that which is equivalent
to this which is equivalent to this which
is equivalent to this which means the original
set
that started with is shown to be unsatisfiable.
And remember that everything is to be
expressed in clause form. So, if I could so
have that problem to solve if you look at
that
top 5 lines there I have 4 premises given
and 1 confusion to be drawn can I set of
produce an unsatisfiable formula from there.
So, the process is straight forward. So, let
us look at the clause form here. So, I have
C 1 C 2 C 3 C 4 C 5. What am I trying to do?
If I look at my logical notation I am trying
to do this P 1 P 2 P 3.
..
So, I am saying given these 5 clauses all
those 4 statements which are equivalent to
clauses, because this is the end statement
it is broken down into 2 clauses. Because
the
clause form says that the clause is has only
the this junction side inside. So, P becomes
the separate clause R becomes the separate
clause this becomes R or Q this becomes not
P or S or T and this is anyway not R or S.
So, what am I really trying to do was this
that
can I derive T from this clauses. If you go
the back to the deductions you know it said
that if you can do that then you should be
able to derive C 1 and C 2 sorry. So, remember
that that is what a deduction said that you
could take actually you could do it 1 by 1.
But
eventually we will come to this formula and
I will leave that as a small exercise. Because
we are also shown somewhere in between if
we have P and Q and the whole thing
implies R then P implies Q implies R. So,
the 2 formulas are simple. So, eventually
we
can all the ans come together here. So, this
is the set of premises implies the conclusion
is what we are trying to show to be true.
So, what are trying to show? You are trying
to show that this formula this larger formula
is a topology what I have with me is a method
which can show that a given formula is
unsatisfiable can I brief this gap is not
it? So, that is why I ask this question there
are 3
kind of statements valid statement, satisfiable
statement and unsatisfiable statement. If
I
take a negation of a formula what where does
this how to how do they get related to each
other if I take a negation of satisfiable
formula for example, if I take the negation
of valid
formula or take a negation of unsatisfiable
formula. So, there is a clear relation and
you
.need to think about little bit about this
between the valid formula and the unsatisfiable
formulas. A valid formula is true under all
valuations which means every row in the truth
table. It will end up with true, if take if
you take the negation of that formula then
every
lower ends of become false. So, I have this.
So, I am trying to show that this is true
which means you show that negation of this
C 1 and C 2 and C 3 and C 4 and C 5
implies T is unsatisfiable.
Instead of trying to show that that this is
the topology which means you can be derived
and assuming a sound and complete system.
Instead of trying to show that it is a
topology I can say that take it is negation
and that there is a unsatisfiable formula.
So,
you must convenience yourself that this is
the sound step that if I take topology and
convert and convert its take it is negation
it becomes unsatisfiable. So, I produce now
what I think is a unsatisfiable formula and
of course, to check whether it is unsatisfiable
instead of constructing a 2 table. I will
use the resolution method to check whether
that is
the case. Now, just serious of steps if I
go to take this not inside so I have to convert
this
into clause form. Remember that the resolution
method applies only to clause form if I
take this not inside I will get
not of not of C 1 C 5 or T. So, remember this
equivalence
which said that alpha implies beta is not
equivalent to not alpha or beta. So, this
whole
thing I am taking as alpha. So, I am taking
not of this alpha and or this T and then when
I
have push this not finally, inside what I
will get this C 1 and C 2 and C 3.
So, that is the logically equivalent formula
now I have the formula that I have been
interested in clause form. So, each of these
is a clause I we already said that. So, each
of
them is a clause. So, we end this, this is
just a literal from not T is also clause essentially.
Now, we have a approach to using the resolution
method which is that you take the set of
clauses that are given to you which is the
optimizes. You take the conclusion and take
it
is negation not of T and add it as a clause
and the claim is that this set is unsatisfiable
is
it unsatisfiable we can try and show that
using the resolution method essentially. So,
the
resolution proofs all usually shown as directed
graph directly recycle graph. So, the
resolution they are called. So, let us try
and do the resolution method here. So, just
write
the clauses again now this is P this is 1
clause this is R this is not R or Q not P
or not S or
T not R or S. These are the 5 given clauses
and the negation of this is P I have the 6
clauses. So, C 1 to C 5 when negation of the
goal and negation of the conclusion which
is the 6 clauses.
.So, before we proceed you should be able
to see this is a very proof contradiction
what
we are saying for the given these clauses
assume that conclusion is not true. And then
show the whole set becomes unsatisfiable which
means of course, this is unsatisfiable.
The only reason why this could be unsatisfiable
if this last clause was not correct which
means C 1 C 2 C 3 C 4 C 5 are anyway given
to us you cannot assume them to be false.
The only reason why this formula becomes false
is because of not of T is there so not of
T meaning is false. Therefore, not of T must
be false itself it means T must be true it
is
proved by contradiction. So, that with a small
task of finding a proof and what is the
proof is a derivation which ends in an empty
clause or a null clause. So, let us see we
can
take any 2 clauses and resolve them. So, for
example, a h m well in this there are not
too
many choices, but in general a larger problem
will after you many choices, but in this
case we do not have too many. So, let us take
this and this and you get negation of Q. So,
you must see that what I am doing is applying
the resolution step from this clause. I am
removing R from this clause I am removing
not of R.
So, from this clause I am removing R and from
this clause I am removing not of R. So,
what I am left with this Q then is that correct
this Q is not very useful for me I can take
this and this and I can get S. So, remember
this is a directed graph I can take any 2
clauses. So, this is just a set. So, I can
take now this and this I get not P or T see
I can
resolve this with this or I can resolve this
with this. But just for the sake of the argument
let say we will resolve this with this. So,
you can see that actually we have derived
T we
have actually derived T, but off course, as
we know from the national deduction method
that is quite possible to do that. But our
method does not stop here our method says
we
have must derive the null clause. So, you
can see from this and this we can derive the
null form. So, this graph represents the proof
that the given set of clauses is unsatisfiable
and the proof wholes, because of this equivalence
that we have seen that we are keep
adding new things. And in the end we added
the empty clause and in the empty clause
basically stands for false you can see that
the empty clause is saying T is true. And
at the
same time you are saying not T is true and
obviously that stands for false or
contradiction.
If we can derive an empty clause then we have
shown that this set of clauses
unsatisfiable which means this large formula
is unsatisfiable. And it can only be
unsatisfiable if not T false nothing else
can be false because say that are premises
given
.to us if not T is false then T must be true.
So, let us quickly just look at this rule
what
does says it says P or it says in terms of
literals at least P and P implies Q. And you
can
do Q now you can see that if I want to converted
into clause form. I have P and not P or
Q and I deriving Q because you know these
2 are equivalent essentially. So, we can see
that is just 1 example of the resolution rule
been applied or if you look at says P implies
Q and not Q implies not P. And you can see
this is again not P or Q and not Q and not
P.
So, again in this form when you replace P
implies Q with not P or Q you can see it is
a
same resolution rule being applied take a
literal from here Q take the negation from
other
1 and cancel that and whatever remains is
that. So, all these rules as we can see are
special cases of the resolution rule that
we have stated here. If at the resolution
rule more
general than this as you saw in this example
we does not have to be only 2 literals it
can
be more than 2 literals.
So, we use not P or not S or T and consider
it with S. So, removed S from here and what
was left was not P or T is not it? So, that
is so the resolution method is a sound and
complete proof procedure for the case of proportional
logic is it to introduced in 1965.
And since an lot of theorem proving work is
based essentially on the resolution method
essentially it is most popular way of proving
theorems, but so far we have seen the
proportional logic. So, what is the language
of proportional logic? We have set of
propositions and they could be stand for anything.
And we do not know the only thing
that is sort of this system is solving out
for us is the meaning of the connectives when
you have this connectives what do the sentences
mean? What do compound sentences
mean when they when are they true and then
we can set of know extend that truth value
of essentially if you go back to the example
we started with this the Socrates argument.
All men are mortal Socrates in a man; Socrates
is man this is beyond our reach to talk
about this argument is beyond the reach of
proposition logic. Because we cannot really
do anything with this sentences essentially,
because what you need here is to somehow
understand what you mean by all. And then
relation between being man and being mortal
and then to say the same relation between
being man and being mortal this is applied
to
Socrates, because Socrates happen to be a
man. Now, this is not possible in proportion
logic, because if you say this is P this is
Q then there is nothing we can be do. There
is no
logical connective applied here essentially
we could say for example, m stands for man
and n something else R stands for mortal.
And you could say m implies R is, but you
can
.see that motion of all is essentially. To
handle this we need to go to first order logic
which is a more expressive language which
allows us to look inside sentences.
Remember in proportion logic a sentence is
atomic and the only thing you can say about
a sentence is that in our mind it stands for
something. And whether it is true or false,
but
in first order logic a sentence can be broken
down into its consequence. And you can
look at the relation between the different
constitutes what is the relation between of
being between being a man and being a mortal?
And then saying that this relation carries
a what to Socrates, because Socrates is a
man therefore, same relation was applied to
him
that also mortal that is possible in first
certain logic. First certain logic will introduce
motion of individuals men Socrates and so
on. In proportion logic there is no individuals
there are only sentences, the sentences can
only be true or false whereas, the individuals
are things which can participate in relation
essentially. So, in the next class, when you
meet on Wednesday we will look at of logic
and we will look at all these proof methods
in the context of first order logic plus some
extra rules. So, we will stop here.
.