Let us get back to our local search. And the
key words, that you must keep in your mind
is Optimization.
.
Remember, that we converted the states space
search problem to on optimization
problem, by saying that we want the best value
for the heuristic function. And
essentially, we are developing these local
search algorithms, to explore the surface
define
by the heuristic function, which we are now
calling evaluation function. Because, that
is
for the optimizing community call set. And
looking for minimum and maximum value,
as a case maybe…
And because we are exploring local search
algorithms, which means that, the algorithm
will not necessarily search the entire space.
But, we will terminate, using some criteria
before that especially. We have the problem
of local optimum. And essentially, we are
exploring these different algorithms to try
and get around this problem of local optima.
Because, the simplest algorithm that we saw
hill climbing is very efficient, it requires
very little space.
.In fact, a constant space or being search
for that matter, which also requires constant
space. And it will just go up the slop and
stop. It will not take an exponential amount
of
time. But, the travel is that. That is not,
what we want? We want an global optima, which
will not be the maxima, that the hill climbing
will find. So, we have looking at ways of
getting around or getting beyond those local
optima’s. So, therefore one method that
we
saw in the last class was . essentially.
And we have said that, hill climbing we will
associate with exploitation. And by this,
we
mean exploitation of the heuristic function
or exploitation of the local knowledge or
the
gradient, that you can measure the gradient
around you. And you will always follow the
steepest gradient path. And this, we will
term as the exploitation of the gradient
essentially. Now, optimization does not happen
only in the computational world,
essentially I mean.
There is optimization happening in the physical
world as well and in nature as well. We
will see some examples from nature and from
physical world. So, in physical world for
example, when we talk of materials, you want
to produce materials of certain quality.
And very often, this quality is dictated by
the way, it is atoms are arranged. So, for
example, if atoms are arranged in the nice
array like structure, then you get good
crystalline materials or if atoms are arranged
to the close to each other in a metal, then
or
in a ceramic. Then, you get material, which
has good properties like good strength of
material and things like that. Now, the way
to arrive at materials with good properties,
very often involves creating a liquid version
of that material and then solidifying, it
is
essentially. So, casting for example, you
make a mould. And then you melt the material
from which we want to make the cast.
And pole the material in to the mould. And
then it solidified and takes the shape of
the
cast essentially. This is how, many of the
. statue that you see, are
made essentially. And there are many other
things, which are made by casting. Now, as
I
said, the properties of these materials is
dictated by the way, that these atoms are
arranged in the… And it is desirable to
arrange the atoms in a systematic fashion,
which
in other words corresponds to low energy levels,
essentially.
So, you want the final form to have low energy.
And in that sense, you have a
minimization problem. So, materials you want
to be in minimum energy state. So, you
.can imagine that, if some material is in
gaseous form, it is got some maximum amount
of
random movements happening and more energy.
And as it becomes liquid, the energy
levels come down. And as it become solid,
the energy levels come down.
But, even in solids if we can arrange the
matter in to minimum energy levels, then we
get
good properties of materials.
.
And typically, the process that is used for
minimum energy is call, annealing. And by
annealing, we basically mean controlled cooling.
That you do not allow to cool the
material, at it is own space or in some sense.
But, you make it cool slowly at a control
rate. So, that the atoms settle down in to
the minimum energy state. So, annealing is
a
physical process of minimization, which is
a kind of an optimization problem, that we
are also talking about. And we will take some
inspiration from annealing, in a few
moments.
..
You know some ethic called as random walk,
which we associate with exploration. So,
random walk as a name suggest is that, you
take a step in any random direction or make
a move to any random neighbor essentially.
And there is no other no criteria, which will
tell you which neighbor to move to essentially.
Now, hill climbing you generate the
neighbors of a given candidate. Inspect the
evaluation heuristic values or evaluation
function values, objective function values.
And choose a best amongst them and move to
that essentially. Random walk is simply
just taking a step in any random direction
essentially. Now, obviously you can see that,
random work has it is property of exploring
the states space or the search space,
whichever the search space. It could be the
solution space. But, of course it will not
be
guided. It will not have any desire to reach
our state, still at maximize essentially.
Just
keep going one and one.
So, when deterministic way that we saw of
going beyond maxima in hill climbing, we
saw was Tabu search. But, today we want to
look at a non deterministic or the stochastic
or randomized approach to exploring the space.
And our goal is to have a judicious mix
of exploration and exploitation. Exploration,
because it is exploration which will stop
us
from getting stock at local optima, and exploitation,
because it is exploitation which
takes us to optima in the first place essentially.
.So, it is just at what we want to reach the
global optimize, as far as possible. So, we
do
not want to have pure exploitation. Because,
we could have started in the wrong place
and you would end up in a local optimize.
So, as I mentioned in the end of the last
class,
we would want to make a move with a certain
probability, which is control in such a
fashion. That if the move is a good move,
then the probability is high. And if the move
is
not a good move, then the probability is low.
.
So, we will use the notation c as current,
as we did in the last class, current node
and n as
a next node. In hill climbing, n is the best
amongst the neighbors. In random walk, n is
any random neighbor of c. So, there is a relation
between c. So, this is c and then there
are many possible neighbors. And one of them
is n. Associated with this c and this n, we
will have their heuristic values or evaluation
values, which you can call as a eval c for
this node c.
Therefore, node n we will have eval n. And
if we have maximizing, then we want eval n
to be greater than eval c. If we want minimizing,
then we wanted to be smaller
essentially. So, which means that hill climbing
would have chosen the one with the
maximum eval n and value around here. But,
now we are given up this strategy of
inspecting all of them, and then choosing
the best amongst them.
We are inside adopting a strategy, in which
you will just take of random neighbor and
either move to it or not move to it, essentially.
So, this is the choice, we will make that.
.We will either move from c to n or we will
remain at c, which means that at, we will
generate another random neighbor at that point.
And again, either move to that or not
move to that. It is a little bit difference
from, what we have been doing so far, essentially.
In random walk, we always move with 100 percent
surety to the next neighbor. But, we
do not want to do that. We want to move with
a certain probability. And the probability
should be such that, for good moves it should
be high and good move. So, we will
associate that term delta E as eval n minus
eval c. And the equation, that I am going
to
write is going to be for maximization. And
you can just flip the sign for minimization
essentially.
So, this delta is something that, we want
our probability to be influence by. So, should
we make this move from c to n? It depends
upon, what is the delta E is? If delta E is
positive, then I would more likely want to
make a move with the high probability. If
delta E is negative, which means that n is
worst than c. I would still want to allow
that
move to be made, because that is our goal
to get of maximum essentially. We do not
want to stuck at maximum.
So, we will allow even bad moves, which means
with negative delta E to be made but,
with a lower probability essentially. So,
the function that we will use for computing
this
probability will be a function of delta E.
And one more parameter, which will be you
will
used to control, how this delta E is influences
the probabilities essentially? So, we want
two things. The delta E should influence the
probability. And secondly, I want to control
how delta E influences probably?
Did any one give a thought to this function?
Or you might have write about it, some way.
So, the function that I will use… So, what
is the nature of this function? We want the
function of delta E. The function should be
range should be limited to one. It should
be
between 0 and 1, essentially. Because, it
is a probability, we want to measure. We want
to get a probability measure. It is domain
should be infinite, practically infinite.
Because, I am not going to put any constraint
on, how much is the difference between
the evaluation function of two nodes? It could
be a, to any degree essentially. So, we
want a function, which will stay within this.
So, let me draw that function here. I mean,
let me draw the domain at least. So, this
is what my destiny is... So, this is going
to be 1,
.this is going to be 0. And here, let us say
delta E is equal to 0. And here, delta E is
increasing. And here, in the opposite direction
it is decreasing essentially.
Delta E is equal to 0 means, the next node
is as the same value as the current node
essentially. So, obviously you can imagine
that, you do not want to, you do not care.
You
can move to it or you do not move to it. You
are getting the same evaluation function
essentially. So, we want the function which
is going to be a monotonically increasing,
as
you go from left to right but, stay within
these nodes. So, you can imagine. They could
be. There is more than one function, that
you can choose to do that.
.
We will choose one. And that function is called
the sigmoid function. So, we will write
this as the following that P. It is the probability
of making the move. So, let me just say P
c n. If we interpreted, as saying that P c
n is a probability of making a move from c
to n
is 1 over 1 plus. This is basically the sigma
at function. And like as I said, we will have
a
second parameter, which will allow us to control,
how much delta E influences the
probability?
Because, we should be able to work at any
in some sense, place in this spectrum. And
the
spectrum starts with hill climbing, which
means that the moment delta E is positive.
You
will accept it, with probability one. The
moment that is negative. You will reject it,
with
probability one or accept it with probability
zero. And on the other hand is a random
.work at the other extreme, which means that
it does not care, whether delta E is positive
or negative.
You will always accept it with probability
0.5. But, we want to be able to operate,
anywhere in this range essentially. So, we
need a second parameter. And the second
parameter, traditionally is call T essentially.
So, this is a simple algorithm, generate.
So,
n is a random neighbor
of c. So, let us assume. You have a function
called random
neighbor of c. And then we say eval delta
E.
According to this formula, eval n minus eval
c and move with probability. So, it is a little
bit like the random work. Accepts, if I may
use the analogy of somebody being
inebriated. This person is little bit too
inebriated. That sometimes, he does not even
make
a move .. So, sometimes he makes a move, sometimes
does not
make a move. So, sometimes he goes some c
to n and sometimes, he just stays there and
after while, he makes another moves and some
other moves essentially.
This algorithm is call stochastic hill climbing.
So, I will just write HC for hill climbing.
It is not purely hill climbing. Hill climbing
would only go in the direction of the steepest
radiant. But, it has a tendency to go in the
direction of better values. So, we have still
talking about maximization. So, it still has
a tendency to go up. So, let us inspect some
values, which I have got from this book. So,
how to solve it by .?
So, there given some examples. So, I am just
taking their example.
.
.So, what is the effect of delta E. Let us
assume that, T equal to 10, some value. And
we
are using that, value 10 here to compute this
delta E essentially. And let us assume that,
eval c is equal to 107, some value. And values
better than 107 are good, values less than
107 are bad for this essentially. So, let
construct a small table of values and say,
how it
effects? So, this is a value for eval n. So,
if this is 80. That means, it is a not a good
value.
It is less than 107. So, delta E so I write
minus delta E here. Minus delta E is 27. Then,
e
raise to minus delta E by T, e’s value is
14.88. And this is the probability. This is
0.06.
So, if according to this formula, and this
function is called sigmoid function. If my
eval n
equal to 80, then I will move to it to the
very small probability, as you can see 0.06
essentially. So, 6 times out of 100, I will
move to that node. Otherwise, I will not move
to that.
And that is, what we want essentially. You
want the search to focus more towards better
moves and less towards, you see. Let us look
at some more examples. If this is 100, this
is little bit better. This becomes 7, this
becomes 2.01 and this becomes 0.33. So, we
are
studying the effect of, how this function
sigmoid function response to changing delta
E
essentially? So, this is still a bad value
because, we are starting with eval c equal
to 107.
We are still going 7 points lower. And it
will moving to that with one third probabilities,
essentially. Then, just for the sake of completion,
you take this. This happens to be 1.0
and 0.50, which is nice. Because, what this
function is telling us? Is that, if eval n
equal
to eval c you may or may not move to that,
which means you move to that probability
0.5. And you can stay back at with probability
0.5, which is what we would expect?
Now, let us took at better values 120, which
becomes minus 13, 0.27 and 0.78. So, if you
find the better value, then we will move to
with probability 0.78. How do you move it
to
the probability 0.78? We discuss at the last
class. You generate .
number in the range 0 to 1. And if that number
is less than 0.78, you move. Otherwise,
you do not move essentially. Less, you know
equal to 0.78. One more value 150, which
is much better.
So, this table basically which I have taken
from this book. Illustrates, how stochastic
hill
climbing response to different values of delta
E. As you can see, if delta E is high and
what you have written here is negation of
delta E. If delta E is high, if we get a good
.improvement, it makes some move with greater
probability. Otherwise, it makes a move
with the lesser probability. All this is for,
this value of T equal to 10 essentially.
How do you choose this value? It is a next
question, because we will see in a moment.
What is a influence of T essentially? I will,
let us first finish that and then we will
do the
discussion. So, now let us assume that we
have looking at this case. So, not this case.
We
are looking at this case, which is the better
case. And let us see that if eval n equal
to 120
and of course, eval c is 107, how does temperature
affects the probability?
So, let us look at different values of T.
Then, we have e is to minus 13 by T. And then
we
have probability P. So, let us take a low
value and we will assume, 1 is a low value.
This
comes to and you can do this yourself actually.
So, let me first write out this values. With
5, it is... So, this is how temperature of
it is, this. So, I have used our term temperature.
And in fact, that there is a connection with
annealing, that we will shortly see.
So, we will call this parameter, temperature.
And delta E is also stand for energy in some
sense. Of course, in this case you want to
maximize. Otherwise, you would have a
formula in which, this goes to negation of…
Instead of minus delta E, you would have
plus delta E, if you wanted to minimize. So,
how does this behave? Let us see. At very
low temperature or very low value of T, the
probability is 1. So, you can see that, this
is
like hill climbing.
If you keep this parameter low, then it tends
to behave like hill climbing. Well, in the
sense that if you see the better more, it
will make it essentially. Then, as temperature
increases and this is where the analogy with
real world materials comes in to play. The
energy levels increase. The entropy keeps
increasing and so on so forth. Or randomness
keeps in improving. And at very, very high
temperatures, this is 10 is to 10.
The probability is 0.5. And you can see that,
there is a bit like random walk. So, we can
control the behavior of our probability function
by controlling temperature. If you want it
to be more random, we will keep high temperature.
So, as you are above 0.5, it is
approaching a random walk. It is more random
essentially. Irrespective of, what value of
delta E is? It will be 0.5 essentially. So,
it will be randomly make a move essentially.
If you wanted to make it, so if you want to
explore more, you keep the temperature high,
making to behave like a random walk. If you
wanted to follow the radiant, then keep the
.temperature low. Making it, behave like a
little bit like hill climbing, essentially.
If it
sees that, well hill climbing in the sense,
hill climbing always moves to a better spot.
The
actual algorithm moves to the best amongst
them.
But, since we are generating only one, we
will take this as an approximation to hill
climbing. So, it would move only, if the node
n was better than node c, if temperature
was low. If temperature was high, it would
less move, irrespective of whether. So, as
an
exercise I would ask you to look at, either
of these values and construct the table for
T.
And you will see that, there would be similar
thing. That they would, at high temperature
they will, it will still converts to 0.5 and
at low temperatures, it will converts to zero,
towards zero. Then, it will not move it all,
essentially. If we are getting a worst, these
two values are worst in this and these two
values are better than this, essentially.
So, we
have noted. We have seen the example of a
better value.
So, how does this sigmoid function look? If
you are to plot it, it depends on the
parameter temperature .. So, let us say, this
is the value of 0.5
through this. So, this is all curves was passed
to this point, essentially. Why because? We
have said here that when delta E is equal
to 0, it gives us a value of 0.5. When, you
can
see that, this is going to be irrespective
of temperature, because this term has become
zero ..
So, irrespective of temperature, this value
is going to be 0.5. So, all the curves for
temperatures will pass through .. When temperature
is low, this
curve looks like this.
..
Basically the step function. This is T equal
to 1. When temperature is high, this curve
looks like a straight line, here. This is,
what T equal to, this is 10 is to 10. It is
always
0.5. Otherwise, it gives us a behavior, which
looks like the following. So, a typical
sigmoid curve will cross this at some place
and then go down towards zero here. And go
up towards one place. So, this is a typical
shape of a sigmoid curve.
And it is nice for us, because we want a function,
which will have the range of 0 to 1 and
domain which is infinite. And as we change
the values of temperature, the shape of this
curve, changes. So, with a different temperature,
the curve may look like this. So, as
temperature goes down, this curve, this slope
become sharper and sharper, like this. And
as the temperature goes up, it becomes flatter
and flatter essentially.
So, this is T raises to 10 is to 10. Somewhere,
you know there will be a curve, which will
be like this. So, there is a series of curves.
So, this is a direction of increasing T. The
curves become flatter as T. This is just a
nature of this function. We are just looking
at it,
to get some insides and towards happening
essentially. Now, instead of saying that,
I will
make a choice of the value T. We follow, what
is done in the physical world, which is to
say that, I will cool down the system gradually.
And hope that, it will settle into an
optimal state essentially.
..
So, if we remove this and put in a clause,
where we initialize T into some values, let
us
say very high. Whatever that very high value
is… And very often, the algorithm has two
loops. There is one loop in which, you do
this loop a few times at a constant T. Some
people, call it as e power something. But,
that does not a matter. It is a inner loop,
in
which you do this whole process. What is this
process?
Generating a random neighbor and either, moving
to it and not moving to it, depending
on how good that neighbor is given by this
probability here, essentially. You keep doing,
this as a certain number of types. And then
you change T from monotonic decreasing
function. So, something, some function. The
simplest is, T is equal to T minus 1. But,
that may not necessarily with the best function,
you know. This is a very empirical
process.
This function, that we are looking for determines.
What this people call it as a cooling
lead. And this is, at most of the times determined
empirically essentially, which means
that you take a domain, do some experiments
and try to see, what works and what does
not work and then try to keep that value.
And then this is a outer loop. So, you do
in an
inner loop, you do this some number of steps.
Then, you decrease the temperature and do
some more number of steps essentially.
So, what is the intuition behind this? And
simulated annealing. So, it is called simulated
annealing. It is a algorithm, very well known
algorithm call simulated annealing. It is
.very popular in the optimization community.
It is used very often. And this is basically
the algorithm. That you started at the high
temperature, which means you start with high
random movement. Allow the system to go to
any candidate.
But, gradually bring down the temperature
and make it behave more and more like, hill
climbing. What would be the intuition? Why
should it work? What is the idea behind this
decreasing of temperature? How does it help?
Decreasing the random means, therefore it
does. But, what is the intuition behind? Why
does it work? Why does it help us find,
good values good.
Student: . local meaning.
But, remember that towards the end, when T
becomes low, it is going to behave more
and more like hill climbing. How do you account
for that fact? It is true that, initially
we
wanted to behave randomly. And then later
on we wanted to follow the heuristic function
or all essentially. What is changing over
this period of time?
Student: .
If that is high initially, why do you want
this high initially and what is the effect
of this
cooling? You know, I heard that somebody say
that, this is like one of those toys, which
has the concerting rings. We might have seen
with some small balls of wall bearing like
objects inside them. And you have to move
them all towards the center. And this person
who is a respected computer scientist said
that, you know.
It is a bit like, you first move it randomly
and then gradually. You let it try to control
the
movement. But, you think that object will
little bit or something like that. So, let
we give
you an intuition behind this. So, what is
the claim that we are making? The claim that
we
are making is that, at many problems this
gives us very good solutions, which means
it
gives us close to optimal solutions essentially.
What are the kind of problems, where this
works, were the surface is gadget essentially.
Where hill climbing would have got stuck at
first local maxima or minimize, it is found?
But, this algorithm can get beyond many local
maxima and move towards better maxima.
So, what is an intuition to say that, it moves
towards better maxima? So, this is a basic
.idea that, I would not make you to think
about. Let us assume that, that is… So,
there is
this big gadgets surface.
.
So, let us say. This is how your one dimensional
surface looks like, essentially. Its gadget
in the sense that, hill climbing would, depending
on where it is started, hill climbing
would have got stuck in one of these local
maxima. But, we are saying that something
like simulated annealing, will go very close
to the global maxima, essentially. So, the
idea is this essentially. That, take a certain
snap shot of this, which looks like this.
It is like that, one of these things here.
Let us call this point A and next, call this
point as
B and next call this point C. And we want
to maximize which means, we want this value
to be high, higher. We want to go to C rather
than to A. We want to go to the top of this
essentially. Now, in this one dimensional
world which means, you know these are the
set
of candidates and these are the heuristic
functions and you can move either left or
right.
You want to not get stuck at A but, you want
to be at C. And then this I have given to
apply all over this slope, essentially here.
Now, you can see that, to move from A to B,
it
has to overcome an energy gap, which is this
much, which means when I say overcome
the energy gap, basically I am saying that,
it is going against the heuristic function.
You
want to maximize but, you want to go down
here.
.You want to go down here, maybe two three
steps depending on, what is the granularity?
You want to take two three steps down there
and end up in B. And of course, then after
that, it will have a natural tendency to go
up because, that is the natural tendency of
this
algorithm. If it sees a better move, as we
have seen here .. The
better the delta E, the better the probability
of moving to that move, essentially.
So, it is a natural tendency of going here.
So, to go from… So, let us call this E AB.
And
likewise, let us call this E CB. To go from
A to C, it has to overcome an energy gap of
E
AB. To go from C to A, it has to overcome
an energy gap of E CB. So, just imagine that,
there is somebody with the helium balloon
tied to that first. Let us try to visualize,
trying
to pull him up essentially. So, he has to
walk down all this way. Pulling that helium
balloon which is a greater distance, essentially.
So, a greater energy gap essentially. So,
to go to from A to C, you have to overcome
this
energy gap. And then of course, naturally
the algorithm will take you up, because it
has
this tendency of going up. To go from C to
A, you have to emerge the greater energy gap
essentially, which is this E CB essentially.
As you works for this, you can certain
comment. The idea, which says that, there
is a greater chance of it, moving from A to
C,
essentially.
In general, not initially. Initially, when
the temperature is high, going up and going
down
is all the same for this algorithm. It will
just do any more randomly. But, as the
temperature goes lower and lower, it is still
not hill climbing. It is still some intermediate
temperature. But, either intermediate temperature
as you can see, ..
The probabilities, unfortunately we have drawn
the probabilities for negative moves.
But, maybe we should do that and see that.
That, as the temperature goes down, the
probability of making negative moves goes
down essentially. As a temperature becomes
one, the probability or negative moves tends
to zero essentially. So, as a temperature
goes down, the probability of moving some
energy gap will depend on the energy gap
essentially, And since this gap is larger
than this. It is no likely, that algorithm
will go for
A to B and then to C.
And remember that, B to C is a kind of automatic.
Like in the sense, there is a most
likely behavior, because of this thing. And
it is less slightly, it is come down from
C to
B. And then go to A essentially. And this
is specially the case, as temperature is brought
.down essentially. So, you can see in some
sense, you can see that temperature it is
ability
to go down in this slope essentially. As temperature
is high, the algorithm has higher
ability to go down or you can say, go down
greater distance essentially.
As we gradually reduce the temperature, it
is ability to go down in this. Remember, this
is maximization problem. Decrease this, which
means that it is easier for it to go from
A
to B, then it is come from C to B, which means
that it is more likely to end up in C.
Because, after the temperature has become
really down. If it happens to be here, it
will
go to C. If it happens to be here, it will
go to A essentially.
That is hill climbing part of it, essentially.
So, this is a kind of intuition behind simulated
annealing. That initially, you allow the algorithm
to explore many different parts. But,
gradually bring down the temperature. In the
process, in some sense pushing it towards
the global maxima, essentially. Pushing it
towards higher peeks, in this example
essentially. Why because? It is at any given
temperature, which is not infinite.
I mean, if you assume 10 is to 10 is infinite.
It is more likely that, it will climb down
form it is local peek, then it is from a higher
peek, which means it is more likely, that
it is
a little climb up to the higher peek from
a local peek, which means that this is very
likely, that it will go from A to C essentially
at any given temperature. And eventually,
you bring the temperature down. So, that it
is a kind of just goes to that nearest peek
that
it is that.
Actually, there is a simpler version of randomize
algorithm, which I have not mention.
But, this is probably a good time to mention
it. That algorithm is called iterated hill
climbing. And what it essentially does? And
this is, this works in the solution space.
So,
something like, if you are solving sat or
solving TSPS or something like that, where
you
are looking for a solution. You are not looking
for a path from the start state to the goal
state.
In fact, that there is no notion of go start
state. So, . for examples.
There is no start. Unless of course, you think
of the empty board as a start state. But,
that
is not really critical to the solving the
problem. So, if you want to solve ((Refer
Time:
44:16)). You have to find with the final solution,
somehow with the other essentially.
And so when we look at the solution space
search and perturbation methods, you could
start at any random location, essentially.
.So, again consider SAT as a example. You
can choose any supposing, you have n
variables. You could choose any assignment
for those n variables. And that is a starting
point from which you apply those operators,
that we discussed earlier, essentially.
.
So, what iterated hill climbing says? You
essentially, that choose a random state of
starting point random means. So, in this example,
it would mean choose one here, choose
one here, choose one here, choose one here
and so on. So, put it in some kind of a loop.
Choose random start. And simply do hill climbing.
Do not do anything else. Just do hill
climbing. So, you can imagine that, if I want
to do this, then this starting point will
take
me to this maximum.
This starting point will take me to this maximum
and so on and so forth. And if you have
chosen a sufficiently large number of random
starting points, then one of them is likely
to hit global maxima, essentially. So, that
is a hope. Of course, it depends on the nature
of the surface. If it is very gadget, then
you may need many, many starting points. But,
if
the surface is like this, then you can see
that if we start anywhere between this range,
means anywhere here and you will end up with
this global maxima essentially.
So, iterated hill climbing is very simple
algorithm. It says that, do many hill climbing
searches. But, start at different randomly
selected points and because, hill climbing
is
simple. Computationally, this algorithm is
simple essentially. You can also think of
this
as a parallel search. That you start all these
searches at the same time and all of them
.happens in the same time. So, after the end,
you will just find what is the best candidate
that you got? And you, that is an answer essentially.
So, there is something to be said with more
than one candidate, searching with more than
one candidates. So, we have already seen a
couple of examples. Beam search, searches
through. Always selects be best candidates
in the next level and so on, if remember.
This
is little bit like beam search. In the sense
that, except that you ,these things are not
allowed to interact with each other.
So, this will have its own trajectory and
this will have its own trajectory and so on.
But,
they are the be parallel searches taking place,
essentially. Does it make sense for two
candidates to interact in some way? If you
are doing a search in which, there are many
candidates like a parallel search, like this.
Does it make sense for two candidates to
interact? We will address that, in the next
class which will be and we will stop here,
with
this. So, that is a new algorithm that we
will look at, which is based on working with
a
population of candidates, which are allowed
to interact with each other in some sense,
essentially. We will stop here.
.