Let us go back to nature today, and remember
we are doing optimization. So, does nature
to optimization?
.Yes sir, yes sir, n colony optimization.
Somebody said yes. Yes, but we are not going
to say n colony optimization, that is an
algorithm that if you, may not get time to
look at the today probably in the next class
essentially, what is it, what is optimization
happening there?
.Natural selection.
Natural selection, which is different from
n colony optimization.
N colonies are known to is very good at finding
food, if you leave a anything which
edible you know, a biscuit or lump of sugar
then, you can be sure that you know, within
some time ants would be there, somehow they
find it, you look at that in the next class
may be I think, we will go to natural selection.
So, you can think of, of course, many of us
considered human beings to be the pinnacle
of life forms. So, we can say, we have come
through a process of natural selection which
of course, is attributed, the theory is attributed
to Charles Darwin and you must have
heard about the well known phrase, survival
of the fittest, but what is nature doing
essentially.
So, let us set of step back and see what is
it trying to do? So, we can say it is trying
to
design live forms essentially. So, we have
whole wide spectrum diversity of life on earth
starting with cockroach, not starting with
a cockroach, starting with you know, some
.amoebas, and ants, and birds, and animals,
and so, we think that we are on top of it.
What would be the objective of this design
process, what is it trying to designed?
I mean if of course, we are trying to sting
by sting nature is like thing to design
something. Have you heard, how many of read
anything by Richard Dawkins? Which
one, which book have you read?
Student- The God delusion.
The god delusion, that is one of his most
recent books I think, in which he says that
he is
kind of anti institution of religion, but
any way his one of the earlier books was called
the
blind watch maker, it was quite a well known
book, it quite a hit in that time. The
argument in the western society was whether
or not there was a god who created the
universe and the earth and human beings at
the center of earth.
And the argument was that, you know that everything
is so perfect, the world is so
perfect, we just have the right amount of
oxygen in our air and we have everything that
we need, we have water flowing and we have
day and night and all this kind of stuff,
that
there must be a watch maker. If the universe
functions so perfectly like a Swiss watch
for
example, Switzerland is known for its mechanical
watches then, it could not have come
out of random.
So, this is an arguments against Darwin. Darwin
said that we came out of evolution. So,
people would aghast at the notion that we
have evolved from apes. Sometimes I think
that the apes might be more aghast at this
notion. The idea was that, such a perfectly
functioning world must have a maker behind
it of the watch maker, like a watch maker.
But Dawkins and Darwin, they are all on the
same side, they say that there is a built
in
ratchet mechanism. In a sense that if you
find some improvement somehow then, that
improvement sticks around essentially. So,
there is a ratchet mechanism, if you by
mistake or by some chance event designed something
which works then, it has a
tendency to persist.
..
There is a person called Steven grand
is somewhere in the UK, he wrote this book
call
creation, which the institute has one copy
which is with me at this moment. If you want
to have a look at it, you can come and borrow
it I think. You know I have heard about
creatures, these are computational . of people.
Life forms that you create in the so called
cyber world, artificial fish, artificial this
thing,
artificial that, in the creatures I means.
So, the term creature, if you just look up
creature
on the on the net, you will find some sites,
one of them is maintained by Steve Grand.
So, he is the, in this book that he wrote,
he wrote something very profound at least
I
found it profound and it is that whatever
persists.
Just imagine a random world where there is
no watch maker, there is no creator, he says
that see this is at this is a kind of tautology
whatever persists, persists. Obviously, I
mean
that is what we say well, this is the fundamental
thing behind how life has emerged out
of chaos I might say essentially. I mean after
big bang I suppose there were chaos for the
lot of time and so, if you follow what Steve
grand is saying then the, you can say an
equivalent statement at the goal of life.
So, if life is you know some driving force
or something is to live, and by live essentially
.e mean persists essentially. But there is
no, one cannot describe some external high
level
goal to life, it just happens at we happen
to persists so, we are their essentially,
a goal of
life is simply to be there essentially. Now,
you can say that nature is experimenting,
I do
not really need to say.
Nature is, again when you say nature we do
not want to anthropomize again, nature is
not like god or some devata or somebody we
doing something. Nature is some term that
we use for everything that is around us. A
set of creating different designs for life
forms.
At least we can . like that nature is doing
it, see very often people
for the sake explanation describe a design
motive behind things which are happening.
So, why did we develop a neocortex? Because
you know, it helped us reason at a
symbolic level I think like that essentially,
but of course it is not, there is no motive
behind it. It just so happens that we walled
a cortex which allowed us to do thinking so,
we are thinking essentially. So, which is
what Steve grand says? Whatever persists
essentially. And this a basic mechanism behind
nature’s effort to design life forms, and
the goal of this life form is nothing but
to live, to persists essentially, and that
is our
. instinct to persists.
So, if you what walk out of this building
and you see somebody with a gun pointing at
you, the first thing you do is ., that is
our inbuilt nature to persists
essentially. And if you think of it in combination
with what is Steve grand say just
imagine that in the initial chaos there were
only atoms floating around then, molecules
form then, molecules combined into forming
bigger molecules.
And then, eventually organic molecules came
into being which has this tendency of
surviving and sticking together and then,
of course making copies of themselves and
so
on and so forth. Things which happened, happened
and those things which survive,
survive which is what Darwin called as survival
of the fittest essentially. Of the many
things that you are trying out, some things
survive and they are the fittest essentially.
So, when you say survival of the fittest,
one has to you know look at it from a careful
perspective, there it is not as if your first
determining fitness and then talking about
.survival. It is a other way around fact essentially.
When you say survival of the fittest,
what we really mean is that, the once who
survives are the fittest essentially.
Now, these life forms compete with each other.
What do they compete for? They
compete for whatever resources that they need
essentially, material resources, primarily
material resources like food and so, on. And
there is a limited amount of food and
remember that food is a building, food provide
just a matter for building our bodies
essentially. So, if a child grows up it is
by eating food and you know having that food
transform into various things inside his system.
So, they compete for resources which mean
that, some life forms succeeds and some life
forms fails essentially. Just imagine that
there is a bunch of people in a room, let
us say
there are 50 people in the room and there
are only let us say 20 cakes or something
like
that, and of course you cannot divide the
cake such you know.
Then, there is some mechanism by which people
are given cakes. So, some 20 people
will get cakes and 30 people will not get
a cakes and to be taking a next game point
of
you the is a very extreme you, but in some
time what is happening in the nature
especially that different life terms are like
different species.
.
.And nature is experimenting again I would
like to set of question that we say nature
is
experimenting it, nature is a not a like a
person setting of a there is a experiment
and
these things a happening on their own and
making view them as experiment essentially.
So, how is nature doing? It is nature is doing
generate and test. It is searching in,
remember that we started off by saying for
the basic paradigm of search algorithm that
we had look at this generate and test. Generate
a candidate and test, you know the
candidate, the solution that we had a smaller
problem, nature does not have a goal.
So, we do not have a goal test function, but
by testing we mean something else here. So,
what do you mean by generate? So, there was
a French poet, I do not know remember his
name unfortunately right now whose . he said
this process that a
world, this process of evaluation is that
one makes up the combination and the other
chooses.
So, there are two forces which are applying,
one is which is making up the combination,
which we will call as generate, and test is
basically other chooses. So, these are two
things essentially. What you mean by the other
chooses? Listen that there is a force with
natural selection which says that it will
select some people who will survive and will
not
people some creature will survive and some
which will survive essentially.
So, there were, there were selection happening
which is like a text function and there is
a
process of generating, creating new features
is happening. And so, just imagine this
world in which new creatures and by creatures
I mean individuals, I been created all this
time. And each of them is competing with other
creatures, they may be from the same
species or they may be from the different
species.
But everybody is competing for food essentially.
So, at the fundamental limit, I mean
that is so strongest basic urge is to eat
essentially, and that, where that we cannot
survive
essentially. How does these combinations come
out? Let us talk about other chooses
before we do that essentially. So, just imagine
that there is a rabbit o there is species
of
rabbit and there are these rabbits on field
and they are being chased by foxes essentially
also let us say on the same field. So, there
is a relation between them, the fox species
and
.the rabbit species. And I will use this as
a, which denotes the positive influence on
the
population essentially.
So, this is like some people call influence
diagrams. How does the population of rabbits
influence the population of foxes? We say
that there is a positive influence, beside
the
more the rabbits are there out there, the
more the foxes will get to eat them and therefore
the foxes will survive essentially. So, the
more, there is no famine nor
And of course there is a negative influence
of the population of the foxes and the rabbits
essentially. There of course there is this
whole eco system out there. So, when you have
foxes then, you have let us say tigers, when
you have tigers you have let us say bacteria.
And . familiar with this necessity you know.
The birds help
pollinate the flowers and there is the dependence,
the whole eco system there, it is a
stable eco system then, which every population
is having some influence on other
population essentially.
So, now a day’s people one hears that is
suddenly bees vanish from this world, you
might have heard some news item. The bees
vanish when it will affect certain food chain
which means we stop getting things of a certain
kind. So, we have this stable eco
systems, but we also have catastrophic on
the way essentially.
So, like 60000 years ago or whatever when
the predominant life form was we ((Refer
Time.) so on. And mammals were you know small
smelly creatures hiding from
., but suddenly something happened and we
do not quite know what
happened. And . became extinct and mammals
become prominent
and then, human of course the most prominent
of those all essentially. So, we are talking
about competition.
..
Thus competitor competition between species.
So, let us say we have rabbits and cows
and goats and sheep, all trying to go for
some ., I do not know
whether the rabbits eat grass, but at least
cows and goats and sheep all competing for
grass essentially so, there is a computation
between species. And there is also a
competition within the species. So, we are
going to focus on this, competition within
the
species. What do you mean by this? So, just
imagine again this bunch of rabbits on this
field and let us say 2 or 3 foxes come running
and the rabbits all run away.
Or more likely if you have watched some . it
is some set of bunch
of deer and one or two lions come running
then, all the Deers are running away. And
the
lion catches a in some sense of weakest one
essentially, the one which cannot run away
fastest so, the lion catches the weakest one
and the fastest deer they escape essentially.
To . leave to tell let us say another team.
So, there is competition
within the species. So, if there is a prey
and the age of species which is preyed upon,
there is competition within the species to
escape or to catch .
essentially. So, again the strongest lions
will be able to catch deer, by strongest we
mean
fastest so, whatever is the good quality,
the fastest rabbits will be able to escape.
.So, fastest is just a, just a actually that
I am using it, it is not necessarily fastest,
it could
be something else, cleverest or you know something
which can disguises itself very well
or any kind of things that nature adopts to.
So, there is a constant battle between the
predator and the prey essentially, both are
involving.
How are they involving? Because within, the
competition within the species is selecting
better and better individuals, which are propagating
there propagates in some fashion to
the next level essentially. So, that bring
us to one makes up the combination. So, what
is
the combination that nature has adopted? It
is of sexual reproduction
and what is it lead
to it? Leads to genetic mixing, this is a
key. How does nature experiments with different
life form?
It mixes up genes of individuals. So, every
creatures is at least from this earth has
born of
two parents and inherits the genes from both
the parents. And there of course there is
this
whole theory of which are the dominant ones
and which are the recessive once and that
kind of stuff. But eventually there is a experimentation
with newer or newer
combinations of genes that life is doing.
So, we are, we up, we use the term genotype
for this. Nature is experimenting with the
genotype of, so, genotype is like the design
of a creature. So, of course you know
amongst human being we say that this child
has inherited the height from one parent or
both parent or something like that essentially
or colour of hair or colour of eyes, all kinds
of things that you have inherited from parent.
So, you inherit some from one parent some
from another parent, and within a human
family one sibling may brighter than another
sibling and things like that because they
have inherited different things from different
parents and so on. So, we have this whole
churning of the genes which is happening then
with the genotype.
And at this other level which we call as a
phenotype, it is competition is happening.
It is
a physical creature which is competing on
the, in the real world essentially. So, what
is
this we have to do with the optimization?
We want to look at a method of optimization
which is kind of takes inspiration from this
world of natural selection.
.So, this whole idea here is that of emergent
behavior
and the idea of emergent behavior
is that you put together simple parts to give
you a more complex things essentially. So,
nature is, it is this building blocks of life,
which are called the genes that we have, which
is trying out with different combination of
genes and letting them loose in the world.
And if they survive, they survive.
So, they are competing for food they are competing
for mates, they are competing for
shelter, the once who manage to win they will
pass on their genes to the next generation
and in the process we will have in some sense
fitter population. So, the population of
rabbits becomes faster, again I am using faster
just as we are talking about it. As they
evolve they become faster, at the same time
foxes are becoming faster. So, there is a
sort
of war going on between them essentially.
So, emergent behavior
is this approach to
optimization, it says let us try to do this
so called random mixing of genes.
So, again this is a randomize process, and
see if we can somehow keep track of the best
one. So, what is the basic idea? You allow
for random mixing of genes
and you have a
mechanism for keeping the best. So, this thing,
one makes up the combination and the
other chooses. So, there is this two processes,
one is combining things which generates
and test, one is combining things to produce
a new creatures and there is some
mechanism which is judging. So, which creatures
are good and which creatures are bad
and allowing them to survive essentially.
And in the process, we want to see if we can
improve upon the designs and come up with
the optimal design, whatever optimal means
here.
..
So, this idea of optimization is called by
the known name of genetic algorithms, also
called GAS for example. And they were devised
around 1980 or so by John Holland, and
one of his students call David Goldberg
is still very active in this area. And in
fact, he
has written a book which is called genetic
algorithms or something like that, which is
a
very popular book on this topic essentially.
So, the idea of the genetic algorithms is
that
they work with populations.
So, the first thing of course is you have
to first appears to encode. You are working
in the
solutions space so, you have to encode a solution
as a string so, I just used a term string.
But if I were to be from this community, instead
of string I would say chromosome. So,
it is a chromosome which start of contains
the design decisions that you are going to
work with, but will tend to think of it as
a string essentially. So, the first thing
is to
encode the solution as a string. So, the simplest
example that we can think of is the sat
problem where the solution is just a bits
string essentially or TSP can be encoded as
some sort of string.
And for any kind of a problem that you want
to solve with GAS, you have to encode it as
a string essentially. So, this population
is a population of strings essentially. So,
this
population p 1, p n let us say we have n population
of n elements inside it essentially.
.Then, the next thing you want to do so, the
first thing is to encode.
Candidate solutions are string essentially
so, essentially what are we trying to do that
we
will work with the population of initial randomly
generated candidates. And then, try to
mix up the strings to produce new candidate
which will hopefully be better essentially.
And how do we decide better?
So, we do not let loose this things in to
the designs in to the real world as nature
does.
We devise something call a fitness function,
it s a f of n which is the same as what we
call eval of n which was the same as what
we call of a h of n start with.
Remember that we came to this world of optimization
by starting with a heuristic
function and that we said the evaluation,
we call it the evaluation because that is
what the
optimization community calls it. And in particular
the genetic algorithms can be calls it a
fitness function essentially. So, with every
candidate we have a fitness value, which tells
us how good that candidate is essentially.
I have to see how much time we will have.
So,
there are, there are 3 basics steps to a genetic
algorithms so, we start with a initial
population P.
.
.And then, the first step is the so, this
is the preliminary what we are doing designing
the
system, but the algorithms itself, the GA
algorithms has 3 steps, the first step is
called
selection which is proportional to fitness.
So, unlike the real world, genetic algorithm
does cloning essentially so, just creates
copies of candidates.
So, what we do? We have these candidates p
1, p 2, p 3, p n and for that each of them
we
have a fitness function, and we reproduce
this population, clone this population by
clone
individuals in this population, in proportion
to their fitness which means we will make
more copies of fit candidates and less copies
of unfit candidates, less meaning 0
essentially or more could be 1, 2, 3, 4, anything.
How do we do this? We create, it is a similar
process to how do we create this whole
random process. We can think of it as a . in
which we assign sectors
proportional to their fitness in is p 1, is
p 2, is p 3, is p 4 and so on. The amount
of angle
they get is proportional to the fitness value
so, p 4 is very fit so it gets a large angle,
p 3
is and so on and so forth. And we just sort
of rotate it randomly and we have a some
pointer, where ever it stops that candidate
gets to reproduce once.
So, we rotate it let us say P 4 it stops at
P 4. So, remember that this is something which
can rotate and we give it a random rotation
like . and observe where
the needle is. We do this n times and generate
n new, a population of n new elements.
So, let us call it P 1 prime, P 2 prime, P
n prime. So, this is the first step, selection.
We
are just making copies of the original, but
which the difference that everyone does not
get to make a copy.
Fit members have a greater chance of making
more copies that you can see there is very
lightly that P 4 will stop at, the P 4 will
be created, will stop at this, at this arrow
more
than once essentially. So, P 4 may get more
copies, this thing whatever it is here will
probably get 0 copies or something like that.
But of course it depends upon chance, the
randomized algorithm, we cannot say deterministically
what will come about it. All we
are saying is that these rule wheel we will
spin n times and whichever names of the
candidates appear against the needled we will
create a copy of that.
.So, we will create a new population of n
candidates and you can see that this population,
the fit members will have a greater chance
of appearing more than once, and unfit
members may get the wheeled out essentially.
So, it is a little bit difference of what
happens in nature, we do not create the final
thing, final individuals and out, and send
them out to compete.
We allow them to clone in proportion to how
good they are essentially and they can get
to clone more than once. After that is the
second step is called in .
of the j a community, it is called cross over.
And what we do here? We randomly pair
this population.
So, for example, we may pair P 1 with some
other one, P 2 with somebody else and so
on and so forth. We randomly pair of these
elements of this new population and we
randomly mix up their genes, that mix up of
genes is called cross over and that is just
a
term that we use. So, the idea is something
like this for example, let us say P 1 is a
made
up of let us say gene which we call x. Let
us say that there are 9 components to this.
So, for example, if it is a sat problems with
9 variables then, there will be 9 bits
essentially. So, we are just calling them
x 1 to x 9 then, P 2 so, let us say p 1 is
been
paired with p 2, or you can call it P i and
P j. Since, I am using, that is a P i and
P j and
let us call this y 1, y 2, y 3 up to y 9.
So, where these 2 parents so, p 1 and p i
and p j are the two parents which have been
mated together by this random process of mating.
We just randomly made two elements
and then, we wanted to the mix up their genes.
So, one way of doing it to just draw line
somewhere and generate new children. So, c
1 is equal to we take x 1, x 2, x 3, x 4,
from
here and then, y 1, y 5, y 6, y 9, from this
essentially. The other child get the other
genes
so, this will get y 1 to y 4 and x 5 to x
9.
This process of mixing of genes is called
cross over, and you can see why it is called
cross over is that you know some genes are
crossing over from one candidate to the other
and vice versa policy. This particular cross
over is called single point cross over, but
you
can devise other cross overs, I mean there
is no, nothing . about this
.single point of a, just to illustrate we
have done that.
So, we will randomly choose a point here and
everything on one side will go to one child
and the other side will go to the other child
and likewise for the other distinguish. So,
we
can imagine a sat problem in which you get
first 4 bit value from one candidate, one
solution and the, and the next 5 bits from
the other parent essentially, in likewise
for the
other child essentially.
So, you can see this 2 components of it talked
about, one makes up the combination is
being done by the cross over part, and this
the other chooses is being done by the
selection part essentially. And we basically
put this in to a loop essentially. You take
a
population generate a new . population, do
cross over and go all
over again.
Now, for the sake of completeness that sometimes
a population may be lacking a gene
essentially. So, how do, new kind of species
emerge out of this process essentially? We
have a third step so, the first step is selection,
the second step is cross over, and the third
step is called mutation. And by mutation we
mean random and not only random it is a
rare event. Every once in a while you change
one gene randomly in one individual so, we
had this whole population of n elements here
which is reproduced according to fitness
then, we do cross over to make sub genes.
And then, we make some random change in
one candidate.
So, this is a just to allow for new genes
to come in or if a so, for example, if you
have a
population of this sat problem let us say
these 9 variables sat problem and you have
a
population of 50 candidates and it so happens
that all 50 of them have their 3 rd bit as
essentially. Now, we can see that if all 50
of them as a 3 rd bit as 0 then, however much
we do this churning the 3 rd bit will remain
0. Because both parents are going to have
the
3 rd bit as 0 and this cross over operation
will result in the 3 rd bit means 0 in both
the
children essentially.
So, you have lost that 3 rd bit in some sense.
To create it to something like that, we have
a random change somewhere in mutation, but
we do it very rarely essentially. These are
.just for the sake of completeness. So, the
primary processes is selection and cross over,
but there is a process which once in a while
we do which we make some change in some
candidates essentially or random change in
some candidate.
So, when we talk about sat we are talking
about bits, but otherwise we have to do this
encoding in to the production in a low careful
fashion. And then, we have to because you
know one bit is nice, but most, for most problems
you cannot have a components
represented by 1 bit, you will have a chunk
of bits. Then you have to devise a algorithm
to move around chunk of bits rather than you
know just single bits and then, you have to
be careful about mutation that you can change
mutate something in to something
meaningful and not something which is not
meaningful ..
.
So, from this we get a new population let
us call this P 1 prime prime, P 2 prime prime,
P
n prime prime. So, the first P prime population
we got by cloning and this P prime prime
population we got by cross over essentially
and let us say mutation has been taken into0
account here essentially.
Now, there are variations to what people do
at this stage, if I assume that these are
sorted
on fitness values then these are the best
on the, just for the sake of processing, these
are
.sorted, the most fit numbers are here and
the least fit numbers are here. So, what one
might do is that, one might take the most
fit k elements where k is a little bit smaller
than
n and we place it in the original population
by the least fit k elements.
So, what are we doing here is that we started
with this population of n elements, and let
us assume that they are sorted according to
the fitness here just for sake of allowing
me
to draw this diagram. We clone the entire
population to get a new population and when
I
say entire population, it means that you get
representation in proportion to a fitness
value.
A very fit member will get more copies, and
a very unfit member will get less copies or
copies, some will have to have 0 copies then,
you do this cross over, mix up the genes,
took arrived at this population which is now
mix up the genes of the old ones. Now,
some people would argue that what if there
was a very good candidate here. This P 1,
let
us say its fitness value is 98 or something
like that, and everything else let us say
began
with 67 and 65 and so and so forth. Are not
you losing your candidate with fitness value
98 essentially?
To, create it to this, one way to devise this,
is that you take the most fit to most fit
candidate in this new population and add them
or substitute this least k fit population
with this worst k fit population. Then, keep
those few top from the original population
here, we just design question.
You can say k equal to n and that is what
really happens in nature essentially. I mean
nature does not allow one to live in definitely
essentially. If you want read some of these
work by Goldberg in fact this book by Goldberg
then, he goes on to study as to how
should we design these encoding scheme so,
that good genes in some science have a
tendency to stick together and carry forward
essentially.
So, let us say if we have this some or let
us say this sat example with 9 genes or 9
variables. And let us say some good values
we have found in some candidate where let
us say x 3 and x 4, we have found what should
be the value in the ultimate solution. How
do we kind of make sure that, they stick around
together essentially. So, Goldberg talks
.about things like cluster of jeans and so
on which will so, he calls, he has a some
notion
of saying that if you have gains which sort
of a design kept together then, they will
stay
together. They are more likely to be not split,
broken up essentially.
Essentially one of the things with this genetic
programming or genetic algorithm
community is concern with is that is there
some way we can ensure that when a
candidate has good genes, we can ensure their
good genes stay together essentially. And
they do not get broken up and divided in because
in this case as we can see, it is a very
clear cut exchange of genes essentially.
Every genes of parent for example, if x 3
is a good gene, it will go to exactly one
child in
this way, in this scheme of thing because
c 1 will get x 3, but c 2 will get y 3 essentially.
So, it is not as if, as it, as it happens
in the real world, their good gene can go
to both the
children, in this case it will go to only
one child.
So, if x 3 and x 5 for example, happen to
be good genes, how can we sort of ensure,
how
can we ensure that you know good genes stay
together? It means they stay in one
candidate only essentially. So, this is a
kind of stuff that Goldberg has looked at,
you will
not go in to those details here, but you can
see that this scheme of things where we select
the k best and replace the k worst with this
k best is in some sense trying to keep the
good candidates still alive essentially.
Of course this even prime prime which is a
totally new candidate because it is got
generated by the cross over. It could be P
1 cross over with some other elements is
totally different then, it could in fact be
better than 98 it is quite possible essentially.
That
is a hope that as we mix up genes, the candidate
with the good genes will propagate their
genes more often and we are showing this by
the process of selection which is
proportional to fitness essentially.
So, I think I will stop close to here, if
there any question you can answer them. In
the
next class when we meet, I will take up an
example again from Goldberg’s book to try
and give you ((Refer Time :49:55)) behind
genetic algorithms. But I also wanted you
to
think about our, not our, the community’s
favorite problems which is the travelling
sales
.man problem. How can we use genetic algorithms
for solving the travelling salesmen
problems? So, either way outside let me say
that because the way that we have encoded
TSP so far is that let us say we have 9 cities.
.
So, let us say parent 1 is 1, 2, 3, 7, 1,
and parent 2 is let us say 1, 2, 3, 4, 5,
6, 7, 8, 9. I
have these two parents which means I have
these two towards. So, here you go from 2
to
3, 3 to 7, and 7 to 1, and 7 and so on. Here
you go for 1 to 2 and 2 to 3 and so on so
forth.
You can see that the single point cross over
will not work here because if I just take
a
random point let us say here after 4 cities
then, what I am doing? I am going from 2 to
to 7 to 1 to 5 to 6 to 7, you can see I have
closed the loop even before, I am not allowed
to that.
In a travelling sales men problem, the solution
must be a permutation of the cities, but if
I do, if I do this single point crossover
and say this is, I will take this cities from
here and
this cities from here. What I get is not really
a candidate tour because this tour has a loop
inside before.
So, again from 2 to 3, 3 to 7, 7 to 1 then,
you are going to 5 to and then to 6 and then,
you are coming back to 7. And you are never
visiting some cities, you never visiting 4,
.you never visiting 8, you never visiting
9. So, that is not a candidate solution. What
we
want is a population of candidate solution,
and what is a candidate solution? In which
every city is visited exactly once and then,
which means basically it is a permutation
of
the number 1 to 9 and this sequence of numbers
that is not a permutation because 7 is
repeated and 4 is missing essentially so,
it is not a permutation. How can we devise
cross
over operators for the TSP essentially.
So, this has, this question is in two parts.
Can we think of a different representation
of
that candidate solution, and can we think
of different operators essentially, different
cross operators? And there is been a considerable
amount of work done in trying to
experiment with different kinds of cross over
operators.
So, we generalize the notion of cross over
to say that you take two parents, and you
must
somehow get two children which are generated
from those two parents essentially. So,
these two things we will do in the next class
to start with. Look at the example of genetic
algorithms for a simple problem and then,
we will look at how TSP can be solved using
j
s and I wanted to give some thought to at
before come to the next class because we will
stop here.
.