So, today we move on to this topic on planning.
So, in the next 6 or 7 lectures, I will cover
little bit of planning and little bit constraint
satisfaction, which is I think enough for
a
introductory course on A I. But next semester,
Dr Narayan swami and I offering a course on
planning and constraint satisfaction, which
will go into much more detail in the topics.
So,
what we are doing here is just a basic, but
the more recent advancements will probably
do in
that course essentially.
So, there is a nice book on planning, which
we are not following here by Malik Galab and
Dina Noven, call automatic planning. They
start the book by this definition of planning
and
they say it is the reasoning side of acting.
So, planning is concerned with actions. Essentially,
we are not deal with them explicitly on and
off. For example, we looked at heuristic for
the
blocks world. We talked about moving blocks
around, but we did not really explicitly module
domains and we do not explicitly module actions.
We will do that in the planning path that
we are doing now.
.Now, just imagine an agent. So, this is world
and the agent inside the world, but will draw
it
here. It perceives the world and deliberates
and then acts. So, this is a model of an agent
in an
environment that we have. The agent perceives
the environment or the world, does some
deliberation or some reasoning as Galab and
all call it. Then, based on that reasoning
the
agent does acting in the world. Of course,
we as human beings do it all the time. We
are
planning consciously or unconsciously. Whatever,
we do these are not random actions that
we do. Anyway almost everything we do has
a certain goal in mind. We think about how
to
achieve that goal and our actions are oriented
towards that achieving the goal essentially.
So, goals of course, can be long term or short
term and things like that, but all the time
in the
world we are planning. Now of course, in the
world of computing, planning is becoming
more and more important as systems are becoming
more and more autonomous. So, for
example, you must have heard about autonomous
cars now a days. So, there is stand forth
car
and if there is a car rally for autonomous
cars. So, you have to let loose the car in
some sense
and it should be able to go to a destination.
Now, if you think about what is involved here?
It is not just route finding, which is what
we
have discussed to some extent, but to drive
a car there are many many actions that you
have
to do. You have to look out for other cars,
you may have to slow, you may have to break,
you
may have to accelerate. All these are actions
and somebody has to decide or some agent or
some program has to decide, which actions
to be done at what time essentially. That
decision
making or this reasoning side of acting is
what planning is all about essentially.
So, we imagine that we have a planning system
and that interacts with some people call an
executive, which interacts with the world
essentially. So, I using the term executive,
it was
used by NASA in one of their early systems,
the remote agent architecture. So, you should
look up on the web about this remote agent.
It was experiment done by NASA experiment
called deep space.
Sometime in the mid 19th, they had this aircraft
flowing spacecraft, flowing somewhere in
space going to earth some asteroid or some
planet or something. In between for 2 or 3
days,
they had removed ground station control from
that space craft, which means they had let
it
function autonomously, deciding for itself
what it would do in the next 2 or 3 days.
During
that period they had also introduced deliberately
a fault in the space craft and which was used
.to testing their automatic fault diagnosis
system, which of course, we are not doing
here, but
apart from fault diagnosis planning was a
experiment that they did.
Then, you must have heard about mars lowers
and the more recent lowers that have been
sent
to mars. Given, the fact that it takes of
the order of 20 minutes, I do not know the
exact figure
for a signal to travel from earth to mars.
You cannot control vehicle on mars as you
would be
controlling a vehicle, let us say in your
lab. If you had a remote or something like
that
because the signal takes that much more time
in such situations, it is inevitable that
you have
autonomous planning built into the system.
So, both in the remote agent architecture
and in the mars lowers, what the scientist
do? is that
they give high level commands go and explore
that area or go and collect samples of this
in
from this area. Then the rest of the activity
is planned by the system on board. So, planning
of
course, these are some of extreme examples
space example, but planning happens all the
time
essentially. You know scheduling holiday planning,
you go to some flight reservation
systems, they will tell you that if you want
to go from here to basils, what are the flights
you
should take? So, all this comes under planning
some way or the other essentially.
So, let us look at this model of what is happening
in the world. Let us see to what degree of
complexity, we can capture this essentially.
So, in planning systems we are going to do
the
following. We are going to talk of domain
description, action let me use the word
specification or action description, describing
what actions are available to you and of course
goal states.
..
.
We will look at this in little bit while,
the early planning systems were kind of domain
specific. People would say I want to build
a system for planning in this domain or planning
in
that domain and so on. But following the theme
that we have been in this course, which says
that a problem solver must be removed from
the domain. You want to find general purpose
planning systems or else this community calls
it domain independent planning essentially,
which means that we will devise a language
to express all this.
So, this is like domain functions that we
talked about in search. The planner would
be
independent of this. You would write the planner
assuming that, you would read a domain
description and a problem description or goal
description and the planner would
automatically compile and run essentially.
So, one of the earliest planners that was
built was
called strips.
..
.
We had possibly talked about it at least in
the context of this Robert called Shakey.
So, if you
remember Shakey was one of the earliest Roberts,
that was built in the computing
community, which could roam around a corridors
of stand Ford University. May be looking
for forward points anything like that know
where you could share itself. It had a on
board
camera and it was on 2 wheels. So, if you
just look up Shakey, you will see some
photographs and I had shown the photographs
during my introduction as well. It was fairly
autonomous cam of course, it could not do
much, it could just roam around the place
and the
planner that they used was called strips.
Some people say, stand ford research institute
planning system essentially and that was the
earliest kind of language description, the
simplest kind of language description that
you can
use for planning. We will sought of look at
this language to start with this essentially,
what
would do all this people had started working
with devising languages. So, these are called
planning domain, description language or in
short PDDL and there are versions of PDDL.
You start with PDDL 1.0 and we will look at
only PDDL 1.0 here in this course and which
is
basically, what strips does essentially?
So, what happens when you go to higher levels
of language? Basically, the richness of the
language increases, you are able to describe
the domain as well as actions of more complex
nature. So, let us see what are those kind
simplifications that we are making in strips.
So, we
had describing strips domains now. So, it
is a term that has become common to use for
the
.simplest kind of planning domains. We call
them strips domains because that is what this
strips planner use essentially and I will
describe them in a short way.
So, these are the simplifications that we
simplifying assumptions that we use, one is
that the
space is finite. So, you can still work with
this idea of space search that we started
this whole
course with where you are in some given state.
You want to be in some desired state and the
actions that you have to chose only now we
will. So, that time we said there is a move
generation function, which takes a state and
gives you successors state. Now, we are saying
that we have access to actions and we will
reason with those actions essentially.
So, the simplest assumption is that the space
is finite essentially. The second assumption
that
we make is that, it is fully observable which
means just as we discussed when we were
talking about games. We said we have complete
information games and incomplete
information games fully observable planning
system is one where, the agent can sense the
entire world, which means this perception
part of the agent is perfect. The agent can
see the
entire world and there is no missing information
essentially.
Each of the assumptions that we are talking
about we can relax and we can richer in some
sense planning problems of planning domain
essentially. The third is, it is static. By
static we
mean that agent is the only one making changes
in the world essentially. So, there is no
other
influence in the world. All this is not allowed,
there is no there no cloud, there is no sun
moving around, there is no rain falling, nothing.
Agent is the only one, which is making
changes in the world and such a domain is
called static.
Obviously, when we talk about multi agent
systems advisable systems like game playing
that
we saw, then this domain this assumption we
are violating and the other problem becomes
more complex essentially. Then the actions
are deterministic. All these are simplifying
assumptions that we are making and what do
we mean by this? That when an agent does an
action, let us say pick up this watch essentially
or know pickup this remote. Whatever action
the agent does, it happens in the real world
and as planned essentially.
So, which means in a deterministic world,
if I want to say throw this ball into the
basket on a
basket ball court, then you put ball into
the basket essentially. Of course, the real
world is not
deterministic when you play basketball, you
would realize that it needs a considerable
amount of practice to get better at it, but
we will make a simplistic assumption. That
the
.world is deterministic, which means that
whatever actions agent does, they will happen
in the
real world.
Just imagine that what would happen, if the
world was not deterministic, then you create
a
plan that you will get out of this building,
you will board your bicycle and go off to
the hostel
and have some tea. Then when you go down,
you find that somebody has stolen your bicycle
or may be bicycle is punctured or something
like that, then you can no longer do the
planning. So, the effect of deterministic
action is, once you planned your plan, plan
can be
executed without any false essentially because
the world is fully observable and static and
deterministic. If you make a plan, the plan
will execute in the world.
So, you want to worry about monitoring the
plan and things like that essentially. So,
now a
days of course, there is a big community looking
at stochastic actions or probabilistic actions.
So, you must have heard about probabilistic
planning. So, they follow a entirely different
approach to planning, what we are doing is
something like search. They do something which
is quite different. So, we have this mark
of decision processes and so on.
Doctor Ravidran talks more about such things
in his course and I think he is also offering
a
course on probabilistic reasoning next semester.
Then simple goals, I mean that we have the
goal test function is on applied on the final
state. You say that this is what you want
to
achieve, you want to be in the hostel and
you want to be eating dosa and having some
coffee
and if that is a situation, then the goal
is satisfied. So, that is what we will call
it as simple
goals. Goals tested only on the final state
as opposed to this, there is a community.
So, if you look at higher levels of prejudice
for example, they would talk about what we
call
as trajectory constraints, which means you
have conditions on the path that you have
are
finding for the goal essentially as well.
So, the trajectory is the solution and you
have
conditions on the solutions essentially. So,
for example, if you are planning a long trip,
you
might say that that at all points I must be
within 5 kilometer, some reason let us say
your
friend is not too well and or susceptible
something. You say that my route must be such
that
all points I must be within 5 kilometers of
a hostel.
So, that is a trajectory constraint you are
may be saying that, I want to go from here
to
Nagpur, that is a final goal, but I have constraints
on the path as well. We will not look at
those, we will only simple goals or you might
have constraints like a every time you go
into a
.room and out of the room, you must switch
on, switch off the lights or something like
that.
These are constraints on the path essentially
also soft constraints.
Our goal description is rigid that only if
those conditions are met. we will say that
a goal has
been achieved essentially. You might have
soft constraints or soft goals, which might
say I
would like to go to the market and if possible
I want to go and see a movie. You know by
all
these stuffs and do some, you may have a plan,
but you may accept the plan, which does not
achieve all the goals completely, but achieve
as many as possible. Then you would have to
save a penalty associated with that.
So, in that if I do not know take this goal
of buying a tooth paste, my plan is not as
good as a
plan, if I had also both the toothpaste. Then
it becomes a optimization problem because
you
have to now find a plan, which satisfies certain
optimality criteria. As refers to this
satisfaction criteria which says, if these
things are true, then I have achieved my goal
whereas, here you are willing to relax it
and that is why it is called soft constraint
that you are
willing to allow for some things not to be
achieved. You would still accept the plan
essentially; obviously, with each such condition
being relaxed the problem becomes harder
than harder.
Then a plan is equal to sequence
of actions. We will assume that our plan is
a sequence of
actions. So, we do not want more complicated
plans, which have networks of actions some
things like that. And one more constraint
which is very important, it is being relaxed
quite
often now a days which is the notion of time.
So, will assume that we do not have a notion
of
time to start with. We will just say action
a happens, then action b happens, then action
c
happens. There is only a notion of sequence
that actions happen in a sequence whereas,
in the
real world, some actions may take more, some
actions may take less amount of time.
So, you may say I will take a bath and they
have a cup of tea and then cycle to the gate.
Each
of these actions may take a different amount
of time. If you want to take that into account,
then you want to have what we call is. So,
what we have is instantaneous actions, but
what
we can have is just write versus durative
actions. So, by durative actions we mean actions,
which have durations and then of course, you
can even start talking about doing things
in
parallel. Once we were talking about time
and durations.
So, you can say that while my sambhar is being
cooked on the left side gas, I will make
something else in the right hand gas. So,
that things will happen in parallel, this
will take so
.much time. Then you might worry about what
is the total amount of time that my plan will
need to execute, which is call make span in
planning terms, but durative actions brings
these
kind of situation.
So, one interesting problem which was raised
by a P. SE. student from one of these
universities, I think Washington university
is the following. He says that and this was
a
problem, which could not be solved by the
techniques that were there till 2007 and it
is a task
of repairing a fuse essentially. So, it is
a very simple problem. Let us say this is
a duration
whatever time t you need to repair the fuse.
So, the situation is that lights have gone
out in the
apartment and you are repairing the fuse and
it takes you that much time.
So, the action is durative, it means it takes
that much amount of time. You have one match
stick essentially and the match stick can
give you light for so much amount of time.
So, this is
along the x axis though y x is meaningless.
Basically, this is a interval over time so,
this takes
so much time, this takes so much time and
the task is to repair the fuse, but you need
light
when you inserting the fuse in to the socket.
So, essentially this match stick must be leaked
in
such a way that it overlaps with the end part
of this fuse repair action.
Now, the trouble with this is from first yearly
we are not into details here. The thing is
that
when you are dealing with durative actions,
you cannot talk about time going in know
seconds or something like that, that would
become simply unmanageable essentially. So,
you
do not do that, what you do is I do anything
at this time point, when I starting this action.
May be I can start another action or no something
like that. Essentially can I do something
when this action is running. So, time jumps
from beginning of action to end of action
essentially and then you plan to do something.
Now, the whole problem with this is that you
cannot reason about it here, you cannot reason
about it here. You have to set of reason about
it in such a way that, this comes into here.
So,
this gave rise gives gave rose to some many
interesting problems in how to build systems,
which will do. Now of course, we have planners
which can do this and they would place an
action somewhere in between so that this saddles
this essentially. So, durative actions of
course, increase the complexity manifold essentially.
So, one way that some people have tried to
model durative actions by seeing to split
it into
two actions saying, this is a start action
and this is a end action, but durative actions
will have
know conditions like that. Something must
be proved throughout or something must be.
So,
.for example if you are taking a bath then
you might have condition that the light must
be on
throughout that, you are afraid of the dark
or something like that.
Now, if you traveling from place a to place
b, then at the end of the action you should
be at
place b. At the beginning of the action you
must be at place a and in between you must
be at
neither place. So, this kind of constrains
on actions make complexity of planning more
and
more difficult essentially. So, I should say
here some sense cross. So, we are not using
durative actions in strips domain. These are
the simplifying assumptions that you make
in
strips domain. Actions are instantaneous,
the goal is fully observable actions are
deterministic, the world is static and we
have simple goals.
Even in these simple domains it was shown
to be p space concrete. So, planning is those
one
of the hard problems that you are trying to
solve and it will always need some exponential
amount of time essentially. Every time you
relax this constraints, the problem becomes
more
complex in terms. So, let us look at how strips
describes actions. So, we will use this blocks
world. You know we already talked about blocks
world, moving blocks around. So, we will
we will see how blocks world is described
in strips essentially and PDDL is basically
is kind
of a standardization of what we are seeing
here essentially. So, first we have domain
predicates.
.
So for example, we might say on x, y where,
x and y are variables to signify that block
x is on
block y, then we can have I use a once used
in strips on table x, then holding x. We assume
.that there is a one arm Robert, which is
moving the blocks around, so that one arm
Robert can
hold one block and that is described by this
predicate saying holding block x. So, this
x y
would be filled up with variable with constraints
in real world, in a real problem essentially.
Clear x says that there is nothing on top
of x essentially, which is a kind of a short
form or
saying that another case there exists y.
So, we will look at first or logical little
bit later in the course case, you are not
familiar with
the language. So, whenever you define a domain,
you have first define what are the
predicates which will define the situation
essentially. So, instead of saying that we
have some
state representation, now we are saying that
you must be define a predicates which describe
the state and the state will be a collection
of such sentences.
.
So, for example, if I have a situation like
this A is on b on c something like this. Then
I will
describe it by saying that on a b, on b c,
on a d, on table c, on table d, on table f,
clear a, clear
e, clear f and this is my one arm Robot. I
need a predicate for that which we will call
arm
empty. So, either you are holding something
or arm is empty essentially. So, we can describe
this state using these predicates essentially
plane values of the variables. We have the
operators or the actions. So, in this simple
world we will assume that there are 4 actions,
one
is pickup.
..
.
So, in PDDL you first describe what are the
predicates that you will use to describe the
world, then you describe actions. Now, actions
are described by 2 things, one is what is
necessary to the action to be applicable?
What should be clue for the action to be applicable
and secondly, what will become clue after
the action is applied essentially?
So, in some sense we have the left hand side
and the right hand side like in the rule that
we
talked about earlier, but in this strips kind
of a thing, we would say that they are three
list, one
is a precondition list, one is the add list
and one is the delete list. This is the original
way in
which strips describe the actions. So, precondition
list is those predicates which must be true
for the action to be applicable. So, if you
want pickup list to be applicable, it should
be true
that it should be on the table and it should
be clear, which means nothing must be on top
of it.
I will just use for this AE and arm must be
empty.
So, if these 3 predicates happen to be true
in my domain, which means of course, I have
to
just see the precondition list is a subset
of my state description. The state description
is the set
of predicates which is describing this thing
essentially. So for example, this will have
on table
f and it will have clear f and arm empty.
So, because these things are in the state
description,
this action becomes applicable. I can pickup
f for example, that is the way that strips
original
description is given.
So, if you look at any text book, we use that
we will distinguish between the 2 actions
in
which we pickup something from the table and
we pick up something from top of another
.block. So, that will have a different precondition
just to illustrate what is happening? It has
to
be owned something either on the table or
on another block. So, this pickup is only
for
picking up things from the table.
So, the add list as they used to call it is
a list of effects, which will become true
if this action
were to be executed. In this case the only
thing we are put is that the Robert will be
holding
this block x and the delete list contains
those things, which will become true, but
no longer
true. That includes things like on table x
and arm empty x. So, it also include clear
x, but as I
will discuss in the moment. You can either
like it or you can ignore it, it does not
matter. So,
corresponding to this, I have an action called
put down. So, precondition list says holding
x
whose add list contains on table x arm empty.
Now, if I want to remove this clear x from
here, then I should add it here. If I do not
remove
it then I should not add it here. You just
think about this that either I must add it
in both these
places or I can live it out of both these
places. What is important is that if you are
picking up
there must be nothing on top of it. So, I
need this clear x at that point. It is obvious
that once
you pick it up and put it down on something
else, there will be nothing top of that at
that
instant. So, clear x will remain true after
that essentially.
.
Corresponding to these there are two more
actions which we call as unstuck because I
will
just name the actions or operators. I will
expect you to them to describe it in more
detail with
this precondition list, add list and delete
list. So, the only difference between unstack
and
.pickup is that, the pickup is from the table
and unstack is from some other object. So,
you can
unstack a from b or you can unstack e from
d. The conditions are similar a must be clear,
a
must be on b and arm must be empty to unstack
it and likewise you can stack it. In the more
modern PDDL language, I would call this as
positive effects.
.
So, if my action is a then this list is the
precondition list of a, this is the effects
positive of a
and this is effects negative of a. So, in
the modern PDDL language we do not use this
name
precondition list, add list and delete list.
We will say preconditions and effects and
effects can
be positive or negative. Positive means they
become true after the action is applied, negative
means that they become false after the action
is applied and the two of them together call
effects.
So, we describe a set of action using the
precondition list and the effects list of
the actions
and we can basically now have a language to
define any domain in which you want to do
planning. What we will need to do is, define
a set of predicates which describe the domain
which means describe the states of the domain
and then define the actions which can be done
essentially. So, what is the planning problem?
A planning problem
is defined by a set of
operators or actions a domain description,
starts state and a goal description essentially.
So,
this is the start and this is the goal. So,
for example, this could be my start state,
I have not
written it in this language, but you can write
it quite easily. My goal description could
simply
be something like a, I could say on, this
could be my goal description.
..
.
So, observe of course, that I do not need
to completely specify the goal as a state.
The start
state I need to completely specify, you say
that it is fully observable. Everything that
is true
must be given, but a goal does not have to
be completely specified. Your goal may simply
be
that as long as those 2 things are true, then
I am happy with my plan essentially. I do
not care
where the other blocks are as long as e is
on c and c is on f, then I am happy. So, e
is on c, c
is on f, this f could be on something else
or it be on the table and I do not care about.
Now of course, this is like what we do in
the real world. We do not necessarily describe
the
goal completely. Let us say this is what I
want to be true, I do not care about anything
else
essentially. So, the goal description is a
set of predicates, the start description is
also a set of
such predicates incenses of predicates. When
do we say that action a is applicable?
..
.
If precondition of a is a subset of start,
it is just like saying that if my preconditions
are true,
then well s does not have to be start it can
be any state. So, an action a is applicable
in a state
s, if preconditions are part of the state
essentially, which means that they are true
essentially.
We say that when the action is applied we
get a new state. So, we progress
new state s prime
where, s prime is given by the given state
that we are in. I will use this as a minus
sign or I
can use a standard minus sign whatever the
effects minus of a union effects plus a.
So, once you define a state and once you define
an action, we know that if an action a is
applicable in a state s, then I can apply
action a to state s to go to a new state s
prime, which
is given. I remove everything which other
negative effects of the action from the state
and
add all the positive effects of the action,
so I get a new state s prime.
A plan pie is a sequence of actions. So, we
have assumed here that our plan is a simple
thing
like sequence of action. So, plan we will
use a term pie is a sequence of actions a
1, a 2 an
essentially. So, the first thing you want
to do is to write small routine, which will
validate a
plan that this plan is doing my task. What
is the task? The task is that I have been
given a
start state, I have been given a goal state
and somebody tells me that, this is a plan
somebody
meaning some program that I have attend. The
program should be able to validate that, this
is
a plan how do I do that before we do that,
how do I do goal test? How do I say that a
given
state is a goal state?
.So, goal test is simple g should be a subset
of state s, g is a set of predicates describing
the
goal. So, if g is a subset of s, then that
s is a goal state. s is a state which describes
the whole
state. We just some conditions have set on
those on the state. So, it is like saying
that I should
be stick on the canteen and having a dosa,
I do not care what everybody else is doing,
if that
is true then i am in a goal state essentially
and that we can test by simply doing a subset
essentially.
So, now having a goal test function how do
I and somebody gives me a plan pie. How do
I
know that the plan is a plan for solving a
problem. I must able to write a small program
to
validate that what will that program do it
will progress over the state. So, it will
apply first
action a 1 to given state, then in the resulting
action it will apply a 2, which means it check
whether a 2 is applicable and apply a 2 and
then keep doing that till we apply all the
actions.
In the resulting state that we have progressed
to remember this, we have this progress
operator. How can we move from state to state
that last state must satisfy that condition,
that
the goal must be a subset of the state essentially.
So, this all we have done today is to describe
the planning domains were to speak. The
planning domain is described using a language
called a planning domain description
language. I have urged to look at some website,
which will tell you a what which will give
you a actual syntax of PDDL. Essentially it
constitutes of a set of predicates which are
used
to describe the domain or define a domain
and a set of operators or actions, which are
the
actions that you can do in the domain.
The real actions are the instances of these
operators, if you want to distinguish between
them.
Then you can describe a planning problem by
saying this is my start state. So, I can say
on ab
is true, on b c is true, on a d is true, on
table f is true, on table d is true, on table
c is true, clear
a, clear e, clear f and arm empty. If I state
all these things, I have said I have described
my
state. I say my goal state is that c must
be on f and e must be on c that is my goal
state. So, I
can now have goal state.
Now, all I need is an algorithm to find a
plan and then of course, I also need to be
able to
validate a plan. We will see that some algorithms
will need this validation check because it
can produce plans sequence of actions, which
are not necessarily plans. So, we need this
check essentially. So, in a next couple of
classes we will look at a few algorithms to
find this
plan. What is the simplest approach you can
think? You are talking of a specific problem
.which is a blocks world domain. Now, this
is just using as a example to illustrate our
planning algorithms. Our planning algorithms
have to be domain independent, we do not
know what are the predicates or what are the
actions, but we should be able to still write
an
algorithm to use that.
So, this solution of course, is a very nice
solution which sought of defines the fact
that I kept
saying it is peace space complete, but in
fact, in the blocks world domain, there is
a very
simple algorithm. It says first put everything
on the table, which will take you if the n
blocks
at most some order n by 2 or something like
that or order n. Let us see just put everything
on
the table and then assemble the thing that
you want to assemble.
So, you want c to be on f pickup c put it
on f, you want e to be unseen, pickup e and
that can
be done in linear time essentially, but that
is a very specific solution to a very specific
problem. We are interested is in domain independent
planning, which means we do not know
the domain, we do not know the predicates,
we do not know the actions. We have a language
to describe the domain, the predicates and
the actions, and the start state, and the
goal state
and then the algorithms should be able to
operate.
So, the simplest approach as you can get is
the power state space search that we have
been
doing all this along. Go to the start state
apply the move gen function. How can you write
a
move gen function? You have to simply test
for all the actions, which are applicable
and they
will basically constitute a move gen function.
They will give you what are the actions you
can do, keep doing that and then we also have
goal test function. So, the simplest is forward
state space search, but we will look at other
approaches and we will do that in the next
class
onwards.
We will stop here.
.