So, shall we begin? So, the last few, the
last few lectures that we had on games was
a bit
of a diversion intended to get you ready for
the assignment, which you will soon give
you, possibly next week. We come back to this
idea of problem decomposition.
.
And today we look at this thing called rule
based systems, also known as production
systems, also somewhat ambitiously known as
expert systems. So, far in our discussions
we have already mentioned 2 systems, one is
Dendral and the other one is R 1 also
known as X CON which were supposed to be 2
of the first so called expert systems. And
by this we mean that programs which harnessed
the knowledge of human experts and use
that for solving problems essentially. So,
this knowledge of that we get from human
experts in this form that we are talking about
was generally in the form of rules or
productions essentially.
..
And the idea is that if you have a state description,
then instead of devising a moves and
function which gives takes one state and gives
you another state. What we do is we look
at some part of the state and based on this
part of the state we device, let us say action
one or another part of the state we look at
we device another action.
So, in some sense we are not looking at the
complete state, but we are looking at what
we call as a pattern in the state. So, these
things are patterns. Now, this pattern is
typically described in the form of a production
or the rule and I will use the syntax of a
language called Opius 5, which I will shortly
tell you. But the basic idea is that the
structure is as follows.
So, you have a rule name and you have pattern
1 and pattern 2 and so on, some number
of patterns and I will shortly describe what
these are followed by action 1, action 2 some
number of action essentially. So, this is
the structure of a rule also known as a
production. And the basic idea is that this
is called the left hand side this is called
the
right hand side because of the arrow here.
This is also called the antecedents and we
can
think of this as a consequent.
So, a rule is basically a set of antecedents
followed by a set of actions or consequents
and
it is a very modular form of knowledge representation.
We have so far not used the word
knowledge representation at all in this course,
we have assumed that somehow you will
have a state representation and somehow you
will have a moves and function which will
.move from one state to another. Now, with
this we for the first time we are talking
about
how do we actually represent things.
And the idea here is that knowledge is represented
in the form of rules. So, here on the
left hand side followed by the right hand
side here. So, the left hand side that we
are
talking about here is essentially the pattern
that we are looking at and if the pattern
matches then the action can be done. So, for
example, the system R 1 had rules like. So,
you should look up the actual rule in X CON
or maybe I can just read out a rule from
here. This says, this is the rule from R 1
its rule name is distribute (Refer Time..
So, remember R 1 was the system which was
used to configure bags machines, deck
vack machines which was some of the most advanced
computing systems at that time
which was in the late 70s. And this rule reads
the following, if that is the left hand side,
the most current active context is distributing
mass first devices and there is a single port
disk drive that has not been assigned to a
mass bus and there are no unassigned dual
port
disk drive and so on and so forth.
And then the action is, then assigned the
disk drive to the mass bus. So, it has a set
of
conditions on the left hand side and in this
example only one action on the right hand
side essentially. So, the idea is to capture
knowledge of a human in this form and use
this
knowledge to solve problems. Now, how does
that happen?
.
.So, there is this idea of an inference engine.
And this inference engine takes on the one
hand data and on the other hand rules and
it generates the, I will just use the loose
term
to say the solution or a sequence of actions.
So, the idea behind rule based systems which
also were for some reason called expert systems
and production systems was that the
problem solver or the human expert or the
domain expert will only provide the rules
for
solving problems.
So, rules like this if some conditions are
true then some action happens, if some
conditions are true then some action happens
and so on. So, you might say for example,
you might have a rule which says is a particular
customer worthy of being given a loan?
Then a bank manager may have a rule of certain
kind that if this persons income is so
much and if he is been a customer for so many
days and if he has no outstanding loans
then you can give him a loan of whatever 10
lacs or something like that.
So, you can have a rule like this. Now, the
thing is that if we allow the domain expert
to
express rules like this then they do not have
to worry about program which works on this
rules. They only write the rules and somebody
else in this case inference engine does the
work for them essentially.
So, this inference engine is the one which
will actually pick rules from the collection
of
rules when a new problem comes beside which
rules to apply and then generate the
solution essentially. Alternatively you might
have a rule, the railways might have a rule
based which says who gets what kind of concession
and so on so. And if you are a war
veteran you get a certain kind of concession
and if you are a sports man you get a certain
kind of concession. If you are a student going
home you get a certain kind of concession
and that kind of stuff.
So, all these so called what which people
now days call as business rules are described
as
a domain people. They are not worried about
computer, computing and programs and
things like that. There task is to only provide
the rules essentially. We could have a rule
for example to say, good student award which
might say that if the student has done all
the assignments and the student has done well
in courses. And if there are no proxies in
the attendance then he is a good student we
can give him an award or her an award.
Focus we do not do that. So, you do not have
to worry about it.
..
So, the basic idea behind rule based systems
is this that a rule is a pattern, action,
combination, there is a collection of rules.
So, this is a whole set which the domain
expert provides. This data pertains to the
current problem that you are trying to solve
and
inference engine. And we will look at this
in some detail today. Is the one which does
the
job of picking rules and applying them to
data and arriving at the solutions essentially.
Which is one reason why some people have called
this as pattern directed inference
systems. In fact, there is a book by this
name, it is a little old.
Now, the thing for you to observe and we will
do this over the next, this lecture and the
next is that rule based programming can be
seen as a different paradigm of programming
in itself essentially. Now, in imperative
programming which is what most people are
used to languages like c and Pascal and so
on. The task of the programmer is to give
a
control flow, say do this action, then do
this action, then do this action.
And of course, you may have more complicated
things like conditional statements and
branches and loops and all this kind of stuff,
but it is the programmer which specifies
what actions have to be done essentially.
Now, you can think of a rule based system,
you
can in some sense port it to an imperative
language and you can. So, remember that the
rule based systems basically consists of a
large number rules set, the domain expert
rights.
You could convert it into an imperative program
and you could have a sequence of if
.then statements, if this then this else this
then this and so on and so forth. The control
flow is fixed and rigid in imperative program,
in rule based systems. On the other hand
you can think of this as follows that you
have this data...
.
in some pool and there are a set of rules
hanging above this. And when I say hanging
above this, this has to sort of make you think
about it slightly differently.
In the sense that there is no control relation
between the different rules. You are not
saying apply this rule first then apply this
rule first and then apply this rule first
and so
on. You are simply saying in each rule you
are giving a little bit of modular piece of
knowledge we say if you see this pattern then
this is the action that you have to do with
it
essentially. And all the rules are kind of
floating around.
So, this is a what we would call is as a rule
base and what the inference engine does is
that it will pick some rule and apply it to
the relevant data and do the relevant action.
Then they may pick another rule and apply
it and so on and so forth. And it will keep
doing that. It is a inference engine, and
we will look at this in a little more bit
detail,
which decides what are the actions which are
actually done. As opposed to an imperative
programming who programmer says do this action
then you do this action and so on and
so forth essentially.
So, before we get into the details, I also
want to highlight the difference between 2
kinds
.of reasoning and we have, we have slowly
talking about this thing we have not really
done so.
.
One is goal directed or backward reasoning
and by this we mean that you reason from
goals to sub goals in some sense. We have
already seen an example of this when we
were talking about planning an evening out
when you say that evening out is planned if
you have an outing plan and if you have a
movie plan and if you have a dinner plan.
So,
those are the sub goals essentially.
So, you start with a major goal and then you
come to the sub goals essentially. And there
are people, a lot of people who feel that
human beings by and large are goal directed
reasons. They are backward reasons, they do
not reason from. So, this is goal directed
versus forward or you might say data driven
reasoning. So, data driven reasoning is some
kind of an algorithm which looks at data and
says that if I say this pattern, I will do
this
action and so on and so forth.
So, the decision of what to do next is driven
by, is decided by the data that is available
to
you, which is the form that we will be looking
at today. Goal directed reasoning says that
if you have to achieve a certain goal, what
sub goals should I achieve essentially? So,
for
example, you might say that if you want to
get a scholarship into a good US university
for doing post graduate studies then what
do you need to do?
.You need to write g r e, you need to do well,
you need to get recommendation letters,
you have to write a excellent statement of
purpose all this kind of stuffs. These are
sub
goals and to do that to get good grades what
you have to do? You have to attend classes
and study hard and write exams well and so
on. So, if you go from goals towards sub
goals and essentially, eventually towards
actions then you can decide what are the
actions that you need to do essentially.
Again let us say that if I have to plan a
trip from here to mandi then in goal directed
reasoning I would say that first maybe I need
to go to Delhi and then from Delhi I need
to fly to Chandigarh or take a train to Chandigarh
and then take a bus or car or something
and then work out the details later essentially.
How do I go from here to the airport?
Now, how do I book my ticket and how do I
go from? The lower details come later. In
goal directed reasoning, you reason from the
high level goals to the low level goals and
at the lowest level you have action essentially.
Now, there is a corresponding
implementational comparison that you can make.
.
It is called backward chaining versus forward
chaining. So, by backward chaining and
forward chaining we essentially are talking
about how the programs are implemented
whereas with backward reasoning and forward
reasoning we are talking about what is the
kind of reasoning you are doing. So, by and
large of course, backward chaining goes
well with backward reasoning and forward chaining
goes well with forward reasoning.
.But it is possible to do forward chaining
and implement backward reasoning or it is
also
possible to implement backward chaining and
implement forward reasoning essentially.
So, this combination of backward reasoning
and backward chaining sorry backward
reasoning and forward chaining is something
or actually you should call it backward
chaining.
So, this combination for those of you have
written programs and prologs you would
recognize that in prolog you are doing essentially
backward reasoning and if you view
the sign, this sign in prolog as in backward
pointing arrow which we will do when we
look at logic a little bit later in this course.
We will look at this then you can see that
you
are essentially chaining from this to this.
So, in backward chaining you are chaining
from
the right hand side to the left hand side
which means you match.
So, this is actually the right hand side,
why because the arrow is pointing this way
I
could have drawn it like that, but in prolog
you write the goal first and then you write
the
sub goals, if you remember prolog that if
you want to sort an array then you have to
have
a combination of array which should be sorted
and so on and so forth. So, it really
depends on the match which side. So, if you
look at this rule format LHS and RHS then
in backward chaining you are matching here
with the RHS and moving to the LHS. So,
you are asking that if this has to be true
then can I show that this is true.
.
In forward chaining, I match the LHS and go
to the right hand side. If I see this pattern
.then I do the sections. So, we will be focusing
today on forward chaining mechanism
because it is a very widely used technique
in the industry. So, I gave you a couple of
examples about banking and giving loans and
so on and so forth.
.
But there is this whole field called business
rule management systems. So, if you just
look at, look up this thing B R M S, there
is a whole community out there which is
developing software for people in business
meaning it could be industry, manufacturing
industry, banking business or anything.
People who are domain experts, to exploit
computing power the basic mechanism is this
that all you ask them to do is write the rules
and you implement the inference engine
which is the general purpose inference engine.
It is like you can say a search engine is
a
general purpose program and in similar manner
inference engine is a general purpose
program which looks at their rules and their
corresponding data and makes all the actions
which are necessary to be done essentially.
Now, let us get down to some examples. So,
the language that I am using, we do not
really have to use it and in, I mean you may
not have to implement it is called O P S 5.
This is the language is devised, which was
devised I think in the 70s,0 also at (Refer
Time. university which is one of the centers
where a lot of a i related work was
done in the middle of the last century.
..
And some people say that O stands for official.
So, it is a official production system
language and its version was 5 became popular.
It was developed by a guy called Charles
Forgy who implemented this algorithm that
we are going to look at for his p h d thesis
and then eventually of course, it became something
which was commercial in nature. So,
of course, what we need to do is to describe
what is this language, what is the syntax
of
this language. And so I will focus we will
first focus on the pattern. So, how do patterns
describe in OPS5.
So, they follow the, something like a, like
a object oriented way of representing things
which are like classes. The syntax that this
language uses is that it uses p to stand for
production then name oh so sorry that is the
language of a rule. So, we will come to rule
a bit later. First we want to talk about patterns.
So, there is a class name followed by
attribute names eventually. So, very much
like the class name in a. Remember that
patterns are these things which are will which
constitutes the left hand side of a rule and
each pattern is made up of a class name followed
by a set of attribute name.
So, this is the data structure that we are
using in this language OPS5. So, for example,
if
I am implementing a program to play cards,
I might have a class name called card then
I
might have a name of a card for example, ace
or queen or 10 the suit of a card. So, for
those of you who are familiar with cards spades
and diamonds and clubs and so on. I
might have the name of a player who is holding
that card and
I might have rank of the
.card. So, by rank I mean the current rank.
So, in most games for example, ace is rank
1 and king is rank 2 and so on. But as the
game progresses these ranks might change.
So, I might want to store that essentially.
So,
this is a, this is a class description and
correspondent to this class description I
may have
several patterns.
.
So, the patterns are the left hand side of
the rule and a rule is signified by this opening
bracket followed by p which stands for production,
and then the production name for
example play any card. Let us say I just want
to write a rule which says play any card
that you have essentially. And in this rule
I might have a pattern which says that you
have a card and I might just specify this
essentially. So, let us, I will come to this
later.
So, next let us just talk about the different
kind of patterns that we can have.
..
So, we can have just a name of the class as
a pattern which means that if the inference
engine can see one data element in your data.
So, remember we have this data which has
a class name card then that will match that
would. Our task is to eventually going to
be
the match the pattern and see which patterns
match. Of course, there may be more than
one rule which may be matching, we will come
to that later and then what action can be
done.
So, for matching the rule we have to match
patterns and each pattern should match some
class description. So, if my this class name
is card and its attributes are name, suit,
player
and rank. Then the pattern must be an instance
of that essentially.
..
So, I can have for example, card, name, ace,
suit, spades. So, here I am saying that so
this is the way data is represented. This
is the way the matter rate as given as to
which
describes the data. So, data itself is written
like this.
.
So, I have a element which OPS5 data is in
the working memory
which is called WM.
..
And each of this is called a working memory
element, these is just the terminology that
they use. So, this is a working memory and
inside these of course, there are this working
memory elements where each element is an instance
of some class name which maybe
not completely specified, which maybe incompletely
specified.
.
So, for example, here I have only said that
there is an element which belongs to the class
name card. Here I am saying there is an element
which belongs to the class name card
and the attribute name has value ace and the
attribute suit has value spade essentially.
.Of course, I can specify other things also,
but any partial description can be there in
the
pattern. We are talking about patterns in
rules essentially. I can say things like card,
name. So, this angular brackets are used to
distinguish variables from constants. So,
ace
is a constant, but anything within angular
bracket is a variable and the variable is
which
will match anything essentially. And I can
have other kinds of relation. So, for example,
I can say rank greater than 1 and so on. So,
these are the patterns. So, the left hand
side
of the rule is made up of collection of such
patterns.
.
You can also have a pattern which says, it
is a negative sign here.. So, this pattern
should
be interpreted differently. It should be interpreted
as saying that there is no such pattern
in your, in your working memory or there is
no such data element in the working
memory which says that player x, this is a
variable x has a card of spades.
So, such a pattern would be used to describe
the fact that a given player does not have
any spade cards in his or hand, her hand.
So, this negation sign basically is the opposite
of this. This says that this must be present
in the database or in the working memory.
This says that it must be absent in the database
and only then this rule will match
essentially.
We will look at some examples. Now, actions
so remember we have patterns and we
have actions. So, the 2 most important actions
in ops 5 is one is called make and after
this you describe the working memory element.
So, you can say for example, card,
.spades sorry suit, name, age and so on and
so forth. So, what this action does?
This makes action. It creates a working memory
element and puts it into the working
memory, how it otherwise it creates a data
element and puts it in the database if you
want
to call it a database. Corresponding to this
there is also a remove action. Now, a remove
action takes an argument like 2 and this 2
as you will see in the example the first 2,
the
second pattern in that particular rule. Remember
these actions are on the right hand side
of a rule and this action is saying that remove
the pattern, remove the data element which
match the second pattern. So, this pattern
number 2 matches some data.
So, that will match something, some working
number x let us call it. And this action is
saying that, remove that from the working
memory or remove that from data essentially.
If you can combine this you can have a action
called modify. So, for example, as the
game progresses you want to change the rank
of a card essentially. So, let us say
somebody has played the ace of spades and
now you want to say king of spades has rank
1 then you could say modify that particular
working memory element and change the
rand to value 1 that is all.
So, we have the so basically we have this
2 actions make and remove, but these can lead
to a third action called, any modify action
can be seen as a combination of make and
remove, remove the old one and put in a new
one, it is like modify. Apart from that you
have standard actions that you may need for
example, reading from a file and so on
which we will not go into here because we
want to focus more on how reasoning is done.
..
So, there are actions like read, write, print.
There is even a action called halt which says
that stop the system essentially and exit
essentially. So, we will not look into those
details here. So, let me now give you a examples
of a few rules and then we will see how
the system operates with these rules essentially.
So, I will write these rules for a card
game and I assume that everybody has some
in cling of what card games are like
essentially.
.
So, let us say we have a rule called play
any card and the pattern is let us say there
is a
.class name called turn which I have not described.
I have only described one class name
here which is this. But obviously, you will
have many different class names in your
system.
So, let us say that you are carefully keeping
track of whose turn it is to play next into
one
data element which is belongs to this class
kind type turn and it says turn to play of
some
variable. So, we have not specified who, some
player p essentially. And let us say that
already somebody has started playing a particular
suit. So, in many games in which you
have to play the card of the same suit at
somebody else has done. So, this is saying
that
the suit that is in place s, some variable
name and this is some player p and this player
has a card of suit s.
So, notice that there is no order sanctity
here essentially. I may say that this name,
suit,
player, rank, but that does not matter because
we are segregating the attribute names with
the attribute values. You can specify the
attribute names in any order. You do not have
to
specify them in this particular order. So,
here I said card with suit s, player p. So,
all I am
saying.
So, whatever I say here that if it is a players
turn to play and the player could match
anything. And if the suit in play is s and
if there is a card which is of suit s and
being
held by player p then that player p should
play that card essentially. So, let us say
I use
this make. So, this is one rule and it has
3 patterns on the left hand side which says
that
there are 3 different class names.
Of course, we are interpreting it as a card
game that, if it is p’s turn to play and
if the suit
in plays s, and if p has a card of this suit
s whose name is n then make working memory
element called play player p that card essentially.
And then of course, maybe we will
have another rule which will take it and print
it onto the screen or something like that
let
us not bother about that.
..
So, let me give you another rule just to so
if you want to not play any card, but you
want
to play the highest card essentially then
what should the rule look like. The first
2 will be
the same, turn. So, let me write this here.
So, the first 2 patterns are still the same
as this
rule, but the other patterns will change.
Now, you want to specify that the card that
you play must be the highest card with your
suit and we can do that by saying the following
next card, player p, suite s. So, first of
course, we are looking for a card being held
by this player and in this suit. Let us say
name n and rank r because we are interested
in picking the highest card we should talk
about the rank and we should say that there
is no higher card essentially, which means
we can say that there is no card the same
player p, name we do not care about. So, this
the that negative thing that I was telling
about. So, between these 2 patterns we are
looking at a set of data elements and picking
the one with the highest rank which means
the lowest number. So, rank 1 we want to look
at or rank 2 whichever is the lowest
available.
So, we are saying that card, player p, suite
s, name n, rank r and there is no card with
this
player p of this suit, same suit s whose rank
is smaller than this r. So obviously, this
r and
this r must match the same value then the
same thing. And you can write more rules
depending on you know what kind of game you
are playing and what is the strategy you
want to adopt and that kind of stuff, but
we would not get into those details here
.essentially.
But you should observe that this one. This
combination of this positive pattern and the
negative pattern can be used to pick the highest
rank. So, for example, I could use such a
rule, variation of this rule to start grading
or something and say let me pick the student
with the highest marks and do something and
then you know that kind of stuff. So, this
can be done. So, the illustrate the power
of this let me show you another rule. Supposing
that I have a array of numbers which is signified
by index and value.
.
And if I have a rule of this kind or this
pattern which says that array index i, value
n and
array index j greater than i. So, I can do
like this, I can put this in brackets and
say that
the index value is j and this value j is greater
than this value i that we are talking about
here, which means if I am talking about the
5th element here I could be talking about
the
7th element or something like that. Let us
say value m which is greater than value n.
So,
I am not. So, some rule it is there.
Then I do the following, modify one value
n. So, I have 2 actions and 2 patterns. The
first pattern let me read it out it says that
index value is i and the value is n. The second
pattern says index value is j which is greater
than i and the value is m which is greater
than n then I am saying modify this first
pattern. Now, the data matching that first
pattern
and change its value attribute to m, which
is what I have taken from here and modify
the
second pattern and change its value attribute
to n essentially.
.So, what am I doing here? I am swapping 2
elements if they satisfy this condition right.
Now, this single rule if I let it loose on
the data then it will end up sorting as the
same the
entire array essentially. So, just think of
you have written a algorithm for sorting
elements. You have looked at all kinds of
sorting algorithms and you wrote them.
.
But here is one single rule, this much. And
this will do the job of sorting for you
essentially. It will repeatedly apply the
rule and we will, we will come to this repetition
part in the next class, but it will repeatedly
apply to, if it is, it is if any 2 elements
out of
place it will swap them essentially and it
will keep doing that till this rule matches
and
eventually of course, everything will be in
place or sorted and then this rule will no
longer apply and your array would be sorted
essentially.
So, this also gives you something to think
about you can write a program. In fact, ops
is a complete programming language like any
other programming language like prolog
or c plus, plus or java or python or whatever.
And you can write any program in any
language, but in some languages some programs
are simpler to write. So, this program of
course, is very easy to write, but what can
you say about this performance? It will
depend on so many other things which we will
address in the next class.
So, supposing you have many elements which
are out of place. This inference engine
here has to decide which instance of the rule
to execute next and therein of course, lies
the key to efficiency. If you exchange the
correct elements first then you will do things
.faster and so on and so forth. But of course,
there is no way of knowing that here, but
it
is a very simple program to sort in this essentially.
So, the idea of rule based systems is that
somebody sits and write down, writes down
this
rule in this thing and then we give it to
an inference engine which basically does the
inferencing for us. Which means basically
it picks a rule, applies it then picks the
next
rule then applies it and keeps doing that
till it either runs out of rules to apply
or it runs
into something like a halt statement here
which we have explicitly given.
So, maybe if you have a certain goal in mind
and if that goal is achieve you will say if
this goal I can see the goal being achieved
then halt essentially. You do not have to
keep
running the program essentially. So, in the
next class you will look inside this inference
engine and it is a very well known algorithm
which is very popular and has extensive use
in the industry for developing these systems.
So, basically the idea in the industry is
that we will write business rules, we will
say
when to give a loan, when to do this, when
to do that, but your program must do the
computations for us. They must, your program
must accept the rules and find the
solutions that we expect the program to produce.
So, in the next class we will look at
inside this inference engine and how it works
essentially.
And we are going to focus on the forward chaining
inference engine, a backward
chaining engine is already you are familiar
with something called prolog. And we might
just look at it a little bit later on in the
course, but today we will focus on forward
chaining essentially. So, I will stop here.
.