So, we are looking at this local search and
your seen that which leads us to a problem
of
local maximum because the algorithm does not
have the excess to the entire things space.
It could get started; it could only see some
options and not all options and could get
stuck
there essentially. So, you want to see how
to get around and we saw that that again which
this algorithm is out of navigating is determine
by the Heuristic function that actualities
this determines also by the more than function.
We will see in a short life well given set
of states it is a move them function will
tells you from which state you can go to which
other states essentially and we will see that
we can play along that as well essentially.
..
So, I want now introduce this problem today
which well known problem here familiar
with no doubt call sat this problem everybody
familiar with satisfiability. So, we just
over quick recap that there is a formula and
you we will assume for simplicity that this
formula is in conductive normal form we does
not have to be, but it is contempt. So, it
is
a Boolean formula we can say, so something
like a orb and all not all band, so on a
formula like that were a, b, c, d, e, all
Boolean variables we can take two values either
true or false and the semantics of and on
or is defined and naught is defined . We want
to
find valuations for a, b, c and all the variables
such that the formula evaluate is true
essentially.
So, that is a satisfiability formula, which
says that can you find values for all the
Boolean
variables such that the overall formula evaluates
it true and obviously you can see that
this is a kind of search problem you can say
something like you start. You say a is equal
to true or a is equals to false that is one
way of looking at it that you that you pick
a
variable a, sign a value to it, take another
value variable sign a value to it. You would
generate a search tree in the process or you
can say pick you can have branches for b at
the sense you can formulate it was the search
problem at various stages. Essentially, we
want to do today is a different way of exploring
the space, what the space is, so let us say
we have variables are five variables.
.So, we had some formula which is construct
over this 5 variables what is the space the
space is for each variable a or b or c or
d or e value of true or false. So, 2 raise
to 5
possible states in this case if you have n
variables, then we have two raise to n states
what if n equal to100. So, it is a similar
problem that if you have dealing with a large
number of variables then this problem could
become hard. In fact, you know that sat
problem was a first problem which was a first
problem which was used by cook to talk
about n p complete next essentially where
n is equal to 100 we have 2 raise to 100 which
is about 10 raised to 30 states.
So, we have a 10 raised to 300 bit number
essentially and we you has to see in earlier
that we cannot trifled bit numbers like 10
raise to 30, it is it is a huge number, little
take a
billions of years to search through all these
things. Even if you could inspector billions
states in a second, we have seen that argument
earlier essentially. So, it is a difficult
problem to solve, of course you must familiar
with the fact that there are variations or
special classes of sat problems which for
example, talk about the length. So, this is
calling a clause and each is call a little,
so the number of literals in a clause actually
is
characteristics take of how hard a problem
is.
So, there is a variation called two sat, which
means the there is only two little literals
for
clause we can have many clauses has you want,
but only two literals per clause. You can
have as many variables as you want, but, if
there only two literals per clause then the
problem is actually quite easy to solve and
some of you must be knowing there well
known will go some Davis Putnam method for
solving two sat. Essentially, 3 sat is m p
complete the 3 movement you go from 2 to 3
that you allow 3 variables per clause, then
the problem becomes m p complete essentially.
..
So, we want to explore something which we
will call a solutions space search which is
lot radically different from what we called
as state space search, but except for the
fact
that we will in the search space every note
will be a candidate solution essentially.
So,
for example, further 5 variables my state
could be something like this one 0, 1, 1,
1 and it
is a candidate solution. This means that I
am thinking weather if I put a equal to 1,
meaning true and b is equal to 0 and c, d,
e and equal to one Boolean formula we true
on
notice easily. So, this is a candidate solution
and we will look at a process of perturbation
which means we will take a candidate solution
and perturbation to give us a new
candidate solution.
It is not other side; well not radically different
from what you have doing earlier the
earlier my said could be called as constructive
mechanism where you assemble a solution
piece by piece. So, that small diagram that
I have drawn on there is illustrative of that,
that first you choose a variable a, then you
choose a variable b, then you choose a
variable c and so on and so forth. We are
doing that here, we are saying that we take
all
the variables at one shot takes that as a
candidates and if it not the solution will
do
something with this candidate to generate
more candidates. Essentially, so in that sense
we call is a solution space search.
Again, I would say it is not radically different
it is just a different way of looking at
things essentially even in a for example,
city problem, you could say that if I had
gone
.from IIT Madras to Marina beach the path
from here to Adyar is that… That is a solution
or not you can think of it like that also
as a candidate in some sense essentially,
but here
we are saying that we have all the values
or all the features of variables such we can
about. So, another example is a n queens problem,
you can have a constructive solution
for the problem you can say place the first
queen then place the second queen. Then,
place a third queen that and you can build
a solution step by step all you can say that
I
will have a candidate placement for all the
queens.
So, for example, in en queens in mike set
let say 6 queens I could say this is a candidate
6, 1, 3, 4, 5, 2 and I would interpret this
as saying that the that this is the first
column this
is the second column third column. So, I am
saying the first column queen is a 6 row,
the
second column queen is in the first row the
third column queen is in a third row and so
on and so forth. This is my candidate solution
and I will do something with this may be I
will do formulation of some sort to generate
other candidates solutions. So, that is the
solutions space way of looking at things not
radically different, but it sort of helps
us to
visualize the space a little bit different.
Now, remember that for this problem there
are 2 raise to n possible states essentially
and
what move and function should give us is how
to navigate this spaces. So, one way we
can divides several move then functions essentially
for this one simple, so we will call
them as follows I will call this function
one, which says change one bit. Essentially,
if
you look at this notation where they convey
it is the big thing, you allowed changing
one
bits. So, I have tables like 0, 1, 0, 0, 0,
sorry 0, 0, 1, 1, 1, so have change the first
bit then
1, 1, 1, 1, 1, I change the second bit 1,
0, 0, 1, I came the third bit here, so this
is one
move than function that I have all her neighborhood
function.
So, that is why am use a name n have, it is
a neighborhood function a given a candidate
solution a this be a neighborhood of the solution
which is the same as what we called is a
move then the start essentially. So, back
to our problem of local maximum why did we
get into the silk limbic algorithm because
we wanted to save on space essentially? Now,
a days space is hardly a problem essentially
I am in computer system I remember that in
1990 I have the pc in the department which
had 30 megabits of hard disk and other day
I
was talking to someone and he said this machine
was only 2 GB RAM.
.Essentially, you know look space is now days
is not so much, so, problem you had a
heard this is militates famously supposed
to has said a some point that who will need
more than 64 k of RAM. So, space of course
has change essentially, so we should also
add adopt to the changing world essentially.
So, at a before we come to this till the very
simple variation to claiming this why do want
to restrict yourself to only one success
essentially why not more than one essentially,
I will just will illustrate that with a such
three as follows.
.
It starts with a search the start note, then
a next a there are five successes for a every
note
may be like this. So, you generate five successes
fill claiming says move to the best one
what is what is, so about moving to only 1
and a move to 2 essentially. So, let us take
say
I move to this one or I move I consider both
I do not throw I throw either I keep this
to
best to once generate five children for this
five children’s. For this again thing the
best
two cumulate five children and move on this
algorithm is called main search and this
elastration has beam bits width into 2, so
what have it done. Instead of hills claiming
which explore only one path in the space they
are saying we are allowed to explore more
than one part simultaneously this space.
So, in this example beam beats as to be called
as to, so this beam is like you can think
of
a like a beam of thoughts light know you should
shining into and you can have more than
one. So, at every level we have to notes this,
so we will came going down the search
.space, but you will keep more than one option
available essentially listen algorithm. It
has been use very successfully in speech recognition
and it imagines that is useful in
situations where there are a few options which
are likely to be candidates’ solution
essentially. So, if you can keep more than
one option, so what is the problem in speak
recognition that you start with the speak
signal then converted into phonemes, then
syllabus then words and so on.
Now, it turns out that very often different
word combinations sounds similar essentially,
so very often we think you said this or did
you say this, we know the such a thing is
possible impact, this in the chapter on Maxwell
language processing. They are given an
example of women who goes to New York and
says women come from New York. I do
not remember and we say everything here cause
to nominal egg essentially. So, what was
she saying what did a here what did the listener
here the listener said cost
whatever a
nominal eggs the listener thought that women
is saying that everything is cause a
nominal.
Essentially, the women was actually saying
work cost, but intended to say was
everything a calls on arm in a egg, but you
know people speak with different actions and
that kind of I am sure you can see make both
are them sound the similar. I cannot do that
so easily, but that is what and what the twist
a heard was cost nominal egg we can see
that this kind of problem is actually very
the case in speech recognition the people
speak
with different actions. The listener cannot
always make sense of what at the same time
in
the number of variation options that one has.
I am not too many essentially and then
algorithm. Then, I will go some which can
keep more than one options alive is likely
to
succeed in recognizing the correct sequence
of word.
Essentially, in signal processing circles
called is a Viterbi algorithm basically is
beams
search essentially now what is the complexity
of beam search space complexity level yes
considered that it is a constant because the
beam builds is speaks instead of one known.
You are going to keep beam known at every
stage alive and so times number of
neighbors is a maximum have to deal with essentially
that is a constant space algorithm.
It makes around the hill local maximum problem
where you know one bars may not have
a good successor, but for example, all these
may be bad, but this may have too good
successes. So, may be some were have this
solution will find which would not have
.worked out in this was better than this if
this was better than this only this would
I am in
selective only this launch should have gone.
It should be because we have kept two
options both these branches are there so that
one variation of how to get around this local
maximum.
Next, come back to this solutions space sat
problem essentially, so I want to talk about
another algorithm which is. So, remember that
I said that, so what is this is an about as
a
move than function it connects givens state
in this case a given a candidate solution
to
other candidates solutions, but why should
I choose this neighborhood function. Now,
that is only cap what does the hill claiming
algorithm do, it generates all this five
neighbors and picks the best amongst them
if it is better than it moves, so otherwise
it is
where it is. So, the complexity of the algorithm
will also move them function will depend
on how many in move how many in neighbors,
we have will have to keep this.
Essentially, I can think of another move them
function neighbor function, so just call it
n
two and it says change any two bit. So, n
1 says change one bit see that for this small
problem of five variables sat problem, next
my end to will give me a different neighbor
function. So, for example, one of the neighbors
would be 1, 1 or let me just see in the
first 2 bits 0, 1, 1, 1, 1 another neighbor
could be I change first and third bit 0, 0,
0, 1, 1.
It gives me a different set of neighbors not
only he keeps a different set of neighbors
it
gives me more neighbors. So, this n 1 gives
me 5 neighbors or n neighbors if n variables
are n there this n two gives me n c 2 neighbors
in this example that is ten neighbors. So,
it is a different neighborhood function, I
can choose between different functions how
can
I explore this information can I device an
algorithm which it will try to make use of
different neighborhood function.
..
So, I can have n one n two then I can have
n three and up to n if I have n variables
and
this case up to n five I can again say change
all five essentially of course, that will
give
me only one neighbor. It move at me far from
their all I can have combination I can
device n 1 2 which says change 1 or 2 bits
or change up to 2 bits essentially, I can
say
change up to 3 bits essentially or n 1, 2,
3, I can go up to none n which in our example
would be n 1, 2, 3, 4, 5.
So, the first thing I want you to observe
is that they are if you go down this path
they are
more dense the neighborhood is more bun dense
as you go down this set of
neighborhood function. So, I cannot write
this here, so I can choose a sequence of
neighborhood functions, which are in cleansing
lead dense, which means they give me
denser and denser neighborhood. Thus most
simplex other most parts is n one which
allow we taken get by changing one bit and
then I can get n 2, we say 10, there I can
get
n 1 2 which as 10 plus this 5 which is 15
and so on.
..
I can create a sequence of neighborhood function
n one n two which is increasing density
how should I choose bits neighborhood function
to use remember neighborhood function
same as move then essentially. So, we have
now the option of choosing move gen
function on and we on the keeping mind that
we role on the gets struck in the local
maxima, so what will be the heuristic function
here? If have a clause like this for a
formula like this h of n for a given candidate
solution these are all candidate solution
say
how do you give them a value any suggestion
number of clauses number of clauses it
makes a true that is a simplest you have doing
it.
So, will keep that in mind or we can modify
this to say weighted number, so if a clause
has more literals then give it more weight.
So, another possibility and basically it gives
you an idea how much of the solution is solved
in some sense if I have twenty clauses an
I one candidates satisfies 7 and another one
satisfies is 12. Then, may be the 12 is better
than 7, just again a take remember just takes
a not perfect this is only. We will basically
assume that the most clauses the better the
heuristic function, so we want to know device
a algorithm it will search in this solution
space and try to device in algorithm, which
will
not get struck in a local maximum.
So, what which what is a criteria one should
use for choosing a neighborhood function.
So, two things one is that we want to also
keep a list on time complexity is time
complexity going to all these going to affect
may time complexity all in what manner
.these functions will affect my time complexity.
So, that is why I am saying remember the
hill claiming algorithm what will be do it
generates all the neighbors and then picks
the
best amongst them and moves to them moves
that neighbor then generates all the
neighbors. Then, thus that what about this
function this one what is the neighborhood
function take this all example five variables
a, b, c, d, e and this one is saying.
You can change any number of bits you want
change 1 or 2 or 3 a when I say one or 2 I
mean any one any 2, any 3, any 4, any 5, what
is the neighborhood function entire space
is the neighborhood function. Every note is
connective directly to every other notes it
can
you can move from any state to another any
other state in one step. How many maxima
will this have? One only one which is the
global maxima which is the solution, they
may
be more than one maxima. So, that one is the
point, but what is going to be the
complexity of the move gen function remembers
that we said generates all the neighbors
this is choosing this the move gen function
and using hill climbing.
What are you doing? You are just doing a force
saying generates all possible states and
then pick the one best pronounce them, obviously
how many states are there we have
major observation that there are two states
to n states essentially. If the neighborhood
has
to a to n states then you have actually the
problem and may be not a group force search
which is no point solving because you know
to which instates part to many inspect any
way. So, this hill claiming algorithm if you
want to use this use they function the of
5,
but may be for 30 or 40 or 100 variables would
not even start of it would spend this
whole life then waiting the neighborhood function
done that.
So, what is the next base thing we can do,
so we cannot choose the dense function that
what I am trying to say why all we in president
dense function because dense functions
will not have this difficulty of getting struck
in local maximum? What is the advantage
of choosing a farce neighborhood function
faster the neighborhood generate it faster
essentially and choose us remember that hill
claiming algorithm. Basically, it says
generate the neighbors pick the best amongst
them if is better move to that then generate
the neighbors and so on.
So, what do we do can we device the nice algorithm
which will give us which allow us to
see thus parcel the algorithm the neighborhood
function the lesser the state you can. It
is
true that is obliviously the milling of the
parts the mold likely it is that you not connected
.to the better state that denser the algorithm.
The mold likely it is that for any given say
there is always a better state which the extreme
example is this algorithm because any
state which is not a optimal solution a global
maxima has is connected to the global
maxima.
Every state has a better state and a only
state is do not have better state of the global
maxima states. So, if you can try imagine
this that choosing move gen function is also
devising the landscape. It is a difficult
for me to visualize it here, but it is what
a move
gen function telling you will that one function
is saying from here you can go to this to
this to this to this or to this one. Another
one is saying that from here you can go to
some
other set or together essentially and what
is the lotion of a local maxima lotion of
a local
maxima is that this state is better than always
neighbors that is a lotion of a local maxima
if all the neighbors are the entire set like
in the example then it is a global maxima.
So, in another way of looking at it is that
denser function in many if you to the denser
neighborhood function then probability of
the likely hood of a state being as local
maxima becomes lesser because it has to be
a better than more neighbors. Essentially,
it
just a very naïve way of looking at it, but
you can get some intention or that essentially.
So, we would like to use a denser function
because it is not likely to have states which
are local maxima which mean the surface, it
generates would be smoother and a cooler
surface is more amenable to hill claiming.
Essentially, if a surface has no local maxima,
then you will restore global maxima, so
that will a simple approach to and is given
in this book which has mention it also given
in my book, but, I first edit here which is
how to solved by modern in. It will really
go
and look at this book because begging in a
every chapter a given nice interesting puzzle
that you can solve. Essentially, may be one
of these days I will give you one of the
puzzles the algorithm is simple that you have
access to a set up neighborhood functions
and you do the following.
..
So, I will just write it very briefly call
hill claiming, so the meaning of this is,
so I call on
sorry we just say hill claiming. So, H c stands
for hill claiming hills hill claiming with
a
neighborhood function and you put i is equal
to 1 and in a put i is equal to i plus 1 and
put it into a move, what is the meaning of
this algorithm? So, we should work out the
details I am not going to write the details
the meaning of this algorithm is and depending
on what the resource is is allow you will
go into this loaf. Once you run out of resource
is you say stop something here, but inside
this is a another loaf which is the hill claiming
loaf and that is saying use the I as neighborhood
function.
I am assuming that their order crossing to
increasing density use the i h neighborhood
function and when you terminate when you come
out of hill claiming remember there we
no longer have the notional gold test. So,
in fact it is of course you can put in a gold
test
check, so for example, in a sat problem you
can say yes if all my clauses are satisfied
then stop you can put then that extra check,
but we are looking at optimization more
generally know. So, we want to find the maximum
value of this heuristic function, so
what we are saying is it start with the most
sparse hill claiming most sparse
neighborhood function claim us as claim up
as much as you can, using a hill claiming
analogy.
Then, switch to a different neighborhood function
the next one an en claim up again and
then keep doing that using neighborhood function.
So, if you can visualize this somehow
.you can say think of the neighborhood function
as you know giving you connection with
ladles from one state to another state so
on. So, each of them is a ladder and if the
ladder
is going up you claim up if you does not going
up you stop essentially and many stop
suddenly get a different set of ladders. Let
us say this launch and see if you have better
state then you keep claiming the different
set of ladders and so on.
So, what is the advantage the intention behind
this is that you do most of the claiming in
the early stages that you early sparse a function
will take you up quite a bit. Then, when
you gets struck on some local maxima suddenly
you have different ladder take you two
another this is the algorithm its call variable
neighborhood descent well they are talking
about minimizing. So, it is imagined you are
going down a value into the claiming hill
or
v d n were this is saying is that use sequence
of denser neighborhood functions. Each
stage you do hill claiming and you can have
variation on this you can work out
variations.
For example, one could say that after having
using n to should that n 1 again allowed
because now I am in a different states may
be a n one will help from there is a. So,
this a
way essence that you try think of essentially
for the basic idea is simple that if you us
talk on a local maxima use a denser function
and try that. Essentially, this means that
depending on how were the resources you have
you will explore it as many of this
neighborhood function as possible essentially.
So, I was on the end with one example that
we of discuss earlier, which is the example
and what with a I want into a visualize what
will the terrain look like men. Let us see
call
when expert and by expert we mean not necessarily
who will find optimal solution, but
who will solve it quickly according to alone
solution, how will the terrain how will that
journey look like.
..
So, the idea that I am trying to talk about
is this that this is the solution, so this
means
you know what the solution that move 1 is,
move 2, move 3, move 4 and so on.
Somebody else gave you a solution how will
the terrain look like given some heuristic
function like the number of tiles in place
or something like that initially the number
of
tiles out of place. Let us see initially little
be some value which that a out of place finally,
of course it choose be 0, but how was the
journey and remember that we said we makes
does observation. When, you have partially
solve the rubrics you many mode to move
further from their you have to disrupts some
of the earlier partial solution that is reflect
by saying that the journey is like this.
You do like this and you have solve the top
row, but now you have on do the middle row
you have to disrupt this, but you do something
better then like this then there a some
variation then a. So, it will be something
like this, so whatever trying to illustrate
here is
that if a expert the solving is the rubrics
cube, then at each state on the way if you
want
to flirt the heuristic value it would something
like this. Of course, it means that may be
this is an excavation maybe it is like this
function like that that real one problems
a
search there it is not. So, easy to devise
heuristic function which will generates most
of
surface essentially, so Rubik’s cube is
just an example of that which mean that I
cannot
solve.
.I cannot even hope to solve rubric cubic
hopes an using a hill climbing like algorithm
because I will find it extremely difficult
to device a heuristic function whose surface
would be monotonically decreasing towards
the goal state essentially. In practice since
I
have to disrupt the cube on the way I will
be first two go against the heuristic function
essentially. So, going with a heuristic function
we will call exploitation of the heuristic
knowledge and as oppose to a exploitation
is following. Somebody told you do this
sense, so you do that essentially as oppose
to exploitation is the notion of exploration
to
explore new idea new areas of the space essentially.
So, for our only attempted exploration has
been this beam search in which we have said
you will keeps many candidates alive, but
in the next class then we meet we will see
how
to try to increase component of exploration
in search. The reason behind that is at exploit
pure exploitation which means purely following
the heuristic function is going to end of
in local maxima even in the surface has local
maxima what kind of algorithm. Can we
think of that will go beyond the local maxima
and to the global maxima. So, I will stop
here and will take that of next week essentially.
.