Let's look at a 2nd example where big data
can have a big impact on saving lives.
I mean,
literally saving lives one life at a time.
I collaborated with a number of
world-class researchers in San Diego, and
an industrial group who are dedicated to
improving human health through research
and practice of precision medicine.
What is precision medicine?
It is an emerging area of medicine
targeted toward an individual person.
Analysing her genetics, her environment,
her daily activities so
that one can detect or
predict a health problem early,
help prevent disease and
in case of illness provide the right drug
at the right dose that is
suitable just for her.
Very recently the White House and
the National Institute of Health here
in the U.S. have declared it to be
a top priority area for research and
development for the next decade.
The expected learning
outcome of this video is for
you to give example of sensor,
organizational and
people-generated data used
in precision medicine.
And, explain why the integration of
different kinds of data is critical
in advancing healthcare.
For any technology to
succeed in real life we need
not only a certain level of maturity of
the technology itself, but a number of
enabling factors including social
economic environment, market demands,
consumer readiness, cost effectiveness,
all of which must work together.
Why is big data for
precision medicine important now?
Let's see.
An important aspect of precision
medicine is to utilize
an individual's genetic profile for
his or her own diagnoses and treatment.
Analyzing the human genome,
which holds the key to human health
is rapidly becoming more affordable.
Today's cost to sequence a genome is less
than 10% of what it
cost just back in 2008.
But, human genomic data is big.
How big?
In a perfect world, just the three
billion letters of your genome
would require about 700
megabytes to store.
In the real world, meaning the kind of
data generated from genome sequencing
machines, we need 200GB to store a genome.
And it takes now about
a day to sequence a genome.
We are finally beginning to create more
electronic records that can be stored and
manipulated in digital media.
Most doctors offices and hospitals now
use electronic health record systems
which contain all details of
a patient's visit and lab test.
How big is this data?
As a quick example The Samaritan Medical
Center Watertown New York at 294 that
Community Hospital reported
120 terabytes as of 2013.
The data value more than double
in just the last two years.
So clearly just in a past two years
dramatic changes have prepared the health
care industry to produce and analyze
larger mounts of complex patient data.
To summarize what we have seen so far
the key components of these changes are:
Reduced cost of data generation and
analysis, increased availability of cheap
large data storage, and they increased
digitization of previously paper records.
But we need one more capability to advance
toward the promised land of individualized
health care practices.
We need to combine various types of
data produce by different groups in
a meaningful way.
Let's look at this issue from
the same point of view as Ilka did.
With her discussion of how big data
can help with wildfire analytics.
The key is the integration of
multiple types of data sources.
Data from sensors,
organizations and people.
In the next few slides,
we look at each of these, and
then I'll share a story about some of the
new and really exciting ways people data
especially has the potential to
change healthcare big data landscape.
Let's start with sensor data.
Sure, digital hospital equipment
have been producing sensor data for
years, but it was unlikely that
the data was ever stored or
shared, let alone
analyzed retrospectively.
These were intended for
real-time use, to inform healthcare
professionals, and then got discarded.
Now we have many more sensors and
deployment.
And many more places
that are capturing and
explicitly gathering information
to be stored and analyzed.
Let's just take a new kind of data
that's increasingly becoming
common in our daily lives.
Fitness devices are everywhere now
their sales have skyrocketed
in the last few years.
They are in wristbands, watches, shoes and
vests, directly communicating with your
personal mobile device, tracking several
activity variables like blood pressure,
different types of activities,
blood glucose levels, etc at every moment.
Their goal is to improve wellness.
By having you monitor
your daily status and
hopefully improve your
lifestyle to stay healthy.
But the data they generate can be
very useful medical information
because this data is about what
happens in your normal life and
not just when you go to the doctor.
How much data do they generate?
The device called FitBit can
produce several gigabytes a day.
Could this data be used to save healthcare
costs, effect a healthier lifestyle?
That's a question mark.
It's safe to guess that this data
alone wouldn't drive the dream of
precision medicine.
But what if we consider integrating
it with other sources of data
like electronic health records or
a genomic profile?
This remains an open question.
This is an open arena for research that
my colleagues at scripts are doing.
It's also a potentially significant area
for product and business development.
Let's look at some examples of health
related data being generated by
organizations.
Many public databases
including those curated and
managed by NCBI, the National Center for
Biotechnology Information,
had been created to capture the basic
scientific data and knowledge for
humans and other model organisms at
the different building blocks of life.
These databases carry both experimental
and computed data that are necessary to
observations for
unconquered diseases like cancer.
In addition,
many have created knoweledge-bases
like the Geneontology and
The Unified Medical Language System
to assemble human knowledge in
a machine processable form.
These are just a few examples of
organizational data sources and
governmental data gathered by health
care systems around the world
could also be used as a massive
source of information.
But really some of
the most interesting and
novel opportunities seem likely to come
from the area of people generated data.
Mobile healths apps is an area
that is growing significantly.
There are apps now to monitor heart rates,
blood pressure, and
test oxygen saturation levels.
Apps, we might say,
record data from sensors but
are also obviously generated from people.
But there is more people generated
data that's interesting beyond censure
measurements.
In 2015 the Webby People's Voice Award
went to an app which supports
meditation and mindfulness.
Rather than an electronic sensing device,
a human would indicate how many
minutes per day they spent meditating.
If they interact with the app
which reminds them to be mindful,
then we have human generated behavior
that we couldn't get from a sensor.
There are well over 100,000 health apps
today in either iTunes or Google Play.
And by some estimates
the Mobile Health App market
may be worth 27 billion dollars by 2017.
So really we are just seen the beginning
of what data might be generated here
from what's being called human sensors,
but to really understand where the power
of people generated data might take us
in the era of big data for healthcare.
Let's imagine how things stand now.
In general,
a patient goes to see their doctor and
maybe their doctor asks if they have had
any side effects from their medications.
The accuracy and
hence the quality of data patients provide
in this kind of setting is very low.
Not that it's really the patients fault.
It might have been days or
weeks ago that they experienced something.
They may be unsure whether something
they experienced was actually a reaction
to then report it.
And there might be details about exactly
when they took a medication that
are meaningful, but
they've forgotten it after the fact.
Today, people are self reporting reactions
and experiences they are having.
We're on Twitter, on blog sites,
online support groups,
online data sharing services: these
are sources of data that we've
never had before that can be used to
understand in a far more detailed and
personal rate the impact of drug
integrations are responses to certain
If applications were designed
to integrate doctor and
hospital records with information
on when drugs were taken and
then to further mine social media or
collect self reports from patients.
Who knows what kinds of questions
we will be able to answer?
Or new questions we may be able to ask?
Where does big data come from?
The first thing I would like to
say before talking about big data
is that it is not new.
Most of the big data sources existed
before, but the scale we use and
apply them today has changed.
Just look at this image of open
link data on the Internet.
I thought this image was so cool.
It shows not only there are so
many sources of data, but
they're also connected.
If you want to check it out yourself,
we'll give you the link
at the end of this video.
Big data is often boiled down to a few
varieties of data generated by machines,
people, and organizations.
With machine generated data we refer to
data generated from real time sensors in
industrial machinery or vehicles that
logs that track user behavior online,
environmental sensors or
personal health trackers, and
many other sense data resources.
The Large Hadron Collider
generates 40 terabytes of data
every second during experiments.
But human generated data, we refer to
the vast amount of social media data,
status updates, tweets,
photos, and medias.
With organizational generated data we
refer to more traditional types of data,
including transaction
information in databases and
structured data open
stored in data warehouses.
Note that big data can be either
structured, semi-structured, or
unstructured, which is a topic we will
talk about more later in this course.
In most business use cases, any single
source of data on its own is not useful.
Real value often comes from combining
these streams of big data sources
with each other and
analyzing them to generate new insights,
which then goes back into
being big data themselves.
Once you have such insights,
it then enables what we call data
enabled decisions and actions.
Let's now look into these different
types of big data in more detail.
Why is Big Data generated
by machines useful?
Let's go back for
a second to our first example for
machine generated big data planes.
What is producing all
that data on the plane?
If you look at some of
the sensors that contribute
to the half terabyte of
data generated on a plane,
we will find that some of it comes from
accelerometers that measure turbulence.
There are also sensors built into
the engines for temperature, pressure,
many other measurable factors
to detect engine malfunctions.
Constant real-time analysis of all
the data collected provides help
monitoring and
problem detection at 40,000 feet.
That's approximately 12,000
meters above ground.
We call this type of
analytical processing in-situ.
Previously, in traditional relational
database management systems,
data was often moved to
computational space for processing.
In Big Data space In-Situ
means bringing the computation
to where data is located or,
in this case, generated.
A key feature of these types
of real-time notifications is
that they enable real-time actions.
However, using such a capability
would require you to approach your
application and your work differently.
If you are using an activity tracker, you
should probably come up with a strategy
for how you will incorporate the usage of
these useful gadgets into your lifestyle.
Just like that, if you're planning to
incorporate Big Data driven insights into
your organization, you need to define
a new strategy, and a new way of working.
Most Big Data centric businesses have
updated their culture to be more real-time
action oriented, refining real-time
processes to handle anything from customer
relations and fraud detection,
to system monitoring and control.
In addition, such volumes of real-time
data and analytical operations that need
to take place requires an increased
use of scalable computing systems,
which need to be a part of the planning
for an organizational Big Data strategy.
They see affects of such
changes also in SCADA system.
SCADA stands for Supervisory Control and
Data Acquisition.
SCADA is a type of industrial control
system for remote monitoring and
control of industrial processes
that exists in the physical world,
potentially including multiple sites,
many types of sensors.
In addition to monitoring and control,
SCADA system can be used to define
actions for reduced waste and improved
efficiency in industrial processes,
including those of manufacturing and
power generation, public or
private infrastructure processes,
including water treatment, oil, and
gas pipelines, and
electrical power transmission, and
facility processes including buildings,
airports, ships, and space stations.
They can even be used in smart
building applications to monitor and
control heating, ventilation,
air conditioning systems like HVAC,
access, and energy consumption.
Again, the management of these processes
once the trends, patterns, and
anomalies are identified in real-time
needs to be decided in the Big Data case.
As a summary, as the largest and fastest
type of Big Data, machine generated
data can uniquely enable real-time
actions in many systems and processes.
However, a culture shift is needed for
its computing and real-time action.
Big data generated by machines.
It's everywhere and there's a lot.
Do big planes require big data?
Absolutely!
Did you know that a Boeing 787 produces
half a terabyte of data
every time it flies?
Really, almost every part of
the plane updates both the flight and
the ground team about
its status constantly.
Where's all this data coming from?
This is an example of machine-generated
data coming from sensors.
If you look at all sources of big data,
machine data is the largest
source of big data.
Additionally, it is very complex.
In general, we call machines that provide
some type of sensing capability smart.
Have you ever wondered why you
call your cell phone a smartphone?
Because it gives you a way
to track many things,
including your geolocation, and
connect you to other things.
So what makes a smart device smart, smart?
Generally speaking, There are three
main properties of smart devices
based on what they do with sensors and
things they encapsulate.
They can connect to other devices or
networks, they can execute services and
collect data autonomously,
that means on their own, they have
some knowledge of the environment.
The widespread availability of the smart
devices and their interconnectivity
led to a new term being coined,
The Internet of Things.
Think of a world of smart devices at home,
in your car, in the office,
city, remote rural areas,
the sky, even the ocean,
all connected and all generating data.
Let's look at an example of a device
that has some of these things in it.
An activity tracker is a device or
application for monitoring and
tracking fitness-related metrics
such as distance walked or run,
calorie consumption, and in some cases,
heartbeat and quality of sleep.
What if everyone in New York City
wore an activity tracker?
What if everyone wore several?
I personally have three activity
trackers that I use on a daily basis.
One to track my sleep, another one
to track my physical activity, and
a third, my smartphone,
that goes everywhere with me.
So it is not that unusual to imagine that
this will be the case for many people.
As you have already heard from in
a previous lecture on personalized data,
such activity trackers
have enabled a new way
of doing patient intervention
via personalized medicine.
Similarly, the sensors in planes have
generated a new way of looking at
fleet management and flight safety.
As a summary,
machines collect data 24/7 via
their built-in sensors,
both at personal and industrial scales.
And thus, they are the largest
of all the big data sources.
Organization-Generated Data.
Benefits come from combining
with other data types.
How are some organizations
benefiting from big data?
Let's look at real world examples to
see the advantages these organizations
are getting out of big data.
One of these companies is UPS.
UPS delivers 16 million shipments per day.
They get around 40 million
tracking requests.
That's huge.
An estimate of how much data UPS has
on its operations is 16 petabytes.
Can you guess how much money UPS can
save by reducing each driver's route
by just one mile?
If they can reduce distance traveled
by each truck by even one mile,
UPS can save a whopping $50 million U.S.
per year.
This is where big data steps in.
Utilizing complex optimization
over large datasets
can lead to route optimizations that were
previously not visible to the company.
Big data, together with smart processing,
enables UPS to manage thousands
of route optimizations.
Let's travel from package
delivery to the retail domain.
An organization from
the retail shopping domain
that heavily utilizes big data is Walmart.
Walmart is a big organization that gets
250 million customers in 10,000 stores.
Did you know they collect 2.5
petabytes of data per hour?
They collect data on Twitter tweets,
local events, local weather,
in-store purchases, online clicks and
many other sales, customer and
product related data.
They use this data to find patterns
such as which products are frequently
purchased together, and what is the best
new product to introduce in their stores,
to predict demand at
the particular location,
and to customize customer recommendations.
Overall, by leveraging big data and
analytics, Walmart has maintained
its position as a top retailer.
UPS and Walmart examples were just two out
of a number of companies using big data.
Big data is producing results for
companies in all sectors.
Studies forecast spending on
big data technologies to go up
drastically in the next five years.
A study by Bane and Company
suggests that early adopters of big
data analytics have gained a significant
lead over the rest of the corporate world.
For graphics referenced here,
we see that companies that use
analytics are twice as likely
to be in the top quartile of financial
performance within their industries.
Five times as likely to make decisions
much faster than market peers.
Three times as likely to
execute decisions as intended.
And twice as likely to use data very
frequently when making decisions.
This points to the growth and
demand of people and
technology centered around or
specializing in big data applications.
As a summary, organizations are gaining
significant benefit from integrating
big data practices into their culture and
breaking their silos.
Some major benefits to organizations are
operational efficiency, improved marketing
outcomes, higher profits, and
improved customer satisfaction.