The first up in our rapid tour
of modern systems is Redis.
Redis calls itself an in-memory
data structure store.
In simple terms, Redis is not a full blown
DBMS, in the sense we discussed earlier.
It can persist data on disks, and
does so to save its state, but
it's intended use is to optimally
use memory and memory based methods
to make a number of common data
structures very fast for lots of users.
Here is a list of data
structures that Redis supports.
A good way to think about them is
to think of a data lookup problem.
Now, in the simplest case,
a lookup needs a key value pair
where the key is a string and
the value is also a string.
So for a lookup we provide the key and
get back the value.
Simple, right?
Let's see.
I'm sure you've seen captures like this.
These are small images used by websites
to ensure that the user is a human and
not a robot.
The images presented to the user,
who is supposed to write the text he or
she sees in the image, into a text box.
Upon success, the user is let in.
To implement this,
one obviously needs a key value stored,
where the key is the idea of the image.
And the value is the desired text.
Now what if we wanted to use
the image itself as the key,
instead of an ID number that
you generate separately?
The content of the image,
which let's say is a .jpg file,
can be thought of as a binary string.
But can it serve as a key then?
According to the Redis specification,
it can.
The Redis string can be binary and
can have a size of up to 512 megabytes,
although its internal limit is higher.
So, small images like this can indeed
be used as binary string keys.
In some application scenarios,
keys may have an internal structure.
For example,
product codes may have product family,
manufacturing batch, and the actual
product ID strung together into one ID.
The example shown here is a typical
Twitter style key to store the response
to comment one, two, three, four.
How long do we want to
keep the comment around,
this is a standard big data issue
when it comes to streaming data
whose data values have limited
utility beyond the certain period.
One typically would not look for
this response possibly three
months after the conversation.
One would certainly not like to keep
such a value in memory for a long time.
Because the memory is being used as
a cache for rapid access to current data.
In fact Redis has the ability
to delete an expired key and
can be made to call a function
to generate a new key.
An interesting side
benefits to structured keys
that it can encode
a hierarchy to the structure.
In the example,
we show keys that represent
increasingly finer subgroups of users.
With this structure,
a lookup on user.commercial.entertainment
will also retrieve values
from user.commercial.entertainment.movie
industry.
A slightly more complex case occurs
when the value is not atomic,
but a collection object like a list
which by definition is an ordered set.
An example of such a list
can come from Twitter,
that uses Redis list to store timelines.
Now borrowed from a Twitter presentation
about their timeline architecture
our timeline service can
take a specific ID, and
it quickly identifies all tweets of
this user that are in the cache.
These tweets are then populated
by the content of the tweet,
then returned as a result.
This list can be long, but the insertion
and delete operations on the list
can be performed in constant
time which is in milliseconds.
If a tweet is retweeted,
the IDs of those tweets are also added
to the list of the first tweet, as you can
see for the three cases in the figure.
When the lists are long,
space saving becomes an important issue.
So Redis employs a method called
Ziplists which essentially
compacts the size of the list in
memory without changing the content.
Often producing significant
reduction in memory used.
Of course,
while Ziplists are very efficient for
retrieval, they are a little more complex
for insertion and deletion operations.
Since Redis is an open source system,
Twitter made a few innovations
on the Redis data structures.
One of these innovations is that
they created lists of Ziplists.
This gave them the flexibility of
having constant timing insertions and
deletions and at the same time used the
compressed representation to save space.
In 2012, the timeline service has about
40 terabytes of main memory, serving
30 million user queries per second.
Running on over 6,000
machines in one data center.
For those interested I would like to point
you to two wonderful Twitter presentation
explaining Twitter's use of Redis
among other design issue for
a realtime data system like Twitter.
We also introduce links in
the supplemental readings for this lesson.
Now the value to be looked up by the keys
can actually be more complicated and
can be records containing
attribute value pairs themselves.
Redis values can be hashes
which are essentially named containers
of unique fields and their values.
In the example, the key, std:101,
is associated with five
attributed value pairs.
The hashed attributes
are stored very efficiently.
And even when the list of attributed
value pairs in a hash is really long,
retrieval is efficient.
Horizontal scalability or
scale out capabilities refers
to the ability of a system
to achieve scalability when the number
of machines it operates on is increased.
Redis allows data partitioning through
range partitioning and hash partitioning.
Rate partitioning takes a numeric key and
breaks up the range of keys into bins.
In this case, by bins of 10,000
each of bin is assigned a machine.
And ultimately, a partitioning is where
computing a hashing function on a key.
Suppose we have 10 machines.
We pick the key and use the hash
function to get back a number.
We represent the number, modular 10,
and the result, in this case,
2, is the machine to which
the record will be allocated.
Replication is accomplished in
Redis through master-slave mode.
The slaves have a copy of the master node.
And can serve read queries.
Clients write to the master node.
And master node replicates to the slaves.
Clients read from the slaves to
scale up the read performance.
The replication processes are synchronous.
That is that slaves do not get replicated
data, it locks them with each other.
However, the replication
process does ensure
that they're consistent with each other.
The next system we'll explore is Vertica.
Which is the relational DBMS
designed to operate on top of HTFS.
It belongs to a family of DBMS
architectures called column stores.
Other products in
the same family are UCDV,
Carrot Cell Xvelocity from Microsoft and
so forth.
The primary difference
between a row store and
a column store is shown
in the diagram here.
Logically, this table has five columns.
Emp number, department number,
hire date, employee last name and
employee first name.
In a row oriented design the database
internally organizes the record
two four by two.
In a column store,
the data is organized column wise.
So the nth number column is stored
separately from the department id
column and so forth.
Now suppose a query
needs to find the ID and
department ID of all employees who were
hired after first of January, 2001.
The system only needs to look up
the hire date column to figure
out which records qualify.
And then pick up the values of the ID,
and the department of ID columns for
the qualifying records.
The other columns are not touched.
So if a table has 30 to 50 columns, very
often only a few of them are needed for
any single query.
So for tables with 500 million rows and
40 columns a typical query is very fast,
and uses much less memory because a full
record is not used most of the time.
My own experience is that with
an application that needed a database
with 150 billion tuples in a table.
Accounting operation took a little
under three minutes to complete.
A second advantage of the column store
comes from the nature of the data.
In a column store,
data in every column is sorted.
The figure on the right shows
three sorted columns of a table
with three visible columns.
The bottom of the first column shown here
has many accurate sixteen
transactions on the same day.
The second column has customer ids which
can be numerically close to each other.
They are all within seventy
values of the first customer.
So in the first case we can just
say that the value is one, one,
2007, and
the next 16 records have this value.
That means we do not have to store
the next 16 values thus saving space.
Now this form of shortened
representation is called compression.
And this specific variety is
called run-length encoding or RLE.
Another form of encoding can
be seen in the second column.
Here the customer ids a long integer,
but for
the records shown there
are nearby numbers.
So, if we pick a value in the column and
just put the difference between
this value and
other values The difference will be small.
It means,
we'll need fewer bites to represent them.
This one of compression is called
Frame-of-reference encoding.
The lesson to remember here is
that compressed data presentation
can significantly reduce the total
size of a database and if BDMS.
Should use all such tricks
to improve space efficiency.
While the space efficiency and
performance of Vertica is impressive for
large data, one has to be careful
about how to design a system with it.
Like Google's Web Table, and
Apache Cassandra, Vertica allows
the declaration of column-groups.
These are columns like first name and
last name which are very
often accessed together.
In Vertica,
a column group is like a mini table
which is treated like a little
row storied in the system.
But because these groups represent
activists that are frequently co accessed
the grouping actually
improves performance.
So an application developer is
better off when the nature and
the frequency of user queries
are known to some degree.
And this knowledge is applies
to designing the column groups.
An important side effect of column
structure organization of vertical
Is that the writing of data into
Vertica is a little slower.
When rows are added to a table,
Vertica initially places
them in a row-wise data structure and
then converts them into a column-wise
data structure, which is then compressed.
This lowness can be perceptible for
large uploads or updates.
Vertica belongs to a new breed of
database systems that call themselves
analytical databases.
This means two slightly different things.
First, Vertica offers many more
statistical functions than in
classical DBMS.
For example one can perform
operations over a Window
to see an example consider a table of
stock ticks having a time attribute,
a stock name and
a value of the stock called bid here.
This shows that data values in
the table now we would like to compute
a moving average of
the bit every 40 seconds.
We show the query in a frame below.
Now we aren't going into the details of
the query just consider the blue part.
It says the average,
which is the AVG function in yellow.
It must be computed on
the last column which is bit.
But, this computation
must be over the range that is
computed on the timestamp call.
So, the range is defined by a 40
second row before that current row so,
here the computation of the average
advances for the stock abc.
And for each computation,
the system only considers the rows whose
timestamp is within 40 seconds
before the current row.
The table on the right shows
the result of the query.
The average value, 10.12.
Is the same as the actual value, because
there are no other rows within 40 seconds.
The next two result rows average
over the preceding rows,
was times R within 40
seconds of the current row.
When we get to the blue row,
that we notice that it occurs 1 minute
16 seconds after the previous row.
So we cannot consider the previous
sort in the computation.
Instead, the result is just the value
of the bid in the current row.
The takeaway from this example is
that analytical computations like
this are happening inside the database and
not in an external application.
This brings us to the second feature
of Vertica as an analytical database.
R is a well known free statistics
package that's used by statisticians,
data minors, predictive analytics experts.
Today, R can not only
read data from files,
but it can go to an SQL database and
grab data to perform statistical analysis.
Over time, R has evolved and
given rights to distributed R which
is a high performance platform for R.
As expected in this distributed setting,
the system operates in
a master slave mode.
The master node coordinates computations
by sending commands to the workers.
The worker nodes maintain
data partitions and
apply the computation
functions to the data.
Just getting the data parallelly,
the essential data structure
is a distributed array.
That is an array that is
partitioned as shown here.
Now in this diagram
the partitions are equal, but
in practice they may be
all different sizes.
On which, one can compute a function for
each of these mini-arrays.
The bottom diagram, shows a simple
work flow of constructing and
deploying a predictive model.
The role of Vertica here,
is that it's a data supplier to the worker
nodes of R, and a model consumer.
The data to be analyzed is
the output of the vertica query,
which is transferred in memory through
a protocol called vertica fast transfer
through distributed R as a dArray.
When the model is created in R,
it should come back as a code that
goes through vertica as a function.
This function can be
called from inside Vertica
as if it was a user defined function.
Now in sophisticated applications,
the features of the data needed for
predicted modeling will also be
computed inside the DBMS possibly
using the new analytical operations
of Vertica that we've just shown.
Now this will make future
computation much faster and
improve the efficiency of
the entire analytics process.
Going forward, we believe that most DBMS's
will want to play in the analytics field,
will support similar functions.
Most of you have heard of
MongoDB as a dominant store for
JSON style semi-structured data.
MongoDB is very popular and
there are a number of excellent
tutorials on it on the web.
In this module we would like to discuss
a relatively new big data management
system for semistructured data that's
currently being incubated by Apache.
It's called AsterixDB.
Originally, AsterixDB was conceived by
the University of California Irvine.
Since it is a full fledged DBMS,
it provides ACID guarantees to
understand the basic design of AsterixDB,
let's consider this incomplete JSON
snippet taken from an actual tweet.
We have seen the structure of JSON before.
Here we point out that entities and
user, the two parts
in blue are nested, that means embedded,
within the structure of the tweet.
If we represent a part of the schema of
this abbreviated structure in AsterixDB,
it will look like this.
Here a dataverse is like a name space for
data.
Data is declared in terms of data types.
The top type, which looks like
a standard data with stable declaration,
represents the user portion of the JSON
object that we highlighted before.
The type below represents the message.
Now, instead of nesting it like JSON.
The user attribute highlighted in
blue is declared to have the type
TwitterUserType, thus it captures
the hierarchical structure of JSON.
We should also notice that
the first type is declared as open.
It means that the actual data can have
more attributes than specified here.
In contrast, the TweetMessage
type is declared as closed,
meaning that the data instance must have
the same attributes as in the schema.
AsterixDB can handle spatial data as given
by the point data types shown in green.
The question mark at the end of the point
type says that this attribute is optional.
That means all instances need not have it.
Finally, the create dataset actually
asks the system to create a dataset
called TweetMessages, whose type is
the just declared quick message type.
AstrerixDB which runs on HDFS provides
several options for credit support.
First it has its own query language
called the Asterix query language
which resembles the XML
credit language query.
The details of this query language
are not important right now.
We are illustrating the structure of
a query just to show what it looks like.
This particular query asks for
all user objects from the dataset
TwitterUsers in descending order of their
follower count and in alphabetical
order of the user's preferred language.
What is more interesting and distinctive
is that AsterixDB has a creative
processing engine that can process
queries in multiple languages.
For its supported language
they've developed a way to
transfer the query into a set of low
level operations like select and
join which their query
exchange can support.
Further, they've determined how
a record described in one of these
languages can be transformed
into an Asterix.
In this manner, the support hive queries,
which is expressed in like this.
Xquery, Hadoop map reduce,
as wall as a new language
called SQL++ which extends SQL for JSON.
Like a typical DB BDms,
AsterixDB is designed to operate
on a cluster of machines.
The basic idea, not surprisingly,
is to use partition data parallellism.
Each data set is divided into
instances of various types
which can be decomposed to different
machines by either range partitioning or
hash partitioning like
we discussed earlier.
A runtime distributed execution
engine called Hyracks is used for
partitioned parallel
execution of query plans.
For example, let's assume we have
two relations, customers and orders,
as you can see here.
Our query is find the number of orders for
every market segment that
the customers belong to.
Now this query need a join operation
between the two relations,
using the O_CUSTKEY as a foreign
key of customer into orders.
It also needs a grouping operation,
which for
each market segment will pull together all
the orders which will then be counted.
You don't have to understand the details
of this diagram at this point.
We just want to point out that
the different parts of the query
that are being marked,
the customer filed here has two partitions
that reside on two nodes,
NC one and NC two respectively.
The orders file also has two partitions.
But each partition is dually replicated.
One can be accessed either of nodes NC3 or
NC2 and the other on NC1 and NC5.
Hyracks will also break up
the query into a number of jobs and
then fill it out which tasks can
be performed in parallel and
which ones must be
executed stage by stage.
This whole thing will be managed
by the cluster controller.
The cluster controller is also
responsible for replanning and
reexecuting of a job
if there is a failure.
AsteriskDB also has the provision
to accept real time data from external
data sources at multiple rates.
One way is from files in a directory path.
Consider the example of tweets.
As you have seen with the hands-on demo,
usually people acquire tweets by accessing
data through an api that twitter provides.
Very typically a certain volume of tweets,
lets say for
every 5 minutes, is accumulated into
a .json file in a specific directory.
The next 5 minutes,
in another .json file, and so forth.
The way to get this
data into asterisks DB,
is to first create an empty
data set called Tweets here.
The next task is to create a feed.
That is an externally resource.
One has to specify that it's coming from
the local file system called local fs here
and the location of the directory,
the format and
the data type it's going to copy it.
Next, the feed is connected
to the data set and
the system starts reading unread
files from the directory.
Another way for AsteriskDB to access
external data is directly from an API,
such as the Twitter API.
To do this,
one would create a dataset as before.
But this time the data feed is
not on the local file system.
Instead it uses the push Twitter
method which invokes the Twitter
client with the four authentication
parameters required by the API.
Once the feed is defined it is
connected to the data set as before.
Now we move to another Apache product for
large scale text data
searching called Solr.
Systems like Solr, and
its underlying text indexing engine, are
typically designed for search problems.
So they would typically be
part of a search engine.
But before we talk about Solr or
large scale text, we need to first
appreciate some fundamental challenges
when it comes to storing,
indexing, and matching text data.
The basic challenge comes from
the numerous ways in which
a text string may vary, making it
hard to define what a good match is.
Let us show some of these challenges.
Remember in each case,
we're asking whether the strings shown on
either side of the double
tilde sign should match.
The first issue is about spelling
variations and capitalization.
The second issue relates
structured strings.
Where different parts of a string
represent different kind of information.
We have seen this before for file paths,
URLs, and like in this case, product IDs.
The problem is that the searcher may
not always know the structure or
my job on misposition,
the internal punctuations.
The next problem is very common with
proper nouns which are represented in
various ways, including dropping a part of
the string, picking up only the initials.
But consider the last variation, should
BH Obama really match the full name?
The next example is about
frequently used synonyms.
If the document has one of the synonyms,
while the query uses another,
should they match?
Example 5 illustrates
a very common problem.
People use abbreviations all the time.
If we look at text and social media and
instant messaging, we see a much
wider variety of abbreviations.
How well should they met with
the real correct version of the term?
Now problem six is a special
case of problem five.
Many long nouns are shortened
because we take the first initial
letter of each significant word.
We say significant because we
drop words like of as shown here.
This is called initialism.
Just so you know, when an initialism
can be said like a real word,
it's called an acronym.
Thus IBM is an initialization,
but NATO is an acronym.
Now problem seven and
problem eight show two
different situation where we first must
decide what to do with the period sign.
In the first case, we should not
find a match because students and
American are in two different
sentences punctuated by a period sign.
But in the second case we should
find a match because the period
does not designate a sentence boundary.
Lucene, the engine on which Solr is
built is effectively not a database,
but a modern inverted index.
What's an inverted index?
Let's first define a vocabulary
as a collection of terms.
Where a term may be a single word or
it can be multiple words.
It can a single term or
it can be a collection of synonyms.
But how would a search
engine know what a term is?
We'll revisit this question
in a couple of slides.
For now, let's just say that if we
have a corpus of documents, we can
extract most of the terms and construct
a vocabulary for that collection.
We can then define occurrence, as a list
containing all the information necessary
for each term in the vocabulary.
It would include information like,
which documents have the term?
The positions in the document
where the term occurs.
We can then go on to compute the count of
the term in the document and the corpus.
Referring back to a previous module
in this course, we can also compute
the term frequency and inverse
document frequency for the collection.
An inverted index is
essentially an index which for
every term stores at least the ID of
the document where the term occurs.
Practically, other computed numbers or
properties associated with the terms
will also be included in the index.
Solr is an open source
enterprise search platform.
The heart of Solr is its search
functionality built for full text search.
However, Solr provides much
more than tech search.
It can take any structured document,
even CSV files
which can be broken up into fields,
and can index each field separately.
Full text indexes where text columns
are supplemented by indexes for
other types of data, including numeric
data, dates, geographic coordinates, and
fields where domains are limited
to an emergent set of values.
Solr provides other facilities
like faceted search and
highlighting of terms that match a query.
Now if you're not familiar
with the term faceted search,
let's look at the screenshot
from amazon.com.
I performed a search on the string,
Dell laptop.
Consider the highlighted
part of the image.
Each laptop record carries a lot of
attributes like the display size,
the processor speed,
the amount of memory, and so forth.
These attributes can be put into builds
like processor type has Intel i5, i7, etc.
Faceted search essentially extracts
the individual values of these fields and
displays them back to the user, usually
with a count of the number of records.
We see this in the upper
part of the marked portion,
which says there are 5619
laptops per 411 tablets.
These are called facets.
If a user clicks on a facet,
documents with only those values,
that's just the tablets,
will be presented back to the user.
Now let's get back to the question
of what a term is, and
how a Solr system should know it.
Solr allows the system designer to
specify how to parse a document,
by instructing how to tokenize
a document and how to filter it.
Tokenization is the process of
breaking down the characters read.
For example, one can break
the stream at white spaces, and
get all the words as tokens.
Then, it can filter out the punctuation
like the period, the apostrophe, and so
on, just to get the pure words.
The code snippet on the right
essentially achieves this.
It uses a standard tokenizer that gets
the words with immediate punctuation.
The first filter removes the punctuations.
The second filter turns
everything into lowercase.
And the third filter uses
a synonym file to ensure that
all the synonyms get the same
token after ignoring the case.
The last filter removes common
English words like a and the.
While a similar process would need to
happen when we get the query string.
It will also need to go through a
tokenization and token filtering process.
In the query analyzer example, there
are six filters within the tokenizer.
We use a pattern tokenizer which
will remove the white spaces and
periods and semi-colon.
The common grams filter creates
tokens out of pairs of terms, and
in doing so, makes sure that words
in the stopword file are used.
So if we have the string,
the cat, the term the should
not be ignored in this filter.
Now, the filters here
are executed in order.
After the common grams
filter is already done,
the next filter removes all
the stopwords in the file.
The fifth filter makes sure that if
the queries coming from a web form,
all the HTML characters are stripped off.
Finally, the remaining words are stemmed,
so that runs and
running in the query would match
the word run in the document.
We'll end this section with a discussion
on Solr queries, that is searches.
We present a CSV file with nine
records and seven attributes.
We issue queries against
the system by posing a web query.
In these examples, we show some of
the queries one can post to the system.
This will be covered in more detail
during the hands-on session.
Just notice that the q equal to is a query
and the fl is what you want to back.
Listens on activity who will be performing
queries assessing the Postgres database.
First, will open a terminal window and
start the Postgres shell.
Next, we will look at table and
column definitions in database.
Who’s in query the content
of the buy-clicks table?
And see how to do this query, but filter
specific rows and columns from the table.
Next, we will perform average and
some aggregation operations
on a specific column.
And finally,
we will see how to combine two tables
by joining them on a single column.
Let's begin.
First, click on the terminal
icon at the top of the toolbar
to open a Terminal window.
Next, let's start the Postgres
shell by running psql.
The Postgres shell allows us to
enter queries and run commands for
the postgres database.
We can see what tables are in
the database by running \d.
This says that there are three
tables in the database,
adclicks, buyclicks and gameclicks.
We could use \d table name to see
the definition of one of these tables.
Let's look at the definition of buyclicks,
we enter \d buyclicks.
This shows that there's seven
columns in the database.
These are the column names and here's
the data type for each of the columns.
Now let's look at the contents
of the buyclicks table.
We can query the contents by running
the command select * from buyclicks;.
The select says that
we want to do a query.
The star means we want to
retrieve all the columns and
from buyclicks says,
which table to perform the query from.
And finally, all commands in Postgres
shell need to end with a semicolon.
When we run this command we see
the contents of the buyclicks table.
Column header is at the top and
the contents are below.
Again hit Space to scroll through
the contents, and hit Q when we're done.
Now, let's view the contents
of only two of the columns.
Let's query only the price and
the user id from the buyclicks table.
To do this we run select price,
userid from buyclicks.
This command says,
we want to query only the price and
userid columns from the buyclicks table
When we run this,
We only get those two columns.
We can also perform queries that
just select certain rows and
meet a certain criteria.
For example,
let's make a query that only shows
the rows containing the price over $10.
You can do this by running select price,
userid from buyclicks where price > 10.
This query says, we only want to see
the price and userid columns from
the buyclicks table where the value in the
price column has a value greater than 10.
We run this, we see that we always
have price values greater than 10.
The SQL language has a number of
aggregation operations built into it.
For example,
we can take the average price by running,
select avg(price) from buyclicks.
This command will show the average price
from all the data in the buyclicks table.
Another aggregate operation is sum.
We can see the total price by running,
select sum(price) from buyclicks.
We can also combine two tables
by joining on a common column.
If you recall we have three
tables in our database adclicks,
buyclicks and gameclicks.
We look at the description the definition
of adclicks buy running \d adclicks.
You can see that it also
has a column called userid.
Let's combine buyclicks and
adclicks based on this common column.
You can do this by running, select adid,
buyid, adclicks.userid from adclicks join
buyclicks on adclicks.userid
= buyclicks.userid
This query says,
we want to just see the adid, buyid and
userid columns, and
we want to combine the adclicks table,
the buyclicks table, and
we will be combining them on
the userid column and
it's common in both those tables.
When we run it,
you see just the three columns.