Hello, I hope you enjoyed your first
programming experience with Spark.
Although the words count
example is simple,
it is useful in starting to
understand how to work with RDDs.
After this video, you'll be able to use
two methods to create RDDs in Spark,
explain what immutable means,
interpret a Spark program as a pipeline
of transformations and actions, and
list the steps to create a Spark program.
So let's remember where we are.
We have a Driver Program that
defines the Spark context.
This is the entry point
to your application.
The driver converts all the data to RDDs,
and
everything from this point on
gets managed using the RDDs.
RDDs can be constructed from files or
any other storage.
They can also be constructed from
data structures for collections and
programs, like lists.
All the transformations and actions on
these RDDs take place either locally,
or on the Worker Nodes
managed by a Cluster Manager.
Each transformation results in
a new updated version of the RDD.
The RDDs at the end get converted and
saved in a persistent storage like HDFS or
your local drive.
As we mentioned before,
RDDs get created in the Driver Program.
The developer of the Driver Program,
who in this case is you,
is responsible for creating them.
You can just read in a file
through your Spark Context, or
as we have in this example,
you can provide an existing collection,
like a list to be turned into
a distributed collection.
You can also create an integer
RDD using parallelize,
and provide a number of partitions for
distribution as we do create
the numbers RDD in this line.
Here, the range function in Python
will give us a list of
numbers starting from 0 to 9.
The parallelize function
will create three partitions
of the RDD to be distributed, based on
the parameter that was provided to it.
Spark will decide how to assign partitions
to our executors and worker nodes.
The distributed RDDs can in the end be
gathered into a single partition on
the driver using
the collect transformation.
Now let's think of a scenario were we
start processing the created RDDs.
There are two types of operations
that help with processing in Spark,
namely Transformations and Actions.
All partitions written in RDD,
go through the same transformation in
the worker node, executors when
a transformation is applied to an RDD.
Spark uses lazy evaluation for
transformations.
That means they will not be
immediately executed, but
instead wait for
an action to be performed.
The transformations get computed
when an action is executed.
For this reason,
a lot of times you will see run
time errors showing up at the action stage
and not at the transformation stages.
It is very similar to Haskell or Erlang,
if any of you are familiar
with these languages.
Let's put some names on
these transformations.
We can have a pipeline by converting a
text file into an RDD with two partitions.
Filter some values out of it, and
maybe apply a map function to it.
In the end, the run,
the collect action on the mapped RDDs
to evaluate the results of the pipeline
and convert the outputs into results.
Here, filter and map are transformations,
and collect is the action.
Although the RDDs are in memory,
and they are not persistent,
we can use the cash function
to make them persistent cash.
For example, in order to reuse the RDD
created from a database query that could
otherwise be costly to re-execute,
we can instead cache these RDDs.
We need to use caution when
using the cache option,
as it can consume too much memory and
generate a bottleneck itself.
As a part of the Word Count example, we
mapped the words RDD to generate tuples.
We then applied reduceByKey
to tuples to generate counts.
In the end, we convert the number
of partitions to one so
that output is one file
when written to this later.
Otherwise, output will be spread
over multiple files on disk.
Finally, saveAsTextFile is an action
that kickstarts the computation and
writes to disk.
To summarize, in a typical Spark program
we create RDDs from external storage or
local collections like lists.
Then we apply transformations
to these RDDs,
like filter, map, and reduceByKey.
These transformations get lazily
evaluated until an action is performed.
Actions are performed both for local and
parallel computation to generate results.
Next, we will talk more about
transformation and actions in Spark.
In the last video,
we talked about the programming model for
Spark where RDD's get generated from
external datasets and gets partitioned.
We said, RDDs are immutable meaning they
can't be changed in place even partially.
They need a transformation
operation applied to them and
get converted into a new RDD.
This is essential for keeping track
of all the processing that has been
applied to our dataset providing the
ability to keep a linear chain of RDDs.
In addition, as a part of a big data
pipeline, we start with an RDD.
And through several transformation steps,
many other RDDs as
intermediate products get executed
until we get to our final result.
We also mention that
an important feature of Spark
is that all these transformation are lazy.
This means they don't execute
immediately when applied to an RDD.
So when we apply a transformation,
nothing happens right away.
We are basically preparing our big
data pipeline to be executed later.
When we are done defining all
the transformations and perform an action,
Spark will take care of finding the best
way to execute this computation and
then start all the necessary
tasks in our worker nodes.
In this video, we will explain some
common transformation in Spark.
After this video, you will be able
to explain the difference between
a narrow transformation and
wide transformation.
Describe map, flatmap,
filter and coalesce as narrow
transformations and
list two wide transformations.
Let's take at look at, probably the
simplest transformation, which is a map.
By now,
you're well versed in home networks.
It applies the function to each
partition or element of an RDD.
This is a one to one transformation.
It is also in the category of element-wise
transformations since it transforms
every element of an RDD separately.
The code example in the blue
box here applies a function
called lower to all
the elements in a text_RDD.
The lower function
turns all the characters in
a line to lower case letters.
So the input is one line
of text with any kind of
capitalization and the outfit is going
to be the same line, all lower case.
In this example, we have two worker
nodes drawn as orange boxes.
The black boxes are partitions
of our dataset.
We work by partition and not by element.
As you would remember this, it is the
difference between Spark and MapReduce.
The partition is just a chunk of our data
with some number of elements in it and
the map function gets applied to all
elements in that partition in each
worker node locally.
Each node applies the map
function to the data or
RDD partition they received independently.
Let's look at a few more in
element-wise transformation category.
FlatMap is very similar to map.
However, instead of returning
an individual element for each map,
it returns an RDD with an aggregate of
all the results for all the elements.
In the example in the blue box,
the split_words fuction
takes a line as an input,
which is one element and it's output
is each word as a single element.
So, it splits a line to words.
The same thing gets done for each line.
When the output for
all the lines is flattened,
we get a simple
one-dimensional list of words.
So, we'll get all the words in
all the lines in just one list.
Depending on the line length the output
partitions might be of different sizes.
Detected here by the height of
each black box being different.
In Spark terms, map and
flatMap are narrow transformations.
Narrow transformation refers to
the processing where the processing
logic depends only on data that is
already residing in the partition and
data shuffling is not necessary.
Another very important
transformation is filter.
Often, we're interested just
in a subset of our data or
we want to get rid of bad data.
Filter transformation takes the function
take executes on each element
of a RDD partition and
returns only the elements that
the transformation element returns true.
The example code in the blue box here,
applies a filter
function that filters out words
that start with the letter a.
The function starts with a,
takes the input word,
then transforms it to lowercase and
then checks if the word starts with a.
So, the output of this operation will be
a list with only words that start with a.
This is another narrow transformation.
So, it only gets executed locally
without the need to shuffle any RDD
partitions across the word kernels.
The output of filter depends on
the input and the filter functions.
In some cases,
even if you started with even RDD
partitions within the worker nodes,
the RDD size can significantly vary across
the workers after a filter operation,
then this happens is a pretty good
idea to join some of those partitions
to increase performance and
even out processing across clusters.
This transformation is called coalesce.
Coalesce simply helps with balancing
the data partition numbers and sizes.
When you have significantly reduced
your initial data after some filters and
other transformations,
having a large number of partitions
might not be very useful anymore.
In this case,
you can use coalesce to reduce the number
of partitions to a more manageable number.
Until now, we talked about narrow
transformations that happen in a worker
node locally without having to
transfer data through the network.
Now, let's start talking
about wide transformations.
Let's remember our Word Count example.
As a part of the Word Count example, we
map the words RDD could generate tuples.
The output of map is a key value pair
list where the key is the word and
the value is always one.
We then apply it reduceByKey
to tuples to generate counts,
which simply sums the values for
each key or word.
Let's imagine for a second that we use
groupByKey instead of reduceByKey.
We will come back to reduceByKey
in just a little bit.
Remember, mapped outputs tuples,
which is a list of key value
pairs in the forms of word one.
At each worker node, we will have
tuples that have the same word as key.
In this example, apple as the key and
1 as the count and 2 worker nodes.
Trying to group together, all the counts
of a word across worker nodes
requires shuffling of
data between these nodes.
Just like we do for the word apple here.
GroupByKey is the transformation
that helps us combine values with
the same key into a list without applying
a special user define function to it.
As you see on the right, the result
of a groupByKey transformation on all
the map outputs by the word apple is
the key ends up in a list with all ones.
If you instead apply the function to
list like summing up all the values,
then we could have had
the word count results.
In this case, 2.
If we instead applied a function to
the list like summing up all the values,
then we would have had
the word count results.
If we need to apply such functions to
a group of values related to a key like
this, we use the reduceByKey operation.
ReduceByKey helps us to combine
the value using a reduce function,
which in the word count
case is a simple summation.
In groupByKey and
reduceByKey transformations,
we observe the behavior that require
shuffling of the data across work nodes,
we call such transformations
wide transformations.
In wide transformation operations,
processing depends on data
residing in multiple partitions
distributed across worker nodes and this
requires data shuffling over the network
to bring related datasets together.
As a summary, we have listed a small
number of transformations in Spark with
some examples and distinguished between
them as narrow and wide transformations.
Although this is a good start,
I advise you to go through the list
provided at the link shown here after
you complete this beginner course.
Read about the rest of the transformations
in Spark before you start programming in
Spark and have fun with transformations.
Lastly, we will introduce
you to Spark GraphX.
After this video,
you will be able to describe GraphX is,
explain how vertices and
edges are stored in GraphX, and
describe how Pregel works at a high level.
GraphX is Apache Spark's Application
Programming Interface for
graphs and graph-parallel computation.
GraphX uses a property graph model.
This means, both nodes.
And edges in a graph can
have attributes and values.
In GraphX, the node properties
are stored in a vertex table and
edge properties are stored
in an edge table.
The connectivity information, that is,
which edge connects which nodes,
is stored separately from the node and
edge properties.
GraphX is built on special RDDs for
vertices and edges.
VertexRDD represents a set of vertices,
all of which have an attribute called A.
The EdgeRDD here extends
this basic edge storing by
the edges in columnar format on
each partition for performance.
Note that VertexID are defined
to be unique by design.
The edge class is an object
with a source vertex and
destination vertex and an edge attribute.
In addition to the vortex and
edge views of the property graph,
GraphX also has triplet view.
The triplet view logically joins
vortex and edge properties.
GraphX has an operator that
can execute operations
from the Pregel library for
graph analytics.
This Pregel operator executes
in a series of super steps
which defines a messaging protocol for
vertices.
We will revisit graph analytics and
using GraphX in more detail in
course five of the specialization.
In summary, Spark can be used for
graph parallel computations.
GraphX uses special RDDs for
storing vertex and edge information.
And the pregel operator works
in a series of super steps.
Now, we will introduce you to Spark MLlib.
After this video, you will be
able to describe what MLlib is,
list the main categories of
techniques available in MLlib,
and explain code segments
containing MLlib algorithms.
MLlib is a scalable machine learning
library that runs on top of Spark Core.
It provides distributed implementations
of commonly used machine learning
algorithms and utilities.
As with Spark Core, MLlib has APIs for
Scala, Java, Python, and R.
MLlib offers many algorithms and
techniques commonly used in
a machine learning process.
The main categories are machine learning,
statistics and some common utility
tools for common techniques.
As the name suggests,
many machine learning algorithms
are available in MLlib.
These are algorithms to build models for
classification, regression, and
clustering.
There are also techniques for
evaluating the resulting models.
For example,
you can compute the values for
a receiver of creating characteristic
that we call an ROC curve.
A common statistical technique for
plotting the performance
of a binary classifier.
Statistical functions
are also provided in MLlib.
Examples are summary statistics,
means, standard deviation, etc.
Correlations and
methods to sample a dataset.
MLlib also has techniques commonly
used in the machine learning process,
such as dimensionality reduction and
feature transformation methods for
preprocessing the data.
In short, Spark MLlib offers
many techniques often used in
a machine learning pipeline.
Let's take a look at an example to
compute summary statistics using MLlib.
Note that we will use the spark pipe
of API similar to the ones used for
our other examples in this course.
Here is the code segment to
compute summary statistics for
a data set consisting
of columns of numbers.
Lines of code are in white, and
the comments are in orange.
The first line imports statistics
functions from the stat module.
The second line creates an RDD
of Vectors with the data.
You can think of each vector
as a column in a data matrix.
The next line denoted with three invokes
the column stats function to compute
summary statistics for each column.
The last three lines show
by four print out the mean,
variance and number of non-zero
entries for each column.
As you can see from this example,
computing the summary statistics for
a data set is very
straightforward using a MLlib.
Here is another example.
Although we will go through the ratio
learning details in our next course,
here we give you a hint of how to
use two ratio learning techniques.
One for Classification,
and one for Clustering.
This code segment, shows the six steps to
build a DecisionTree for classification.
The first line imports
the DecisionTree module,
the second line imports MLUtils module,
the next line fails the DecisionTree
to classify the data for two classes.
Then, the model is printed out and
finally the model is saved in a file.
Here is another MLlib example,
this time for clustering.
This code segment shows the 5-step
code to build a k-means clustering.
The first line imports the k-means module,
the second line
imports an array module from numpy,
the next two lines read in the data and
parses it using space as the limiter,
then the k-means model
is built by dividing the parsedData
into three clusters.
Finally, the cluster centers
are printed out for each.
In summary,
MLlib is Spark's machine learning library.
It provides algorithms and
techniques that are implemented
using distributors processing.
The main categories of algorithms and
techniques available in machine
learning library are machine learning,
statistics and utility functions for
the machine learning process.
Over the next couple of videos,
we will introduce you to the basic
components of the Spark stack.
In this lecture, we start with Spark SQL.
After this video, you will be able to
process structured data using Spark's SQL
module and explain the numerous
benefits of Spark SQL.
Spark SQL is the component of Spark
that enables querying structured and
unstructured data through
a common query language.
It can connect to many data sources and
provides APIs to convert
the query results to RDDs in Python,
Scala, and Java programs.
Spark SQL gives a mechanism for
SQL users to deploy SQL queries on Spark.
Spark SQL enables business
intelligence tools to connect to
Spark using standard connection
protocols like JDBC and ODBC.
Spark SQL also provides APIs to
convert the query data into DataFrames
to hold distributed data.
DataFrames are organized as named
columns and basically look like tables.
The first step to run any SQL Spark
is to create a SQLContext.
Once you have an SQLContext,
you want to leverage it
to create a DataFrame so you can deploy
complex operations on the data set.
DataFrames can be created
from existing RDDs,
Hive tables or many other data sources.
A file can be read and converted into
a DataFrame using a single command.
The show function here will display
the DataFrame in your Spark show.
RDDs can be converted to DataFrames but
require a little more work.
First you will have to
convert each line into a row.
Once your data is in a DataFrame,
you can perform all sorts of
transformation operations on it
as shown here, including show,
printSchema, select, filter and groupBy.
To summarize, Spark SQL lets you
run relational queries on Spark.
It also lets you connect to
a variety of databases, and
deploy business intelligence
tools over Spark.
We will go through some of this
functionality in one of the readings and
in the upcoming hands-on session.