Next we will talk about Spark streaming.
After this video you will be able to
summarize how Spark reads streaming data,
list several sources of streaming
data supported by Spark, and
describe Spark's sliding windows.
Spark streaming provides
scalable processing for
real-time data and
runs on top of Spark Core.
Continuous data streams are converted or
grouped into discrete RDDs which
can then be processed in parallel.
Spark Streaming provides APIs for Scala,
Java, and Python,
like other Spark products.
Spark Streaming can read
data from many different
types of resources,
including Kafka and Flume.
Kafka is a high throughput published
subscribed messaging system,
and Flume collects and
aggregates log data.
Spark Streaming can also read from batch
input data sources, such as HDFS,
S3, and many other non SQL databases.
Additionally, Spark Streaming can read
directly from Twitter, raw TCP sockets,
and many other data sources that
are real-time data providers.
So how does it all work?
Here we show you a flow of
transformations and actions
which you will try in the upcoming reading
and hands-on exercises on Spark Streaming.
Spark streaming reads
streaming data and
converts it into micro batches
which we call DStreams which is short for
discretized stream.
In this example a 10 second
stream gets converted
into five RDDs using a batch
length of 2 seconds.
Similar to other RDDs,
transformations such as map, reduce,
and filter can be applied to DStreams.
DStreams can be aggregated
into Windows allowing you to apply
computations on sliding window of data.
In this example the Window
size is 4 seconds and
the sliding interval is 2 seconds.
In summary, Spark Streaming is
Spark's library to work with
streaming data in near real time.
DStreams can be used just
like any other RDD and
can go through the same
transformation as batch datasets.
DStreams can create a sliding window to
perform calculations on a window of time.
Now that we know what machine learning
is and have seen some examples of it,
let's talk about how we
do machine learning.
In this lecture we will get an overview of
the main categories of machine learning
techniques.
After this video you will be able to
describe the main categories of
machine learning techniques and
summarize how supervised learning
differs from unsupervised learning.
There are different categories of
machine learning techniques for
different types of problems.
The main categories are listed here.
They are classification,
regression, cluster analysis, and
association analysis.
We will cover each one in
detail in the following slides.
In classification, the goal is to
predict the category of the input data.
An example of this is predicting the
weather as being sunny, rainy, windy, or
cloudy.
The input data in this case would be
sensor data specifying the temperature,
relative humidity, atmospheric pressure,
wind speed, wind direction, etc.
The target or what you're trying to
predict would be the different weather
categories, sunny, windy,
rainy, and cloudy.
Another example is to classify
a tumor as either benign or malignant.
In this case,
the classification is referred to as
binary classification since
there are only two categories.
But you can have many categories as well.
As the weather prediction
problem shown here.
Another example is to identify hand
written digits as being in one of ten
categories, zero to nine.
Some more examples of classification
are classifying a tumor from a medical
image as being benign or malignant.
Predicting whether it
will rain the next day.
Determining if a loan application is
high-risk, medium-risk or low-risk.
Identifying the sentiment of a tweet or
review as being positive,
negative, or neutral.
When your model has to predict
a numeric value instead of a category,
then the task becomes
a regression problem.
An example of regression is to
predict the price of a stock.
The stock price is a numeric value,
not a category.
So this is a regression task
instead of a classification task.
If you were to predict whether
the stock price will rise or
fall, then that would be
a classification problem.
But if you're predicting
the actual price of the stock,
then that is a regression problem.
That is the main difference between
classification and regression.
In classification,
you're predicting a category and
in regression,
you're predicting a numeric value.
Some other examples of regression
are estimating the demand of a product
based on time or season of the year.
Predicting a score on a test,
determining the likelihood of
how effective a drug will be for
a particular patient, predicting
the amount of rain for a region.
In cluster analysis,
the goal is to organize similar
items in your data set into groups.
A very common application of
cluster analysis is referred to as
customer segmentation.
This means that you're separating your
customer base into different groups or
segments based on customer types.
For example it would be very beneficial
to segment your customers into seniors,
adults and teenagers.
These groups have different likes and
dislikes and
have different purchasing behaviors.
By segmenting your customers to different
groups you can more effectively provide
marketing adds targeted for
each groups particular interests.
Note that cluster analysis is
also referred to as clustering.
Some other examples of cluster
analysis are, identifying areas of
similar topography, such as desert region,
grassy areas, mountains etc.
Categorizing different types of
tissues from medical images.
Determining different groups of weather
patterns, such as snowy, dry, monsoon.
And discovering hot spots for different
types of crime from police reports.
The goal in association analysis is
to come up with a set of rules to
capture associations between items or
events.
The rules are used to determine when
items or events occur together.
A common application of association
analysis is known as market
basket analysis.
Which is used to understand
customer purchasing behavior.
For example, association analysis can
reveal that banking customers who have
CDs, or Certificates of Deposits,
also tend to be interested in
other investment vehicles such
as money market accounts.
This information can be used for
cross selling.
If you advertise money market accounts to
your customers with CDs they are likely to
open such an account.
According to data mining folklore
a supermarket chain used association
analysis to discover a connection between
two seemingly unrelated products.
They discovered that many
customers who go to the store
late on Sunday night to buy
diapers also tend to buy beer.
This information was then
used to place beer and
diapers close together and
they saw a jump in sales of both items.
This is the famous diaper,
beer connection.
Some other applications of association
analysis are recommending similar
items based on the purchasing behavior or
browsing histories of customers.
Finding items that are often purchased
together, such as garden hose and
potting soil, and
offer sales on these related items at the
same time to drive sales of both items.
Identifying web pages that
are often accessed together so
that you can more efficiently offer up
these related web pages at the same time.
We have now looked at the different
categories of machine learning techniques.
They are classification,
regression, cluster analysis, and
association analysis.
We have also seen some
examples of each category
There is also another categorization
of machine learning techniques, and
that is supervised versus
unsupervised approaches.
In supervised approaches the target,
which is what the model is predicting,
is provided.
This is referred to as having labeled
data because the target is labeled for
every sample that you
have in your data set.
Referring back to our example of
predicting a weather category of sunny,
windy, rainy or cloudy,
every sample in the data set is labeled
as being one of these four categories.
So the data is labeled and predicting the
weather categories is a supervised task.
In general, classification and
regression are supervised approaches.
In unsupervised approaches
on the other hand,
the target that the model is
predicting is unknown or unavailable.
This means that you have unlabeled data.
Going back to our cluster analysis
example of segmenting customers into
different groups.
The samples in your data are not
labeled with the correct group.
Instead, the segmentation is performed
using a clustering technique to group
items based on characteristics
that they have in common.
Thus, the data is unlabeled and
the task of grouping customers into
different segments is an unsupervised one.
In general, cluster analysis and
association analysis
are unsupervised approaches.
In summary,
in this lecture we looked at the different
categories of machine learning techniques.
We discussed classification, regression,
cluster analysis and association analysis.
We also defined what supervised and
unsupervised approaches are,
in machine learning.
In this lecture,
we will review each of the steps in
the machine learning
process in greater detail.
After this video, you will be able
to explain the goals of each step in
the machine learning process, and list key
activities in each step in the process.
This is the machine learning process
that we saw in the last lecture.
In this lecture,
we will cover each step in more detail.
We will describe the goals
of each step and
the key activities performed in each step.
The first step in the data science
process is to acquire the data.
The goal of the step is to identify and
obtain all data related
to the problem at hand.
First, we need to identify all
related data and the sources.
Keep in mind, that data can come from
different sources such as files,
databases, the internet, mobile devices.
So remember to include all data related
to the problem you're addressing.
After you've identified your data and
data sources,
the next step is to collect the data and
integrate data from the different sources.
This may require conversion,
as data can come in different formats.
And it may also require aligning the data,
as data from different sources may have
different time or spacial resolutions.
Once you’ve collected and integrated your
data, you now have a coherent data set for
your analysis.
The next step after acquiring data is
to prepare it to make it suitable for
analysis.
There are two parts to this step,
explore data and preprocess data.
We will discuss data exploration first.
In data exploration, you want to
do some preliminary investigation
in order to gain a better understanding of
the specific characteristics of your data.
This in turn will guide
the rest of the process.
With data exploration,
you'll want to look for
things like correlations,
general trends, outliers, etc.
Correlations provide information
about the relationship
between variables in your data.
Trends in your data will reveal if the
variable is moving in a certain direction,
such as transaction volume
increasing throughout the year.
Outliers indicate potential
problems with the data, or
may indicate an interesting data
point that needs further examination.
Without this data exploration activity,
you will not be able to
use your data effectively.
One way to explore your data is
to calculate summary statistics
to numerically describe the data.
Summary statistics are quantities
that capture various characteristics
of a set of values with a single number,
or a small set of numbers.
Some basic summary statistics that you
should compute for your data set are mean,
median, mode, range and
standard deviation.
Mean and median are measures of
the location of a set of values.
Mode is the value that occurs most
frequently in your data set, and
range and standard deviation
are measures of spread in your data.
Looking at these measures will give you
an idea of the nature of your data.
They can tell you if there's
something wrong with your data.
For example, if the range of
the values for age in your data
includes negative numbers, or
a number much greater than a hundred,
there's something suspicious in
the data that needs to be examined.
Visualization techniques
also provide quick and
effective ways to explore your data.
Some examples are, a histogram,
such as the plot shown here,
shows the distribution of the data and
can show skewness or
unusual dispersion in outliers.
A line plot, like the one in the lower
left, can be used to look at trends in
the data, such as,
the change in the price of a stock.
A heat map can give you an idea
of where the hot spots are.
A scatter plot effectively shows
correlation between two variables.
Overall, there are many types
of plots to visualize data.
They are very useful in helping
you understand the data you have.
The second part of the prepare
step is preprocess.
So, after we've explored the data, we need
to preprocess the data to prepare it for
analysis.
The goal here is to create the data
that will be used for analysis.
The main activities on this
part are to clean the data,
select the appropriate variables to
use and transform the data as needed.
A very important part of
data preparation is to
clean the data to address quality issues.
Real world data is nothing.
There are many examples of quality issues
with data from real applications including
missing values, such as income
in a survey, duplicate data,
such as two different records for the same
customer with different addresses.
Inconsistent or invalid data,
such as a six digit zip code.
Noise in the collection of data
that distorts the true values.
Outliers, such as a number much
larger than 100 for someone's age.
It is essential to detect and
address these issues that can negatively
affect the quality of the data.
Other activities in data preprocessing
can be broadly categorized as
feature selection and
feature transformation.
Feature selection refers to
choosing the set of features to
use that is appropriate for
the application.
Feature selection can
involve removing redundant or
irrelevant features, combining features,
or creating new features.
During the exploring data step,
you may have discovered that two
features are very correlated.
In that case,
one of these features can be removed
without negatively effecting
the analysis results.
For example,
the purchase price of a product and
the amount of sales tax pain
are very likely to be correlated.
Eliminating the sales tax
amount then will be beneficial.
Removing redundant or irrelevant features
will make the subsequent analysis simpler.
You may also want to combine features or
create new ones.
For example,
adding the applicants education level
as a feature to a loan approval
application would make sense.
There are also algorithms to
automatically determine the most relevant
features based on various
mathematical properties.
Feature transformation maps the data
from one format to another.
Various transformation operations exist.
For example, scaling maps
the data values to a specified
range to prevent any one feature from
dominating the analysis results.
Filtering or aggregation can be used to
reduce noise and variability in the data.
Dimensionality reduction maps the data
to a smaller subset of dimensions
to simplify the subsequent analysis.
We will discuss techniques to prepare
data in more detail later in this course.
After preparing the data to
address data quality issues and
preprocess it to get it in
the appropriate format,
the next step in the machine learning
process is to analyze the data.
The goals of the staff are to
build a machine learning model,
to analyze the data and to evaluate
the results that you get from the model.
The analyze steps starts with this
determining the type of problem you have.
You begin by selecting appropriate machine
learning techniques to analyze the data.
Then you construct the model using
the data that you've prepared.
Once the model is built, you will
want to apply it to new data samples
to evaluate how well the model performs.
Thus data analysis involves selecting
the appropriate technique for
your problem, building the model,
then evaluating the results.
As there are a different
types of problems,
there are also different
types of analysis techniques.
We will cover algorithms for
building machine learning models in a much
more detail in week three of this course.
The next step in the machine learning
process is reporting results from your
analysis.
In reporting your results, it is important
to communicate your insights and
make a case for
what actions should follow.
In reporting your results,
you will want to think about what to
present, as well as how to present.
In deciding what to present, you should
consider what the main results are,
what insights were gained
from your analysis, and
what added value do these insights
bring to the application.
Keep in mind that even negative results
are valuable lessons learned, and
suggest further avenues for
additional analysis.
Remember that all findings
must be presented so
that informs decisions can be made for
next steps.
In deciding how to present,
remember that visualization is an
important tool in presenting your results.
Plots and summary statistics
discussing the explore step
can be used effectively here as well.
You should also have tables with
details from your analysis as backup,
if someone wants to take
a deeper dive into the results.
In summary, you want to report your
findings by presenting your results and
the value added with graphs
using visualization tools.
The final step in
the machine loading process
is to determine what action should be
taken based on the insights gained.
What action should be taken based
on the results of your analysis?
Should you market certain products
to a specific customer segment to
increase sales?
What inefficiency is can be
removed from your process?
What incentives would be effective
in attracting new customers?
Once a specific action
has been determined,
the next step is to implement the action.
Things to consider here include, how can
the action be added to your application?
How will end users be affected?
Assessing the impact of the implemented
action is then necessary to evaluate
the benefits gained.
The results of this assessment
determine next steps,
which could suggest additional analysis or
further opportunities,
which would begin another cycle
of the machine learning process.
In summary, we've looked at the steps in
the machine learning process in detail.
The goals or main activities of each
step were discussed in this lecture.
Remember that this is
an iterative process,
in which each step can be repeated
more than once, and findings from
each step may require a previous step
to be repeated with new information
Hello, everyone.
You have probably heard of machine
learning before, enough to grab your
attention and bring you to this class.
However, you might be wondering
what machine learning is.
We will talk about that
in this lecture and
discuss how we can see machine learning
in action in our day-to-day life.
After this video you will be able to
explain what machine learning is.
And list three applications of machine
learning encountered in everyday life.
Since this course is about machine
learning, lets define what that means.
We hear this term a lot these
days used in many contexts.
So it's good to start out with a solid
definition of what machine learning means.
Machine learning is the field of study
that focuses on computer systems that can
learn from data.
That is the system's often called
models can learn to perform a specific
task by analyzing lots of examples for
a particular problem.
For example, a machine learning
model can learn to recognize
an image of a cat by being shown lots and
lots of images of cats.
This notion of learning from data
means that a machine learning
model can learn a specific task
without being explicitly programmed.
In other words, the machine learning
model is not given the step
by step instructions on how to
recognize the image of a cat.
Instead, the model learns
what features are important
in determining whether it picture contains
a cat from the data that has analyzed.
Because the model learns to
perform this task from data
it's good to know that the amount and
quality of data available for
building the model are important factors
in how well the model learns the task.
Because machine learning
models can learn from data
that can be used to discover hidden
patterns and trends in the data.
These patterns and trends lead to
valuable insights into the data.
Thus the use of machine learning allows
for data driven decisions to be made for
a particular problem.
So to summarize, the field of machine
learning focuses on the study and
construction of computer systems
that can learn from data
without being explicitly programmed.
Machine learning algorithms and
techniques are used to build models,
to discover hidden patterns and
trends in the data allowing for
data-driven decisions to be made.
You may have heard that machine learning
is an inter-disciplinary field.
This is very true.
Machine learning combines concepts and
methods from many disciplines, including
math, statistics, computer science,
artificial intelligence, and optimization.
In applying machine learning to a problem,
domain knowledge is essential
to the success of end results.
By domain knowledge we mean
an understanding of the application or
business domain.
Knowledge about the application,
the data related to the application, and
how the outcomes will be used are crucial
to driving the process of building
the machine learning model.
So domain knowledge is also an integral
part of a machine learning solution.
Machine learning has been used in many
different learning application, many of
which you'll probably encounter in your
daily life, perhaps without realizing it.
One application of machine learning that
you likely used this past weekend, or
even just today,
is credit card fraud detection.
Every time you use your credit card,
the current purchase is analyzed
against your history of credit card
transactions to determine if the current
purchase is a legitimate transaction or
a potentially fraudulent one.
If the purchase is very different
from your past purchases, such as for
a big ticket item in a category that
you had never shown an interest in or
when the point of sales location
is from another country,
then it will be flagged
as a suspicious activity.
In that case,
the transaction may be denied.
Or you may get a call from your
credit card company to confirm that
the purchase was indeed made by you.
This is a very common use of machine
learning that is encountered in
everyday life.
Another example application of machine
learning encountered in daily life is
handwritten digit recognition.
When you deposit a hand-written check into
an ATM, a machine learning process is used
to read the numbers written on the check
to determine the amount of the deposit.
Handwritten digits are trickier
to decipher than typed digits
due to the many variations
in people's handwriting.
A machine learning system can sift through
the different variations to find similar
patterns to distinguish a one from a nine,
for example.
Recommendations in what sites is
another example application of
machine learning that most people
have experienced first hand.
After you buy an item on a website you
will often get a list of related items.
Often this will be displayed
as customers who bought this
item also bought these items,
or you may also like.
These related items have been associated
with the item you purchased by
a machine learning model, and
are now being shown to you since
you may also be interested in them.
This is a common application of
machine learning used often in
sales and marketing.
Here are some other examples of where
machine learning has been used.
Like targeted ads on mobile devices.
Sentiment analysis of social media data,
climate monitoring to detect seasonal
patterns, crime pattern detection, and
a healthiness analysis of drugs
among many other applications.
As you can see from this short list,
machine learning has been used in
various applications including science,
medicine, retail, law enforcement,
education and many others.
Let's take a few minutes to discuss the
different terms which refer to this field.
The term we are using for this course is
machine learning, but you may have heard
other terms such as data mining,
predictive analytics and data slangs.
So what is the difference
between these different terms?
As we have discussed, machine learning
has its roots since statistics,
artificial intelligence, and
computer science among other fields.
Machine learning encompasses
the algorithms and
techniques used to learn from data.
The term data mining became popular
around the time that the use
databases became common place.
So data mining was used to refer to
activities related to finding patterns in
databases and data warehouses.
There are some practical data management
aspects to data mining related to
accessing data from databases.
But the process of finding
patterns in data is similar, and
can use the same algorithms and
techniques as machine learning.
Predictive analytics refers to analyzing
data in order to predict future outcomes.
This term is usually used in the business
context to describe activities such as
sales forecasting or predicting
the purchasing behavior of a customer.
But again the techniques used to make
these predictions are the same techniques
from machine learning.
Data science is a new term that is
used to describe processing and
analyzing data to extract meaning.
Again machine learning techniques
can also be used here.
Because the term data science became
popular at the same time that big
data began appearing, data science usually
refers to extracting meaning from big data
and so includes approaches for collecting,
storing and managing big data.
These terms evolved at different times and
may have encompassed
different sets of activities.
But there have always been more
similarities than differences between
them.
Now they are often used
interchangeably and
have come to mean
essentially the same thing.
The process of extracting valuable insight
from data, the core algorithms and
techniques for doing this do not
change with different terms.
To summarize, in this lecture we've
discussed what machine learning is and
how it is being used.
Machine learning models learn from data to
perform a task without being explicitly
programmed.
They are used to discover patterns and
trends in the data.
And a lab for data driven decisions to
be made for the problems being studied.
We also discuss in this lecture examples
of how machine learning is being used.
We see how the example applications
that machine learning can be applied
to many different areas.
What are the steps in
the Machine Learning Process?
We will discuss those in this lecture.
After this video, you will be able
to identify the steps in the machine
learning process and discuss why
the machine learning process is iterative.
This diagram illustrates the steps
in the machine learning process.
In this lecture,
we will cover an overview of these steps.
In the next lecture,
we will cover each step in more detail.
It should be kept in mind that all of
these steps need to be carried out with
a clear purpose in mind.
That is, the problem or opportunity that
is being addressed must be defined with
clearly stated goals and objectives.
For example,
the purpose of a project may be to study
customer purchasing behavior to come up
with a more effective marketing strategy
in order to increase sales revenue.
The purpose behind the project will
drive the machine learning process.
The first step in the machine
learning process is to get
all available data related
to the problem at hand.
Here, we need to identify all data
sources, collect the data, and
finally integrate data from
these multiple sources.
The next step in the machine learning
process is to prepare the data.
This step is further divided into two
parts, explore data and pre-process data.
The first part of data preparation
involves preliminary exploration
of the data to understand the nature
of the data that we have to work with.
Things we want to understand about
the data are its characteristics, format,
and quality.
A good understanding of the data
leads to a more informed analysis and
a more successful outcome.
Once we know more about the data
through exploratory analysis,
the next part is pre-processing
of the data for analysis.
This includes cleaning data,
selecting the variables to use, and
transforming data to make the data more
suitable for analysis in the next step.
The prepared data then would be
passed on to the analysis step.
This step involves selecting
the analytical techniques to use,
building a model using the data,
and assessing the results.
Step four in the machine learning
process it to communicate results.
This includes evaluating the results with
respect to the goal set for the project.
presenting the results in
a easy to understand way and
communicating the results to others.
The last step is to apply the results.
This brings us back to
the purpose of the project.
How can the insights from our analysis
be used to provide effective marketing
to increase sales revenue?
Determining actions from insights gained
from analysis is the main
focus of the act step.
Note that the machine learning
process is a very iterative one.
Findings from one step may require
a previous step to be repeated
with new information.
For example, during the prepare step, we
may find some data quality issues that may
require us to go back to the acquire
step to address some issues with data
collection or to get additional data that
we didn't include in the first go around.
Each step may also require
several iterations.
For example, it is common to try different
analysis techniques in the analyze step
in order to get reasonable
results from the model.
So, it is important to recognize that
this is a highly iterative process, and
not a linear one.