Hello everyone and welcome to a series of
lessons on graph analytics with Neo4j.
In this first tutorial we are going to go
briefly through the process of downloading
and installing Neo4j, and
then we'll go ahead and run Neo4j and
provide a brief review of
the Neo4j graphical interface.
So, let's get started.
To download Neo4j,
you'll want to browse to neo4j.com, and
once you're at that URL,
you should see a webpage similar to this.
Neo4j typically will detect which
operating system you're running, but
if you want to download
other versions of Neo4j,
click this link in the upper
right-hand corner to download Neo4j.
We're going to use the community edition,
so we'll click this link right here.
But if you'd like to
explore other releases,
you can click the link down here.
When we click
the Download Community Edition link,
Neo4j should automatically
begin the download.
There are versions of Neo4j for
Windows, Mac, and Linux.
Neo4j is developed with the Java
programming language, so
you'll want to be sure you have the
minimum system requirements to run Neo4j.
We'll provide a link to those system
requirements in the resources of
this video.
This example is with
the Mac OS X operating system.
And we've downloaded the .dmg file and
we can click to open that.
And as is the case with the Mac
applications to install is very
straightforward.
We'll just click and drag this icon
into the Applications folder and
that should automatically install.
Once the application is installed,
we should see it listed in
the Applications folder.
So let's go ahead and run Neo4j.
To run Neo4j, you'll just double-click
on the application's icon.
Neo4j is browser-based, so
it launches a web server, and
it launches a URL specific to Neo4j.
So to activate that server
we'll click the Start button.
If it's your first time using Neo4j
then you probably won't have any graph
databases available to open,
so Neo4j makes it easy for
you by providing a default
graph database of movie data.
To run Neo4j, you click this link and
that should launch your default browser.
Installation on Windows should be
just as straightforward as OS X.
You'll click the same
Download Neo4j button and
when the download page opens,
you'll click Download Community Edition.
Neo4j should recognize you're running
Windows and should download an executable.
Once that downloads we can run it and
we'll step through the same steps
which are typical for
a Windows operating system.
Now I already have Neo4j
installed in my Windows system so
I will be updating my
existing installation.
And Neo4j downloads a Java jar file.
Once the application's installed
it will open the dialog box and
we can start up our web server.
And the same URL is available and
when we click that, our default
browser should be launched and we should
see the same interface we see In OS X.
You should be able to subsequently
run neo4j by accessing the executable
in the Windows Start menu.
So let's take a look at
the neo4j interface.
As I mentioned previously,
neo4j is a browser-based application.
So once the application launches it
should open your default browser and
in my case, I'm using the Chrome browser.
And you should see a URL like
this in the address bar.
Most browsers provide a full-screen
viewing mode, so I'm going to go ahead and
activate that, in this case,
what Chrome calls presentation mode.
The interface for
neo4j consists of three main areas.
There's the command line along the top
where you can issue commands and you can
paste content into the command line and
execute multiple lines at one time.
You can specify these commands
to be one of your favorites.
You can clear the command box.
And you can run, or execute,
the commands with the Play button.
On the left-hand side is an expandable and
collapsible panel that provides
supplementary information about the
database you're currently working with.
There's an option to list your favorites,
and
Neo4j provides an initial
default listing of favorites.
And there's supplementary information and
links to references and
examples and tutorials and so on.
You can also modify the configuration
of your Neo4j installation for
your particular user.
And there's additional information
about the application.
The third area is the main panel in
the middle where the results of all of
the commands that you
execute are displayed.
In fact, this panel itself has been
generated by issuing a command,
which is displayed in
the very top of the panel.
The command is ;play start.
In fact, if I type that command into my
command line I should be able to generate
a duplicate of that panel,
and sure enough, there it is.
The upper right-hand corner of these
panels I can pin the panel to my webpage,
and I can do this with as
many panels as I want and
the window will simply allow
me to scroll up and down.
I can view this particular
panel full screen.
Or it can cancel or close it,
which is what I'm going to do.
Now you can see neo4j makes it very
easy to learn all about graph analytics.
So let's go ahead and get started
with learning how to create and
modify our first graph network.
Next we're going to get started with Neo4j
by creating our first graph network.
To do this,
first we will review a graphical or
a diagrammatic representation
of a graph network.
Then, we'll introduce you to an equivalent
text representation of that network.
Then, we will build on those text
representations in the form of pseudocode,
with the ultimate goal being
to develop an actual script
to create our network in Neo4j.
Then, we'll go ahead and run the script to
create the network, and we'll explore it,
and confirm it structure and content.
You're looking at a simple graph network,
consisting of five nodes and five edges.
Each node represents a person,
an individual.
And, the edges represent
relationships between those people.
Each node has a number associate with it,
N1 through N5.
And, each edge has a corresponding number
associated with it, E1 through E5.
Edges are relationships such
as Harry is known by Tom,
or Julian is coworker of Harry.
We could have more or less edges, but we
wanted to keep things relatively simple,
while still maintaining
a reasonable degree of complexity.
What we want is a script that we can
process with Neo4j in order to
create an actual graph network.
So, let's look at a text
representation of this network.
So, here we list our five nodes and
five edges, and we're going to begin
the process of extending the text
descriptions of our graph network.
I'm going to scroll down briefly,
and just show you the end result, so
you have a better idea of what
the final goal is going to be.
This is the actual code that we're going
to submit to Neo4j in order to create
our network.
But, we're going to back
up a little bit and
look at some simplified
versions of this syntax, so
we can better understand how simple the
graph network relationships really are.
Here, we list the five nodes and
five edges, as you saw just a moment ago.
And down below,
we have a simple notation structure,
which attempts to describe
the five edge relationships.
The first line represents the edge E1.
We can see that the nodes N1 and
N2 are included,
because Harry is known by Tom, and
Tom is node N1 and Harry is node N2.
The same goes for the second line,
the relationship between Julian and Harry.
Julian is co-worker of Harry, and so on.
So, let's take this a step further
by defining our graph network,
so that each node is
a particular type of node.
In this case, we're going to define a node
type as what we're calling a ToyNode.
As we introduce each node and
its relationship with other nodes,
we'll define the node
to be of type ToyNode.
So, on this first line,
N1 goes through e1 to N2.
And, both of those are introduced for
the first time, so
we'll define them as type ToyNode.
But, on the next line, since we
already introduced N2 as type ToyNode,
we don't need to repeat that statement.
And, so we continue in the same manner
with the remaining edge relationships.
Taking this even further, we'll apply
a similar kind of constraint to our edges.
In this case, we'll define our network
such that each edge is a particular type,
which we're calling ToyRelation.
Next, we're going to add
properties to our nodes and edges.
Our nodes can have properties
such as name or job,
so in this case, our first node,
N1, will have the name Tom.
And, the appropriate syntax for this
includes curly braces surrounding the key
value pairs, a colon separating
the key value pairs, and
the values defined within single quotes.
Likewise, each edge may have
a specific type of relationship,
including co-worker, wife, and friend.
So, finally this brings us to the actual
code we're going to use to create our
graph network.
So, let's go ahead and copy this,
and paste it into Neo4j, so
we can take a look at our network.
Here we are, running Neo4j in our browser.
So, I'm going to paste the code that
I just copied from my text file
into the command line
in the Neo4j interface.
And, I'll click the Play button
to execute those commands, and
we'll see the results returned
in this newly displayed panel.
We can see that we have 5 labels added,
5 nodes were created, 13 properties were
set, 5 relationships were created, and the
entire process required 31 milliseconds.
However, we still can't actually view our
graph unless we issue yet another command.
So, let's shuffle to our text file,
and take a look at that command.
What this command does,
is it tries to identify a match
in which a particular node has
a relationship with any other node.
And, then we'll return those nodes and
relationships.
So, we'll go ahead and copy this, and
we'll paste it in to our command line,
and we'll execute.
And, there's our graph.
When we mouse over the nodes, we can see
information displayed on the bottom.
And, when we select those nodes, that
information is displayed permanently along
the bottom,
likewise with edge relationships.
So, we would expect to see things such
as Michelle is the wife of Harry,
Julian is a co-worker of Harry, and so on.
So, it looks like our network
has been created successfully.
We can also display
information in a tabular format
by clicking the Rows icon on the left.
And, we'll see that this information
is not constrained by the directed
nature of our graph.
For example, we see that Harry
has a relationship with Tom,
in which Harry knows Tom.
But likewise, down here,
Tom has a relationship with Harry,
in which Tom knows Harry.
Next, we're going to learn
how to add to this graph and
modify some of the properties
of the nodes and edges.
In this segment, we're going to
learn how to import data into Neo4j.
We will begin by using a fairly simple
spreadsheet consisting of only a few
rows and three columns in a format
that's fairly typical for
importing into a graph database.
We will review the Neo4j CYPHER
script used to perform this import.
And then we'll run the script and
validate the resulting graph.
Then we'll demonstrate
a similar process but
with a more challenging dataset,
consisting of terrorist network data.
We will review this dataset and
the script commands necessary for
performing the import.
And we'll run the script and
explore the resulting graph.
And finally, we will review a third
dataset that you will use yourself to
perform similar data inport operations.
First, let's take a look
at our sample dataset.
This spreadsheet consists of just
a few rows and three columns.
Each column has a heading.
The first column heading is Source,
the second column heading is Target, and
the third column heading is distance.
You can imagine that this might represent
data from a simple road network in which
the Source and
Target values represent towns, and
the distance values represent the actual
distance in miles between the towns.
So let's take a look at
the Neo4j CYPHER script and
see what we will need to do to
import our spreadsheet data.
The first line of code
performs the actual import.
The other three lines of code provide
constraints to the formatting
of that data.
Since our data file is
a comma separated values or
CSV file,
we will need to specify that in our code.
Our file also contains headers.
And if you're using
a Windows operating system,
your file path will look
something like this.
Since we're running Neo4j in a browser,
the file path needs
to conform to the HTTP address
conventions of the word file,
followed by a colon,
followed by three forward slashes and
then the hard disk letter where the file
is located, plus the path to that file.
If you're using Mac OSX,
your command will be similar, but
the file path will probably
look something more like this.
The next three lines specify which
nodes will be the source nodes and
which nodes will be the target nodes.
And the properties will attach to them as
well as defining the relationships and
the properties we will
attach to the relationships.
As we read each line of data n,
we're going to use keyword line,
to specify the individual line
we're currently working on.
We use that here at the end
of our load command and so
we'll have to continue to use it
in the subsequent merge commands.
Our source node variable
is going to be n and
we'll use the MyNode type,
which we've made up ourselves.
We're going to add a Name property
to each of our source nodes.
And we're going to attach the value in
the Source column to that particular node.
Likewise for our target nodes,
we'll use a variable m.
We'll define them as the same type,
MyNode.
We will give them a Name and we will
extract that name from the Target column
on the particular line we're working with.
Finally, we need to define
our edge relationships.
We're going to give each
edge a label of the word TO,
and we're going to add a property called
dist, which represents the distance.
And we'll attach the values
in the distance column
from the particular line
we're currently working on.
So let's go ahead and copy this code and
paste it into Neo4j, and see what happens.
Now, I'm working on a Mac OSX machine, so
I'm going to copy this code down here and
perform the import operation.
So I've pasted the line
of code into Neo4j and
I'll click Execute.
And it takes a few moments to run.
There's not too much data so it shouldn't
take more than just a few seconds.
And now we get the results in which
11 labels, 11 nodes have been added,
25 properties have been set and
14 relationships have been created.
So let's take a look
at this graph network.
We can see that the nodes are listed
all as MyNode and there's our graph.
The edge relationships should all
have different distance values and
each node should be named
a different letter.
Okay, so
let's try a more difficult dataset.
Here is the spreadsheet
containing terrorist data.
The spreadsheet consists of seven
columns with headings such as Country,
ActorName, ActorType, AffiliationTo,
AffiliationStartDate,
AffiliationEndDate, and any aliases
associated with that particular terrorist.
This dataset consists of
over 100,000 rows of data.
Since that could take a very long
time to load into Neo4j, we will be
working with a subset of this dataset
consisting of the first 1,000 rows.
That much data will still
include three countries,
which should be plenty of data for
our purposes.
So here is the script we're going to use
to import the subset of terrorist data,
which shares similarities with
the script we used previously.
But since there are more
columns in our dataset,
we're going to include some additional
properties into our graph network.
The first line of code is very similar
to the load command we've
used in previous datasets.
The second line of code will use
a variable c and a label Country for
the particular nodes representing
the individual countries in the dataset.
In this particular case, we're going to
use the keyword row instead of line to
read our data n, but
it really doesn't matter.
We could use either word as long we
are consistent from command to command.
So we're using the term row and
associating the value in the Country
column with the node that we're
working on in that particular row.
We will do something similar with
nodes that are intended to represent
the actors or
the actual individual terrorists.
We're going to use a variable a and
we will associate a property
called Name, and associate
the ActorName with that property.
We'll also associate
a property named Aliases, and
associate the value in the Aliases
column with that property.
And finally,
we will define a property called Type and
associate the values in the ActorType
column with that property.
We're going to create nodes
representing organizations as well and
we will use the variable o, and
the label Organization for those nodes.
We will attach a single property
to these nodes called Name and
we'll assign the values in
the AffiliationTo column to that property.
Then we're going to define
relationships between the Actors and
the Organizations they're affiliated with.
The relationship label is
going to be AFFILIATED_TO and
we'll define a property called Start.
And we'll assign the values in the
AffiliationStartDate with that property.
Likewise, we will define
a property called End and
assign the values in
the AffiliationEndDate with that property.
And finally, we're going to create
relationships between the countries and
the actors.
In this case, we will define relationships
with the label IS_FROM that will
describe the fact that a particular
actor is from a particular country.
So if all this makes sense,
let's go ahead and copy this script and
paste it into Neo4j, and see the results.
So here we are in Neo4j, and
I'm going to go ahead and
paste that script into the command line,
and we will execute it.
We loaded 1,000 rows of data, which
consists of 658 labels and 658 nodes.
3,464 properties and
1,403 relationships and
it took about two and a half seconds.
So let's look at a small
subset of this network.
Here, we see the equivalent of
the first 25 rows of the dataset.
There's only enough data
such that 1 Country,
8 Actors and 15 Organizations are visible.
Let's go ahead and
change this command to 250.
By clicking on the line of
code in the top of our panel,
it automatically gets pasted
into the command line above.
So all we need to do is add a zero on the
end of our command and execute that again.
Now we have a much larger,
more complex graph,
but we still only have one country.
In order to see more than one country,
we'll need to render the entire 1,000
rows of our terrorist data subset.
But in so doing, we will have a difficult
time viewing the entire graph.
The community edition of Neo4j
is limited in its ability to
navigate a graph network.
But I'm going to show you
a little trick by editing
the HTML behind the scenes to
scale the view of our graph.
So let's go ahead and
render all 1,000 rows.
So most recent versions of the major
browsers provide the ability to go behind
the scenes and edit the HTML.
So the trick is to find a place on
the viewing panel that does not have
any objects.
So that when you right-click and
inspect the element,
you'll be inspecting the viewing area.
Neo4j uses SVG graphics, or
Scalable Vector Graphics to
render its graph networks.
And SVG uses a g element,
which can be seen here on the right.
So in order to change the scale of our
view, we simply need to double-click and
add scale, open parentheses, and
the scale factor that we'd like.
We hit Return and
the graph network now is zoomed out.
I'm going to try to position it so
we can see at least two countries,
and I'll close my HTML panel.
And so now we can view two countries.
We can see Albania in the upper region,
and Afghanistan in the lower right.
And we can see that there are actors and
organizations that have
relationships with both countries.
Now there are add ons to Neo4j that
make navigating a graph network a little
easier, but
this trick is convenient for those of you
who have not added any Neo4j extensions.
The last thing that we're going to do
is take a look at the sample dataset of
gene-disease associations, and give you
an idea what's going to be expected of
you in the accompanying assignment for
this module.
This data consists of
information associating
different genes with different diseases.
The spreadsheet consists of
columns with headings for geneId,
geneSymbol, geneName, diseaseId,
the diseaseName, the score that
represents the extent to which that gene
is associated with that
particular disease.
The NumberofPubmed articles
containing that information.
The associationTypes,
there are up to three different types of
associations between a gene and a disease.
And then the sources of data and
information that confirm this
gene disease relationship.
Now this dataset contains
over 400,000 rows of data.
So if you have difficulty
importing this entire dataset,
then you'll be better off extracting
the first few thousand rows.
So you're goal will be to
define the load statement,
which includes a CSV with headers,
that will allow you to import enough
data into Neo4j to give you an idea
that you've done it successfully.
We've already learned a little
about the Neo4j interface.
And we've learned how to create
a relatively simple graph with it.
In this lecture,
we're going to learn how to add
another node and an edge to the graph.
We'll also go through
the process of adding a node and
edge incorrectly to the graph.
And we'll learn how to
correct that mistake.
And finally we'll learn how to modify
an existing node's information.
Okay, so here's our network that we
created in the previous lecture.
The first modification
that we want to make,
is adding a single node to the network.
So let's say that Julian has a fiance and
her name is Joyce and
she works as a store clerk.
So let's look at the code that we're
going to use to make that modification.
So this process involves two steps or
two separate commands.
First command requires you to find the
node that you want to add the new node to.
So we use the match command and
we specify the ToyNode named Julian.
Once that command is issued then
we'll use the merge command and
define the relation between Julian and
the new node.
And it's going to be fiancee.
And then the new node
will also be a ToyNode.
And the name is Joyce, and
her job is store clerk.
So let's go ahead and
copy both these lines of code.
And we'll paste them into our command
line, and we'll run these commands.
And the results that
are returned look good.
Neo4j says that it has added 1 label,
created 1 node, set 3 properties,
created 1 relationship, and
it's required 55 milliseconds to execute.
So let's look at that network.
Maybe the easiest way to
view an existing network,
if it's the only one you're working on and
you know the constraints involved,
just ToyNodes, is to expand the panel on
the left and just click the ToyNode node.
And you'll easily see the new network.
And we can confirm that Joyce
has been successfully added, and
when we select that,
we can see that her job is store clerk.
The command that was issued automatically
by clicking the ToyNode button in
the panel Is a little different than what
we've been using to view our networks.
But they both work essentially
the same with this particular network.
So next let's see what happens if
we do something incorrectly, and
how to correct the mistake.
So to do this,
we'll need to get back to our original
network without the added node.
And maybe the easiest way to do
this is to delete everything and
recreate our original network.
So first I'm going to copy and
paste command to delete all
of the nodes and edges.
You'll find this command in the getting
started video supplementary resources.
It involves the match command and
I'm matching all nodes and
all relationships and I'm deleting
those nodes and relationships.
So let's issue that command,
which should say it's deleted 6 nodes and
6 relationships, and sure enough.
Neo4J's command line has a nice feature of
maintaining a history of the commands and
so in OSX we can use the command+up
arrow to cycle through the commands and
find the original create command
that created our network.
On Windows, it's a CTRL+up arrow command.
So here I've found that command and
I'm going to re-execute it.
And we have our original
network back again.
Let's view that network.
And there it is.
So let's say for whatever reason I am
not quite fully understanding how to add
an additional node to an existing network,
and I want to use the create command.
For example, I might be thinking that
this statement right here will
accomplish the same kind of thing.
By using the create command and
by specifying a ToyNode named Julian.
Well, if we go ahead and
give that a try let's see what happens.
So I'll copy this command and I will paste
it into my command line and execute it.
And it says it's added 2 labels and
created 2 nodes and set 4 properties.
And if we look at this, We
see we've actually got another node named
Julian who has a relationship with Joyce.
So that much is correct, but it's not
the same Julian from the original network.
So how do we undo this?
Well, we'll need to specify the Julian
that has a relationship with Joyce and
delete both the Julian and
the Joyce notes.
So here we'll use the match
command once again.
And we'll identify the node, the ToyNode,
with the name Joyce and any relationship
she has with any other node should be
deleted in addition to that other node.
Let's go ahead and copy this.
And we'll paste it into our
command line and execute.
And it says it deleted 2 nodes and
deleted 1 relationship.
Let's view our network again.
And it's back to normal.
So that's one example of how you can
intuitively figure out how to correct
certain mistakes.
Next we're going to modify
information of an existing node.
So if you remember when we first created
our network, Harry didn't have a job.
So let's go ahead and add a job to Harry.
First of all,
we'll need to actually select
the node by using the match command.
So we'll issue that here and
we'll specify that that node
name must be equal to Harry.
And then we're going to
use the set command and
specify that job will be equal to drummer.
So let's go ahead and copy that.
And we'll paste it and execute it.
And the results that are returned
says that one property has been set.
But let's say that Harry does
more than just play drums.
Let's say that he can
also play lead guitar.
So in this case we will be
adding an additional property
to a property that already exists and
we'll see how Neo4J handles that.
It's a relatively simple modification
we make, in which we're setting
the job key equal to the existing job key
+ an additional value to that key,
in this case, lead guitarist.
So let's copy that statement.
And we'll paste it and execute it.
And we get a similar result returned and
then let's look at our network.
And when we select Harry, sure enough
now we see that he has two jobs.
They're separated by a comma.
One is drummer and one is lead guitarist.
There's much more you can do with Neo4j,
but
we'll want to move on and
learn some more advanced capabilities
that work us closer towards
managing our big data challenges.
Next, we will talk about
Path Analytics using Cypher,
the query language for Neo4j.
Here's the listing of the various
queries we will be demonstrating.
There are some things that Cypher
is capable of doing very well.
And there are other things that
require a little bit of creativity
in order to get the results
that you're looking for.
And we'll show you some examples of that.
It's also important to keep in mind
that because we're working with paths,
which are an official
structure in graph networks,
each one of these examples
includes a new variable.
Which in this case,
we're using the letter p to represent for
the actual path objects that
we're going to be returning.
You may also see the complete word
path instead of just the single letter
p to represent these objects.
We're going to continue to use the data
set of a simple road network that we've
already been using in previous
demonstrations that contains 11 nodes and
14 edges.
So the first query we're
going to demonstrate
is finding a path between specific nodes.
So this would be very much like trying
to find a root between two different
locations in our road network.
In this case, we're going to find
a path between the node named H and
the node named P.
To do this,
we'll use the match command and
we'll say match p which is a variable
we're using to represent our path,
= node a, going through an edge to node c.
There's something slightly different about
this edge, and that is that we're using
a star to represent an arbitrary number
of edges in sequence between a and c, and
we'll be returning all of those edges
that are necessary to complete the path.
And in this case we only want
to return a single path.
So when we submit this query,
we see this path.
It consists of eight nodes and
seven edges.
And it begins with H and ends with P.
Now, another common function we
will use frequently with paths
is finding the length
between two specific nodes.
So we'll issue the same two lines of code
and then we'll use this new command,
length, to return an actual value.
We want to be returning an actual path.
And we just want a single value.
And when we submit this query,
we get the result seven.
And we can see that by visually
inspecting the graph or our seven edges.
But because most networks
are much more complex than this,
we would need to understand the necessary
query to return the length.
And ideally,
in the case of our road network,
we would want to find the shortest
path between those two nodes.
So in this case we're introducing yet
another new command specific
to paths called shortestPath.
We will use the same variable key, and
the same descriptions in our syntax,
in connecting node a with node c.
And in this case, were going to look for
the shortest path between node a and
node p, and we're going to return that
path as well as the length of that path.
And we're just going to
return a single path.
And when we submit this query,
we get a path that's five nodes and
four edges long and if we look at
the text results that are returned,
we'll see a length displayed
in the length column.
And that value is 4, and we can see
that by visually inspecting our graph.
The next query we are going to demonstrate
is intended to illustrate that
there may be more than one shortest path.
And so, we may want to know all of the
possible shortest paths in order to make
a choice between which one we prefer.
So we'll be using a command that is built
into Neo4j called, allShortestPaths.
We'll be issuing a similar query
to what we issued previously,
we're going to try to find all of the
shortest paths between node a and node p.
And instead of the letters a and c, we're
using the terms source and destination.
But the results that we're going to return
will actually be in the form of an array.
We're using a new term, extract,
which is based on the following.
Assuming we have matched our path p,
we want to identify
all of the nodes in p and
extract their names.
And we'll return these names as a listing,
which we'll call the variable paths.
If there's more than one shortest path,
we'll get multiple listings of node names.
So when we submit this query, the results
are listed in the rows display and
we see there are actually
two shortest paths.
They each have five nodes and four edges.
Now, we may want to issue a query
that finds the shortest path but
with particular constraints or
conditions that we place on them.
So in this case we still want
to find the shortest path, but
in this case we may want to constrain
the path length to be greater
than a particular value, in this case 5.
And then, we want to return essentially
the same results that we returned in
the previous query.
But we'll also want to return the length
of the resulting path just so
we have that information conveniently.
So when we issue this command
we get a path with length six
between node A and node P.
So it's clearly longer than the shortest
path that we had found earlier.
Now that we are somewhat familiar
with the two shortest path commands,
the shortest path, or a single path and
the all shortest paths command or multiple
shortest paths, we're going to use
that in a little bit of a creative way
to return the diameter of the graph.
And if you remember from
a previous lecture,
the definition of
the diameter of the graph
is actually the longest continuous
path between two nodes in the graph.
So by using the shortest path command, but
returning all possible shortest paths,
we're actually going to get the longest
path included in those results returned.
Now, if we look carefully at this script,
it is a little different
than our previous scripts.
In this case our match command is
matching all nodes of type MyNode.
We'll assign those to the variable end.
We're also matching the all nodes of type
MyNode and assigning that to variable m.
So these matches are the same.
But we want to place a constraint
such that the nodes in n are not
the same as the nodes in m, and
then we want to find all of the shortest
paths between unique nodes in n and m.
And return the names of those nodes as
well as the length of that resulting path.
And the trick is to use
the command order by.
And so for those of you who are familiar
already with SQL query language,
you'll recognize order by.
You'll also recognize the descend command.
So if we order the resulting paths
by their length in descending order,
and only return 1, that path should
actually be the longest path.
And that's equal to
the diameter of the graph.
So when we submit this query,
here's the results that we get.
We get a path between node e and
node l with length severn.
Or maybe it occurs to you that maybe this
is not the only diameter of the graph,
the only path with length of seven.
So we can modify our query just a little
bit and change the limit from one to five.
And we'll see the results.
And sure enough,
we actually get five paths.
And 3 of those have length 7.
So there are actually three
distinct paths which qualify as
a diameter of this particular graph.