Step 2-B: Pre-processing Data
The raw data that you get directly from
your sources are never in the format that
you need to perform analysis on.
There are two main goals in
the data pre-processing step.
The first is to clean the data to
address data quality issues, and
the second is to transform the raw
data to make it suitable for analysis.
A very important part of data preparation
is to address quality
of issues in your data.
Real-world data is messy.
There are many examples of quality issues
with data from real applications including
inconsistent data like a customer with two
different addresses, duplicate customer
records, for example, customers address
recorded at two different sales locations.
And the two recordings don't agree.
Missing customer agent demographics or
studies.
Missing values like missing a customer
age in the demographic studies.
invalid data like an invalid zip code for
example, a six digit code.
And outliers like a sense of failure
causing values to be much higher or
lower than expected for a period of time.
Since we get the data downstream
we usually have little control
over how the data is collected.
Preventing data quality problems as
the data is being collected is not
often an option.
So we have the data that we get and
we have to address quality issues
by detecting and correcting them.
Here are some approaches we can take
to address this quality issues.
We can remove data records
with missing values.
We can merge duplicate records.
This will require a way to determine
how to resolve conflicting values.
Perhaps it makes sense to retain the newer
value whenever there's a conflict.
For invalid values, the best estimate for
a reasonable value can be
used as a replacement.
For example, for
a missing age value for an employee,
a reasonable value can be estimated based
on the employee's length of employment.
Outliers can also be removed if
they are not important to the task.
In order to address data
quality issues effectively,
knowledge about the application,
such as how the data was collected,
the user population, and the intended
uses of the application is important.
This domain knowledge is
essential to making informed
decisions on how to handle incomplete or
incorrect data.
The second part of preparing data
is to manipulate the clean data into
the format needed for analysis.
The step is known by many names.
Data manipulation,
data preprocessing, data wrangling,
and even data munging, some operations for
this type of operation I mean data
munging, wrangling, preprocessing,
include, scaling, transformation,
feature selection,
dimensionality reduction,
and data manipulation.
Scaling involves changing the range of
values to be between a specified range.
Such as from zero to one.
This is done to avoid having certain
features that large values from
dominating the results.
For example,
in analyzing data with height and weight.
To magnitude of weight values is much
greater than of the height values.
So scaling all values
to be between zero and
one will equalize contributions from
both height and weight features.
Various transformations can be performed
on the data to reduce noise and
variability.
One such transformation is aggregation.
Aggregate data generally results
in data with less variability,
which may help with your analysis.
For example, daily sales figures
may have many serious changes.
Aggregating values to weekly or monthly
sales figures will result in similar data.
Other filtering techniques can also be
used to remove variability in the data.
Of course, this comes at
the cost of less detailed data.
So these factors must be weighed for
the specific application.
Future selection can involve removing
redundant or irrelevant features,
combining features, and
creating new features.
During the exploring data step,
you might have discovered that
two features are correlated.
In that case one of these
features can be removed
without negatively affecting
the analysis results.
For example,
the purchase price of a product and
the amount of sales tax paid,
are likely to be correlated.
Eliminating the sales tax amount,
then will be beneficial.
Removing redundant or
irrelevant features will make
the subsequent analysis much simpler.
In other cases, you may want to combine
features or create new ones.
For example,
adding the applicant's education level
as a feature to a loan approval
application would make sense.
There are also algorithms to automatically
determine the most relevant features,
based on various mathematical properties.
Dimensionality reduction is useful when
the data set has a large number of
dimensions.
It involves finding a smaller
subset of dimensions that
captures most of
the variation in the data.
This reduces the dimensions of the data
while eliminating irrelevant features and
makes analysis simpler.
A technique commonly used for
dimensional reduction is called
principle component analysis or PCA.
Raw data often has to be manipulated to
be in the correct format for analysis.
For example, from samples recording
daily changes in stock prices,
we may want the capture price changes for
a particular market segments
like real estate or health care.
This would require determining which
stocks belong to which market segment.
Grouping them together, and
perhaps computing the mean, range,
standard deviation for each group.
In summary,
data preparation is a very important
part of the data science process.
In fact, this is where you will spend most
of your time on any data science effort.
It can be a tedious process,
but it is a crucial step.
Always remember, garbage in, garbage out.
If you don't spend the time and
effort to create good data for the
analysis, you will not get good results
no matter how sophisticated
the analysis technique you're using is.
Step 3: Analyzing Data.
Now that you have your
data nicely prepared,
the next step is to analyze the data.
Data analysis involves building
a model from your data,
which is called input data.
The input data is used by the analysis
technique to build a model.
What your model generates
is the output data.
There are different types of problems, and
so there are different types
of analysis techniques.
The main categories of analysis techniques
are classification, regression,
clustering, association analysis,
and graph analysis.
We will describe each one.
In classification, the goal is to
predict the category of the input data.
An example of this is predicting
the weather as being sunny,
rainy, windy, or cloudy in this case.
Another example is to classify
a tumor as either benign or malignant.
In this case, the classification is
referred to as binary classification,
since there are only two categories.
But you can have many categories as well,
as the weather prediction problem
shown here having four categories.
Another example is to identify
handwritten digits as
being in one of the ten
categories from zero to nine.
When your model has to predict
a numeric value instead of a category,
then the task becomes
a regression problem.
An example of regression is to
predict the price of a stock.
The stock price is a numeric value,
not a category.
So this is a regression task
instead of a classification task.
Other examples of regression
are estimating the weekly sales of a new
product and
predicting the score on a test.
In clustering, the goal is to
organize similar items into groups.
An example is grouping a company's
customer base into distinct segments for
more effective targeted marketing
like seniors, adults and
teenagers, as we see here.
Another such example is identifying
areas of similar topography,
like mountains, deserts,
plains for land use application.
Yet another example is determining
different groups of weather patterns,
like rainy, cold or snowy.
The goal in association analysis
is to come up with a set
of rules to capture associations
within items or events.
The rules are used to determine when
items or events occur together.
A common application of association
analysis is known as market
basket analysis, which is used to
understand customer purchasing behavior.
For example, association analysis
can reveal that banking customers
who have certificate of deposit accounts,
surety CDs, also
tend to be interested in other investment
vehicles, such as money market accounts.
This information can be used for
cross-selling.
If you advertise money market
accounts to your customers with CDs,
they're likely to open such an account.
According to data mining folklore,
a supermarket chain used association
analysis to discover a connection between
two seemingly unrelated products.
They discovered that many customers who go
to the supermarket late on Sunday night
to buy diapers also tend to buy beer,
who are likely to be fathers.
This information was then
used to place beer and
diapers close together and
they saw a jump in sales of both items.
This is the famous diaper beer connection.
When your data can be transformed into
a graph representation with nodes and
links, then you want to use graph
analytics to analyze your data.
This kind of data comes about when
you have a lot of entities and
connections between those entities,
like social networks.
Some examples where graph analytics can
be useful are exploring the spread of
a disease or epidemic by analyzing
hospitals' and doctors' records.
Identification of security threats
by monitoring social media,
email and text data.
And optimization of mobile
communications network traffic.
telecommunications network traffic,
to ensure call quality and
reduce dropped calls.
Modeling starts with selecting,
one of the techniques we listed
as the appropriate analysis technique,
depending on the type of problem you have.
Then you construct the model
using the data you've prepared.
To validate the model,
you apply it to new data samples.
This is to evaluate how well the model
does on data that was
used to construct it.
The common practice is to divide
the prepared data into a set of data for
constructing the model and
reserving some of the data for
evaluating the model after
it has been constructed.
You can also use new data prepared the
same way as with the data that was used to
construct model.
Evaluating the model depends on the type
of analysis techniques you used.
Let's briefly look at how
to evaluate each technique.
For classification and regression,
you will have the correct output for
each sample in your input data.
Comparing the correct output and
the output predicted by the model,
provides a way to evaluate the model.
For clustering,
the groups resulting from clustering
should be examined to see if they
make sense for your application.
For example, do the customer
segments reflect your customer base?
Are they helpful for
use in your targeted marketing campaigns?
For association analysis and
graph analysis, some investigation will be
needed to see if the results are correct.
For example, network traffic delays
need to be investigated to see what your
model predicts is actually happening.
And whether the sources of the delays
are where they are predicted
to be in the real system.
After you have evaluated your model to get
a sense of its performance on your data,
you will be able to
determine the next steps.
Some questions to consider are,
should the analysis be
performed with more data in order
to get a better model performance?
Would using different data types help?
For example, in your clustering results,
is it difficult to distinguish
customers from distinct regions?
Would adding zip code
to your input data help
to generate finer grained
customer segments?
Do the analysis results suggest
a more detailed look at
some aspect of the problem?
For example, predicting sunny
weather gives very good results,
but rainy weather
predictions are just so-so.
This means that you should take a closer
look at your examples for rainy weather.
Perhaps you just need more
samples of rainy weather, or
perhaps there are some
anomalies in those samples.
Or maybe there are some missing data
that needs to be included in order
to completely capture rainy weather.
The ideal situation would be that your
model platforms very well with respect to
the success criteria that were determined
when you defined the problem at
the beginning of the project.
In that case, you're ready to
move on to communicating and
acting on the results that you
obtained from your analysis.
As a summary, data analysis involves
selecting the appropriate technique for
your problem, building the model,
then evaluating the results.
As there are different types of problems,
there are also different
types of analysis techniques.
Step four, reporting insights.
The fourth step in our data science
process is reporting the insights gained
from our analysis.
This is a very important step
to communicate your insights and
make a case for
what actions should follow.
It can change shape based on your
audience and should not be taken lightly.
So how do you get started?
The first thing to do is to look
at your analysis results and
decide what to present or report as the
biggest value or biggest set of values.
In deciding what to present you
should ask yourself these questions.
What is the punchline?
In other words, what are the main results?
What added value do
these results provide or
how can the model add to the application?
How do the results compare to
the success criteria determined at
the beginning of the project?
Answers to these questions are the items
you need to include in your report or
presentation.
So make them the main topics and
gather facts to back them up.
Keep in mind that not all of
your results may be rosy.
Your analysis may show results that are
counter to what you were hoping to find,
or results that are inconclusive or
puzzling.
You need to show these results as well.
Domain experts may find some of
these results to be puzzling, and
inconclusive findings may
lead to additional analysis.
Remember the point of
reporting your findings
is to determine what
the next step should be.
All findings must be presented so
that informed decisions can be made.
Visualization is an important
tool in presenting your results.
The techniques that we discuss and
explore in data can be used here as well.
What were they?
Scatter plots, line graphs,
heat maps, and other types of graphs
are effective ways to present
your results visually.
This time you're not
plotting the input data, but
you're plotting the output
data with similar tools.
You should also have tables with
details from your analysis as backups,
if someone wants to take
a deeper dive into the results.
There are many visualization
tools that are available.
Some of the most popular open
source ones are listed here.
R is a software package for
general data analysis.
It has powerful visualization
capabilities as well.
Python is a general purpose
programming language
that also has a number of packages to
support data analysis and graphics.
D3 is a JavaScript library for
producing interactive web based
visualizations and data driven documents.
Leaflet is a lightweight mobile
friendly JavaScript library
to create interactive maps.
Tableau Public Allows you
to create visualizations,
in your public profile, and share them,
or put them, on a site, or blog.
Google Charts provides
cross-browser compatibility,
and closed platform portability
to iPhones and Android.
Timeline is a JavaScript library
that allows you to create timelines.
In summary, you want to report your
findings by presenting your results and
value add with graphs
using visualization tools.
Step 5, Act, turning insights into action.
Now that you have evaluated
the results from your analysis and
generated reports on the potential value
of the results, the next step is to
determine what action or actions should
be taken, based on the insights gained?
Remember why we started
bringing together the data and
analyzing it in the first place?
To find actionable insights
within all these data sets,
to answer questions, or for
improving business processes.
For example,
is there something in your process that
should change to remove bottle necks?
Is there data that should be added to your
application to make it more accurate?
Should you segment your population
into more well defined groups for
more effective targeted marketing?
This is the first step in
turning insights into action.
Now that you've determined
what action to take,
the next step is figuring out
how to implement the action.
What is necessary to add this action
into your process or application?
How should it be automated?
The stakeholders need to be identified and
become involved in this change.
Just as with any process improvement
changes, we need to monitor and
measure the impact of the action
on the process or application.
Assessing the impact
leads to an evaluation.
Evaluating results from the implemented
action will determine your next steps.
Is there additional analysis that need
to be performed in order to yield
even better results?
What data should be revisited?
Are there additional opportunities
that should be explored?
For example, let's not forget
what big data enables us to do.
Real-time actions based on high
velocity streaming information.
We need to define what part of our
business needs real-time action to be
able to influence the operations or
the interaction with the customer.
Once we define these real time actions,
we need to make sure that
there are automated systems, or
processes to perform such actions, and
provide failure recovery
in case of problems.
As a summary, big data and
data science are only useful if
the insights can be turned into action,
and if the actions are carefully
defined and evaluated.
Steps in the Data Science Process.
We have already seen a simple linear
form of data science process,
including five distinct activities
that depend on each other.
Let's summarize each activity further
before we go into the details of each.
Acquire includes anything that makes
us retrieve data including; finding,
accessing, acquiring, and moving data.
It includes identification of and
authenticated access to all related data.
And transportation of data from
sources to distributed files systems.
It includes way to subset and match
the data to regions or times of interest.
As we sometimes refer to
it as geo-spacial query.
The next activity is prepare data,
we divide the pre-data activity.
Into two steps based on
the nature of the activity.
Namely, explore data and pre-process data.
The first step in data preparation
involves literally looking
at the data to understand its nature,
what it means, its quality and format.
It often takes a preliminary
analysis of data, or
samples of data, to understand it.
This is why this step is called explore.
Once we know more about the data
through exploratory analysis,
the next step is pre-processing
of data for analysis.
Pre-processing includes cleaning data,
sub-setting or
filtering data, creating data,
which programs can read and
understand, such as modeling raw
data into a more defined data model,
or packaging it using
a specific data format.
If there are multiple data sets involved,
this step also includes integration
of multiple data sources, or streams.
The prepared data then would be
passed onto the analysis step,
which involves selection of
analytical techniques to use,
building a model of the data,
and analyzing results.
This step can take a couple
of iterations on its own or
might require data scientists
to go back to steps one and
two to get more data or
package data in a different way.
Step four for communicating results
includes evaluation of analytical results.
Presenting them in a visual way,
creating reports that include
an assessment of results with
respect to success criteria.
Activities in this step can often be
referred to with terms like interpret,
summarize, visualize, or post process.
The last step brings us back to the very
first reason we do data science,
the purpose.
Reporting insights from analysis and
determining actions from insights based
on the purpose you initially defined
is what we refer to as the act step.
We have now seen all the steps in
a typical data science process.
Please note that this is an iterative
process and findings from one step
may require the previous step to
be repeated with new information.