Analytical operations
in big data pipelines.
After this video,
you will be able to list common analytical
operations within big data pipelines and
describe sample applications for
these analytical operations.
In this lesson, we will be
looking at analytical operations.
These are operations used in analytics,
which is the process of
transforming data into insights for
making more informed decisions.
The purpose of analytical operations is to
analyze the data to discover meaningful
trends and patterns, in order to gain
insights into the problem being studied.
The knowledge gained from these insights
ultimately lead to more informed
decisions driven by data.
Here are some common analytical operations
that we will discuss in this lecture.
Classification, clustering,
path analysis and connectivity analysis.
Let's start with classification.
In classification, the goal is to predict
a categorical target from the input data.
A categorical target is one
with discreet values or
categories, instead of continuous values.
For example, this diagram shows
a classification task to determine the
risk associated with a loan application.
The input consists of the loan amount,
applicant information such as income,
age, debts, and a down payment.
From this input data,
the task is to determine whether
the loan application is low risk or
high risk.
There are many classification techniques
or algorithms that can be used for
this problem.
We will discuss a specific one, namely,
decision tree in the next slide.
The decision tree algorithm is
one technique for classification.
With this technique,
decisions to perform the classification
task are modeled as a tree structure.
For the loan risk assessment problem,
a simple decision tree is shown here,
where the loan application is
classified as being either low risk, or
high risk, based on the loan amount.
The applicant's income,
and the applicant's age.
The decision tree algorithm is implemented
in many machine learning tools.
This diagram shows how to specify
decision tree from input data, KNIME.
A graphical user-interface-based
machine learning platform.
Some examples of classification
are the prediction of whether cells from
a tumor are benign or
malignant, categorization of
handwritten digits as being zero,
one, two, etc, up to nine.
And determining whether a credit card
transaction is legitimate or fraudulent,
and classification of a loan application
as being low-risk, medium-risk or
high-risk, as you've seen.
Another common analytical
operation is cluster analysis.
In cluster analysis, or clustering,
the goal is to organize similar
items in to groups of association.
This diagram shows an example of cluster
analysis in which customers are clustered
into groups according to their
preferences of movie genre.
So, customers who like Sci-Fi
movies are grouped together.
Those who like drama movies
are grouped together,
and customers who like horror
movies are grouped together.
With this grouping, new movies,
as well as other products,
such as books, can be offered to
the right type of costumers in order to
generate interest and increase revenue.
A simple and commonly used algorithm for
cluster analysis is k-means.
With k-means,
samples are divided into k clusters.
This clustering is done in order
to minimize the variance or
similarity between samples
within the same cluster
using some similarity
measures such as distance.
In this example, k is equal to three, and
k-means divides the original data shown
on the left into three clusters,
shown as blue, green, and
red on the chart on the right.
The k-means clustering algorithm is
implemented on many machine-learning
platforms.
The code here shows how to read in and
parse input data, and
perform k-means clustering on the data.
Other examples of cluster analysis
are grouping a company’s customer base
into distinct segments for more effective
targeted marketing, finding articles or
webpages with similar topics for
retrieving relevant information.
Identification of areas in the city with
rates of particular types of crimes for
effective management of law
enforcement resources, and
determining different groups of weather
patterns such as rainy, cold or snowy.
Classification and cluster analysis
are considered machine learning and
analytical operations.
There are also analytical
operations from graph analytics,
which is the field of analytics where
the underlying data is structured as, or
can be modeled as the set of graphs.
One analytical operation using
graphs as path analysis,
which analyzes sequences of nodes and
edges in a graph.
A common application of path analysis
is to find routes from one
location to another location.
For example, you might want to find the
shortest path from your home to your work.
This path may be different depending on
conditions such as the day of the week,
time of day, traffic congestion,
weather and etc.
This code shows some operations for
path analysis on neo4j,
which is a graph database system
using a query language called Cypher.
The first operation finds the shortest
path between specific nodes in a graph.
The second operation finds all
the shortest paths in a graph.
Connectivity analysis of graphs
has to do with finding and
tracking groups to determine
interactions between entities.
Entities in highly interacting
groups are more connected
to each other than to entities
of other groups in a graph.
These groups are called communities, and
are interesting to analyze as they
give insights into the degree and
patterns of the interaction between
entities, and also between communities.
Some applications of connectivity analysis
are to extract conversation threads.
For example,
by looking at tweets and retweets.
To find interacting groups, for example,
to determine which users are interacting
with each other users, to find
influencers, for example, to understand
who are the main users leading to
the conversation about a particular topic.
Or, who do people pay attention to?
This information can be used to
identify the fewest number of
people with the greatest influence.
For example, for political campaigns,
or marketing on social media.
This code shows some operations for
connectivity analysis on neo4j using
the query language, Cypher, again.
The first operation finds the degree
of all the nodes in a graph,
and the second creates a histogram
of degrees for all nodes in a graph
to determine how connected a node in
a graph is, we need to look at its degree.
The degree of a node is the number
of edges connected to the node.
A degree histogram shows the distribution
of node degrees in the graph and
is useful in comparing graphs and
identifying types of users, for
example, those who follow, versus those
who are followed in social networks.
To summarize and add to these techniques,
the decision tree algorithm for
classification and k-means algorithm for
cluster analysis that we covered in this
lecture are techniques
from machine learning.
Machine learning is a field of analytics
focused on the study and construction of
computer systems that can learn from data
without being explicitly programmed.
Our course on machine learning in
this specialization will cover these
algorithms in more detail,
along with other algorithms used for
classification and cluster analysis.
As well as algorithms for
other machine learning tasks,
such as regression,
association analysis, and tools for
implementing and
executing machine learning algorithms.
As a summary of the Graph Analytics,
the Path Analytics technique for finding
the shortest path and the connectivity
analysis technique for analyzing communities
that we discussed earlier,
are techniques used in graph analytics.
As explained earlier,
graph analytics is the field of analytics,
where the underlying data is structured or
can be modeled as a set of graphs.
Our graph analytics course in the
specialization will cover these and other
graph techniques, and we'll also cover
tools and platforms for graph analytics.
In summary, analytic operations
are used to discover meaningful
patterns in the data in order to provide
insights into the problem being studied.
We looked at some of the examples of
analytical operations for classification,
cluster analysis, path analysis and
connectivity analysis in this lecture.
In this hands-on activity,
we'll be performing word count on
the complete works of Shakespeare.
First, we will copy the Shakespeare
text into the Hadoop file system.
Next, we will create a new
Jupyter Notebook, and
read the Shakespeare
text into a Spark RDD.
We will then perform WordCount
using map and reduce,
and write the results to HDFS and
view the contents.
Let's begin.
In the intro to big data course,
we copy the Shakespeare text into HDFS.
Let's see if it's still there.
If not, we can copy it now.
Click on the terminal icon
at the top of the toolbar.
Now we can run hadoop fs- ls to see what's
in our hadoop filesystem directory.
There are no files in HTFS,
so let's copy it.
If you already have words.txt in your HTFS
directory, you can skip this next step.
Cd into downloads,
big-data-3/spark-wordcount.
We can do ls to see the file.
Let's copy this file to HTFS.
We run Hadoop,
fs copy from local, words.txt.
We can write Hadoop fs -ls again
to verify that the file is there.
Now let's do work count in spark.
We will do this in an iPython
notebook using Jupyter server.
Look on the web browser icon,
the top of the toolbar.
And go to the Jupyter server URL,
which is local host port 8889.
Next, let's create a new iPython notebook
The first step is to read the words.txt
files in HTFS into a spark RDD.
We'll call the RDD, lines.
We can read it using the spark context SC,
in calling the text file method.
The argument is the URL of
the word set TXT file and HDFS.
Let's run this We can
view the contents of this RDD
by calling lines.take(5).
The argument 5 says how many
lines to show of the RDD.
Next, we'll transform this RDD
of lines into an RDD of words.
We'll say, words = lines.flatmap,
lambda line:
line.split Double quote
space double quote.
This creates a new RDD called, words,
by running flatMap over the line RDD.
The argument is this lambda expression.
A lambda in Python is a simple way
to declare a one line expression.
In this case,
there's one argument called line and
we called it split method on this line and
we split on spaces.
We can run this and
look at the contents of words.
We can see that each element
now is an individual word.
Next, we'll create tuples of these words.
We'll put them in a new RDD called tuples.
Enter, tuples
= words.map:lambda
word; (word, 1).
This creates the tuples
by transforming words.
This uses map and another lambda function.
In this case, the lambda takes
one argument and returns a tuple.
Where the first value of
the tuple is the word.
The second value, is the number 1.
Not that in this case, we use map,
whereas before, we used flat map.
In this case, we want a tuple for
every word in the words.
So we have a one to one mapping
between inputs and outputs.
Previously, while we were splitting lines
into word, each line had multiple words.
In general,
you want to use map when you have a one to
one mapping between inputs and outputs.
In flatMap you have a one to many or
none mapping between inputs and
outputs Let's run this and look at tuples.
We can see that each word now has
a tuple initialized with the count of 1.
We can now count all the words by
combining or reducing these tuples.
We'll put this in a new RDD called counts.
So we'll say counts equals
tuples.reduce by key.
Lambda a,b:.
a + b.
In this case, the lambda function
takes two arguments, a and be, and
will return the result of adding a and b.
To view the result,
You can see now that the counts for
each words have been created.
We can write this result back to HDFS.
Let's say
counts.coalesce(1).saveAsTextFile,
and then the URL.
The coalesce means we only
want a single output file.
Let's go back to our shell and
view the results.
We'll run hadoop fs -ls
to see the directory.
And run it again to look inside
the wordcount directory.
And once more,
to look inside wordcount/outputDir.
As you recall,
the output from hadoop jobs is part-0000.
This is also true for spark jobs.
Let's copy this file to
the local file system.
We'll run hadoop fs CopyToLocal
wordcount/outputDir/part-00000.
You can view the results with more.
In this hands on activity,
we will be using Spark Streaming
to read weather data.
First, we open
the Spark Streaming Jupyter Notebook.
Next, we will look at sensor format and
measurement types.
We'll then create a Spark DStream of
weather data, read the measurements, and
create a sliding window of the data.
We will define a function to display the
maximum and minimum values in the window.
We start to stream processing
to give their results.
Before we begin this activity, we need
to change the virtual box settings for
our carder virtual machine.
Start streaming needs more
than one thread of execution.
So we need to change the settings to
add more than one virtual processor.
First, shut down your cloudera virtual
machine and go to the virtual box manager.
Select the cloudera virtual box and
click on settings.
Next, click on system, click on Processor.
And change the number of
CPU's to be two or more.
When you're done, click okay,
and start the machine as usual.
Let's begin.
First, click on the browser icon
at the top of the tool bar.
Navigate to the Jupyter Notebook server,
monitoring local host calling 8889.
We'll then go in to downloads.
Big data 3.
Spark-streaming.
Let's then open Spark-Streaming notebook.
This first line, shows the example
data we get from the weather station.
Each line has a time stamp and
a set of measurements.
Each of these abbreviations is
a particular type of measurement,
followed by the actual value.
The next cell shows the key for
these measurements.
For this hands-on, we are interested
in the average wind direction.
Which is abbreviated as DM.
This next cell, defines a function
that parses each line of text and
pulls out the average wind speed.
We define it here, so
we don't have to type it in later.
Let's run this cell.
Next, let's create
a streaming spark context.
First, we'll need to import the module.
We'll enter from pyspark.streaming
import StreamingContext.
We can create a new streaming context.
We'll put in in a variable called ssc.
We'll enter ssc = StreamingContext(sc,1).
The SC is a StreamingContext.
The 1 specifies the batch interval,
1 second in this case.
Let's run this.
Next, we'll create a dstream.
We'll import the streaming weather data,
over a TCP connection.
We'll put this in a dstream called, Lines.
Let's say lines = ssc.socketTextStream,
we'll enter the host name in
port of the weather station,
rtd.hpwren.ucsd.edu for 12028.
Let's run this.
Next, we'll create a new d-stream called
vals that would hold the measurements.
We'll say vals = lines.flatMap parse.
This calls the parse function,
we defined above for
each of the lines coming
from the weather station.
The resulting D-Stream will have just
the average wind direction values.
We'll run this.
Next, we'll create a window that
will aggregate the D-Stream values.
We'll say, window = vals.window(10,5).
The first argument specifies that the
length of the window should be 10 seconds.
The second argument specifies that
the window should move every 5 seconds.
Let's run this.
Next, we'll define a function
that prints the minimum and
maximum values that we see.
We'll start by entering the definition.
Def stats,
this will take an rdd as an argument.
Next, let's print the entire
contents of the rdd.
Print, parenthesis rdd.collect,
this'll print the entire
content of the rdd.
In a real big data application,
this will be impractical due
to the size of the data.
However, for this hands on,
the rdd is small, and so
we can use this to see
the contents of the rdd.
Next, we'll print the min and max.
Before we do that however,
we should check to make sure that
the size of the rdd is greater than zero.
We'll check that rdd.count
is greater than 0.
Finally, we'll print the MinID, MAX.
We'll enter print (“max = {} min =
{}”) Outside of the quote we'll do
.format(rdd.max,rdd.min())).
Let's run this, next,
let's call this function stats.
So all the rdds in our sliding window.
I'll enter window.foreachRDD(stats).
Run this.
We're now ready to start
our streaming processing.
We can do this by entering ssc.start.
We'll run this to start the streaming.
When we want to stop this streaming,
we'll run ssc.stop
Please scroll up and
look at the beginning of the output.
We'll see that it's printing the full
window and the min and max values.
Notice that in the beginning,
the window is not yet filled.
In this case, there's only three entries.
We count to see that the window
is moving by five measurements.
For example, the last five
measurements in the second window,
are the first five measurements
in the third window.
In this hands on activity we
will be using SparkSQL to
query data from an SQL database.
First we will open
the SparkSQL Jupyter Notebook.
We will connect Spark to a Postgres table.
And then view the Spark DataFrame
schema and count the rows.
We will view the contents
of the data frame.
See how to filter rows and columns.
And finally perform aggregate
operation on a column.
Let's begin.
First, click on the browser icon,
the top of the toolbar.
>> [SOUND]
>> Next,
navigate to the Jupyter Notebook server.
It's localhost:8889.
Go to Downloads,
Big Data 3, Spark SQL.
To open the SparkSQL Notebook.
The first three cells have
already been entered for you.
First, we import the SQLContext, run this.
Next, we create an SQLContext
from the SparkContext run this.
And next, we'll create a Spark DataFrame
from a Postgres table.
We used the read attribute format.
The jdbc argument means that we're
using a Java database connection.
The next line sets the URL option.
It says we're using Postgres
database running on the local host.
The database name is Cloudera and
the username is Cloudera.
The second option, DB table,
says we want our data frame
to be the game clicks table.
And finally we call load.
Let's execute this.
You can see the schema of the data
frame by calling df.printschema.
This shows the name of each
column along with the data type.
We can count the rows in this
df frame by calling df.count.
We can look at the first five
rows by calling df.show(5)
This shows all the columns
in the data frame.
We can select specific columns
by using the select method.
Let's select just the User ID and
Team Level columns.
I'll enter df.select("userid",teamlevel.
Parenthesis.
And finally we only want to
see the top five rows.
So we'll do .show(5).
We can also select rows
that have a specific value.
Let's look for the rows where
the team level is greater than one.
We'll enter df.filter.
We'll specify that we want team level
greater than one by entering df,
square bracket, team level,
greater than one.
And again, we only want the user ID and
team level columns.
And finally only the first five rows.
We can use the group by method to
aggregate a particular column.
For example, the ishit column
has a value of zero or one.
And we can use group by to count how
many times each of these values occurs.
Or a df.groupby ishit, and
we'll call count to count the values
We can also perform aggregate statistical
operations on the data in a data frame.
Let's compute the mean and
sum values for ishit.
First we need to import
the statistical functions we'll
run from.pyspark.sql.functions
import star.
Next we'll run df.select
(mean) ishit,sum ishit
We can also join two data
frames on a particular column.
Let's join the existing data frame of the
game clicks table with the adclicks table.
First, we need to create data frame for
the adclicks table.
Let's go back up.
Copy the content of this cell,
Paste it.
We put the adclicks table
the data frame called df2.
And we'll change the db table
option to the adclicks.
Run it.
Let's print the schema of df2.
You can see that it also has
a column called user id.
So let's join the game clicks
data frame with the add
clicks data frame on this column.
We put the result in a new
data frame called merged.
We'll say merge = df.join.df2 "userid".
We'll run it.
Let's look at the schema.
We'll call merge.printschema.
We can see that this merged data frame
has the column for both game clicks and
adclicks.
Finally we'll look at the top five
rows in this merged data frame.
We'll run merge.show.
We have now seen some
simple transformations and
how Spark can create RDDs from
each other using transformations.
We learned that transformations are
evaluated after an action is performed.
So we can simply define actions as RDD
operations that trigger the evaluation of
the transformation pipeline and return
the final result to the driver program or
save the results to a persistent storage.
We can also call them the last
step in a Spark pipeline.
Let's now look at a few action operations.
After this video, you will be able to
explain the steps of a Spark pipeline
ending with a collect action and list
four common action operations in Spark.
A very common action in Spark is collect.
In this example, we can imagine that
initially we are reading from HDFS.
The RDD partitions that go through
the transformation steps in our big data
pipeline are defined as flatMap and
groupbyKey.
When the final step is done,
the collect action is called and
Spark sends all the tasks for
execution to the worker notes.
Collect will send all the resulting
RDDs from the workers and
copy them to the Java virtual
machine on the driver program.
And then, this will be piped
also to our Python shell.
While collect copies all the data,
another action, take,
copies the first n results of the driver.
If the results are too large
to fit in the driver memory,
then there's an opportunity to write
them directly to HDFS instead.
Among many other actions,
reduce is probably the most famous one.
Reduce takes two elements and
returns a result, like sum.
But in this case, we don't have a key,
we just have a large area of some values.
And we are running this function over and
over again to reduce everything
to one single value.
For example,
to the global sum of everything.
Another very useful action Is saveAsText,
to save the results to local disk or
HDFS, and
this is very useful if the output of
the power computation is pretty large.