Welcome to Big Data Integration and
Processing.
Welcome to course three of
the big data specialization.
I'm Amarnath Gupta.
And I'm Ilkay Altintas.
We are really excited to
work with you in this course
to develop your understanding and skills
in big data integration and processing.
By now you might have just
finished our first two courses and
learned the basics of big data
modelling and management.
If you haven't, it's not required.
But for those that less background
in the data modelling and
data management areas you
might find it valuable.
We understand that you may not have
any background on data management.
We are going to introduce Query languages,
we'll first look at SQL in some detail,
and then move to Query languages for
MongoDB which is a semi structured
data management system, and Aerospike,
which is a key value store.
We will also introduce concepts
related to processing of big data as
big data pipelines.
We talk about data structures and
transformations related to batch and
stream processing as steps in a pipeline.
Providing us a way to talk
about big data processing
without getting into the details
of the underlying technologies.
Once we have reviewed the concepts and
related systems, we will switch gears
to hands on exercises with Spark,
one of the most popular big data engines.
We will show you examples of patch and
stream processing using Spark.
As you know for
many data science applications
one has to use many different databases
and analyze the integrated data.
In fact, data integration is one leading
cause leading to the bigness of data.
We'll give you a rapid exposure to
information integration systems
through use cases and point out the big
data aspects one should pay attention to.
We are also excited to show you
examples of data processing using Splunk.
Our goal here is to provide you
with simple hands on exercises
that require no programming, but
show you how one can use interfaces like
Splunk to manage and process big data.
We wish you a fun time learning and
hope to hear from you in the discussions
forums and learner stories as usual.
Well, happy learning and think big data
In this video, we will talk about
the challenges of ingesting and
processing big data and
remind ourselves why need any paradigm and
programming models for big data.
After this video, you will be able to
summarize the requirements of programming
models for big data and
why you should care about them.
You will also be able to explain
how the challenges of big
data related to its variety, volume and
velocity affects its processing.
Before we start,
let's imagine an online gaming newscase,
just like the one we have for
Catch the Pink Flamingo.
You just introduced the game,
and users started signing up.
You start with a traditional
relational database,
keeping track of user sessions and
other events.
Your game server receives
an event notification every time
a user opens his session and
makes a point in the game.
Initially, everything is great,
your game is working and
the database is able to handle the event
streams coming into the server.
However, suddenly your game becomes
highly popular a good problem to have.
The database management system in
your game server won't be able to
handle the load anymore.
You start getting errors that the events
can't be inserted into the database
at the speed they are coming in.
You decide that you will have a buffer or
a queue to process the advancing chunks.
Maybe also at the same time processing
them to be organized in windows of time or
game sessions.
However, in time as the demand goes up,
you will need more processing nodes and
even more database servers
that can handle the load.
This is, a typical scenario that
most web sites face when confronted
with big data issues related to
volume and velocity of information.
As this scenario demonstrates,
solving the problem in one step
might be possible initially.
But the more reactive fixes
the game developers add, the system
becomes less robust and
more complicated to evolve.
While the developers initially
started with an application and
the database to manage.
Now they have to manage a number
of issues related to this
infrastructure management just to
keep up with the load on the system.
Similarly, the database servers
can be effected and corrupted.
The replication and fault tolerance of
them need to be handled separately.
Let's start by going through these issues.
Let's say,
one of the processing nodes went down.
The system needs to manage and
restart the processing and
there will be potentially some
data loss in the meantime.
The system would need to
check every processing node
before it can discard data.
Each note and each database has
to be replicated separately.
Batch computations that need data from
multiple data servers need to access and
maintain use of the data separately which
might end up being quite slow and costly.
Big data processing techniques
we will address in this course,
will help you to reduce the management
of the mentioned complexities,
including failing servers and
breaking compute nodes.
While helping with the scalability of the
management and processing infrastructure.
We will talk about using big data systems
like Spark to achieve data parallel
processing scalability for
data applications on commodity clusters.
We will use to Spark Runtime Libraries and
Programming Models to
demonstrate how big data systems can
be used for application management.
To summarize, what our imaginary game
application needs from big data system.
First of all, there needs to be a way
to use common big data operations
to manage and split large volumes
of events data streaming in.
This means the partitioning and
placement of data in and
out of computer memory along with a model
to synchronize the datasets later on.
The access to data should
be achieved in a fast way.
The game developers need
to be able to deploy
many event processing jobs to
distributed processing nodes at once.
And these are potentially the data
nodes we move the computations to.
It should also enable
reliability of the computing and
enable fault tolerance from failures.
This means enabling
programmable replications and
recovery of event data when needed.
It should be easily
scalable to a distributed set of
nodes where the data gets produced.
It should also enable scaling out.
Scaling out is simply adding new
resources like distributed computers to
process more or faster data at
scale without losing performance.
There are many data
types in an online game.
Although, we talked about
time click events and
scores, it would be easy to imagine
there are graphs of players,
text-based chats, and
images that need to be processed.
Our big data system should
enable processing of such
a mixed variety of data and
potentially optimize handling of
each type separately as well
as together when needed.
In addition, our system should
have been able both streaming and
batch processing, enabling all
the processing to be debuggable and
extensible with minimal effort.
That means being able to handle
operations at small chunks of data
streams with minimal delay,
that is what we call low latency.
While at the same time handle processing
of potentially all available data
in batch form and
all through the same system architecture.
Latency is a word that we use and
hear a lot in big data processing,
here we refer to how fast the data
is being processed, or simply
the difference between production or event
time and processing time of a data entry.
In other words, latency is quantification
of the delay in the processing of
the streaming data in the system.
While some big data
systems are good at it.
Hadoop for instance is not a great choice
for operations that require low latency.
Let's finish by remembering
the real reasons for
all these requirements
of big data processing.
Making a different from processing
in a traditional data architecture.
Big data has varying volume and
velocity requiring the dynamic and
scalable batch and stream processing.
Big data has a variety requiring
management of data in many
different data systems and
integration of it all at scale.
Next, we'll describe
aggregation functions.
We have seen the first query before.
Select count(*) simply
translates to a count function.
Now we could also say
db.Drinkers.find.count.
But using count directly
is more straightforward.
Now, let's ask to count the number
of unique addresses for drinkers.
So, we don't care what the address is.
We just care if it exists.
This is accomplished through
the $exists:true expression.
Thus, if an address exists for
a drinker, it will be counted.
Another area where we need to count is
when we have an array valued attribute,
like places.
If we just want the number
of elements in the raw list,
we'll write db.country.findplaces.length
and we'll get six.
However, if we want distinct values, we'll
use distinct instead of find and then
use the length for counting the number
of distinct elements, in this case 4.
Now, MongoDB uses an internal machinery
called the aggregation framework,
which is modeled on the concept
of data processing pipelines.
That means documents enter
a multi-stage pipeline which transforms
the documents at each stage until
it becomes an aggregated result.
Now we have seeing a similar mechanism for
relational data.
The aggregation pipelines starts
by using the aggregate primitive.
The most basic pipeline stages provides
filters that operate like queries and
the document transformations that
modify the form of the output document.
The primary filter operation is $match,
which is followed by a query condition.
In this case, status is A.
And expectedly, the $match operation
produces a smaller number of documents
to be processed at the next stage.
This is usually followed
by the $group operation.
Now this operation needs to know which
attributes should be grouped together.
In the example here cust_id
is the grouping attribute so
it is passed as a parameter
to the $group function.
Now notice the syntax.
_id:$cust_id says that the grouped
data will have an _id attribute,
and its value will be
picked from the cust_id
attribute from the previous
stage of computation.
Thus, the $ before the cust_id
is telling the system that
cust_id is a known variable in
the system and not a constant.
The $group operation also needs a reducer,
which is a function that operates on an
activity to produce an aggregate result.
In this case, the reduce function is sum,
which operates on the amount
attribute from the previous stage.
Like $cust_id, we use $amount to
indicate that it's a variable.
As we saw in the relational case,
data can be partitioned into chunks on
the same machine or on different machines.
These chunks are called chards.
The aggregation pipeline of MongoDB
can operate on a charded collection.
The grouping operation in MongoDB
can accept multiple attributes like
the four shown here.
Also shown is a post grouping directive
to sort on the basis of two attributes.
The first is a computed count
variable in ascending order.
So the one designates the ascending order.
The next sorting attribute is secondary.
That means if two groups have
the same value for count,
then they'll be further sorted
based on the category value.
But this time the order is descending
because of the -1 directive
In course two we have seen Solar,
a text search engine from Apache.
MongoDB has a built in text search engine
which can be invoked through the same
aggregation framework we saw before.
Imagine that MongoDB documents in this
case are really text documents placed in
a collection called articles.
In this case, the $match directive of
the aggregate function must be told
it's going to perform a text
function on the article's corpus.
The actual text function is $search.
We set search terms like "Hillary
Democrat" such that having
either term in a document will
satisfy the search requirement.
As is the case of any text engine,
the results of any search returns
a list of documents, each with a score.
The next task is to tell MongDB to
sort the results based on textScore.
What's the $meta here?
Meta stands for metadata,
that is additional information.
Remember that the aggregation
operations are executed in a pipeline.
Any step in the pipeline can
produce some extra data, or
metadata, for each processed document.
In this example, the metadata
produced by the search function
is a computed attribute called textScore.
So this directive tells the system to pick
up this specific metadata attribute and
use it to populate the score attribute
which would be used for sorting.
Finally, the $project class
does exactly what is expected.
It tells the system to output only
the title of each document and
suppress its id.
The last item in our
discussion of MongoDB is join.
We have seen that join is a vital
operation for data management operations.
Interestingly, MongoDB introduced this
equivalent of join only in version 3.2.
So, the joining in MongoDB also
happens in the aggregation framework.
There are a few ways of
expressing joins in MongoDB.
We show one here that explicitly performs
a join to a function called look up.
We use an example form
the MongoDB documentation.
Now here are two document collections,
order and inventory.
Notice that the item key in
orders has values abc, jkl, etc.
And the sku key in the inventory has
comparable values abc, def, etc.
So these two are joinable by value.
The way to specify this join,
one can use this query.
The db.orders.aggregate
declaration states that orders is
sort of the home, or local collection.
Now in the aggregate, the function
$lookup needs to know what to look up for
each document in orders.
The from attribute specifies the name
of the collection as inventory.
The next two parameters are the local and
foreign matching keys,
which are item and sku, respectively.
The last item, as:,
is a construction part of
the join operation which says how to
structure the match items into the result.
Now before we show you the results,
let's see what should match.
The abc item in order should
match the abc in sku.
Similarly, the jkl item
should match the jkl in sku.
Okay, but there is one more twist.
Here is the actual result.
The first two records show
exactly what we expect.
There is a new field called
inventory-docs in the batching record.
The third record however,
shows something interesting.
Inventory has two records shown here,
what do they match?
Now they match the empty
document in orders because
orders has a document
whose item field is null.
So it matches documents and
inventory where the sku item is also null,
explicitly as in document 5, or
implicitly as in document 6.
This concludes our discussion of
queries in the context of MongoDB.
In this hands on activity, we'll be
using Pandas to read CSV files and
perform various queries on them.
Pandas is a data analysis library for
Python.
First, we'll create a new
Jupyter Python Notebook.
Next, we will use Pandas to read
a CSV file into a DataFrame.
We'll then view the contents of the
DataFrame and see how to filter rows and
columns of it.
Next, we will perform average and
sum operations on the DataFrame.
And finally, show how to merge two
DataFrames by joining on a single column.
Let's begin.
We'll start by creating
a new iPython notebook.
Clicking on New and
selecting Python 3 under notebooks.
First, we'll import the Pandas
library by writing import pandas.
Remember that in iPython notebooks,
to run a command,
we hold down the shift key and hit Enter.
Next, let's read buyclicks.csv
into a Pandas DataFrame.
We'll put it in a variable
called buyclicksDF.
We'll read it using pandas.read_csv,
and we'll read the buy-clicks.csv file.
We can see the contents of the file by
just running the variable by itself.
And notice that the file has many rows and
then iPython truncates this,
the dot, dot, dot.
We can see only the top five
rows by calling .head(5).
Next, let's look at only two
columns in the buyclicks data.
Let's look at price and user ID.
We can do these by first entering
buyclicks DataFrame in the same text for
specifying only certain columns to
show is open bracket open bracket and
then the name of the columns
you want to view.
So, want your price and
user ID, and again,
we only want to see the first five rows,
so we'll do .head(5).
Now, let's query the buyclicks data for
only the prices less than 3.
First, we'll enter buyclicksDF,
One square bracket,
to filter our particular column,
we enter buyclicksDF and then column name.
Now, we specify the limit of
the query by entering <3.
This shows first five rows where
the price is less than three.
We can also perform aggregate
operations on Panda's DataFrames.
We can sum all the price data by
entering buyclicksDF['price'].sum.
Another aggregate operation we can
perform is looking at the average.
Let's look at the average for price.
The function is called mean.
So, once your buyclicksDF ['price'].mean.
Can also join two DataFrames
on a single column.
First, let's read in another
CSV into a different DataFrame.
We'll read in adclicks.csv.
So we'll says adclicksDF
= pandas.read_csv,
we'll say ('ad-clicks.csv').
To verify that we read this data
successfully, let's look at the contents.
Now, let's combine
the buyclicks DataFrame and
the adclicks data frame
on the user ID call.
We'll put the result in the new
DataFrame called mergeDF.
So we'll say mergeDF = adclicksDF.merge
Then, we need to say which
DataFrame we're merging with,
buyclicksDF, and
the column that we're merging on.
So we'll say on='userid'.
Finally, we can look at the contents
with this merged DataFrame.
So now from MongoDB we will go to
Aerospike which is a key value store.
Key value stores typically offer an API.
That is the way to access data using a
programming language like Python or Java.
We will take a very brief look
at Aerospike, which offers both
a programmatic access and
a limited amount of query access to data.
The data model of Aerospike
is illustrated here.
Data are organized in lean spaces which
can be in memory or on flash disks.
Name spaces are top level data containers.
The way you collect data in name spaces
relates to how data is stored and managed.
So name space contains records,
indexes, and policies.
Now policies dictate name space
behavior like how data is stored,
whether it's on RAM or disk, or
how how many replicas exist for
a record, and when records expire.
A name space can contain sets,
you can think of them as tables.
So here there are two sets,
people and places,
and a set of records
which are not in any set.
Within a record,
data is stored in one or many bins.
Bins consist of a name and a value.
The example written here is in Java, and
you don't have to know Java to
follow the main point here.
Here we are creating indexes on key
value data that's handled by Aerospike.
This data set comes from Twitter.
Each field of a tweet is extracted and
put into Aerospike as a key value pair.
So we declare the namespace to be
example, and the record set to be tweet.
The name of the index to be TestIndex,
and the name of the bin as user name.
Since this index is stored
on disk an SQL-like command,
like SHOW INDEX, shows the content
of the index as you can see here.
This routine shows
how data can be inserted into
Aerospike programmatically.
Again, the goal is to point out a few
salient aspects of data insertion
regardless of the syntax of the language.
Now since this is a key value store,
one first needs to define the key.
This line here says that the key in
the namespace call example, and set call
tweet, is the value of the function getId,
which returns the ID of a tweet.
When the data is populated,
we are essentially creating bins.
Here, user name is the attribute and
the screen name obtained
from the tweet is the value.
The actual insertion
happens here in the client.
The client.put statement,
where we need to mention the key and
the bins we have just created.
Now why are we inserting
two bins at a time?
Two bins with two ids and user name?
This is an idiosyncrasy
of the Aerospike client.
After data is inserted one can
create other data using AQL
which is very much like SQL.
This screenshot shows a part of
the output of a simple select star query.
Now in your hands-on exercise, you'll be
able to play with the Aerospike data.
This is just a screenshot showing
the basic query syntax of AQL,
that is Aerospike Query Language,
and a few examples.
The last two lines show a couple of
interesting features of the language.
The operation between 0 and 99,
is a nicer way of stating a range query,
which gives a lower and
upper limits on a variable.
The last line shows the operation cost,
which transforms one type
of data to another type.
Here it transforms coordinates,
that is latitude and longitude data,
to a JSON format called GeoJSON which is
designed to represent geographic data
in a JSON structure.
We will finish our coverage of queries
with a quick reference to an advanced
topic, which is beyond
the scope of this course.
Now you have seen in prior courses that
streaming data is complex to process
because a stream is infinite in nature.
Now does this have any impact on
query languages and evaluation?
The answer is that it absolutely does.
We'll mention one such impact here.
This shows a pictorial
depiction of streaming data.
The data is segmented into five pieces,
shown in the white boxes in the upper row.
These can be gathered, for example every
few seconds, or every 200 data objects.
The query defines a window to select
key of these data objects
as a unit of processing.
Here case three.
So three units of data
are picked up in a window unit.
To get the next window it
is moved by two units,
this is called a slide of the window.
Since the window size is three and
the slide is two,
one unit of information overlaps
between the two consecutive windows.
The lower line in this diagram shows
the initialized item, let's ignore it,
followed by two window sets of
data records for processing.
Thus the query language therefore,
will have to specify a query
that's an SQL query, over a window,
which is also specified in the query.
Now in a traffic data stream example,
the SQL statement might look like this.
Where the window size is 30 second, and
the slide is the same size as window
giving output every 30 seconds.
So streaming data results in changes
in both the query language and
the way queries are processed.