Next we'll consider queries
where two tables are used.
Let's consider the query,
find the beers liked by drinkers who
frequent The Great American Bar.
For this query, we need
the relation's Frequents and Likes.
Now look at the scheme of these
relations in the light blue box.
They have a common
attribute called drinker.
So if we use the attribute drinker,
we need to tell the system
which one we are referring to.
Now look at the SQL query, the FROM clause
in the query has these two relations.
To handle a common attribute name issue,
we need to give nicknames,
aliases to these relations.
Therefore in the FROM clause we say,
Likes has the alias L and
Frequents has the alias F.
Since we want to find beers like before,
we use a SELECT DISTINCT clause for beer.
As we saw before, using SELECT DISTINCT
avoids duplicates in the result.
The WHERE clause has two
kinds of conditions,
the first kind is
a single table condition.
In this case, bar = The Great American Bar
on the Frequents relation.
The second kind is a joined condition
which says that the drinker's attribute in
the frequency relation is the same as the
drinker's attribute of the Likes relation.
We encode this in SQL in the last
line of the query using aliases.
Why did we not say L.beer in the SELECT
clause or F.bar in the first condition?
We could have,
the query would have been equally right.
But we are using a shortcut because we
know that these attributes are unique
already in the query.
Now let's look at the query again,
this time from the viewpoint
of evaluating the query.
There are many ways to evaluate the query,
but
the way it's most likely
to be evaluated is this.
The query will first look at the tables
that have single table conditions.
So it would perform a select operation
on the Frequents table to match
the records of the condition
that The Great American Bar
equal to The Great American Bar.
Why is this strategy good?
It's because the selection operative
reduces the number of triples to consider.
Thus, if there are thousand
triples in the relation frequents,
maybe 60 of them matches the desired bar.
So in the next step, we have to deal with
a fewer number of records than thousand.
All right, the next step will
be a Join with a Likes relation.
A Join requires two relations
in a Join condition,
the Join condition comes from the query.
The first relation shown with
an underscore symbol here
is a result of the previous operation.
Another way of saying this
is that the result of
the selection is piped
into the Join operation.
That means we do not create
an intermediate table from
the result of the selection.
The results are directly supplied to the
next operator, which in this case is Join.
Now the result of the Join operator is an
intermediate structure with columns beer
from Likes relation and
the drinker from the Frequents
relation that we've processed.
This intermediate set of triples is
piped to the Project operation that
picks up the beer column.
Now we need to process
the DISTINCT clause for
Deduplicate elimination,
which then goes to the Output.
We have already seen how the select
project queries on single tables
are evaluated when the tables
are partitioned across several machines.
We'll now see how we process Join
queries in the same setting.
For our case, consider that the Likes and
Frequents tables are on
two different machines.
In the first part of the query,
the selection happens on the machine
with the Frequents table.
The output of the query is a smaller
table with the same scheme as Frequents,
that is with drinkers and bars.
Now we define an operation
called Semijoin,
in which we need to move data
from one machine to another.
The goal of the Semijoin operation is
to reduce the cost of data movement.
That is to move data from
the machine which has
the Frequents data to
the machine with the Likes data.
The cost is reduced if we ship less data.
The way to it is to first find which
data the join operation actually needs.
Clearly, it needs only the drinkers
column and not the bars column.
So the drinkers column is projected out,
then
just this column is transmitted
to the second machine.
Finally, the join is performed by looking
at the values in the Likes column
that only matches the values
in the shipped data.
That means only the data from Likes that
matches the drinkers that are chosen.
These are then the join results which
would go to the output of the operation.
Now here you can see the Semijoin
operation graphically.
The red table on the left is the output
of the selection operations on the left.
The white table on the right
is the table to be joined to.
Since we need only the Drinkers column,
it is projected to create
a one-column relation.
Notice that the red table has two entries
for Pete, who frequented two bars.
But the output of the project
is condensed in the yellow table
to just show the Drinkers,
where Pete appears only once.
For those of you with
a background in computer science,
this can be done using a hash
map like data structure.
This one-column table is now shipped
to Site2, which has the Likes relation.
Now at Site2, the Shipped relation
is used to find matches from
the Drinkers column and
it finds only one match called Sally.
So the corresponding result triples,
in this case,
only one triple is produced
at the end of this operation.
Now, the original table and
the matching table are shipped
to the last of the operation
to finish the Join operation.
And more efficient version of
this is shown in the next slide.
In this version, the first two
steps this and that are the same.
Then the result of the reduce
is also shipped to Site1 to find
the matches from the red relation.
Another reduce operation
is performed on Site1 now
to get the matching records
on the red relation.
Finally, these two reduced
relations are shipped to
the site where the final join happens.
And all of this may seem
like a lot of detail.
Let me repeat something I've said before.
If we have a system like DB2 or Spark SQL
that implements multi-site joins, it
will perform this kind of operation under
the hood, you don't have to know them.
However, if we were to implement
a similar operation and all that you have
is Hadoop, you may end up implementing
this kind of algorithm yourself.
The queries in real life are little more
complex than what we have seen before.
So let's consider a more complex query.
Let’s find bars where the price
of Miller is the same as or
less than what the great American bar
called TGAB here charges for Bud.
You may say, but we do not really
know what TGAB charges for Bud.
That's correct, so
we can break up the query into two parts.
First, we will find this unknown price,
and then we'll use that price
to find the bars that would sell Miller
for the same price or better price.
Now this is a classic situation where
the result from the first part of
the query should be fed as
a parameter to the second query.
Now this situation is called a subquery.
We write this in SQL as
shown in the slide here.
What makes this query different is that
the part where price is less than equal
to, instead of specifying
a constant like $8,
we actually place another query which
computes the price of a Bud at TGAB.
The shaded part is called the inner query,
or the subquery.
In this case, both the outer query and
the inner query use the same relation,
which is Sells.
Now in terms of evaluation,
the inner query is evaluated first,
and the outer query uses its output.
Now while it may not be
obvious at this time,
notice that the inner query is
independent of the outer query.
In other words,
even if we did not have the outer query,
we can still evaluate the inner query.
We say in this case that
the subquery is uncorrelated.
Let's look at another
example of a subquery.
In this example,
we want to find the name and
manufacturer of each beer
that Fred didn't like.
So how do we know what Fred didn't like?
We do however know that the set of
beers that Fred likes because they
are listed in the Likes relation.
So we need to subtract this set from the
total set of beers that the company has
recorded.
This subtraction of sets can
be performed in several ways.
One of them is to use
the NOT IN construct.
So the query class's job is to take
every name from the Beers table and
output it only if it does not appear
in the set produced by the inner query.
Similar to the previous query,
the subquery here is also uncorrelated.
Now this is a more sophisticated query.
The intention is to find
beers that are more expensive
than the average price of beer.
But since beers have different
prices in different bars,
we have to find the average for every bar.
Therefore the idea is to find
the average price of beer for
every bar and then compare the price of
each beer with respect to this average.
Now look at the query and the table.
Let's assume we are processing
the first table.
The beer is Bud, and the price is $5.
Now we need to know if $5 is greater than
the average price of beer sold at HGAT.
To do this,
we need to compute the inner query, okay?
So now let's look at the fourth row.
The price of Guinness needs to be
compared to that average again for HGAT.
In fact for
every table processed by the outer query,
one needs to compute the inner query for
that bar.
This makes the inner subquery
correlated with the outer query.
Now a smart query processor will store
the average once it's computed and
then reuse the stored value instead
of computing over and over again.
What's an aggregate query?
Let's use a simple example of
finding the average price of Bud.
This is like a simple select project
query with the additional aspect
that it takes a list of price values
of Bud from different bars and
then computes an average.
In the example shown,
the average of the five prices is 4.2.
In other words the average function,
the AVG function, takes a list of
values and produces a single value.
Now there are many functions
that have this behavior.
The SUM function takes
a list of values and
adds them up to produce a single value.
The COUNT function takes
a list of list of values and
counts the number of items
in that list and so on.
These are called aggregate functions.
Now if we wanted to count only the price
values that are different, that is 3,
4, and 5 just once, we can write
the SELECT clause a little differently.
We would say that the average
is over distinct values
of price which in this
case will result in 4.
You should recognize that most analytical
operations need to use statistical
functions which are aggregates.
So another important
analytical requirement
is computing the statistical
aggregate by groups.
For example, we often compute the average
salaries of employees per department.
Now back to our example here,
we want to find the average price paid for
Bud per drinker, where we know
that a drinker visits many bars.
So the grouping variable here is drinker.
So we have three attributes at play,
price which we need to aggregate,
drinker which we need to group by,
and bar which is a join attribute.
The fourth attribute, namely beer,
is used for selection and
does not participate in grouping.
So after the selection we will
get an intermediate relation
containing drinker, bar, and price.
With this, the GROUP BY operation
will create one result row for
each drinker and place the average
price over all such rows.
Now how does GROUP BY and
aggregate computation work
when the data is partitioned?
Let's take the same query.
We are looking for the average
price of Bud grouped by drinker.
But this time the result of the selection
are in two different machines.
Imagine that this time they are range
partitioned by row numbers,
which we have not shown
to maintain clarity.
Now with the GROUP BY operation the data
will get repartitioned by the grouping
attribute, that's drinker.
And then the aggregate
function is computed locally.
To accomplish this repartitioning task,
each machine groups its own data locally,
determines which portions of data should
be transmitted to a different machine,
and accordingly ships it to that machine.
Now there are several variants
of this general scheme
which are even more efficient.
Now if this reminds you of the map
operation you saw in your previous course,
you are exactly right.
This fundamental process of grouping,
partitioning, and redistribution of data
is inherent in data-parallel computing and
implemented inside database systems.
Welcome back.
In this video, we will provide you
a quick summary of the main points from
our last course on big data modeling and
management.
If you had just completed our second
course and do not need a refresher,
you may now skip to the next lecture.
After this video, you will be able
to recall why big data modeling and
management is essential in preparing
to gain insights from your data,
summarize different kids of data models.
Describe streaming data and the different challenges
it presents, and explain the differences
between a database management system and
a big data management system.
In the second course, we described
a data model as a specification
that precisely characterizes
the structure of the data,
the operations on the data, and
the constraints that may apply on data.
For example, a data model may state that
a data is structured like
a two-dimensional array or a matrix.
For this structure,
one may have a data access operation,
which given an index of the array,
we use the cell of the array to refer to.
A data model may also specify
constraints on the data.
For example, while a total
data set may have many arrays,
the name of each array must be unique and
the values of a specific array
must always be greater than zero.
Database management systems handle
low level data management operations,
help organization of the data
using a data model, and
provide an open programmable
access to data.
We covered a number of data models.
We showed four models that were
discussed in more details.
The relational data to date
is the most used data model.
Here, data is structured like tables
which are formally called relations.
The relational data model has been
implemented in traditional database
systems.
But they are being refreshly implemented
in modern data systems over Hadoop and
Spark and
are getting deployed on cloud platforms.
The second category of data gaining
popularity is semi-structured data,
which includes documents like HTML pages,
XML data and
JSON data that are used by
many Internet applications.
This data can have one element nested or
embedded within another data element and
hence can often be modeled as a tree.
The third category of data
models is called graph data.
A graph is a network where
nodes represent entities and
edges represent relationships
between pairs of such entities.
For example, in a social network,
nodes may represent users and
edges may represent their friendship.
The operations performed on graph data
includes traversing the network so
that one can find friend of
a friend of a friend if needed.
In contrast to the previous three models,
that there is a structure to the data,
the text data is much more unstructured
because an entire data item
like a new article can
be just a text string.
However, text is the primary form of data
in information retrieval systems or
search engines like Google.
We also discussed streaming data,
or data with velocity, as a special
class of data that continually come
to the system at some data rate.
Examples can be found in data coming
from road sensors that measure traffic
patterns or stock price data from
the stock exchange that may come
in volumes from stock
exchanges all over the world.
Streaming data is special because a stream
is technically an infinite data source.
And therefore,
we keep filling up memory and
storage and will eventually go
beyond the capacity of any system.
Streaming data, therefore, needs
a different kind of management system.
For this reason,
streaming data is processed in memory,
in chunks which are also called windows.
Often only the necessary
part of the data stream or
the results of queries against
the data stream is stored.
A typical type of query against streaming
data are alerts or notifications.
The system notices an event like multiple
stock price changing within a short time.
Streaming data is also used for
prediction.
For instance, based on wind direction and
temperature data streams,
one can predict how a wildfire
is going to spread.
In the last course, we also covered
a number of data systems that we called
big data management systems.
These systems use
different data models and
have different capabilities, but
are characterized by some common features.
They are also designed from the start for
parallel and distributed processing.
Most of them implement data partition
parallelism, which, if you can recall,
refers to the process of segmenting
the data into multiple machines so
data retrieval and manipulations can be
performed in parallel on these machines.
Many of these systems allow a large
number of users who constantly update and
query the system.
Some of the systems do not maintain
transaction consistency with every update.
That means,
not all the machines may have all
the updates guaranteed at every moment.
However, most of them provide
a guarantee of eventual consistency,
which means all the machines will
get all updates sooner or later.
Therefore, providing better accuracy and
time.
The third common characteristic
of big data management systems is
that they are often built on top of
a Hadoop-like platform that provides
automatic replication and
a map-reduce style processing ability.
Some of the data operations performed
within these systems make use of these
lower level capabilities.
After this refresher on data modeling and
management, let's start big data
integration and processing.
So, hi.
In the previous course, we saw
examples of different data models and
talked about a few current
data management systems.
In this module,
we'll focus on data retrieval.
Data retrieval refers to
the way in which data desired
by a user is specified and
retrieved from a data store.
Note that in this course, we are using
the term data retrieval in two ways.
Assume that your data is stored in a data
store that follows a specific data model,
like for
example the relational data model.
By data retrieval, we will refer to, one,
the way you specify how to get
the desired data out of the system,
this is called the query
specification method, and two,
the internal processing that occurs within
the data management system to compute or
evaluate that specified retrieval request.
While query specification can apply to
small data stores or large data stores,
we'll keep an eye on the nature of
query evaluation when the data is big.
Further, we'll consider how
the query specification changes
when we deal with faster streaming data.
A query language is a language in which
a retrieval request is specified.
A query language is often called
declarative, which means it lets you
specify what you want to retrieve without
having to tell the system how to retrieve.
For example, you can say,
find all data from relation employee
where the salary is more than 50k.
Now, you don't have to write a program
which will tell the system to open a file,
skip the first 250 bytes,
then in a loop pick the next 1024 bytes,
probe into the 600th byte and
read an integer, and so forth.
Instead of writing such
a complicated procedure,
you just specify the data items that
you need and the system does the rest.
For example, SQL,
structured query language,
is the most used query language for
relational data.
Now, in contrast to a query language,
a database programming
language like Oracle's PL/SQL or
Postgres's PgSQL are high-level
procedural programming languages
that embed query operations.
We will look at some query
languages in detail and
show examples of database
programming languages.
The first query language
we'll look at is SQL,
which is the ubiquitous query
language when the data is structured,
but has been extended in many ways
to accommodate other types of data.
For this course, we'll stick to
the structured aspect of the language.
Now, you should know that SQL is used for
classical database management systems
like Oracle as well as modern Hadoop
style distributed systems such as Spark.
Now, we will work with
an illustrative example.
First, we need to define
the schema of the database.
Now, think of a business called the
Beer Drinkers Club that owns many bars,
and each bar sells beer.
Our schema for
this business has six relations of tables.
The first table lists these bars,
the names, addresses, and
the license number of the bar.
Notice that the attribute name is
underlined because it is the primary key
of the bars relation.
Recall that the primary key
refers to a set of attributes,
in this case just the name,
that makes a record unique.
Note that the relation bars
with the attribute name
within parenthesis is the same
as the table shown on the right.
We will use both representations
as we go forward.
The second table called Beers, this is
the names and manufacturers of beer.
Now, not every bar sells the same
brands of beer, and even when they do,
they may have different prices for
the same product because of differences
in the establishment costs.
So the Sells table records which
bar sells which beer at what price.
Now, our business is special.
It also keeps information about
the regular member customers.
So the Drinkers relation has the name,
address, and phone of these customers.
Well, not only that,
it knows which member visits
which bars and
which beer each member likes.
Clearly, the Beer Drinkers Club
knows its customers.
The most basic structure of an SQL
query is a SELECT-FROM-WHERE clause.
In this example, we're looking for
beer names that are made by Heineken.
So we need to specify
our output attribute,
in this case the name of the beer.
The logical table which will be used to
answer the query, in this case, Beers.
And the condition that all the desired
data items should satisfy,
namely, the value of the attribute
called manf is Heineken.
Now, there are few things to notice here.
First, the literal Heineken
is put within quotes,
because it's a single string literal.
Remember that in this case,
the string is supposed to match exactly,
including the case.
Secondly, if you go back to the data
operations discussed in course two,
you will recognize that this form
of query can also be represented
as a selection operation on the relation
Beers with a condition on the manf
attribute, followed by
a projection operation
that outputs the name attribute from
the result of the selection operation.
So the selection operation finds all
tuples of beer for which the manufacturer
is Heineken, and from those tuples
it projects only the name column.
The result of the query is a table
with one single attribute called name.
We illustrate some more features of SQL,
using two example queries.
The first looks for
expensive beer and its price.
Let's say we consider a beer to be
expensive if it costs more than $15
per bottle.
From the schema,
we know that the price information is
available in the table called Sells.
So the FROM clause should use Sells.
The WHERE clause is intuitive and
specifies the price of the beer
to be greater than 15.
Now notice that the Sells relation
also has a column called bar.
Now, if two different bars sell
the same beer at the same price,
we'll get both entries in the result.
But that's not what we want.
Now regardless of the multiplicity
of bars that have the same price for
the same beer,
we want the result just once.
So this is achieved through
the SELECT DISTINCT statement,
which ensures that the result
relation will have no duplicate.
The second example shows the case
where more than one condition
must be specified by the result.
In this query,
the business must be in San Diego and
at the same time it must be
a temporary license holder,
which means the license
number should start with 32.
As we see here, these conditions
are put together by the AND operator.
Thus, the query will pick
the third record in the table
because the first record satisfy the first
condition and not the second condition.
In a few slides, we'll come back to
the evaluation of this type of queries
in the context of big data.
Now, remember, one can also place a limit
on the number of results to return.
If our database is large, and
we need only five results, for
example, for a sample to display,
we can say LIMIT 5.
Now, the exact syntax of this LIMIT
clause may vary between DBMS vendors.
Now if the table of beers was large and
had millions of entries,
the table would possibly need
to be split over many machines.
Another way of saying that is that
the table will be partitioned
across a number of machines.
Since a query simply
performs a selection and
projection here,
it can be evaluated in parallel.
Remember that name is
the primary key of the table.
One standard way of partitioning the data
is called a range partitioning
by the primary key.
This simply means that the rows
of the table are put in groups
depending on the alphabetical
order of the name value.
So beers with names starting with E and
B here are placed in Machine 1.
Those starting with C and
D are in Machine 2.
And if there are too many rows for
entries where the name starts with H,
maybe H is split into Machines 5 and 6.
This is shown in the sketch here.
Next, we will show how queries
are performed over partition tables.
But before we do that, you should know
that all database management companies,
like IBM, Chair Data, Microsoft, and
others, have a solution like this for
large volumes of data,
where data partitioning is used.
Newer systems, like Spark and SQL,
are naturally distributed, and
therefore, offer data partitioning.
So, we show the same partition
tables as we saw before.
Now we'll ask two queries.
The first query asks for
all tuples as records from the beers table
where the name of the beer starts with Am.
And the second query is
exactly what we asked before.
The first query in
the SQL looks like this.
We said SELECT* FROM Beers to mean
all attributes from table beers.
The WHERE clause shows the syntax for
a partial match query.
In this query,
there are two new syntax elements.
The first is a predicate called like.
When we use like,
we're telling the query engine
that we only have partial information
about the string we want to match.
This partly specified string
is called a string pattern.
That means, there is this part
of the string we know and
a part that we do not know.
In this case, we know that our design
string starts with Am, so we'd write Am,
and then we put % to refer to the part
of the string that we do not know.
Putting them together, we get Am%.
If we wanted to find, say,
Am somewhere in the middle of the string,
we would write the pattern as %Am%.
The second query is not new.
We saw it in the last slide.
However, as we'll see next, evaluating
the second query will be a little more
tricky in a partition database than
that we usually see for big data.
Let's talk about the first query
in this data partition setting.
The question to ask is, do we need to
touch all partitions to answer the query?
Of course not, we know that the name is
a primary key for the table of beers.
We also know that the system did arrange
partitioning on the name attribute.
This means that the evaluation
process should only access Machine 1
because no other machine will have
records for names starting with A.
Now this is exactly what we, as humans,
do when we look up an entry in
a multivolume encyclopedia.
We look for the starting words, then
figure out which specific volume would
have that entry,
then pick up just that volume.
Thus, so long as the system
knows the partitioning strategy,
it can make its job much more efficient.
When a system processes
thousands of queries per second,
this kind of efficiency actually matters.
Now raised partitioning is
only one of many partitioning
schemes used in a database system, okay.
Let's try to answer the second query
in the same partition setting.
Now the query condition is on
the second attribute, manf.
Now in one sense, it's a simpler query.
There is no light pattern here, and
we know exactly the string that we are
looking for, namely the string Heineken.
However, this time,
we really cannot get away
by using the partitioning information
because the partitioning activity is
different from the attribute on which
the query condition is applied.
So this query will need
to go to all partitions.
Technically speaking,
the query needs to be broadcast
from the primary machine to all machines,
as shown here.
Next, this broadcast query
will be independently, and
in parallel,
execute the query on the local machine.
Then, these results need to be
brought back into the primary machine.
And then,
they need to be unioned together.
And only then, the results can be
formed and returned to the client.
Now, this might seem
like a lot of extra work.
However, remember, the shaded part of
the query is executed in parallel,
which is the essence of
dealing with large data.
Now, at this point, you might be thinking,
wait a minute, what if I had 100 machines,
and the desired data
is only in 20 of them?
Should we needlessly go through all 100
machines, find nothing in 80 of them, and
return 0 results from those machines?
Then why do the extra work?
Can it not be avoided?
Well, to do this, it would need
one more piece in the solution,
it's called an index structure.
Very simply,
an index can be thought of as a reverse
table, where given the value in a column,
you would get back the records where the
value appears as shown in the figure here.
Using an index speeds up query
processing significantly.
With indexes, we can solve this
problem in many different ways.
The top table shows the case where
each machine has its own index for
the manf column.
This is called a local index because
the index is in every machine
that holds the data for
that table on that machine.
In this case,
looking up Heineken in the index,
we would know which records
would have the data.
Since the index is local, the main query
will indeed go to all machines, but
the lookup will be really instant, and the
empty results would return very quickly.
In the second case,
we adopted a different solution.
Here, there is an index on the main
machine, all on a separate index server.
Now when we place a data
record in a machine,
this index keeps an account of the machine
that contains the record with that value.
Look at the second table to the right.
Given the value of Heineken,
we know that it is only in three machines,
and therefore,
we can avoid going to the other machines.
Clearly, we can always use
both indexing schemes.
This will use more space,
but queries will be faster.
Now this gives you some of the choices
you may need to make with big data,
whether you use a parallel DBMS or
a distributed data solution.