Data Science.
Getting value out of big data.
We have all heard data science turned
data into insights or even actions.
But what does that really mean?
Data science can be
thought of as a basis for
empirical research where data is used
to induce information for observations.
These observations are mainly data,
in our case,
big data, related to a business or
scientific case.
Insight is a term
we use to refer to the data
products of data science.
It is extracted from a diverse amount
of data through a combination of
exploratory data analysis and modeling.
The questions are sometimes more specific,
and sometimes it requires
looking at the data and patterns in it
to come up with the specific question.
Another important point to recognize
is that data science is not static.
It is not one time analysis.
It involves a process where models
generated to lead to insights
are constantly improved through further
empirical evidence, or simply, data.
For example, a book retailer like
Amazon.com can constantly improve
the model of a customer's book preferences
using the customer demographic,
his or her previous purchases and
the book reviews of the customer.
The book retailer can also
uses information to predict
which customers are likely
to like any book,
and take action to market
the book to those customers.
This is where we see insights
being turned into action.
As we have seen in the book marketing
example, using data science and analysis
of the past and current information,
data science generates actions.
This is not just an analysis of the past,
but
rather generation of actionable
information for the future.
This is what we can call a prediction,
like the weather forecast.
When you decide what to wear for
the day based on the forecast of the day,
you are taking action based
on insight delivered to you.
Just like this, business leaders and
decision makers
take action based on the evidence
provided by their data science teams.
We set data science teams.
This comes from the breadth of information
and skill that it takes to make it happen.
You have probably seen diagrams like
this one that describe data science.
Data science happens at
the intersection of computer science,
mathematics and business expertise.
If we zoom deeper into this diagram and
open the sets of expertise we will
see a variation of this figure.
Even at this level, all of these circles
require deeper knowledge and skills
in areas like domain expertise, data
engineering, statistics and computing.
An even deeper analysis of these
skills will lead you to skills like
machine learning, statistical modeling,
relational algebra,
business passion, problem solving and
data visualization.
That's a lot of skills to have for
a single person.
These wide range of skills and
definitions of data scientists having them
all led to discussions like
are data scientists unicorns?
Meaning they don't exist.
There are data science experts who have
expertise in more than one of these
skills, for sure.
But they're relatively rare, and
still would probably need help from
an expert on some of these areas.
So, in reality, data scientists
are teams of people who act like one.
They are passionate about the story and
the meaning behind data.
They understand they problem
they are trying to solve, and
aim to find the right analytical
methods to solve this problem.
And they all have an interest in
engineering solutions to solve problems.
They also have curiosity about each
others work, and have communication
skills to interact with the team and
present their ideas and results to others.
As a summary, a data science team often
comes together to analyze situations,
business or scientific cases, which none
of the individuals can solve on their own.
There are lots of moving
parts to the solution.
But in the end, all these parts
should come together to provide
actionable insight based on big data.
Being able to use evidence-based
insight in business decisions is more
important now than ever.
Data scientists have a combination
of technical, business and
soft skills to make this happen.
Getting started,
characteristics of big data.
By now you have seen that big data is a
blanket term that is used to refer to any
collection of data so large and
complex that it exceeds the processing
capability of conventional data
management systems and techniques.
The applications of big data are endless.
Every part of business and society
are changing in front our eyes due to that
fact that we now have so much more
data and the ability for analyzing.
But how can we characterize big data?
You can say, I know it when i see it.
But there are easier ways to do it.
Big data is commonly characterized
using a number of V's.
The first three are volume,
velocity, and variety.
Volume refers to the vast amounts of
data that is generated every second,
mInutes, hour, and
day in our digitized world.
Variety refers to the ever increasing
different forms that data can come in
such as text, images,
voice, and geospatial data.
Velocity refers to the speed at
which data is being generated and
the pace at which data moves
from one point to the next.
Volume, variety, and
velocity are the three main dimensions
that characterize big data.
And describe its challenges.
We have huge amounts of data
in different formats, and
varying quality which must
be processed quickly.
More Vs have been introduced
to the big data community
as we discover new challenges and
ways to define big data.
Veracity and
valence are two of these additional V's we
will pay special attention to as
a part of this specialization.
Veracity refers to the biases,
noise, and abnormality in data.
Or, better yet, It refers to the often
unmeasurable uncertainties and
truthfulness and trustworthiness of data.
Valence refers to the connectedness
of big data in the form of graphs,
just like atoms.
Moreover, we must be sure to
never forget our sixth V, value.
How do big data benefit you and
your organization?
Without a clear strategy and
an objective with the value
they are getting from big data.
It is easy to imagine that organizations
will be sidetracked by all these
challenges of big data, and not be
able to turn them into opportunities.
Now let's start looking into the first
five of these V's in detail.
How does data science happen?
Five P's of data science.
Now that we identified what data science
is and how companies can strategize around
big data to start building a purpose,
let's come back to using data science
to get value out of big data around
the purpose or questions they defined.
Our experience with building and
observing successful data science projects
led to a method around the craft with
five distinct components that can be
defined as components of data science.
Here we define data science
as a multi-disciplinary
craft that combines
people teaming up around
application-specific purpose that
can be achieved through a process,
big data computing platforms,
and programmability.
All of these should lead to
products where the focus really
is on the questions or purpose that are
defined by your big data strategy ideas.
There are many technology,
data and analytical research, and
development related activities
around the questions.
But in the end, everything we do
in this phase is to reach to that
final product based on our purposes.
So, it makes sense to start with it and
build a process around how
we make this product happen.
Remember the wild fire
prediction project I described?
One of the products we described
there was the rate of spread and
direction of an ongoing fire.
We have identified questions and
the process that led us to
the product in the end to solve it.
We brought together experts around
the table for fire modeling,
data management, time series analysis,
scalable computing,
Geographical Information Systems,
and emergency response.
I asked them,
let's not dive into the techniques yet.
What is the problem at large?
How do we see ourselves solving it?
A typical conversation around
the process starts with this question.
Then from then on,
drilling down to many areas of expertise,
often we blur lines between the steps.
My wildfire team would start listing
things like, we don't have an integrated
system or we don't have real-time
access to data programmatically,
so we can't analyze fires on the fly.
Or they can say, I can't integrate
sensor data with satellite data.
All of this leads me to challenges
I can then use to define problems.
There are many dimensions of data science
to think about within this discussion.
Let's start with the obvious ones,
people and purpose.
People refers to a data science team or
the projects stakeholders.
As you know by now,
they're expert in data and
analytics, business, computing,
science, or big data management,
like all the set of experts I
listed in my wildfire scenario.
The purpose refers to the challenge or
set of challenges defined by your
big data strategy, like solving the
question related to the rate of spread and
direction of the fire perimeter
in the wildfire case.
Since there's a predefined team
with a purpose, a great place for
this team to start with is
a process they could iterate on.
We can simply say, people with purpose
will define a process to collaborate and
communicate around.
The process is conceptual
in the beginning and
defines the set of steps an how
everyone can contribute to it.
There are many ways to
look at the process.
One way of looking at it is
as two distinct activities,
mainly big data engineering and
big data analytics, or
computational big data science,
as I like to call it, as more than simple
analytics is being performed here.
A more detailed way of looking at
the process reveals five distinct steps or
activities of this data science process,
namely acquire, prepare,
analyze, report, and act.
We can simply say that
data science happens
at the boundary of all these steps.
Ideally, this process should
support experimental work and
dynamic scalability on the big data and
computing platforms.
This five step process can be used in
alternative ways in real life big data
applications, if we add the dependencies
of different tools to each other.
The influence of big data pushes for
alternative scalability approaches
at each step of the process.
Just like you would scale
each step on its own,
you can scale the whole
process as a whole in the end.
One can simply say, all of these steps
have reporting needs in different forms.
Or there is a need to draw all these
activities as an iterating process,
including build, explore, and
scale for big data as steps.
Big data analysis needs alternative
data management techniques and
systems, as well as analytical tools and
methods.
Multiple modes of scalability is needed
based on dynamic data and computing loads.
In addition,
change in physical infrastructure,
streaming data specific urgencies
arising from special events
can also require multiple
modes of scalability.
In this intro course, for simplicity,
we will refer to the process as a set of
five sequential activities that iterate.
However, we'll touch on scalability as
needed in our example applications.
As a part of building
your big data process,
it's important to simply
mention two other P's.
The first one is big data platforms,
like the ones in the Hadoop framework,
or other computing platforms
to scale different steps.
The scalability should be in
the mind of all team members and
get communicated as an expectation.
In addition, the scalable process
should be programmable through
utilization of reusable and
reproducible programming interfaces
to libraries, like systems middleware,
analytical tools,
visualization environments, and
end user reporting environments.
Thinking of big data
applications as a process,
including a set of activities that
the team members can collaborate over,
also helps to build metrics for
accountability to be built into it.
This way, expectations on cost, time,
optimization of deliverables,
and time lines can be discussed
between the the members starting with
the beginning of the data science process.
Sometimes we may not be able
to do this in one step.
And joint explorations like statistical
evaluations of intermediate results or
accuracy of sample data
sets become important.
As a summary, data science can be
defined as a craft of using the five P's
identified in this lecture,
leading to a sixth P, the data product.
Having a process within the more
business-driven Ps, like people and
purpose, and the more technically
driven P's, like platforms and
programmability, leads to
a streamlined approach that starts and
ends with the product, team
accountability, and collaboration in mind.
Data science process
provides guidelines for
implementing big data solution,
as it helps to organize efforts and
ensures all critical steps taken conforms
to pre-define and agreed upon metrics.
Step one, acquiring data.
The first step in the data science
process is to acquire the data.
You need to obtain the source material
before analyzing or acting on it.
The first step in acquiring data is
to determine what data is available.
Leave no stone unturned when it comes
to finding the right data sources.
You want to identify suitable
data related to your problem and
make use of all data that is relevant
to your problem for analysis.
Leaving out even a small
amount of important data
can lead to incorrect conclusions.
Data, comes from, many places, local and
remote, in many varieties,
structured and un-structured.
And, with different velocities.
There are many techniques and technologies
to access these different types of data.
Let's discuss a few examples.
A lot of data exists in
conventional relational databases,
like structure big data
from organizations.
The tool of choice to access data from
databases is structured query language or
SQL, which is supported by all
relational databases management systems.
Additionally, most data base systems
come with a graphical application
environment that allows you to query and
explore the data sets in the database.
Data can also exist in files such as
text files and Excel spreadsheets.
Scripting languages are generally
used to get data from files.
A scripting language is a high
level programming language
that can be either general purpose or
specialized for specific functions.
Common scripting languages with support
for processing files are Java Script,
Python, PHP, Perl, R, and
MATLAB, and are many others.
An increasingly popular way
to get data is from websites.
Web pages are written using
a set of standards approved by
a world wide web consortium or
shortly, W3C.
This includes a variety of formats and
services.
One common format is
the Extensible Markup Language, or XML,
which uses markup symbols or tabs to
describe the contents on a webpage.
Many websites also host web services which
produce program access to their data.
There are several types of web services.
The most popular is REST because it's so
easy to use.
REST stand for
Representational State Transfer.
And it is an approach to implementing
web services with performance,
scalability and maintainability in mind.
Web socket services are also
becoming more popular
since they allow real time
modifications from web sites.
NoSQL storage systems are increasingly
used to manage a variety of data
types in big data.
These data stores are databases
that do not represent data
in a table format with columns and rows as
with conventional relational databases.
Examples of these data stores include
Cassandra, MongoDB and HBASE.
NoSQL data stores provide APIs
to allow users to access data.
These APIs can be used directly or in an
application that needs to access the data.
Additionally, most NoSQL
systems provide data access
via a web service interface, such a REST.
Now, let's discuss our wildfire case study
as a real project that acquires data
using several different mechanisms.
The WIFIRE project stores sensor data from
weather stations in a relational database.
We use SQL to retrieve this data
from the database to create
models to identify weather patterns
associated with Santa Anna conditions.
To determine whether a particular weather
station is currently experiencing
Santa Anna conditions, we access real
time data using a web socket service.
Once we start listening to this service,
we receive weather station
measurements as they occur.
This data is then processed and
compared to patterns found by our models
to determine if a weather station is
experiencing Santa Ana conditions.
At the same time Tweets are retrieved
using hashtags related to any fire
that is occurring in the region.
The Tweet messages are retrieves
using the Twitter REST service.
The idea is to determine the sentiment
of these tweets to see if people
are expressing fear, anger or are simply
nonchalant about the nearby fire.
The combination of sensor data and
tweet sentiments helps
to give us a sense of the urgency
of the fire situation.
As a summary,
big data comes from many places.
Finding and evaluating data
useful to your big data analytics is
important before you start acquiring data.
Depending on the source and
structure of data,
there are alternative ways to access it.
Step 2-A: Exploring Data
After you've put together the data
that you need for your application,
you might be tempted to immediately
build models to analyze the data.
Resist this temptation.
The first step after getting
your data is to explore it.
Exploring data is a part of
the two-step data preparation process.
You want to do some
preliminary investigation
in order to gain a better understanding of
the specific characteristics of your data.
In this step, you'll be looking for
things like correlations,
general trends, and outliers.
Without this step, you will not be
able to use the data effectively.
Correlation graphs can be used
to explore the dependencies
between different variables in the data.
Graphing the general trends of
variables will show you if there is
a consistent direction in which the values
of these variables are moving towards,
like sales prices going up or down.
In statistics, an outlier is a data point
that's distant from other data points.
Plotting outliers will
help you double check for
errors in the data due to measurements.
In some cases, outliers that are not
errors might make you find a rare event.
Additionally, summary statistics provide
numerical values to describe your data.
Summary statistics are quantities
that capture various characteristics
of a set of values with a single number or
a small set of numbers.
Some basic summary statistics
that you should compute for
your data set are mean, median,
range, and standard deviation.
Mean and median are measures of
the location of a set of values.
Mode is the value that occurs
most frequently in your data set.
And range and standard deviation
are measures of spread in your data.
Looking at these measures will give you
an idea of the nature of your data.
They can tell you if there's
something wrong with your data.
For example, if the range of the values
for age in your data includes
negative numbers, or
a number much greater than 100,
there's something suspicious in
the data that needs to be examined.
Visualization techniques also
provide a quick and effective, and
overall a very useful way to look at
data in this preliminary analysis step.
A heat map, such as the one shown here,
can quickly give you the idea
of where the hotspots are.
Many other different types
of graphs can be used.
Histograms show that
the distribution of the data and
can show skewness or unusual dispersion.
Boxplots are another type of plot for
showing data distribution.
Line graphs are useful for seeing how
values in your data change over time.
Spikes in the data are also easy to spot.
Scatter plots can show you
correlation between two variables.
Overall, there are many types
of graph to visualize data.
They are very useful in helping
you understand the data you have.
In summary, what you get by
exploring your data is a better
understanding of the complexity of
the data you have to work with.
This, in turn,
will guide the rest of your process.