Now that Maya has explained
the basics of machine learning,
let's remember how big data
influences analytical applications.
And how we can take advantage of
the existing big data tools and
techniques in machine learning.
How can machine learning
algorithms be scaled up
to process large volumes of data?
Let's talk about that now.
After this video, you will be able to
explain how machine learning
techniques can scale up to big data.
And discuss the role of distributed
computing platforms like Hadoop and
Spark in applying machine
learning to big data.
With the massive amounts of data
that need to be processed for
applications, such as drug
effectiveness analysis,
climate monitoring, and
website recommendations to name a few.
We need to be able to add scalability
to machine learning techniques.
How do we apply machine learning at scale?
One way, is to scale up by
adding more memory, processors,
and storage to our system so
that it can store and process more data.
This is not the big data approach.
Specialized hardware such as
graphical processing units, or
GPUs for short,
can also be added to speed up the miracle
operations common in machine
learning algorithms.
Although this is a good approach,
this is also not the big data approach.
As we learned in our introductory course,
one problem with this approach
is that larger specialized
hardware can be very costly.
Another problem is that we
eventually will hit a limit.
There's only so
much hardware you can add to a machine.
An alternative approach is to scale out.
This means using many local commodity
distribution systems together.
Data is distributed over these
systems to gain processing speed up.
As shown in this illustration the idea is
to divide the data into smaller subsets.
The same processing is applied to
each subset, or map, and the results
are merged at the end to come up with the
overall results for the original dataset.
Let's consider an example,
where we want to apply the same operation
to all the samples in
a dataset of N samples.
In this case, N is four.
If it takes T time units to perform this
operation on each sample,
then with sequential processing
the time to apply that operation
to all samples, is N times T.
If we have a cluster of four processors,
we can distribute the data
across the four processors.
Each process performs the operation on
the dataset subset of N over four samples.
Processing of the four subsets
of the data is done in parallel.
That is, the subsets
are processed at the same time.
The processing time for the distributed
approach is approximately N over 4 times T
plus any overhead required to merge
the subset results and maybe shuffle them.
This is a speedup of nearly four
times over the sequential approach.
On a distributed computing
platform such as Spark or Hadoop,
scalable machine learning algorithms
use the same scale out approach.
Data is distributed across
different processors,
which operate on the data subsets
in parallel using map, reduce, and
other distributed
parallel transformations.
This allows for
machine learning techniques to be
applied to large volumes of data.
In this course, we will use Spark and
its scalable machine learning library,
MLF, to show you how machine
learning can be applied to big data.
And don't forget,
this is the processing of the machine
learning on where the data resides.
And we call this, the Big Data Approach.
However, you can also imagine
a scenario where you also
update the machine learning
algorithms to scale up.
So you can paralyze the machine
learning algorithms themselves,
and also use processing of big
data together with this approach.
In this video, we will provide you with
a quick summary of the main points
from our first three courses to
recall what you have learned.
If you have just completed our third
course and do not need a refresher,
you might skip to the next lecture.
We started our first course explaining
how a new torrent of big data
combined with cloud computing
capabilities to process data anytime and
anywhere has been at the core of
the launch of the big data era.
Such capabilities enable or
present opportunities for
many dynamic data-driven applications,
including energy management,
smart cities, precision medicine,
and smart manufacturing.
These applications are increasingly
more data-driven, dynamic and
heterogeneous in terms of
their technology needs.
They're also more process-driven and
need to be tackled using
a collaborative approach by a team that
puts value on accountability and
reproducibility of the results.
Overall, by modeling,
managing, integrating diverse
data streams we add value
to our big data and
improve our business even more
before we start analyzing it.
A part of modeling and
managing big data is focusing on
the dimensions of the scalability and
considering the challenges associated with
these dimensions to pick the right tools.
We also talked about characteristics
of big data, referring to some Vs
like volume, variety, velocity,
veracity and valence.
Each week presents a challenging
dimension of big data,
namely size, complexity, speed,
quality and connectedness.
We also added a sixth V,
value, referring to the real reason
we are interested in big data.
To turn it into an advantage in the
context of a problem using data science
techniques, big data needs to be analyzed.
We explained a five steps process for data
science that includes data acquisition,
modeling, management,
integration, and analysis.
The influence of big data pushes for
alternative scalability approaches
at each step of the process.
If we just focus on the scalability
challenges related to the three Vs,
we can say big data has varying volume and
velocity, requiring dynamic and
scalable batch and stream processing.
Big data has variety, requiring management
of data in many different data systems,
and integration of it at scale.
In our introduction to
the big data course,
we talked about the version of a layer
diagram for the tools in the Hadoop
ecosystem, organized vertically
based on the interface.
Low level interfaces for storage and
scheduling on the bottom
and high level languages and
interactivity at the top.
Most of the tools in the Hadoop ecosystem
were initially built to compliment
the capabilities of Hadoop for distributed
file system management using HDFS.
Data processing using
the MapReduce engine, and
resource scheduling, and
negotiation using the YARN engine.
Over time,
a number of new projects were built,
either to add to these complementary
tools or to handle additional types of
big data management and processing not
available in Hadoop, just like Spark.
Arguably, the most important
change to Hadoop over time
was the separation of YARN from
the MapReduce programming model
to solely handle resource
management concerns.
This allowed for Hadoop to be extensible
to different programming models and enable
the development of a number of processing
engines for batch and stream processing.
Another way to look at the vast number of
tools that have been added to the Hadoop
ecosystem is from the point of
view of their functionality
in the big data processing pipeline.
Simply put, these are associated
with three distinct layers for
data management and storage,
for data processing and
for resource coordination and
workflow management.
In our second course, we talked in detail
about the bottom layer in this diagram,
namely data management and storage.
While this layer includes Hadoop's HDFS,
there are a number of other systems
that rely on HDFS as a file system or
implement their own no-SQL storage option.
As big data can have a variety of
structured, semi-structured, and
unstructured formats and
gets analyzed through a variety of tools,
many tools were introduced to
fit this variety of needs.
We call these big data management systems.
We reviewed Redis and Aerospike as
key value stores where each data item
is identified with a unique key.
We also got some practical
experience with Lucene and
Gephi as vector and
graph-stores respectively.
We also talked about Vertica as
a column-store database where
information is stored in
columns rather than rows.
Cassandra and
HBase are also in this category.
Finally, we introduced Solr and
Asterisk DB for managing unstructured and
semi-structured text and
MongoDB as a document store.
The processing layer is where
all these different types
of data get retrieved,
integrated, and analyzed,
which was the primary
focus of our third course.
In the integration and processing layer,
we roughly refer to the tools that
are built on top of HTFS and YARN,
although some of them were with
other storage and file systems.
YARN is a significant enable of many of
these tools making a number of batch and
stream processing engines like Storm,
Spark, Flink and Beam possible.
This layer also includes tools
like Hive and Spark SQL for
bringing a query interface on top
of the storage layer, Pig for
scripting simple big data pipelines
using the MapReduce framework and
a number of specialized
analytical libraries,
formation learning, and graph analytics.
Giraph and GraphX of Spark are examples
of such libraries for graph processing.
Mahout on top of the Hadoop stack and
MLlib of Spark Are two options for
machine learning.
Although we had a basic overview
of graph processing and
machine learning for big data
analytics earlier in our second and
third courses,
we haven't gone into the details there.
In this course, we will use Spark's MLlib
as one of our two main tools,
providing a deeper introduction to
the machine learning library of Spark.
The third and top layer in our diagram is
the coordination and management layer.
This is where integrations,
scheduling, coordination, and
monitoring of applications across many
tools in the bottom two layers take place.
This layer is also where the results of
the big data analysis get communicated
to other programs, websites, visualization
tools and business intelligence tools.
Workflow management systems help to
develop automated solutions that
can manage and coordinate the process
of combining data management and
analytical tasks in a big data pipeline as
a configurable, structured set of steps.
Workflow driven thinking also matches
this basic process of data science
that we overviewed before.
Oozie is an example workflow
scheduler that can interact with
many of the tools in the integration and
processing layer.
Zookeeper is the resource
coordination tool which monitors and
manages and coordinates all these
tools and named after animal.
Now that we've reviewed all three
layers we are ready to come back to
the integration and processing layer, but
now in the context of machine learning.
In which we will use machine
learning techniques to
apply to our five step data science
process and analyze big data.
Just a simple Google search for
big data processing pipelines will bring
a vast number of pipelines with
a large number of technologies
that support scalable data cleaning,
preparation, and analysis.
How do we make sense of all of it to
make sure we use the right tools for
our application?
How do we pick the right
pre-processing and
machine learning techniques to
start doing predictive modeling?
Over the next few weeks Dr.
Mei will walk you through some of the most
fundamental machine learning techniques,
along with introductory hands
on exercises we designed for you to ease
you into the world of machine learning.
Let's get started.
Let's go through an overview of the tools
we will be using in this course.
After this video you will be
able to describe what KNIME is.
Describe what Spark MLlib is, and contrast
KNIME and MLlib as machine learning tools.
The machine learning tools that we will
be using in this course are KNIME and
Spark MLlib.
These are both open source tools.
This lecture will introduce
these tools to you.
You will need to use them for
the hands on activities in this course.
KNIME Analytics is a platform for data
analytics, reporting, and visualization.
The KNIME platform uses a graphical user
interface based approach with drag and
drop features to facilitate
constructing an analytic solution.
The basic components in KNIME
are referred to as nodes.
Each node provides
a specific functionalities,
such as reading in a file,
creating a specific type of machine
running model and generating a plot.
Nodes can be connected to create
machine running workflows or pipelines.
KNIME stands for
Konstanz Information Miner.
The Konstanz is for
the University of Konstanz in Germany.
And note that the K in KNIME is
silent in the pronunciation.
In KNIME you assemble the steps that
need to be performed in a machine
learning process by connecting
nodes to create a workflow.
To create a workflow the user
chooses the appropriate nodes
from the node repository and
assembles them into a workflow.
The workflow can then be
executed in the KNIME work bench.
A node implements a specific
operation in a workflow.
In this screenshot we see two nodes.
The file reader node is used to
read data from a text file or
a URL or a web address.
The decision tree learner node
builds a decision tree model.
Each node can have input and output ports
and can be connected to other nodes.
When a node is executed,
it takes data from its input port,
performs some operations on the data and
writes the results to the output port.
Data is transferred between
nodes that are connected.
A node can be configured by opening
up its configuration dialog.
This is where the parameters for
the node can be set.
The Node Repository is where you will find
all the nodes available in your KNIME
installation.
The nodes are organized by categories.
KNIME provides an array of nodes to
perform operations for data access,
data manipulation, analysis,
visualization, and reporting.
As you can see, KNIME provides
a visual approach to machine learning.
It's GUI-based, drag-and-drop approach
provides an easy way to create and
execute a machine learning workflow.
The open source version of KNIME however
is limited in how large of a dataset
it can handle.
There are commercial extensions to
KNIME to manage large datasets and
offer other extra functionalities, but
these extensions are not open source.
Now let's talk about Spark MLlib.
You've worked with Spark before if
you took the third course in this
specialization on big data.
Spark is a distributed computing platform.
MLlib is a scalable machine learning
library that runs on top of Spark.
It provides distributed implementations of
commonly used machine learning algorithms
and utilities.
The ML and MLlib of course stands for
machine learning.
To implement machine learning operations
in Spark MLlib, you need to write code.
So MLlib is not a GUI-based approach.
This segment of code reads and
parses data from a file,
then builds a decision
tree classification model.
MLlib, as with the base Spark core,
provides an application programming
interface, or API, for
Java, Python, Scala and R.
This means that you can write code in
these programming languages to execute
the base operations provided in Spark.
Spark MLlib runs on
a distributed platform.
It provides machine
learning algorithms and
techniques that are implemented
using distributed processing.
So MLlib is used for processing and
analyzing large datasets.
And as we have discussed, writing code is
required to implement operations in MLlib.
In summary, KNIME is a GUI-based machine
learning tool, while Spark MLlib provides
a programming-based scalable platform for
processing very large datasets.
You will be using both Spark MLlib and
KNIME throughout this course.
We have readings and hands-on exercises to
help you get familiar with these popular
open source tools for machine learning.
I think you will find it very informative
and fun to work with these tools.
Welcome to course four of
the big data specialization.
I'm Ilkay Altintas, for the new learners
I'm the Chief Data Science Officer
at the San Diego Supercomputer Center at
the University of California, San Diego.
I feel honored to teach you
the basics of big data modeling,
management, and
analysis in this specialization.
And to work with Dr.
Mai Nguyen on this class.
>> And I'm Mai Nguyen, while most of
you might be familiar with Ilkay,
I'm a new face.
I'm excited to be here to teach you
what I love doing, machine learning.
I received my PhD in computer science
with a focus on machine learning
from the University of
California in San Diego.
Since then,
I have worked as a data scientist,
and instructor of machine
learning in various venues.
I am the Lead for Data Analytics at SDFC.
In this role, I work on data
science projects doing research
on scalability on machine
learning methods to big data.
>> We are really happy to have you in this
course to develop your understanding and
skills in machine learning.
>> And
give you an introductory level experience
with application of machine
learning to big data.
By now you might have just finished
our first three courses and
learned the basics of big data modeling,
management, integration, and processing.
If you haven't, it's not required.
But for those with less background
in big data management and
systems, you might find it valuable.
>> We understand that you may
not even have heard anything on
machine learning yet.
That's why we will start by
discussing what machine learning is.
Describing some sample applications and
presenting the typical process
of a machine learning project to give
you a sense of what machine learning is.
Then we will delve into some
commonly used machine learning
techniques like classification and
clustering.
>> We are also going to show you how
to explore your data, prepare it for
analysis, and evaluate the results you
get with your machine learning model.
These are all necessary steps for
a successful machine learning solution.
>> As you know, for
many data science applications
one has to use many different tools and
methods to analyze data.
In fact, keeping up with the rapid
development of new tools is
one of the challenges of
today's big data environment.
In this course, we will introduce you to
two different types of machine learning
tools namely Nime and Spark MNL.
Nime is a graphical user interface based
tool that requires no programming.
And as representative of
a set of tools used in visual
workflow approach to machine learning.
You will have hand on practice with
Nime as you go through the exercises in
this course.
We are also excited to show you
examples of data processing
using Sparks Machine Learning library and
OwlWeb.
Our goal here is to provide you
with simple hands-on exercises that
require introductory level programming,
to inspire you on how big data machine
learning tools can be operated.
We wish you a fun time learning and
hope to hear from you in the discussion
forums and learner stories as always.
>> We have suggested time estimates
each week for the course.
But feel free to take the course
at a faster or slower pace.
And don't forget to connect to other
learners through the forums to
enhance your learning experience.
>> Happy learning.
In the last lecture we
discussed data quality issues.
We will now discuss some common techniques
for addressing those quality issues.
After this video, you will be able
to define what imputation means,
illustrate three ways to
handle missing values, and
describe the role of domain knowledge
in addressing data quality issues.
As we discussed in the last lecture,
real world data is messy.
Some data quality issues that you can
find in your data are missing values,
duplicate data, invalid data,
noise and outliers.
You will need to clean your data if you
want to perform any meaningful analysis
on that data.
Recall that missing data occurs
when you don't have a value for
certain variables in some samples.
A simple way to handle missing data is
to simply drop any samples with missing
values or NAs.
All machine learning tools provide
a mechanism or command for
filtering out rows with
any missing values.
The advantage of this approach
is that it is very simple.
The caveat is that you are removing
data when you filter out examples.
If the number of samples dropped is large,
then you end up losing a lot of your data.
An alternative to dropping
samples with missing data is to
impute the missing values.
Imputing means to replace the missing
values with some reasonable values.
The advantage of this approach is that
you're making use of all your data.
Oc course, imputing is more complicated
than simply dropping samples.
There are several ways to
impute missing values.
One strategy is to replace
the missing values with the mean or
median value of the variable.
For example, a missing value for years of
employment can be replaced by the mean or
median value for years of employment for
all current employees.
Another approach is to use
the most frequent value
in place of the missing value.
For example, the most frequently
recorded age of customers
associated with the specific item can
be used if that value is missing.
Alternatively, a sensible value can
be derived as a replacement for
a missing value.
For example, a missing value for
income can be set to zero for
customers less then 18 years old, or
it can be replaced with an average
value based on occupation and location.
Note that this approach requires
knowledge about the application and
the variable with missing values in
order to make reasonable choices
about what valuables would be sensible
to replace the missing values.
In the case of duplicate data one
approach is to delete the older record.
Another approach is to
merge duplicate records.
This often requires a way to determine
how to resolve conflicting values.
For example, in the case of multiple
addresses for the same customer,
some logic for determining similarities
between addresses might be necessary.
For example,
St period is the same as Street.
To address invalid data, consulting
another data source may be necessary.
For example,
an invalid zip code can be corrected
by looking up the correct zip
code based on city and state.
A best estimate for a reasonable value
can also be used as a replacement.
For example, for
a missing age value for an employee,
a reasonable value can be estimated based
on the employee's length of employment.
Noise that distorts the data
values can be addressed by
filtering out the source of the noise.
For example, filtering out the frequency
of a constant background noise
will remove that noise
component from a recording.
This filtering must be
done with care however,
as it can also remove some components
of the true data in the process.
Outliers can be detected through
the use of summary statistics and
plots of the data.
Outliers can significantly skew
the distribution of your data and
thus the results of your analysis.
In cases where outliers are not
the focus of your analysis,
you will want to remove these
outlier samples from your data set.
For example,
when a thermostat malfunctions and
causes values to fluctuate wildly,
or to be much higher or
lower than normal,
these samples should be filtered out.
In some applications, however, outliers
are exactly what you're looking for.
So when you detect outliers,
you don't want to throw them out.
Instead, you want to
examine them more closely.
A classic example of this is in fraud
detection, where outliers represent
potential fraudulent use and
those samples should be analyzed closely.
In order to address data
quality issues effectively
knowledge about
the application is crucial.
Things such as how the data was collected,
the user population, the intended use
of the application etc, are important.
This domain knowledge is essential
to making informed decisions on how
to best impute missing values,
how to handle duplicate records and
invalid data and what to do about
noise and outliers in your data.