Hello and welcome.
My name is Rene and I'll be sharing with
you, how to create a report using Pivot.
To access the Pivot interface,
click Pivot on the navigation menu.
The first step is to select
a prebuilt data model.
Now the data model allows you
to create compelling reports and
dashboards without having to know
how to write complex search queries.
As a side note data models are typically
created by a knowledge manager that
understands their
organization's index data.
Grasps the search language and
are familiar with lookups,
transactions, field extractions and
calculated fields.
For our example, we're going to
use Buttercup Games Online Sales.
Now, this data model includes
the online sales activities.
It's made up of nine objects.
Each object represents a specific set
of events in a hierarchical structure.
The http request would include the largest
number of events in this data model.
The next object, successful request,
would be a subset of the http
request events and so on.
Let's say that we want to create a report
for purchases over the last seven days.
We would select the most
appropriate object.
In this case we're going to
select successful purchase.
After you have selected the object
you will notice that a new
Pivot view will display.
If you notice, the count of
successful purchase is the total
number of events for this specific object.
Now, it is based off of all time.
Before you begin, you should have an idea
of what type of report you want to create.
So let's say that we
want to create a bar chart.
We're going to select that
from the left navigation pane.
So the third icon will allow me
to click and select Bar Chart.
So at this point we are ready
to start building our report.
The first selection is Time Range.
Let's set that to the last seven days.
The next one is Filter, now we don't need
to define Filter, because we've already
selected an object of successful purchase
and that's what we're reporting against.
Now, for my x axis,
I'm going to select product name.
You'll notice that I can set the label.
I can set the sort order.
I can even set how many
maximum bars that I want.
The next thing to define is the y axis.
At this time it's set to
count of successful purchase.
But I want the total sales by product.
So I'm going to select price and
then you'll notice that my
value is already set to sum.
So I'm going to keep it as sum.
My report is starting to look really good.
But after reviewing it I might decide that
I want to see values segmented by host.
So let's do that,
in order to set the segmentation
of a specific product name I could go and
set the color to the field that I want.
So I'm going to select Host.
Now, you'll see that my total
sales are segmented by host.
So we really like this report.
Let's go ahead and save it.
So we're going to click on Save As.
Select report and give it a title.
Let's call it Product Sales by Host.
We're going to click Save and
then we're going to view our report.
It was that easy to create
a report through Pivot.
Now, let's just say that we want to go and
work with another Pivot.
This time we're going to just go and
create a statistic table
to view some of that data.
Let's go ahead and click Pivot again.
We'll select the same data model.
Buttercup games online sales and
let's keep to the object that
we're familiar with right now,
successful purchases.
As I mentioned, I want to just
simply create a statistic table.
I want to show you how
we'd go about doing that.
So the first step is to think about what
are some of the row data that you want?
Let's just assume that we want to view
the product names within their categories.
So, let's go ahead, under Split Rows,
we're going to select category first.
Notice that I can set a label if I want.
Let's go ahead and
set it capitalized category.
I'm going to add that to my table.
You'll see that it
becomes the first column.
Now I want to add another column.
Let's go ahead and
click the plus right next to categories.
Again we're still working
with the split rows.
I'm going to select product name, again if
you want to set a label you can do that.
Now this is the label of our column.
Add to table.
And I want you to notice that
now we are viewing each product
within their category.
Now at this point if you look at
the statistic that is being defined,
it's the count of successful purchases.
That is defined as column values.
Now if I want to add to this,
I can append and have another column.
Let's go ahead and click the plus next
to the Count of successful purchase.
This time I want to add the price.
And you'll notice that I have
different values available.
I could do a Sum, a Count,
an Average, Max, Min.
Let's keep it as a Sum and
let's add a label of Total Sales.
And let's Add To Table.
So this is just to show you
how quick it is to go and
build a table with the statistics
that you would need.
Now at this point, if ever you decide,
I only want to view the data for
the last seven days.
Just note that you could go
back up to your filter and
your first filter is
based off of all time.
So we could set that to
the last seven days.
So of course that the data
in our table will change.
Now, the last thing I want to show you
here is if ever you did want to see
the count and the total sales per host,
as we've defined in our previous example.
That is where you could go
to the split columns and
define how you wish to
split that information.
So let's go ahead and select host again.
And I'm just going to
click on add to table.
Now I could see that the information
has been split by host.
I have www1 count of successful
purchases as well as total sales.
And then I have the split of www2 I have
the count and the total sales and etc.
So this concludes our short
video hope you enjoy it.
Thank you.
Welcome.
In this short module we'll talk about
information integration which refers
to the problem of using many different
information sources to accomplish a task.
In this module, we'll look at the problems
and solutions through a few use cases.
So after this video, you'll be able to
explain the data integration problem,
define integrated views and schema
mapping, describe the impact of increasing
the number of data sources, appreciate
the need to use data compression,
And describe record linking,
data exchange, and data fusion tasks.
Our first use case starts with
an example given at an IBM website for
their information integration products.
It represents a very common
scenario in today's business world.
Due to the changing market dynamics,
companies
are always selling off a part of their
company or acquiring another company.
As these mergers and acquisitions happen,
databases which were developed and
stored separately in different companies
would now need to be brought together.
Now take a minute to read this case.
This is the case of an expanding financial
services group that's growing its customer
base in different countries.
And all they want is a single view
of their entire customer base.
In other words, it does not matter
which previous company originally had
the customers, Suncorp-Metway
want to consolidate all customer
information as if they were
in one single database.
And in reality, of course, they may
not want to buy a huge machine and
migrate every subsidiary
company's data into it.
What they're looking to create is possibly
a software solution which would make all
customer-related data to appear as though
they were together as a single database.
This software solution is called
an information integration system.
This will help them ensure that they have
a uniform set of marketing campaigns for
all their customers.
Let's try to see, hypothetically, of
course, what might be involved in creating
this combined data and what kind of use
the integrated data might result in.
So we first create
a hypothetical scenario.
Although Suncorp have a large
number of data sources,
we will take a much simpler situation and
have only two data sources from two
different financial service companies.
The first data source,
which is an insurance company that manages
it's data with a relation of DBMS,
this database has nine tables where the
primary object of information is a policy.
The company offers many
different types of policies
sold to individual people by their agents.
Now as it's true for all insurance
companies, policyholders pay their monthly
dues, and sometimes people make claims
against their insurance policies.
When they do, the details of the claims
are maintained in the database.
These claims can belong to different
categories, and when the claims have
paid to the claimants, the transaction
is recorded in the transactions table.
As we have done several times now,
the primary keys of the table
are the underlined attributes here.
The second company in
our example is a bank,
which also uses a relational database.
In this bank, both individuals and
businesses called corporations here,
can have accounts.
Now accounts can be of different types.
For example, a money market account
is different from a savings account.
A bank also maintains its transactions
in a table, which can be really large.
But the dispute in a bank record
case happens when the bank is
charged a customer, or the customer has
declined responsibility of the charge.
This can happen, for example, if a
customer's Internet account was hacked or
a debit card got stolen.
The bank keeps a record
of these anomalies and
fraudulent events in a disputes table,
all right.
Let's see what happens after the data
from these two subsidiary companies
are integrated.
After the merger the company wants to
do a promotional goodwill activity.
They would like to offer
a small discount to their
insurance policyholders if they're also
customers of the newly acquired bank.
How do you identify these customers?
Let's see.
In other words, we need to use the table
shown on the left to create the table
shown on the right called
discount candidates.
One is to create a yellow tables from
the insurance company database, and
the blue table from the bank database,
and then join them to construct the table
with a common customer ID, and both
the policyKey and bank account number.
Now, this relation, which is derived that
is computed by querying two different
data sources and combining their results,
is called an integrated view.
It is integrated because the data is
retrieved from different data sources,
and it's called a view because
in database terminology
it is a relation computed
from other relations.
To populate the integrated
view discount candidates,
we need to go through a step
called schema mapping.
The term mapping means to
establish correspondence between
the attributes of the view, which is
also called a target relation, and
that of the source relations.
For example, we can map the full address
from individuals to the address attribute
in discountCandidates, but
this would only be true for
customers whose names and
addresses match in the two databases.
As you can see, policyholders uses
the full name of a customer, whereas
individuals has it broken down into first
name, middle initial, and last name.
On the other hand, full address is
a single field in individuals, but
represented in full attributes
in the policyholders relation.
The mappings of account number and
policyKey are more straightforward.
Well, what about customer ID which doesn't
correspond to anything in the four
input relations?
We'll come back to this later on.
Okay, now we'll define
an integrated relation.
How do we query?
For example,
how do you find the bank account number
of a person whose policyKey is known?
You might think, what's the problem here?
We have a table.
Just say select account number from
discount candidates where policyKey
is equal to 4-937528734, and we're done.
Well, yes, you can write this query,
but how the query be evaluated?
That depends on what's called the query
architecture of the data
integration system.
The figure on the left shows
the elements of this architecture.
We'll discover it in more detail,
but on this slide,
we'll just describe
the three axes of this cube.
The vertical z axis specifies
whether we have one data source or
multiple data sources.
Our interest is in the case where
there are multiple data sources.
The x axis asks whether the integrated
data is actually stored physically
in some place or whether it is computed
on the fly, each time a query is asked.
If it is all precomputed and stored,
we say that the data is materialized.
And if it is computed on the fly,
we say it's virtual.
The y axis asks whether
there is a single schema or
global schema defined all
over the data integrated for
an application or whether the data
stay in different computers and
it is accessed in a peer-to-peer
manner at runtime.
Thus, the seemingly simple select
project query will be evaluated
depending on which part of the cube
our architecture implements.
But for now,
let's return to our example use case.
An obvious goal of an information
integration system
is to be complete and accurate.
Complete means no eligible record
from the source should be absent in
the target relation.
Accurate means all the entries in
the integrated relation should be correct.
Now we said on the previous
slide that a matching
customer is a person who
was in both databases and
has the same name and
address in the two databases.
Now let's look at some example records.
Specifically, consider the records
marked by the three arrows.
The two bank accounts and
the policy record do not match for name or
for address.
So our previous method would discard them.
But look at the records closely.
Do you think they might all
belong to the same customer?
Maybe this lady has a maiden name and
a married name, and
has moved from one address to another.
Maybe she changed her Social Security
number somewhere along the way.
So this is called
a record linkage problem.
That means we would like to ensure that
the set of data records that belong to
a single entity are recognized,
perhaps by clustering
the values of different attributes or
by using a set of matching rules so
that we know how to deal with it
during the integration process.
For example, we need to determine
which of the addresses should be
used in the integrated relation.
Which of the two bank accounts?
If the answer is both accounts 102 and
103, we will need to change
the schema of the target's relation
to a list instead of an atomic number
to avoid creating multiple tuples for
the same entity.
As we saw, the schema of adding
process is a task of figuring out
how elements of the schema from two
sources would relate to each other and
determining how they would
map the target schema.
You also saw that this is not really
a simple process, that we are trying to
produce one integrated relation using
a couple of relations from each source.
In a Big Data situation,
there are dozens of data sources, or
more because the company's growing and
each source may have a few hundred tables.
So it becomes very hard to actually solve
this correspondence-making problem
completely and accurately just because
the number of combinations one has to
go through is really, really high.
One practical way to tackle this problem
is not to do a full-scale detail
integration in the beginning but
adopt what's called a pay-as-you-go model.
The pay-as-you-go data
management principle is simple.
The system should provide some basic
integration services at the outset and
then evolve the schema mappings between
the different sources on an as needed
basis.
So given a query, the system should
generate a best effort or approximate
answers from the data sources for
a perfect schema mappings do not exist.
When it discovers a large number
of sophisticated queries or
data mining tasks over certain sources,
it will guide the users to make
additional efforts to integrate
these sources more precisely.
Okay, so how does the first
approximate schema mapping performed?
One approach to do this is called
Probabilistic Schema Mapping.
We'll describe it in more detail next.
In the previous step,
we just decided to create the disk count
candidates rrelation in an ad hoc way.
And in a Big Data situation,
we need to carefully determine
what the integrated schema,
also called mediated schemas, should be,
and we should evaluate them properly.
Since our toy company is trying
to create a single customer view,
it's natural to create an integrated
table called customers.
But how can we design this table?
Here are some options.
We can create the customer table to
include individuals and corporations and
then use a flag called customer
type to distinguish between them.
Now in the mediated schema then,
the individuals first name,
middle initial, last name,
policyholder's name and
corporation's name would all
map to Customer_Name similarly.
The individual's full address,
the corporation's registered address,
and the policyholder's address,
plus city, plus state,
plus zip would all map
to customer address.
Now we can enumerate all such choices of
which attributes to group together and
map for each single attribute
in the target schema.
But no matter how you'll do it,
it will never be a perfect fit because
not all these combinations
would go well together.
For example, should that date of
birth be included in this table?
Would it make sense for corporations?
In Probabilistic Mediated Schema Design,
we answer this question by
associating probability values
with each of these options.
To compute these values, we need to
quantify the relationships between
attributes by figuring out which
attributes should be grouped or
clustered together?
Now two pieces of information
available in the source schemas
can serve as evidence for
attribute clustering.
One, the parallel similarity
of source attributes, and two,
statistical properties
of service attributes.
The first piece of information indicates
when two attributes are likely to be
similar and is used for
creating multiple mediated schemas.
One can apply a collection of
attribute matching modules
to compute pairwise similarity.
For example, individual names and
policyholder names
are possibly quite similar.
Are individual names versus
corporation names similar?
Now, the similarity between two
source attributes, EIN and EZ,
measure how closely the two attributes
represent the same real world concept.
The second piece of information indicates
when two attributes are likely
to be different, and is used for
assigning probabilities to
each of the mediated schemas.
For example, date of birth and
corporation name possibly
will never co-occur together.
But for
large schemas with large data volumes,
one can estimate these measures by
taking samples from the actual database
to come up with reasonable
similarity co-occurrence scores.
To illustrate attribute regrouping, we
take a significant re-simplified example.
Here we want to create customer
transactions as a mediated relation
based upon the bank transactions and
insurance transactions.
Each attribute is given
an abbreviation for simplicity.
Below, you can see three
possible mediated schemas.
In the first one,
the transaction begin and end times
from bank transactions are grouped into
the same cluster as transaction date time
from the insurance transactions,
because all of them are the same type.
Similarly, transaction party, that
means who is giving or receiving money,
and transaction description are grouped
together with transaction details.
The second schema keeps
all of them separate.
And the third candidate schema
groups some of them and not others.
Now that we have multiple mediated
schemas, which one should we choose?
Now I'm presenting here
a qualitative account of the method.
The primary goal is to look for
what we can call consistency.
A source schema is consistent
with a mediated schema if
two different attributes of the source
schema do not occur in one cluster.
And in the example, Med3,
that means related schema three,
is more consistent with bank
transactions because, unlike Med1,
it keeps TBT,
TET in two different clusters.
Once this is done, we can count the number
of consistent sources for each candidate
mediated schema and then use this count
to come up with a probability estimate.
This estimate can then be used
to choose the k best schemas.
Should one ever choose more
than one just best schema?
Well, that's a hard question
to answer in general.
It is done when the top capability
estimates are very close to each other.
[SOUND] The Splunk platform for
operational intelligence is
a revolutionary suite of products that
is unlocking unprecedented value for
thousands of customers around the world.
Why Splunk?
It all starts with machine data.
Machine data is the big data generated by
all the technologies that
power our businesses.
From the applications, servers, websites,
and network devices in the data center and
the cloud, to the mobile device
in the palm of your hand.
Thermostats, train sensors, electric cars,
and the Internet of things.
Machine data is everywhere.
It's fast-growing and complex.
It's also incredibly valuable, why?
Because it contains a definitive
record of all activity and behavior.
Splunk software collects and
indexes this data at massive scale,
from wherever it's generated,
regardless of format or source.
Users can quickly and
easily monitor, search, analyze, and
report on their data, all in real time.
Machine data is different.
It can't be processed and
analyzed using traditional methods.
Splunk software does not rely on brittle
schemas and inflexible databases.
Splunk is easy to deploy, easy to use, and
easy to scale, whether on premises or
in a public, private, or hybrid cloud.
Splunk is also available
as a cloud service.
And for big data environments that
used Hadoop for cheap app storage,
we have Hunk, Splunk analytics for Hadoop.
[MUSIC]
Our customers from around
the world illustrate why so
many organizations use Splunk.
Intuit has standardized on Splunk,
delivering operational visibility for
their leading online products, including
QuickBooks, Quicken, and TurboTax.
Intuit considers Splunk one of
their cornerstone technologies
that is helping them innovate and
deliver better service to their customers.
Cisco, one of the world's
largest technology providers,
empowers their global security
team with Splunk enterprise
to gain a centralized view into
end user and system activities.
Splunk has dramatically helped
improve their incident detection and
response rate.
Splunk was key to Domino's Pizza's
success during the Super Bowl,
by monitoring database uptime and
order response.
Armed with new levels of
customer understanding,
Domino's was able to strengthen their
online business, in addition to saving
hundreds of thousands of dollars replacing
legacy technologies with Splunk.
We are thrilled to hear Domino's
call Splunk their secret sauce.
Another great Splunk story includes
cars and the Internet of things.
Working together with the Ford Motor
Company and Ford's OpenXC platform,
Splunk delivered connected car dashboards
to examine driving behavior and
vehicle performance.
UK-based Tesco is one of
the world's largest retailers,
with nearly 1 million customers and
a half billion online orders per week.
Customer satisfaction
is a critical metric.
Tesco deployed Splunk to gain a unified
view across their websites, transactions,
and business, gaining valuable digital
intelligence about their customers.
Splunk was founded to pursue a disruptive
vision to make machine data accessible,
usable, and valuable to everyone.
Find out more about Splunk and
operational intelligence by
downloading the executive summary.
Or better yet,
experience the value firsthand by
downloading Splunk software for free.
Chances are someone in your
organization already has.
[SOUND]
Aggregations in Big Data Pipelines.
After this video you will
be able to compare and
select the aggregation operation that
you require to solve your problem.
Explain how you can use aggregations to
compact your dataset and reduce volume.
That is in many cases.
And design complex operations in your
pipeline, using a series of aggregations.
Aggregation is any operation on a data set
that performs a specific transformation,
taking all the related data
elements into consideration.
Let's say we have a bunch of stars
which are of different colors.
Different colors denote diversity or
variety in the data.
To keep things simple, we will use
letter 'f' to denote a transformation.
In the following slides,
we will see examples of how 'f' can take
the shape of different transformations.
If we apply a transformation that does
something using the information of
all the stars here,
we are performing an aggregation.
Loosely speaking, we can say
that applying a transformation 'f'
that takes all the elements of data
as input is called 'aggregation'.
One of the simplest aggregations is
summation over all the data elements.
In this case,
let's say every star counted as 1.
Summing over all the stars gives 14,
which is the summation of 3 stars for
yellow,
5 stars for green, and
6 stars for color pink.
Another aggregation that you could perform
is summation of individual star colors,
that is, grouping the sums by color.
So, If each star is a 1,
adding each group will result in 3 for
yellow stars, 5 for green stars,
and 6 for pink stars.
In this case,
the aggregation function 'f' will output
3 tuples of star colors and counts.
In a sales scenario, each color could
denote a different product type.
And the number 1 could be replaced
by revenue generated by a product
in each city the product is sold.
In fact,
we will keep coming back to this analogy.
You can also perform average
over items of similar kind,
such as sums grouped by color.
Continuing the example earlier,
you can calculate average revenue per
product type using this aggregation.
Other simple yet useful aggregational
operations to help you extract meaning
from large data sets are maximum,
minimum, and standard deviation.
Remember, you can always perform
aggregation as a series of operations,
such as maximum of the sums per product.
That is, summation followed by maximum.
If you first sum sales for
each city, that is for
each product,
then you can take the maximum of it
by applying maximum function to
the result of the summation function.
In this case, you get the product,
which has maximum sales in the country.
Aggregation over Boolean data
sets that can have true-false or
one-zero values could be a complex mixture
of AND, OR, and NOT logical operations.
A lot of problems become easy
to manipulate using sets.
Because sets don't allow duplicate values.
Depending on your application,
this could be very useful.
For example, to count the number
of products from a sales table,
you can simply take all
the sales tables and create sets
of these products in those tables,
and take a union of these sets.
To summarize, by choosing the right
aggregation, you can generate compact and
meaningful insights that enable faster and
effective decision making in business.
You will find that in most cases,
aggregation results in
smaller output data sets.
Hence, aggregation is an important tool
set to keep in pocket when dealing with
large data sets, and big data pipelines.
Big Data Processing Pipelines:
A Dataflow Approach.
Most big data applications
are composed of a set of operations
executed one after another as a pipeline.
Data flows through these operations,
going through various
transformations along the way.
We also call this dataflow graphs.
So to understand big data
processing we should start by
understanding what dataflow means.
After this video you will be able to
summarize what dataflow means and
it's role in data science.
Explain split->do->merge as a big
data pipeline with examples,
and define the term data parallel.
Let's consider the hello
world MapReduce example for
WordCount which reads one or
more text files and
counts the number of occurrences
of each word in these text files.
You are by now very familiar with
this example, but as a reminder,
the output will be a text
file with a list of words and
their occurrence frequencies
in the input data.
In this application,
the files were first split into HDFS
cluster nodes as partitions of
the same file or multiple files.
Then a map operation, in this case,
a user defined function to count words
was executed on each of these nodes.
And all the key values that were output
from map were sorted based on the key.
And the key values with the same word
were moved or shuffled to the same node.
Finally, the reduce operation
was executed on these nodes
to add the values for
key-value pairs with the same keys.
If you look back at this example, we see
that there were four distinct steps,
namely the data split step,
the map step, the shuffle and
sort step, and the reduce step.
Although, the word count
example is pretty simple it
represents a large number of
applications that these three
steps can be applied to achieve
data parallel scalability.
We refer in general to this
pattern as "split-do-merge".
In these applications, data flows
through a number of steps, going through
transformations with various scalability
needs, leading to a final product.
The data first gets partitioned.
The split data goes through a set of
user-defined functions to do something,
ranging from statistical operations to
data joins to machine learning functions.
Depending on the application's
data processing needs,
these "do something" operations can
differ and can be chained together.
In the end results can be combined
using a merging algorithm or
a higher-order function like reduce.
We call the stitched-together
version of these sets of steps for
big data processing "big data pipelines".
The term pipe comes from
a UNIX separation that
the output of one running program gets
piped into the next program as an input.
As you might imagine,
one can string multiple programs together
to make longer pipelines with various
scalability needs at each step.
However, for big data processing,
the parallelism of each step in
the pipeline is mainly data parallelism.
We can simply define data parallelism
as running the same functions
simultaneously for the elements or
partitions of a dataset on multiple cores.
For example,
in our word count example, data
parallelism occurs in every
step of the pipeline.
There's definitely parallelization
during map over the input
as each partition gets
processed as a line at a time.
To achieve this type of data parallelism,
we must decide on the data granularity
of each parallel computation.
In this case, it is a line.
We also see a parallel grouping of
data in the shuffle and sort phase.
This time, the parallelization is
over the intermediate products,
that is, the individual key-value pairs.
And after the grouping of
the intermediate products
the reduce step gets parallelized
to construct one output file.
You have probably noticed that
the data gets reduced to a smaller set
at each step.
Although, the example we have given is for
batch processing, similar techniques
apply to stream processing.
Let's discuss this for
our simplified advanced stream
data from an online game example.
In this case, your event gets ingested
through a real time big data ingestion
engine, like Kafka or Flume.
Then they get passed into
a Streaming Data Platform for
processing like Samza,
Storm or Spark streaming.
This is a valid choice for processing
data one event at a time or chunking
the data into Windows or Microbatches
of time or other features.
Any pipeline processing of data can
be applied to the streaming data here
as we wrote in a batch-
processing Big Data engine.
The process stream data can then be
served through a real-time view or
a batch-processing view.
Real-time view is often subject to change
as potentially delayed new data comes in.
The storage of the data can be
accomplished using H-Base, Cassandra,
HDFS, or
many other persistent storage systems.
To summarize, big data pipelines
get created to process data
through an aggregated set of steps that
can be represented with the split-
do-merge pattern with
data parallel scalability.
This pattern can be
applied to many batch and
streaming data processing applications.
Next we will go through some processing
steps in a big data pipeline in
more detail, first conceptually,
then practically in Spark.