How do you evaluate
your model performance?
In this lecture, we will look at
different metrics that can be used to
evaluate the performance of
your classification model.
After this video, you will be able to
discuss how performance metrics
can be used to evaluate models.
Name three model evaluation metrics, and
explain why accuracy may be misleading.
For the classification task, an error
occurs when the model's prediction of
the class label is different
from the true class label.
We can also define the different types
of errors in classification depending on
the predicted and true labels.
Let's take the case with the task is
to predict whether a given animal is
a mammal or not.
This is a binary classification task
with the class label being either yes,
indicating mammal, or
no indicating non-mammal.
Then the different types
of errors are as follows.
If the true label is yes and
the predicted label is yes,
then this is a true positive,
abbreviated as TP.
This is the case where the label is
correctly predicted as positive.
If the true label is no and
the predicted label is no,
then this is a true negative,
abbreviated as TN.
This is the case where the label is
correctly predicted as negative.
If the true label is no and
the predicted label is yes,
then this is a false positive,
abbreviated as FP.
This is the case with the label is
incorrectly predicted as positive,
when it should be negative.
If the true label is yes and
the predicted label is no, then this
is a false negative abbreviated as FN.
This is the case where the label is
incorrectly predicted as negative,
when it should be positive.
These definitions can take a while to sink
in, so feel free to hit the pause button
and replay button several times
here to review this part.
These four different types of errors
are used in calculating many evaluation
metrics for classifiers.
The most commonly used evaluation
metric is the accuracy rate, or
accuracy for short.
For classication,
accuracy is calculated as the number of
correct predictions divided by
the total number of predictions.
Note that the number of correct
predictions is the sum of the true
positives, and the true negatives, since
the true and predicted labels match for
those cases.
The accuracy rate is an intuitive
way to measure the performance
of a classification model.
Model performance can also be
expressed in terms of error rate.
Error rate is the opposite
of accuracy rate.
Let's look at an example to see how
accuracy and error rates are calculated.
The table on the left, lists the true
label along with the model's prediction
for a data set of ten samples.
First, let’s figure out
the number of true positives.
Recall that a true positive occurs when
the output is correctly predicted as
positive.
In other words the true label is yes,
and the model's prediction is yes.
In this example there are three true
positives as indicated by the red arrows.
So, TP=3, remember that value
as we'll need it later.
Now, let's figure out
the number of true negatives.
A true negative occurs when the output
is correctly predicted as negative.
In other words, the true label is no and
the model's prediction is no.
In this example there are four true
negatives as indicated by the green
arrows.
So TN = 4,
we'll need to remember this value as well.
Now we use the values for TP and
TN to calculate the accuracy rate.
Using the equation for accuracy rate,
we plug in three for TP and four for TN.
We get seven correct predictions for
the numerator.
The denominator is simply the total number
of samples in our data set, which is ten.
So the accuracy rate for
example is 7 out of 10 which is 0.7 or
70%.
The error rate is the exact
opposite of the accuracy rate.
To calculate the error rate, we simply
subtract the accuracy rate from 1.
For our example that is
1- 0.7 which is 0.3.
So the error rate for
this example is 0.3 or 30%.
There's a limitation with accuracy and
error rates when you have
a class imbalance problem.
This is when there are very few
samples of the class of interest, and
the majority are negative examples.
An example of this is identifying
if a tumor is cancerous or not.
What is of interest is identifying
samples with cancerous tumors, but
these positive cases where the tumor
is cancerous are very rare.
So, you end up with a very small
fraction of positive samples, and
most of the samples are negative.
Thus the name, class imbalance problem.
What could be the problem with using
accuracy for a class imbalance problem?
Consider the situation where only 3%
of the cases are cancerous tumors.
If the classification model
always predicts non-cancer,
it will have an accuracy rate of 97%,
since 97% of the samples will
have non-cancerous tumors.
But note that in this case, the model
fails to detect any cancer cases at all.
So the accuracy rate is
very misleading here.
You may think that your model is
performing very well with such
a high accuracy rate.
But in fact it cannot identify any of
the cases in the class of interest.
In these cases we need evaluation
metrics that can capture how
well the model classifies positive,
versus negative classes.
A pair of evaluations metrics that
are commonly used when there is a class
imbalance are precision and recall.
Precision is defined as the number of
true positives divided by the sum of
true positives and false positives.
In other words, it is the number of true
positives divided by the total number
of samples predicted as being positive.
Recall is defined as the number of
true positives divided by the sum of
true positives and false negatives.
It is the number of true positives
divided by the total number of samples,
actually belonging to the true class.
Here's an illustration that
shows precision and recall.
The selected elements indicated by the
green half circle are the true positives.
That is samples predicted as positive and
are actually positive.
The relevant elements indicated
by the green half circle and
the green half rectangle, are the true
positives, plus the false negatives.
That is samples that are actually
positive, but some are correctly predicted
as positive, and some are incorrectly
predicted as negative.
Recall then is the number of samples
correctly predicted as positive,
divided by all samples that
are actually positive.
The entire circle indicated
by the green half circle and
the pink half circle, are the true
positives plus the false positives.
That is samples that were
predicted as positive
although some were actually positive and
some were actually negative.
Then precision is the number of samples
correctly predicted as positive,
divided by the number of all
samples predicted as positive.
Precision is considered a measure
of exactness because it calculates
the percentage of samples
predicted as positive,
which are actually in a positive class.
Recall is considered a measure of
completeness, because it calculates
the percentage of positive samples
that the model correctly identified.
There is a trade off between precision and
recall.
A perfect precision score of one for
a class C means that every sample
predicted as belonging to class C,
does indeed belong to class C.
But this says nothing about the number of
samples from class C that were predicted
incorrectly.
A perfect recall score of one for
a class C, means that every sample
from class C was correctly labeled.
But this doesn't say anything
about how many other samples were
incorrectly labeled as
belonging to class C.
So they are used together.
For example, precision values can be
compared for a fixed value of recall or
vice versa.
The goal for classification is to
maximize both precision and recall.
Precision and recall can be combined into
a single metric called the F-measure.
The equation for that is 2 times
the product of precision and
recall divided by their sum.
There are different
versions of the F-measure.
The equation on this side is for
the F1 measure which is the most
commonly used variant of the F measure.
With the F1 measure, precision and
recall are equally weighted.
The F2 measure weights recall
higher than precision.
And the F0.5 measure weights
precision higher than recall.
The value for
the F1 measure ranges from zero to one,
with higher values giving better
classification performance.
In summary, there are several metrics for
evaluating the performance
of a classification model.
They are defined in terms of
the types of errors you can get in
a classification problem.
We covered some of the most commonly
used evaluation metrics in this lecture,
namely accuracy and error rates,
precision and recall and F1 measure.
In this lecture, we will discuss how
overfitting occurs with decision trees and
how it can be avoided.
After this video,
you will be able to discuss overfitting
in the context of decision tree models.
Explain how overfitting is addressed
in decision tree induction.
Define pre-pruning and post-pruning.
In our lecture on decision trees, we
discussed that during the construction of
a decision tree, also referred to as
tree induction, the tree repeatedly
splits the data in a node in order to
get successively paired subsets of data.
Note that a decision tree classifier can
potentially expand its nodes until it can
perfectly classify samples
in the training data.
But if the tree grows nodes to fit
the noise in the training data,
then it will not classify
a new sample well.
This is because the tree has partitioned
the input space according to the noise in
the data instead of to
the true structure of a data.
In other words, it has overfit.
How can overfitting be
avoided in decision trees?
There are two ways.
One is to stop growing the tree
before the tree is fully grown
to perfectly fit the training data.
This is referred to as pre-pruning.
The other way to avoid overfitting in
decision trees is to grow the tree to its
maximum size and then prune the tree
back by removing parts of the tree.
This is referred to as post-pruning.
In general, overfitting occurs
because the model is too complex.
For a decision tree model,
model complexity is determined by
the number of nodes in the tree.
Addressing overfitting in decision trees
means controlling the number of nodes.
Both methods of pruning control
the growth of the tree and consequently,
the complexity of the resulting model.
With pre-pruning, the idea is to stop tree
induction before a fully grown tree is
built that perfectly
fits the training data.
To do this, restrictive stopping
conditions for growing nodes must be used.
For example, a nose stops expanding if
the number of samples in the node is less
than some minimum threshold.
Another example is to stop expanding
a note if the improvement in the impurity
measure falls below a certain threshold.
In post-pruning,
the tree is grown to its maximum size,
then the tree is pruned by removing
nodes using a bottom up approach.
That is, the tree is trimmed
starting with the leaf nodes.
The pruning is done by replacing
a subtree with a leaf node if
this improves the generalization error,
or if there is no
change to the generalization
error with this replacement.
In other words, if removing a subtree
does not have a negative effect
on the generalization error,
then the nodes in that subtree only
add to the complexity of the tree,
and not to its overall performance.
So those nodes should be removed.
In practice,
post-pruning tends to give better results.
This is because pruning decisions are
based on information from the full tree.
Pre-pruning, on the other hand, may stop
the tree growing process prematurely.
However, post-pruning is more
computationally expensive since the tree
has to be expanded to its full size.
In summary, to address overfitting in
decision trees, tree pruning is used.
There are two pruning methods,
pre-pruning and post-pruning.
Both methods control
the complexity of the tree model.
In this lecture, we will discuss
what a validation set is and
how it relates to overfitting and
model performance evaluation.
After this video, you will be able to
describe how validation sets can be
used to avoid overfitting.
Articulate how training,
validation, and test sets are used.
And list three ways that
validation can be performed.
In our lesson on classification,
we discussed that there is a training
phase in which the model is built, and
a testing phase in which
the model is applied to new data.
The model is built using training data and
evaluated on test data.
The training and
test data are two different datasets.
The goal in building a machine learning
model is to have the model perform well
on the training set, as well as generalize
well on new data in the test set.
Recall that a model that overfits
does not generalize well to new data.
Recall also that overfitting generally
occurs when a model is too complex.
So to have a model with good
generalization performance,
model training has to stop before
the model gets too complex.
How do you determine
when this should occur?
A validation set can be used to guide the
training process to avoid overfitting and
deliver good generalization performance.
We have discussed having a training
set and a separate test set.
The training set is used
to build a model and
the test set is used to see how
the model performs a new data.
Now we want to further divide up
the training data into a training set and
a validation set.
The training set is used to
train the model as before and
the validation set is used to determine
when to stop training the model
to avoid overfitting, in order to get
the best generalization performance.
The idea is to look at the errors
on both training set and
validation set during model
training as shown here.
The orange solid line on the plot
is the training error and
the green line is the validation error.
We see that as model building
progresses along the x-axis,
the number of nodes increases.
That is the complexity
of the model increases.
We can see that as the model complexity
increases, the training error decreases.
On the other hand, the validation
error initially decreases but
then starts to increase.
When the validation error increases, this
indicates that the model is overfitting,
resulting in decreased
generalization performance.
This can be used to determine
when to stop training.
Where validation error starts to increase
is when you get the best generalization
performance, so
training should stop there.
This method of using a validation set
to determine when to stop training
is referred to as model selection
since you're selecting one from
many of varying complexities.
Note that this was illustrated for
a decision tree classifier, but
the same method can be applied to
any type of machine learning model.
There are several ways to create and use
the validation set to avoid overfitting.
The different methods are holdout method,
random subsampling,
k-fold cross-validation,
and leave-one-out cross-validation.
The first way to use a validation
set is the holdout method.
This describes the scenario
that we have been discussing,
where part of the training data
is reserved as a validation set.
The validation set is
then the holdout set.
Errors on the training set and the holdout
set are calculated at each step
during model training and
plotted together as we've seen before.
And the lowest error on the holdout
set is when training should stop.
This is the just the process that
we have described here before.
There's some limitations to
the holdout method however.
First, since some samples are reserved for
the holdout validation set,
the training set now has less data
than it originally started out with.
Secondly, if the training and holdout sets
do not have the same data distributions,
then the results will be misleading.
For example, if the training data has
many more samples of one class and
the holdout dataset has many
more samples of another class.
The next method for using
a validation set is repeated holdout.
As the name implies,
this is essentially repeating
the holdout method several times.
With each iteration, samples are randomly
selected from the original training data
to create the holdout validation set.
This is repeated several times with
different training and validation sets.
Then the iterates on the holdout set for
the different iterations
are averaged together to get the overall
iterate for model selection.
A potential problem with repeated holdout
is that you could end up with some samples
being used more than others for training.
Since a sample can be used for either
testing or training any number of times,
some samples may be put in the training
set more times than other samples.
So you might end up with some
samples being overrepresented while
other samples are underrepresented
in training or testing.
A way to improve on the repeated
holdout method is use cross-validation.
Cross-validation works as follows.
Segment the data into k number
of disjoint partitions.
During each iteration, one partition
is used as the validation set.
Repeat the process k times.
Each time using a different partition for
validation.
So each partition is used for
validation exactly once.
This is illustrated in this figure.
In the fist iteration, the first
partition, specified in green, is used for
validation.
In the second iteration,
the second partition is used for
validation and so on.
The overall validation error is calculated
by averaging the validation errors for
all k iterations.
The model with the smallest average
validation error then is selected.
The process we just described is
referred to as k-fold cross-validation.
This is a very commonly used approach
to model selection in practice.
This approach gives you a more structured
way to divide available data up between
training and validation datasets and
provides a way to overcome the variability
in performance that you can get when
using a single partitioning of the data.
Leave-one-out cross-validation
is a special case of k-fold
cross-validation where k equals N,
where N is the size of your dataset.
Here, for each iteration the validation
set has exactly one sample.
So the model is trained to
using N minus one samples and
is validated on the remaining sample.
The rest of the process works the same
way as regular k-fold cross-validation.
Note that cross-validation is often
abbreviated CV and leave-one-out
cross-validation is in abbreviated
L-O-O-C-V and pronounced LOOCV.
We have described several ways to use
a validation set to address overfitting.
Error on the validation set is used
to determine when to stop training so
that the model does not overfit.
Note that the validation error that comes
out of this process can also be used
to estimate generalization
performance of the model.
In other words,
the error on the validation set provides
an estimate of the error on the test set.
With the addition of the validation set,
you really need three distinct
datasets when you build a model.
Let's review these datasets.
The training dataset is used to train the
model, that is to adjust the parameters of
the model to learn the input
to output mapping.
The validation dataset is used to
determine when training should stop
in order to avoid overfitting.
The test data set is used to evaluate
the performance of the model on new data.
Note that the test data set should never,
ever be used in any way to create or
tune the model.
It should not be used, for
example, in a cross-validation process
to determine when to stop training.
The test dataset must always remain
independent from model training and
remain untouched until the very end
when all training has been completed.
Note that in sampling the original dataset
to create the training, validation, and
test sets, all datasets must contain the
same distribution of the target classes.
For example, if in the original dataset,
70% of the samples belong to one class and
30% to the other class, then this same
distribution should approximately
be present in each of the training,
validation, and test sets.
Otherwise, analysis results
will be misleading.
To summarize, we have discuss the need for
three different datasets
in building model.
A training set to train the model,
a validation set to determine when to stop
training, and a test to evaluate
performance on new data.
We learned how a validation set can
be used to avoid overfitting and
in the process, provide an estimate
of generalization performance.
And we covered different
ways to create and
use a validation set such
as k-fold cross-validation.
Now that we have seen what
association analysis is,
let's go over the association
analysis process in more detail.
After this video, you will be able
to define the terms support and
confidence, describe the steps
in association analysis, and
explain how association rules
are formed from item sets.
Let's review the set in
association analysis.
They are create item the sets,
then identify the frequent item sets.
Finally, generate the rules.
We will continue with
this example dataset,
there are five transactions
in the dataset.
Each with a set of items
purchased together.
The goal is to come up with rules
describing associations between items.
The first step is to create item sets.
Item sets have different sizes
which need to be created.
We will color code the items so
that each one is easier to pick
out from the transactions table.
We start out with just 1-item sets,
that is, sets with just one item.
The left table is
the dataset of transactions.
The right table contains the 1-item sets
that can be created from this dataset.
As each item set is created, we also need
to keep track of the frequency at which
these item set occurs in the dataset.
This is referred to support for
the item set and
is calculated by dividing the number of
times the item set occurs in the dataset
by the total number of transactions.
This is what is in the Support
column in the right table.
For example, eggs the last
item in the right table occurs
just occurs just once in the dataset,
in the transaction two.
So if Support is 1/5 or
one fifth,the item set with
diaper occurs in all transactions,
so if Support is 5/5 or 1.
The Support for each item set will be
used to identify frequent item sets
in the next step, specifically,
the Support issues to prune, or
remove, item sets that
do not occur frequently.
The support of each item set
will be used to identify
frequent item sets in the next step.
Specifically, the support
is used to prune or
remove item sets that do
not occur frequently.
For example, the minimum support
threshold is set to 3/5.
So looking at the 1-item sets table
We can remove any item set with
the support of less than 3/5.
These item sets are highlighted in pink,
they will be removed before the sets for
two items are created.
The final one item sets are then the item
sets with bread, milk, beer and diaper.
We only consider items that were in
the one item sets, that were not pruned.
The two item sets are shown
in the right table.
We, again,
need to keep track of the support for
these item sets,
just as we did with the one item sets.
For example, for
the last item set, with beer, and
diaper, we see, by looking at
the left table, that beer and
diaper occur together three times In
transactions two, three and four.
So with support is 3/5.
Again, we need to prune
item sets with low support.
The ones highlighted in pink
in the two item sets table.
Those would be the item set with bread and
beer and the item set with milk and beer.
The remaining two items that end.
One item such or
then use to create the three item sets.
Let's look now at
creating three item sets.
The only three item sets that has a
support value greater than minimum support
is the one shown in the right table.
Namely the items start with bread,
milk and diaper.
The second step in association analysis
is to identify the frequent item sets.
But note that the process
that we just described for
creating item sets already
identifies frequent item sets.
A frequent item set is one whose
support is greater than or
equal to the minimum support.
So by keeping track of the support of
each item set as it is being created and
removing item sets with low support,
we are already identifying
frequent item sets.
For our example, the frequent one,
two and three item sets are shown here.
Now that we identified the frequent
item sets, the last step is to
generate the rules to capture
associations that we see in the data.
Let's first define some terms we'll
need to discuss association rules.
The format of an association
rule is shown at the top.
It's written as X arrow Y and
is read as if X, then Y.
The X part is called the antecedent and
the Y part is called
the consequent of the rule.
X and Y are item sets.
An important term in rule
generation is the rule confidence.
This is to find as a support for X and
Y together divided by the support for
X only.
So rule confidence
calculates the frequency of
instances to which the rule applies.
Recall that the support for
X is the frequency of item set X and
is defined as the number of
transactions containing items in X
divided by the total
number of transactions.
The rule confidence measures
how frequently items in
Y appear in the transaction
that contain X.
In other words, the confidence measures
the reliability of the rule by determining
how often, if X and
Y is found to be true in the data.
How is rule confidence
used in rule generation?
Association rules are generated from the
frequent item sets created from the data.
Each item in an item set can be
used as a part of the antecedent or
consequent of the rule.
And you can have many ways to combine
items to form the antecedent and
consequent.
So if we just simply generate
rules from each frequent item set,
we would end up with lots and
lots of rules.
Each item set with k items can
generate 2 to the k-2 rules.
That's a lot of rules.
And the majority of those rules
would not be found in the data.
This is where rule confidence comes in.
We can use rule confidence to
constrain the number of rules to keep.
Specifically, a minimum
confidence threshold is set and
only rules with confidence greater than or
equal to the minimum confidence are
significant and only those will be kept.
Let's look at how this works
with our example dataset.
We call that only one three item set
was created from the transactions.
That three items that contains
items bread, milk and
diaper as shown at the top.
With these three item set let's see
how we can generate rules from it and
determine which rules to keep and
which one to prune.
Let's set the minimum confidence to 0.95.
And here again is the definition for
confidence.
For candidate rule if bread and
milk then diaper,
we can calculate it's confidence
as follows the support for
both antecedent and consequent is
the number of times we see bread, milk and
diaper together in the data, divided
by the total number of transactions.
Items bread, milk and diaper appear
together in transaction 1, 4 and
5 so the support is 3/5.
The support for just the antecedent is
the number of times we see bread and
milk together divided by
the total number of transactions.
Items bread and milk appear together
also in transactions 1, 4, and 5.
So the support is 3/5.
The confidence of this rule is then 1,
or 100%.
This means that the rule is correct 100%.
Every time bread and milk are bought
together, diaper is bought as well.
For candidate rule if bread and
diaper than milk,
we calculate its confidence the same way.
The support for bread, diaper and
milk is 3/5 as before.
Items bread and diaper are paired
together in transactions 1, 2, 4 and 5.
So the support for
the items set with bread and milk is 4/5.
Then the confidence with
this rule is 0.75 or 75%.
Since the minimum confidence is 0.95 or
95%,
the first rule is kept and the second
rule is removed from consideration.
There are several algorithms for
association analysis.
Each uses a different set of methods
to make frequent items set creation and
rule generation efficient.
The more popular algorithms are Apriori,
FP Growth and Eclat.
As a summary, we just looked at the steps
in association analysis in more detail.
We saw how items sets can be created from
a dataset, how frequent items sets can be
identified, and how association rules can
be created from frequent item sets and
pruned using rule confidence.
We've looked at classification,
regression and cluster analysis.
Let's now discuss association
analysis as a machine learning task.
After this video, you will be able to
explain what association analysis entails,
list some applications of association
analysis, define what an item set is.
In association analysis, the goal is to
come up with a set of rules to capture
associations between items or events.
The rules are used to determine when
items or events occur together.
You may remember seeing these images
earlier in the course, where we introduced
the different categories of machine
learning tasks and techniques.
But do you remember what
the association is between these items?
Well, let's recap that story,
in case you don't remember.
The story goes like this.
A supermarket chain used
association analysis to discover
a connection between two
seemingly unrelated products.
They discovered that many
customers who go to the store
late on Sunday night to buy
diapers also tend to buy beer.
This information was then used to
place beer and diapers close together.
And they saw a jump in
sales of both items.
This illustrates that you
can uncover unexpected and
useful relationships with
association analysis.
This diaper and beer story has become
part of the data mining folklore.
It's unclear how much of it true, but it
has become the prime example of what you
can discover with association analysis and
machine learning in general.
A common application of association
analysis is referred to as
market basket analysis.
This is used to understand
the purchasing behavior of customers.
The idea is that you're looking into
the shopping basket of customers
when they are at the market, and
analyzing that data to understand
what items are purchased together.
This information can be used to
place related items together, or
to have sales on items that
are often purchased together.
Another application of association
analysis is to recommend items that
a customer may be interested in, based
on their purchasing or browsing history.
This is very commonly used
on companies' websites
to get customers to buy more items.
There are medical applications as well.
Analysis of patients and treatments may
reveal associations to identify effective
treatments for
patients with certain medical histories.
this diagram illustrates how
association analysis works.
The data set is a collection
of transactions.
Each transaction contains one or
more items.
This is referred to as the item set.
From the given items sets,
generate association rules that capture
which item tend occur together.
In our example, the data set
consists of five transactions.
In the first transaction,
the items are diaper, bread and milk.
The second transaction has items bread,
diaper, beer, and eggs, and so on.
Rules that could be generated from
this data set are shown at the bottom.
For example,
the first rule states that if bread and
milk are bought together,
then diaper is also bought.
The second rule state that if milk is
bought, then bread is also bought.
The association analysis process
consist of the following steps.
The first step is to create item sets.
Item sets are generated for sets with one
item, two items, three items and so on.
Then frequent item sets are identified.
Frequent item sets are those that occur
at least a minimum number of times.
From the frequent item sets,
association rules are generated.
We will take a more detailed look
at these steps in the next lecture.
Some things to note about
association analysis.
Like cluster analysis, each transaction
does not have a label to specify which
item set or rule it belongs to.
So, association analysis
is an unsupervised task.
You may end up with many rules
at the end of the analysis.
But, whether those rules are interesting,
useful,
or applicable, requires interpretation
using domain knowledge of the application.
In addition,
the association analysis process will
not tell you how to apply the rules.
This also requires knowledge
of the application.
So as with cluster analysis,
interpretation and analysis are required
to make sense of the resulting rules
that you get from association analysis.
In summary,
association analysis finds rules to
capture associations between items.
The association rules have intuitive
appeal because they are in the form of
if this, then that,
which is easy to understand.
The results of association
analysis require analysis and
interpretation using domain knowledge
to determine the usefulness and
applicability of the resulting rules.
Next we will cover the steps in
the association analysis process in
more detail.