This is the second hands on exercises for
CSV data.
In the first, we saw how to import
a CSV file into a spreadsheet and
make a simple plot.
In this one,
we will learn how to filter data and
perform some aggregate operations.
We will begin by opening a terminal
window and starting a spreadsheet.
Next, we will load the CSV
data into the spreadsheet and
perform a filter over several columns.
Finally, we will calculate an average and
sum from the data.
Let's begin.
First, we open a terminal window by
clicking on the terminal icon in
the top toolbar.
We can start the spreadsheet
by writing oocalc.
Next, let's load our CSV
data into the spreadsheet.
We click on File > Open, CENSUS.CSV.
And click OK on this
dialog to load the data.
Column F in the spreadsheet is the state,
and
column H is the census population for
2010.
Let's create a filter that
just shows the data for
California, for
counties larger than one million people.
We can create this filter by first
selecting both the state name column and
the census 2000 population column.
Next we go to data,
filter, standard filter.
Here we change the field
name to be the state name,
the condition we leave at equals and
the value we use California.
This filters all the rows,
unless the state is California.
We then want to filter for
all the counties whose population
is greater than one million people.
To do that, in this second line here,
we change the operator to AND.
The field name should be
census 2010 population and
the condition should be greater than.
Then set the value to be one million.
And click OK.
We can see that all the data from the
spreadsheet has disappeared except where
the state name is California and
the population is greater
than one million people.
We can reset or remove this
filter to see all the data again
by going to Data > Filter.
Reset filter.
You can perform aggregate operations
on the data in a spreadsheet.
Next, let's perform some aggregate
operations over the data.
We can compute the average and
the sum of the data.
To do this, let's run these
calculations in a separate sheet.
Create a new sheet by clicking
on the green plus button.
To compute the average we select
a cell and enter =Average( and
then we select the data that we
want to compute the average from.
If we go back to sheet one.
We can select some of
the data from the H column.
So let's just choose several
counties in Alabama.
When we hit Enter,
it takes us back to sheet one and
we can see that the average is computing.
Similarly, we can compute the sum
by entering =sum, open parentheses.
Going back to sheet one and
selecting the columns we want to sum.
When we're done hit Enter and
the sum is computed.
In this hands on exercise,
we will be looking at JSON data.
First, we will open a terminal window and
then look at the contents of a JSON
file containing tweets from Twitter.
Next, we will examine
the schema of this JSON file.
Finally, we will extract different
fields from the JSON data.
Let's begin.
First, we'll open a terminal window,
by clicking on the terminal
icon at the top of the toolbar.
Next, we'll see cd into the directory
containing the json data,
by running cddownload/big/data/2/json.
We can run ls, to see the json file.
The json file is called twitter.json.
We can run more twitter.json to
view the contents of this file.
The json data contains semi-structured
data, which is nested several levels.
There are many tweets in this file, and
it's hard to read using the more command.
You can use space to scroll down and
when we're done, hit q.
We can run the jsonschema.pi command
to view the schema of this data.
We run jsonschema.pitwitter.json
And we'll add a pipe more at the end.
This shows the nested
fields within this data,
at the top level there are fields
like contributors text and id and so
on, but there are also fields nested
within these top level fields for
example entities also contains
called symbols media hashtags and
so on If we scroll down by hitting space,
we'll see that there's
several levels of nesting.
For example, user also has
follow_request_sent, id, and so on.
We can run the print json script to view
the contents of a particular tweet and
a particular field within that tweet.
Let's run print_json.py.
It asks for the file name so
we'll enter twitter.json.
And we'll look at tweet 99.
So let's look at the top
level field called text.
So here we see the text for
note the 99th tweet in this file.
We could also look at a nested field
within the file, by running print_json
again The file name is twitter.json.
We'll look at tweet 99 again.
And we'll look at the field
entities hashtags.
The hashtags that are embedded or
nested within the entities field.
This is the first of two hands
on exercises involving CSV Data.
In this exercise, we will import
a CSV file into a spreadsheet and
make a simple plot.
We will begin by opening a terminal window
and looking at a CSV file in the terminal.
Next, we will start
the spreadsheet application and
import the CSV data into the spreadsheet.
We can then look at the rows and columns
of the CSV file and make a simple plot.
Let's begin, first,
open a terminal shell by
clicking on the black terminal
icon at the top of the toolbar.
Next, let's cd into the directory
containing the CSV data.
We'll run cd space
Download/big-data-2/csv.
We can run ls to
see the CSV files.
The file census.csv contains
census data for the United States.
We can run the command more census.csv
to see the contents of this file.
The first line of this file is the header
with the columns separated by commas.
You can go down in
the file by hitting space.
Hit Q to quit more.
Next, let's start
a spreadsheet application.
We run oocalc to start this.
We can import the census
data CSV file into
the spreadsheet by going to File > Open.
Clicking on downloads.
Big Data 2, CSV, census.csv.
In this dialog click OK.
You can see into this spreadsheet,
import of the CSV data to
a bunch of rows and columns.
Each column that was separated
by a comma in the CSV file,
is a column in the spreadsheet.
We can see that our CSV file
was successfully imported into
the spreadsheet.
If we scroll down to
the bottom of the spreadsheet,
we can see how many rows
there were in the CSV file.
There are 3194 rows in the CSV file.
If this file instead had millions or
10 millions of rows,
then we would have to use a big
data system such as Hadoop or HDFS.
Let's scroll back to the top.
Next, let's make a simple plot of
some of the data in the CSV file.
Let's plot the population estimates for
several years for the state of Alabama.
The state of Alabama is
given in the second row and
the population estimates
are given in these columns.
Let's select J through O,
so you get the population
estimate for 2010 through 2015.
We can create a plot of these values
by clicking on the Chart button.
And clicking finish.
In the second hands on for CSV data,
we'll perform some filtering and
some aggregate operations over the data.
Welcome.
In this module,
we'll talk about data models.
If you completed the introductory
course of this specialization,
you might recall our
video on data variety.
One way to characterize data variety
is to identify the different models of
data that are used in any application.
So what is a data model?
And why do we care about data
models in the context of big data?
In this lesson, we'll introduce you to
three components of a data model and
what they tell us about the data.
So after this lesson, you'll be able
to distinguish between structured and
unstructured data.
Describe four basic data operations namely
selection, projection, union, and join.
And enumerate different types of data
constraints like type, value and
structural constraints.
You'll also be able to explain why
constraints are useful to specify
the semantics of data.
Now, regardless of whether the data is big
or small, one needs to know or determine
the characteristics of data before one can
manipulate or analyze them meaningfully.
Let's use a simple example,
suppose you have data is
a file of records with fields called first
name, last name and date of birth of
the employees in the company that this
file consists of records with fields,
and not for instance plain text,
gives us more insight
into the organization of the data in the
file and hence is part of the data model.
This aspect is called Structure.
Similarly, the consideration
that we can perform
data arithmetic with
the date of birth field, and
not with the first name field, is also
part of our understanding of data model.
These are called Operations.
Finally, we may know that in
this company no one's age
that is today's date minus the date
of birth, can't be less than 18.
So it gives us a way to detect records
with blatantly erroneous dates of birth.
In the following three videos,
we'll look at these three aspects
of data models more carefully.
We mentioned before that a data model
is characterized by the structure of
the data that it admits,
the operations on that structure, and
a way to specify constraints.
In this lesson,
we'll present a more detailed description
of a number of common data models.
We'll start with relational data.
It is one of the simplest and most
frequently used data models today, and
forms the basis of many other
traditional database management systems,
like MySQL, Oracle,
Teradata, and so forth.
So after this video you'll be able to
describe the structural components
of a relational data model.
Demonstrate which components
become a data model's schema.
Explain the purpose of primary and
foreign keys.
And describe Join and other operations.
The primary data structure for
a relational model is a table, like
the one shown here for a toy application.
But we need to be careful about relational
tables, which are also called relations.
This table actually
represents a set of tuples.
This is a relational tuple,
represented as a row in the table.
We were informally calling
this a record before.
But a relational tuple implies that unless
otherwise stated, the elements of it
like 203 or 204, Mary and
so forth, are atomic.
That is,
they represent one unit of information and
cannot be decomposed further.
We'll return to this issue
in the next few slides.
Thus, this is a relation of six tuples.
Remember, the definition of sets,
it's a collection of distinct
elements of the same type.
That means I cannot add
this tuple to the solution.
Because if I do,
it will be introducing a duplicate.
Now in practice, many systems will allow
duplicate tuples in a relation, but
mechanisms are provided to prevent
duplicate entries if the user so chooses.
So I cannot add it.
Here is another tuple I cannot add.
It has all the right
pieces of information, but
it's all in the wrong order.
So it is a tuple dissimilar with
the other six tuples in the relation.
Okay, so how does the system know
that this tuple is different?
This brings our attention to the very
first row that is the header of this table
painted in black.
This row is part of
the scheme of the table.
Lets look at it.
It tells us the name of the table,
in this case employee.
This also tells us the names of the six
columns called attributes of the relation.
And for each column,
it tells us the allowed data type, that
is the type constraint for each column.
Given this schema,
it should now be clear why the last
red row does not belong to this table.
The schema in a relational table
can also specify constraints,
shown in yellow in the third
line of the schema row.
It says that the minimum salary of
a person has to be greater than 25k.
Further, it states that every employee
must have a first and last name.
They cannot be left null,
that means without a value.
Why doesn't department or
title column have this constraint?
One answer can be that a newly
hired employee may not be assigned
a department or a title yet but
can still be an entry in the table.
However, the department column
has another constraint.
It restricts the possible values
that is the domain of the attribute
to only four possibilities.
HR, IT, research, and business.
Finally, the first says
that ID is a primary key.
This means it is unique for each employee.
And for
every employee knowing the primary key for
the employee will also uniquely know the
other five attributes of that employee.
You should now see that
a table with a primary key
logically implies that the table cannot
have a duplicate record because if we do,
it will violate the uniqueness constraint
associated with the primary key.
Let us introduce a new table containing
the salary history of employees.
The employees are identified
with the column EmpID, but
these are not new values that
this table happens to have.
They are the same IDs that are present in
the ID column of the employee's table,
presented earlier.
This is reflected in
the statement made on the right.
The term References means,
the values in this column can exist
only if the same values if you are in
employees the table being referenced,
also called the parent table.
So in the terminology of the relational
model, the EmpID column of EmpSalaries
table is called a foreign key that refers
to the primary key of the Employees table.
Note that EmpID is not a primary
key in this EmpSalaries table.
Because it is multiple to
post with the same EmpID
reflecting the salary of
the employee at different times.
You will remember join is a common
operation that we discussed before.
So here is an example of
a relational join performed
on the first three columns of employee and
EmpSalaries table.
Where employees.ID, and EmpSalaries.EmpID
columns are matched for equality.
The output table shows
all the columns involved.
The common column is represented once.
This form of join is
called a Natural Join.
It is important to understand that
join is one of the most expensive
that means time consuming and
space consuming operations.
As data becomes larger, and tables contain
hundreds of millions of tuples, the join
operation can easily become a bottleneck
in a larger analytic application.
So for analytical big data application
that needs joins, it's very important to
choose a suitable data management platform
that makes this operation efficient.
We will return to this
issue in module four.
We end this video on a practical note.
In many scientific and
business applications,
people start with CSV files,
manipulate them with the spreadsheet,
then migrate their relational system only
as an afterthought where the data becomes
too large to handle the spreadsheet.
While the spreadsheet offers
many useful features.
It does not conform and enforce many
principles of relational data models.
Consequently, a large amount of time
may be spent in cleaning up and
correcting data errors after
the migration actually happens.
Let me show a few examples from
a spreadsheet that has 125,000 rows and
over 100 columns.
The spreadsheet here lists terrorism
attacks gathered from news media.
So each row represents one attack.
This is a valuable piece of data for
people who study terrorism.
But we are going to look at it from
a relational data modelling viewpoint.
First, notice the column marked in green.
It lists two weapons used in
the attack separated by a semicolon.
Why is this really common?
It makes this column non-atomic.
It means that this column actually
has two different values.
In a relational design, this information
will be moved to another table
just like the multiple salaries of
employees were placed in a separate table.
Next, notice the column outlined in red.
It describes the amount of property
damaged by a possible terrorist attack.
In this column, the intended
legitimate values are unknown,
minor, major and catastrophic.
However, the value in the highlighted
part of the spreadsheet is minor and
then within bracket,
likely less than $1 million.
Which means a query like
find all attacks for
which the property damage is equal to
minor cannot be answered directly.
Instead, we need to perform
a substring search for
minor in the beginning of the description.
Which is doable, but
it's a more expensive operation.
This shows the columns of the spreadsheet.
So this is part of the schema of the data.
If you observe carefully you
will see a recurring pattern.
The designer of the data table determined
that there can be at most three types of
attacks within a single encounter and
represented with three separate columns.
Now in proper relational modeling,
one would say that there is a one to many
relationship between the attack and
the number of attack types.
In such a case, it would be more prudent
to place these attack type
columns in a separate table and
connect with the parent using a primary
key, foreign key relationship.
Here's another block,
with a similar pattern,
this time this is about the types and
subtypes of weapons used.
Now can you determine how you might
be able to reorganize this block?
We'll leave this as an exercise.