The Sixth V, Value.
In this module,
we described the five ways which are
considered to be dimensions of big data.
Each way presented a challenging
dimension of big data namely,
size, complexity, speed,
quality, and connectedness.
Although we can list some other rays base
on the context, we prefer to list these
five s fundamental dimensions that this
big data specialization helps you work on.
However, at the heart of
the big data challenge
is turning all of the other dimensions
into truly useful business value.
The idea behind processing all
this big data in the first place
is to bring value to the problem at hand.
In week two we will explore how
to take the first steps into
starting to generate
value out of big data.
Now that we saw all the ways, let's focus
on an example of a big data challenge.
Let's imagine now that you're part
of a company called Eglence Inc.
One of the products of Eglence Inc
is a highly popular mobile game
called Catch the Pink Flamingo.
It's a multi-user game where
the users have to catch special types
of pink flamingos that randomly
pop up on the world map on their
screens based on the mission
that gets updated randomly.
The game is played by millions of
people online throughout the world.
One of the goals of the game is to form
a network of players to collectively
cover the world map with pink flamingo
sightings and compete other groups.
Users can pick their groups
based on player stats.
The game's website sends free
cool stuff to registered users.
Registration requires users to enter
demographic information such gender,
year of birth, city, highest education,
and things like that.
However, most of the users enter
inaccurate information about themselves,
just like most of us do.
To help improve the game,
the game collects realtime usage activity
data from each player and
feeds them to it's data servers.
The players of this game are
enthusiastically active on social media,
and have strong
associations with the game.
A popular Twitter hashtag for
this game is, CatchThePinkFlamingo,
which gets more than 200,000
mentions worldwide per day.
There are strong communities of
users who meet via social media and
get together to play the game.
Now, imagine yourself as the big data
solutions architect for Fun Games Inc.
There are definitely examples of all three
types of data sources in this example.
The mobile app generates data for
the analysis of user activity.
Twitter conversations of players form
a rich source of unstructured data from
people.
And the customer and
game records are examples of data
that this organization collects.
This is a challenging big data example
where all characteristics of
big data are represented.
There are high volumes of player, game and
Twitter data,
which also speaks to the variety of data.
The data streams from the mobile app,
website, and
social media in real-time, which can
be defined as high velocity data.
The quality of demographic data
users enter is not clear, and
there are networks of players which
are related to the balance of big data.
Cloud Computing: An Important
Big Data Enabler.
In our first lecture in this course,
we mentioned the cloud as one of
the two influences of
the launch of the big data era.
We called it on-demand computing, and
we said that it enables us to
compute any time any anywhere.
Simply, whenever we demand it.
In this video,
we will see how we deploy the cloud to
our benefit in our big data applications.
The main idea behind cloud computing
is to transform computing
infrastructure into a commodity.
So application developers can focus on
solving application-specific challenges
instead of trying to build
infrastructure to run on.
So how does this happen?
We can simply define
a cloud computing service,
as a rental service for computing.
You rent what you want,
and return upon usage.
Think about this, you wouldn't buy, or
even build, a truck every time you
have to move a piece of furniture.
You would simply rent.
Why build a computing
cluster when you can rent?
Especially if you are not
using it all the time.
Similarly, you can rent a car or
a bike when you are on vacation.
So you can bike anytime, anywhere.
Let's dig into this question.
What factors do you consider when you're
developing a solution for your yourself or
your client?
Should you build a hardware and
software resources yourself?
Or should you rent these
resources from the cloud?
Let's look at in-house hardware and
software resource building first.
If you choose to develop in-house
capabilities, you have to hire people and
buy hardware that suits your requirements.
These includes, but not limited to,
buying networking hardware,
storage disks, upgrading hardware
when it becomes obsolete, and so on.
Not to forget, the real estate
cost of keeping the hardware.
How do you estimate the size
of your hardware needs?
Do you make a five year estimate,
or ten year?
In today's fast changing world,
it is becoming harder to
estimate future demands.
Getting the software that fits
your needs is equally challenging.
Most software installations
require a lot of tweaking and
manual intervention that
require a lot of skills.
You will need your engineers to do this.
Compatibility issues bring
problems that are hard to foresee.
Most software is updated on a daily basis.
You must ensure you're updated.
This insures you avoid security risks and
get the best.
Over all, building your own data center or
computing power house can be expensive.
And it can be time consuming,
maintaining it is a task by itself.
This requires high initial
capital investments and
efficient operation of several
departments in your business,
which you might not have if
you are a startup company.
Most people forget to include
the cost of disposing old hardware.
Now lets see what the cloud can do for us.
Cloud's benefits are similar to what you
would get from a rental car company.
You pay for what you use,
which means a low capital investment.
You don't need to go to the dealership,
do a negotiation, get a bank loan,
get insurance.
That means quick implementation
of your projects.
Just like you don't need to buy
a car if you only need a car for
a limited use, deploying your application
on a server that is geographically
closer to your client can give you
fast service and happy customers.
For startup and small business,
it can be challenging to do so.
Cloud lets you do this with a click.
You can be sitting at a coffeeshop or your
home and starting your Internet business,
without a huge capital investment,
thanks to the cloud.
And you don't need to have a five or
ten year resource estimation plan.
Adapt to your requirements faster if
your business is growing faster than you
thought.
Cloud lets you forget about
the resource management problems and
lets you focus on your business's products
or domain expertise with minimal cost.
Just as you can rent a truck or
a convertible at a rental car company,
you can build your own
custom machine on cloud.
With a custom machine,
we mean a commodity cluster
made out of the right type of
computing nodes for your application.
You pick not only a CPU or a GPU, but
pick from a whole menu of compute,
memory and storage choices.
It's a buffet on the cloud.
Design machines to suit your application
requirements, data size and analytics.
Get what you want, and
pay for what you use.
Compare this with buying and
maintaining all combinations of
hardware that you possibly would use.
That is so costly and
not possible at all times.
Thanks to all these advantages, there
are many cloud server providers today.
And the numbers are growing.
Here we list some of the players
in the cloud computing market.
Take a moment to look at them.
You will probably recognize
some big names and
some others you have not
even heard of before.
As a summary, cloud does the heavy
lifting, so your team can extract
value from data with getting bogged
down in the infrastructure details.
Cloud provides convenient and
viable solutions for scaling your
prototype to a full fledged application.
You can leverage the experts
to handle security,
robustness, and
let them handle the technical issues.
Your team can work on
utilizing your strengths
to solve your domain specific problem.
Cloud Service Models: Exploration
of Choices.
There are many levels of services that
you can get from cloud providers.
Any cloud computing discussion will
involve terms like application
as a service, platform as a service,
and infrastructure as a service.
All of these refer to business
models around using the cloud
with different levels of engagement and
servicing similar to rental agreements.
IaaS, infrastructure as a service, can be
defined as a bare minimum rental service.
This is like renting a truck from
a company that you can assume has hardware
and you do the packing of your furniture,
and drive to your new house.
You as the user of the service install and
maintain an operating system,
and other applications in
the infrastructure as a service model.
The Amazon EC2 cloud is a good example for
this model.
PaaS, platform as a service,
is the model where a user is provided
with an entire computing platform.
This could include the operating system
and programming languages that you need.
It could extend to include the database
of your choice, or even a web server.
You can develop, and
run your own application software,
on top of these layers.
The Google App engine and Microsoft Azure
are two examples of this model.
SaaS, the software as a service model,
is the model
in which the cloud service provider takes
the responsibilities for the hardware and
software environment such as the operating
system and the application software.
This means you can work on using
the application to solve your problem.
Dropbox is a very popular
software as a service platform.
Ultimately, the decision of which service
you want to explore is a function of
several variables.
It depends on the skill level of your
team to handle computing environment,
development and maintenance.
It also depends on how you
might need to use the service.
You need to pick the right
service model that
best fits you in terms of long term goals.
Finally, when you're deploying a cloud
service you also have to understand
all the security risks, since your
data resides on third party service.
Security is a very important
aspect in today's world of growing
digitization of information.
You must make your client's
data safety a top priority,
and hence this should be an important
criteria in your decision.
All the security risks
must be understood and
evaluated as your data resides
on third party servers.
We are seeing other forms
of services being added
to the family of cloud services.
The logic of infrastructure, platform, and
Software as a Service is
getting extended further.
XaaS is an umbrella term that signifies
even finer-grain control over computing
resources that you want to rent.
For example, storage as a service,
communication as a service,
marketing as a service, and so on.
As a summary, infrastructure as a service,
platform as a service, and application
as a service are three main class service
models that are being used with success.
Picking one will depend on the number
of variables which are company's goals.
These three models have
inspired many similar models
to emerge around cloud computing.
In this lecture we'll be learning about
the basic file manipulation commands for
the Hadoop File System or HDFS.
We'll first start by downloading
a text file of words.
We'll use this text file to copy to and
from the local file system in HDFS and
later on we'll use it
to run word count on.
After we download the text file,
we'll open a terminal shell and
copy the text file from
the local file system to HDFS.
Next, we'll copy the file within HDFS and
also see how to copy file from
HDFS to the local file system.
Finally, we'll see how to
delete a file in HDFS.
Let's start.
We're going to download text
file to copy into HDFS.
It doesn't matter what the contents of
the text file is, so we'll download
the complete works of Shakespeare
since it contains interesting text.
First, click on the icon here
to launch a web browser.
Now we'll search Google for
the complete works of Shakespeare.
I'm going to be using
this first link here.
And we'll provide this link
in the reading section.
So this is the complete
works of Shakespeare and
we'll save it to a text file in the local
file system by clicking on the icon here,
the Open Menu and selecting save page.
So we'll call it words.txt.
And the Save in folder, it's going to
save it into the Downloads directory.
Once that completes, we'll open a terminal
window by clicking on the icon here.
So if we go into the downloads
Ddrectory by typing a cd Downloads and
running ls, we can see that words.txt
was successfully downloaded.
Moving on, let's copy words.txt from the
local file system to the HDFS file system.
The command to do this is hadoop
fs- copyFromLocal words.txt.
When I run this,
it'll copy it from the local directory and
local file system to HDFS.
We can see that the file was
copied by running hadoop fs -ls.
You can see that the file
was successfully copied.
Next, we can copy this file
to another file within HDFS.
We can do this by running hadoop
fs -cp words.txt words2.txt.
The first words.txt is the file
that already exists in HDFS.
The second words 2.txt
is the new file that we're going to
create when we run this command.
Let's run it, and again we're can run
hadoopfs-ls to see the files in HDFS.
We can see the original file words.txt,
and the copy that was made, words2.txt.
Let's copy words2.txt from
HDFS to the local filesystem.
We can do this by running hadoop
fs -copyToLocal words2.txt.
After I run this command, I can call ls to
see the contents of the local file system.
So now we have the new file words2.txt
which we've just copied from HDFS.
The last step in this lecture
is to delete a file in HDFS.
We can delete words2.txt
by running hadoop fs,
but is rn words2.txt.
As you can see,
it printed that it deleted the file.
We can also run hadoop fs- ls,
to verify that the file is deleted.
You can see that there's only the original
words.txt, and words2.txt was deleted.
Getting started.
Why do we worry about foundations?
Starting next week you'll start
diving into the details of the Hadoop
framework for big data.
Before you start, taking a little
bit of time to understand some core
concepts will help you to digest the
information on Hadoop better and faster.
Imagine yourself attending
a chemistry lab.
Before you start hearing about
the tubes and mixtures, you really need
to understand the chemistry or theory
of the practical concepts in the lab.
Similarly, learning these
concepts now will help
you with your understanding of the
practical concepts in the Hadoop lectures.
In addition, we want to prepare you to
understand the tools beyond Hadoop.
Any big data system that you find
will be built on these core concepts.
So these foundations will
help you beyond this course.
Now, let's get started.