In this activity, we will use
Spark to perform cluster analysis.
First, we will load
the minute weather data.
Next, we will remove the unused and
missing data and
then scale the data so
that the mean is zero.
We will then create an elbow plot,
a subset of the data,
to determine the optimal
number of clusters.
And then cluster the full
data set using k-means.
Finally, we will generate parallel plots
to analyze the individual clusters.
Let's begin.
First, let's open the clustering notebook.
Execute the first cell
to load the libraries.
Execute the second cell
to load the data set.
This data set contains weather station
measurements that were taken every minute.
So there's a lot of measurements.
We can count how many rows there are in
the data frame by running df.count.
This says that there are over 1.5
million rows in the data frame.
Clustering this much data on a single
Cloudera VM can take a lot of time.
So let's only work with
one-tenth of the data.
Let's subset the data
into the new data frame.
We'll enter filteredDF
= df.filter((df.rowID
% 10)) == 0.
We then count the rows of the new data
frame by calling filteredDF.count.
The new data frame has one-tenth as
many rows as the original data set.
Let's compute the summary
statistics using describe.
filteredDF.describe, and
to display it nicely,
we'll enter toPandas().transpose.
Run this.
These weather measurements were taken
during the period of a long drought.
As we can see from the mean values
of the two rain measurements,
rain accumulation, the rain duration,
the measurements are close to zero.
Let's count how many rain
values are equal to 0.
FilterDF.filter(filterDF.rain_accumulation
==
0.0).count().
Now let's do rain duration.
filteredDF.filter(filteredDF.rain_duration
==
0.0).count().
We can see from these counts that most
in these two measurements are zero.
So let's remove them from our data frame.
workingDF =
filterDF.drop('rain_accumulation').drop('-
rain_duration').
And we'll also drop the column
called hpwren_timestamp,
since we will not use it.
So .drop('hpwren_timestamp').
Next, let's drop rows with missing values,
and count how many rows were dropped.
before = workingDF.count() workingDF =
workingDF.na.drop() after
= workingDF.count(),
and finally, we'll print the difference,
before- after.
So only 46 rows had missing values and
were dropped.
Next, let's scale the data so that each
feature will have a value of 0 for
the mean and a value of 1 for
the standard deviation.
First, we need to combine the columns
into a single vector column.
We can look at the existing columns
by entering workingDF.columns.
We do not want to include rowID
since it is a row number.
Additionally, the minimum wind
measurements have a high correlation
to the average wind measurements,
so we will not include this either.
Let's create an array of
the columns we want to combine and
then use vector assembler to
create the vector column.
featuresUsed = [.
Now, let's copy and
paste the columns we want to use.
Assembler = VectorAssembler(inputCols
= featuresUsed,
outputCol = "features_unscaled").
And finally, assembled =
assembler.transform(workingDF).
Run this.
Now we'll use standard
scaler to scale the data.
Scaler = standard scaler
inputCol=”features _unscaler”,
outputCol=“features”, withStd = true,
withMean = True,
scalerModel = scaler.fit(assembled),
scaledData =
scalerModel.transform[assembled].
Next we will create an elbow plot
to determine the value k, for
the number of clusters.
To create the elbow plot,
we will calculate the within cluster,
sum of squared error, or WSSE,
for different values of k.
So since some valves running
K-means many times, let's do it for
a smaller subset of the data
since it'll be faster.
First, let's choose the data to work with.
Let's subset the data.
So scaledData =
scaledData.select("features"), ("rowID").
elbowset =
scaledData.filter((scaledData.rowID
%3) == 0).select("features").
And finally,
we'll call the persist method on elbowset.
Persist will keep it in memory,
and make the calculations faster.
Run this.
Now, let's compute the WSSE values for
different values of k.
We'll do for k, 2 to 30.
Clusters equals range(2,31).
wsseList = utils.elbow(elbowset,
clusters).
Run this, This will print out
the value of wsse for each value of k.
As you can tell, this'll take some
time to run, let's skip to the end.
Now let's display the plot of our data.
utils.elbow_plot(wsseList, clusters).
The x axis is k, the number of clusters,
and the y axis is the WSSE value.
You can see that the graph flattens
out between 10 and 15 for k.
So let's choose k equals 12 as
the midpoint for our number of clusters.
We'll now cluster the data into
12 clusters using k-means.
First, let's select the data
we want to cluster.
scaledDataFeat =
scaledData.select("features"),
scaledDataFeat.persist.
Now I'll perform
the clustering using kmeans.
kmeans = KMeans(k=12, seed=1).
model = KMeans.fit(scaledDataFeat),
and finally,
transformed =
model.transform(scaleDataFeat).
Run this.
We can now see the centre
measurement of each
cluster by calling model.clusterCenters.
It is difficult to compare the cluster
centers just by looking at these numbers.
So let's use parallel
plots to visualize them.
P = utils.pd_centers(featuresUsed,
model.clusterCenters).
Let's show the clusters for
dry days where the weather samples
have low relative humidity.
utils.parallel_plot(P[P['relative_humidi-
ty']
< -0.5], P).
The x axis of this chart shows
the different measurement types.
The y values show the standard deviations,
with zero being the mean.
Each line is a different cluster, and
there are five clusters in this graph.
We can see that they all have
a low relative humidity.
Notice that cluster four, the red one,
has a high average wind speed and
a high maximum wind speed.
Additionally, it has a low
average wind direction.
Which means it was coming from
the north and northeast directions.
So this cluster probably
represents Santa Ana conditions.
Next, let's show the plot for warm days,
the weather samples with
high air temperature.
utils.parallel_plot(P[P['air_temp'] >
0.5], P).
Other clusters in this plot have air
temperature greater than 0.5 standard
deviations away from the mean.
However, they have different values for
the other features.
Now let's show the clusters for cool days.
Weather samples with high relative
humidity and low air temperatures.
utils.parallel_plot(P[(P['relative_humidi-
ty']
> 0.5) & (P['air_temp']
< 0.5)], P).
All the clusters in this plot have
relative humidity greater than 0.5
standard deviations and air temp
less than 0.5 standard deviations.
These clusters represent cool
temperature with high humidity and
possibly rainy weather patterns.
So far we have seen all
the clusters except two.
Since it is not falling to any other
categories let's plot this cluster,
utils.parallel_plot(P.iloc[[2]],
P).
Cluster two captures
days with mild weather.
In addition to classification and
regression, machine learning tasks and
techniques can also fall into another
category known as cluster analysis.
After this video, you will be able to
articulate the goal of cluster analysis,
discuss whether cluster analysis
is supervised or unsupervised, and
list some ways that cluster
results can be applied.
In cluster analysis,
the goal is to organize similar items in
your data set into groups or clusters.
By segmenting your data into clusters, you
can analyze each cluster more carefully.
Note that cluster analysis is
also referred to as clustering.
A very common application of cluster
analysis that we have discussed before is
to divide your customer base into segments
based on their purchasing histories.
For example, you can segment customers
into those who have purchased science
fiction books and videos, versus those
who tend to buy nonfiction books,
versus those who have bought
many children's books.
This way, you can provide more targeted
suggestions to each different group.
Some other examples of cluster analysis
are characterizing different weather
patterns for a region,
grouping the latest news articles into
topics to identify the trending
topics of the day, and
discovering hot spots for different
types of crime from police reports
in order to provide sufficient
police presence for problem areas.
Cluster analysis divides all
the samples in a data set into groups.
In this diagram,
we see that the red, green, and
purple data points are clustered together.
Which group a sample is placed in is
based on some measure of similarity.
The goal of cluster analysis is to segment
data so that differences between samples
in the same cluster are minimized, as
shown by the yellow arrow, and differences
between samples of different clusters are
maximized, as shown by the orange arrow.
Visually, you can think of
this as getting samples in
each cluster to be as close
together as possible, and
the samples from different clusters
to be as far apart as possible.
Cluster analysis requires
some sort of metric to
measure similarity between two samples.
Some common similarity measures are
Euclidean distance, which is the distance
along a straight line between two points,
A and B, as shown in this plot.
Manhattan distance, which is
calculated on a strictly horizontal and
vertical path, as shown in the right plot.
To go from point A to point B, you can
only step along either the x-axis or
the y-axis in a two-dimensional case.
So the path to calculate the Manhattan
distance consists of segments
along the axes instead of along a diagonal
path, as with Euclidean distance.
Cosine similarity measures the cosine
of the angle between points A and
B, as shown in the bottom plot.
Since distance measures such as Euclidean
distance are often used to measure
similarity between samples
in clustering algorithms,
note that it may be necessary to
normalize the input variables so
that no one value dominates
the similarity calculation.
We discussed scaling and
normalizing variables in the lecture
on feature transformation.
Normalizing is one method
to scale variables.
Essentially, scaling the input variables
puts the variables on the same scale so
that all variables have equal
weighting in the calculation
to determine similarity between samples.
Scaling is necessary when you have
variables that have very different scales,
such as weight and height.
The magnitude of the height values,
which are in feet and inches,
will be much smaller than the magnitude of
the weight values, which are in pounds.
So scaling both variables to
a common value range will
make the contributions from
both weight and height equal.
Here are some things to note
about cluster analysis.
First, unlike classification or
regression, in general,
cluster analysis is an unsupervised task.
This means that there is no target
label for any sample in the data set.
In general,
there is no correct clustering results.
The best set of clusters
is highly dependent
on how the resulting
clusters will be used.
There are numerical measures to
compare two different clusters, but
since there are no labels to
determine whether a sample has
been correctly clustered,
there is no ground truth
to determine if a set of clustering
results are truly correct or incorrect.
Clusters don't come with labels.
You may end up with five different
clusters at the end of a cluster
analysis process, but you don't
know what each cluster represents.
Only by analyzing
the samples in each cluster
can you come out with reasonable
labels for your clusters.
Given all this, it is important to
keep in mind that interpretation and
analysis of the clusters
are required to make sense of and
make use of the results
of cluster analysis.
There are several ways that the results
of cluster analysis can be used.
The most obvious is data segmentation and
the benefits that come from that.
If you segment your customer base
into different types of readers,
the resulting insights can be used
to provide more effective marketing
to the different customer groups
based on their preferences.
For example, analyzing each segment
separately can provide valuable insights
into each group's likes, dislikes and
purchasing behavior, just like we see
science fiction, non-fiction and
children's books preferences here.
Clusters can also be used to
classify new data samples.
When a new sample is received,
like the orange sample here, compute
the similarity measure between it and
the centers of all clusters, and assign
a new sample to the closest cluster.
The label of that cluster,
manually determined through analysis,
is then used to classify the new sample.
In our book buyers' preferences example,
a new customer can be classified as being
either a science fiction, non-fiction or
children's books customer
depending on which cluster the new
customer is most similar to.
Once cluster labels have been determined,
samples in each cluster can be used as
labeled data for a classification task.
The samples would be the input
to the classification model.
And the cluster label would be
the target class for each sample.
This process can be used to provide much
needed labeled data for classification.
Yet another use of cluster results
is as a basis for anomaly detection.
If a sample is very far away, or
very different from any of the cluster
centers, like the yellow sample here,
then that sample is a cluster outlier and
can be flagged as an anomaly.
However, these anomalies
require further analysis.
Depending on the application, these
anomalies can be considered noise, and
should be removed from the data set.
An example of this would be a sample
with a value of 150 for age.
For other cases, these anomalous cases
should be studied more carefully.
Examples of this are in a credit
card fraud detection, or,
a network intrusion detection application.
In these applications, examples outside
of the norm are the interesting cases
that should be looked at to determine
if they represent potential problems.
To summarize, cluster analysis is used to
organize similar data items into groups or
clusters.
Analyzing the resulting clusters
often leads to useful insights
about the characteristics of each group,
as well as the underlying
structure of the entire data set.
Clusters require analysis and
interpretation to make
sense of the results,
since there are no labels associated with
samples or clusters in a clustering task.
In the next lecture, we will discuss
a specific algorithm for cluster analysis.
k-means clustering is a simple yet
effective algorithm for
cluster analysis that is
commonly used in practice.
After this video,
you will be able to describe
the steps in the k-means algorithm,
explain what the k stands for in k-means
and define what a cluster centroid is.
Recall a cluster analysis divides samples
in a data set into groups or clusters.
The idea is to group similar items in
the same cluster, where similar is defined
by some metric that measures
similarity between data samples.
So the goal of cluster analysis
is to divide data sample
such that sample within a cluster
are as close together as possible.
And samples from different clusters
are as far apart as possible.
k-means is a classic algorithm used for
cluster analysis.
The algorithm is very simple.
The first step is to select
k initial centroids.
A centroid is simply the center of
a cluster, as you see in the diagram here.
Next, assign each sample in
a dataset to the closest centroid.
This means you calculate
the distance between the sample and
each cluster center and assign a sample
to the cluster with the closest centroid.
Then you calculate the mean,
or average, of each cluster
to determine a new centroid.
These two steps are then repeated until
some stopping criterion are reached.
Here's an illustration
of how k-Means works.
(a) shows the original data
set with some samples.
And (b) illustrates centroids
initially selected.
(c) shows the first iteration.
Here, samples are assigned
to the closest centroid.
In (d), the centroids are recalculated.
(e) shows the second iteration.
Samples are assigned to
the closer centroid.
Note that some samples changed
their cluster assignments.
And in (f),
the centroids are recalculated again.
Cluster assignments and
centroid calculations are repeated until
some stopping criteria is reached.
And you get your final clusters,
as shown in (f).
How are the initial centroids selected?
The issue is that the final
cluster results are sensitive
to initial centroids.
This means that cluster results with
one set of initial centroids can be
very different from results with
another set of initial centroids.
There are many approaches to
selecting the initial centroids for
k-means varying in levels
of sophistication.
The easiest and most widely used approach
is to apply k-means several times
with different initial centroids
randomly chosen to cluster you dataset.
And then select the centroids that
give the best clustering results.
To evaluate the cluster results,
an error measure,
known as the within cluster sum
of squared error, can be used.
The error associated with a sample
within a cluster is the distance between
the sample and the cluster centroid.
The squared error of the sample then,
is the squared of that distance.
We sum up all the squared errors for
all samples for
a cluster to the get the squared error for
that cluster.
We then do the same thing for all
clusters to get the final calculation for
the within-cluster sum
of squared error for
all clusters in the results
of a cluster analysis run.
Given two clustering results, the one with
the smaller within-cluster sum of squared
error, or WSSE for short,
provides the better solution numerically.
However, as we've discussed before,
there is no ground truth
to mathematically determine which set of
clusters is more correct than the other.
In addition, note that increasing
the number of clusters,
that is, increasing the value for
k, always reduces WSSE.
So WSSE should be used with caution.
It only makes sense to use WSSE
to compare two sets of clusters
with the same value for k and
generate it from the same dataset.
Also the set of clusters with
the smallest WSSE may not
always be the best solution for
the application at hand.
Again, interpretation and
domain knowledge about what the cluster
should represent and how they will be used
are crucial in determining
which cluster results are best.
Now that there are several metrics that are
used to evaluate cluster results as well.
Choosing the optimal value for k is
always a big question in using k-means.
There are several methods to
determine the value for k.
We will discuss a few here.
Visualization techniques can be used
to determine the dataset to see if
there are natural
groupings of the samples.
Scatter plots and
the use of dimensionality reduction
are useful here, to visualize the data.
A good value for
k is application-dependent.
So domain knowledge of the application can
drive the selection for the value of k.
For example,
if you want to cluster the types of
products customers are purchasing,
a natural choice for k might be the number
of product categories that you offer.
Or k might be selected to represent the
geographical locations of respondents to
a survey.
In which case, a good value for
k would be the number of regions
your interested in analyzing.
There are also data-driven method for
determining the value of k.
These methods calculate symmetric for
different values of k to determine
the best selections of k.
One such method is the elbow method.
The elbow method for determining
the value of k is shown on this plot.
As we saw in the previous slide,
WSSE, or within-cluster sum of
squared error, measures how much
data samples deviate from their respective
centroids in a set of clustering results.
If we plot WSSE for different values for
k, we can see how this
error measure changes as a value
of k changes as seen in the plot.
The bend in this error curve indicates
a drop in gain by adding more clusters.
So this elbow in the curve provides
a suggestion for a good value of k.
Note that the elbow can not always be
unambiguously determined, especially for
complex data.
And in many cases, the error curve
will not have a clear suggestion for
one value, but for multiple values.
This can be used as a guideline for
the range of values to try for k.
We've discussed choosing
the initial centroids and
looked at ways to select a value for
k, the number of clusters.
Let's now look at when to stop.
How do you know when to stop
iterating when using k-means?
One obviously stopping criterion is when
there are no changes to the centroids.
This means that no samples would
change cluster assignments.
And recalculating the centroids
will not result in any changes.
So additional iterations will
not bring about any more changes
to the cluster results.
The stopping criterion can be relaxed to
the second stopping criterion listed here.
Which is when the number of
sample changing clusters is below
a certain threshold, say 1% for example.
At this point, the clusters
are changing by only a few samples,
resulting in only minimal changes
to the final cluster results.
So the algorithm can be stopped here.
At the end of k-means we have a set
of clusters, each with a centroid.
Each centroid is the mean of
the samples assigned to that cluster.
You can think of the centroid as
a representative sample for that cluster.
So to interpret the cluster
analysis results,
we can examine the cluster centroids.
Comparing the values of the variables
between the centroids will reveal
how different or alike clusters are and
provide insights into what
each cluster represents.
For example, if the value for age is
different for different customer clusters,
this indicates that the clusters
are encoding different
customer segments by age,
among other variables.
In summary, k-means is a classic algorithm
for performing cluster analysis.
It is an algorithm that is simple
to understand and implement, and
is also efficient.
The value of k, the number of clusters,
must be specified.
And final clusters are sensitive
to initial centroids.
Linear regression is a very common
algorithm to build regression models.
After this video you will be able to
describe how linear regression works,
discuss how least squares is used in
linear regression, define simple and
multiple linear regression.
A linear regression model captures the
relationship between a numerical output
and the input variables.
The relationship is modeled as
a linear relationship hence the linear
in linear regression.
To see how linear regression works, let's
take a look at an example from the Iris
flower dataset, which is a commonly
used dataset for machine learning.
This dataset has samples of
different species of iris flowers
along with measurements such as
petal width and petal length.
Here we have a plot with petal width
measurements in centimeters on the x axis,
and petal length
measurements on the y axis.
Let's say that we want to predict
petal length based on petal width.
Then the regression task is this,
given a measurement for
petal width predict the petal length.
We can build a linear regression model to
capture this linear relationship between
the input petal width and
the output petal length.
The linear relationship for this samples
is shown as the red line on the plot.
From this example we see that linear
regression works by finding the best
fitting straight line,
through the samples.
This is called the regression line.
In the simple case with
just one input variable,
the regression line is simply a line.
The equation for a line is y = mx + b,
where m determines
the slope of the line and
b is the y intercept or
where the line crosses the y axis.
M and b are the parameters of the model.
Training a linear regression model
means adjusting these parameters to
fit the regression line to the samples.
The regression line can be
determined using what's referred to
as the least squares method.
This plot illustrates how
the least squares method works.
The yellow dots are the data samples.
The red line is the regression line,
the straight line that
goes through the samples.
This line represents the model's
prediction of the output given the input.
Each green line indicates the distance
of each sample from the regression line.
So the green line represents
the error between the prediction,
which is the value of the red regression
line and the actual value of the sample.
The square of this distance is
referred to as the residual
associated with that sample.
The least squares method
finds the regression line
that makes the sum of
the residuals as small as possible.
In other words, we want to find
the line that minimizes the sum
of the squared errors of prediction.
The goal of linear regression then is
to find the best fitting straight line
through the samples using
the least squares method.
Once the regression model is built,
we can use it to make predictions.
For example,
given a measurement of 1.5 centimeters for
petal width, the model will predict
a value of 4.5 centimeters for
petal length base on the regression
line that it has constructed.
In linear regression, if there is only
one input variable then the task is
referred to as simple linear regression.
In cases with more than
one input variables,
then it is referred to as
multiple linear regression.
To summarize, linear regression
captures the linear relationship
between a numerical output and
the input variables.
The least squares method can be used
to build a linear regression model
by finding the best fitting
line through the samples.
We studied the machine learning process,
applied techniques to explore and
prepare data, discussed the different
categories of machine learning tasks,
looked at metrics and
methods for evaluating a model,
learned how to use scalable machine
learning algorithms for big data problems,
and worked with two widely used tools to
construct the machine learning models.
I hope that the lectures, along with
the hands-on activities, have given you
a sound and practical introduction to
machine learning tools and techniques.
I also hope that the course piqued
your interest in the exiting and
rapidly developing field of
machine learning for big data.
Keep in mind that the best
way to learn machine learning
is to do machine learning.
So I encourage you to go out and find
a problem or data set that interest you.
Apply the techniques you've learned in
this course to it and start analyzing.
Thank you for your time and effort on
this course, happy machine learning.