In this lecture, we will discuss
the Naive Bayes classifier.
After this video, you will be able
to discuss how a Naive Bayes model
works fro classification,
define the components of Bayes' Rule and
explain what the naive
means in Naive Bayes.
A Naive Bayes classification model uses a
probabilistic approach to classification.
What this means is that the relationships
between the input features and
the class is expressed as probabilities.
So given the input features for
a sample, the probability for
each class is estimated.
The class with the highest probability
then, determines the label for the sample.
In addition to using a probabilistic
framework for classification,
the Naive Bayes classifier also uses
what is known as Bayes' theorem.
The application of Bayes' theorem makes
estimating the probabilities easier.
In addition, Naive Bayes assumes that
the input features are statistically
independent of one another.
This means that, for a given class,
the value of one feature does not
affect the value of any other feature.
This independence assumption is
an oversimplified one that does not always
hold true, and so
is considered a naive assumption.
The naive independence assumption and
the use of Bayes theorem gives this
classification model its name.
We will cover Bayes theorem and
the independence assumption in
more detail in this lecture.
Before we look at naive
Bayes in more detail,
let's first start with some
background on probability.
Probability is the measure
of how likely an event is,
the probability of an event A occurring
is denoted P and in parenthesis A.
It is calculated by dividing
the number of ways event A can occur,
by the total number of possible outcomes.
For example, what is the probability
of rolling a die and getting six?
When you roll a die you can get
a number from one to six, so
the number of possible outcomes is six.
The number of ways fro getting six is one,
since the way you can get six is if
the die shows six when it stops rolling.
That means that the probability of getting
the number six when you roll a die
is one over six.
This is denoted p of six and
that's equal to one over six and
is read as probability
of six is one over six.
There's also a joint probability,
the joint probability specifies
the probability of event A and
event B occurring together.
In this diagram, the probability of event
A occurring is shown as the blue circle
and the probability of event B
occurring is shown as the green circle.
Then the joint probability,
that is the probability of A and
B occurring together is shown as
the overlap of these two circles.
The joint probability of A and
B is denoted,
P(A,B) for
an example of joint probability,
let's consider rolling 2 dice together.
What is the probability in getting
2 sixes or a six from each die.
If the two events are independent, then
the joint probability is simply the result
of multiplying the probabilities
of the individual events together.
In this case then, we have
the probability of rolling a six for
each die is one over six so
the joint probability is one over 36,
this leads us to conditional probability.
The conditional probability is
the probability of event A occurring
Given that event B has already occurred.
Another way to say this is that
event A is conditioned on event B.
The conditional probability is
the noted P and in parentheses A,
vertical line B and is read as,
probability of A Given B.
This diagram gives a graphical
definition of conditional probability.
As before, the blue circle is
the probability of event A occurring,
the green circle is the probability
of event B occurring.
The overlap is a joint
probability of A and B.
The conditional probability,
P(A given B) then is
calculated as the join probability
divided by the probability of B.
The conditional probability is
an important concept in classification
as we will see later.
It provides the means to specify
the probability of a class label,
given the input values.
The relationship between conditional
probabilities P of B given A and
P of A given B can be expressed
through Bayes' Theorem.
This theorem is named after a reverend
named Thomas Bayes who lived in the 1700s.
It is a way to look at how the probability
of a hypothesis is affected by
new evidence gathered from data.
Bayes' theorem expresses the relationship
between probability of B
given A and probability of A given
B as shown in this equation.
Bayes' Theorem is also known
as Bayes' Rule or Bayes' Law.
Now that we have reviewed some
background on probability
let's see how all this relates
to the classification problem.
With the probabilistic framework the
classification task is defined as follows.
Capital X is the set of values for
the input features in the sample,
given a sample with features X,
predict the corresponding class C.
Another way to state this is,
what is the class label associated with
the feature vector X or how should
the feature vector x be classified?
To find the class label C we need to
calculate the conditional probability of
class C, given X for all classes and
select a class with
the highest probability.
So for classification,
we want to find the value of C that
maximizes the probability of C given X.
The problem is that it is difficult
to estimate this probability,
because we would need to enumerate every
possible combination of feature values and
to know the conditional probability.
For each class given every
possible feature combination and
here is where Bayes'
theorem comes into play.
The classification problem can be
reformulated using Bayes' theorem
to simplify the classification problem.
Specifically, using Bayes' theorem, the
probability of c given x, can be expressed
using other probability quantities,
which can be estimated from the data.
Here's Bayes' theorem again, but
some additional terms defined.
Probability of C I X is referred to
as the posterior probability since
it is the probability of the class label
being C after observing input features X.
Probability of X given
C is the probability of
observing input features X given
that c is the class label.
This is the class conditional probability
since it is conditioned on the class.
Probability of c is the probability
of the class label being C,
this is the probability of each class
prior to observing any input data.
And so
is referred to as the prior probability.
The probability of X is the probability
of observing input features X
regardless of what the class label is.
So for classification we want
to calculate the posterior
probability P(C | X) for each class C.
From Bayes' theorem P(C | X) is related to
the P(X | C) P(C And probability of X.
Probability of X does not depend
on the class C, therefore,
it is a constant value, given the input X.
Since it the same value for
all classes, the probability
of X can be removed from the calculation
of probability of C, given X.
What's left then are probability of
X given C and the probability of C.
So estimating the probability
of C given X boils down to
estimating the probability of X
given C and probability of C.
The nice thing is that
probability of X given C and
probability of C can be
estimated from the data.
So now we have a way to calculate probably
of C given X which is what we need for
classification.
To the estimate the probability of C
which is the probability of the class
of C before observing any input data.
We simply calculate the fraction
of samples with that class label
C in the training data.
For this example, there are four samples
labeled as green circles out of 10
samples, so probability of green
circle is 4 out of 10, or 0.4.
Similarly, the fraction of samples labeled
as red triangles is 6 out of 10, or 0.6.
So estimating the prior
probabilities is a simple count
of number of samples with each class label
divided by the total number of
samples in the training data center.
In estimating probability of X
given C which is the probability
of observing feature factor
X given that the class is C,
we can use the independent
assumption to simplify the problem.
The Independence Assumption of
the Naive Bayes classifier assumes
that each feature X sub I
in the featured vector X
is conditionally independent of every
other feature, given the class C.
This means that we only need to
estimate the probability of X
sub i given C, instead of having to
estimate the probability of
the entire feature X given C.
For every combination of values for
the features in X then we would simply
multiply these individual probabilities
together to get the probability
of the entire feature vector X.
Given the class C to estimate
the probability of X sub I,
given C, we count up the number
of times a particular input
value is observed for
the class c in the training data.
For example, the number of times that we
see the value of yes for the future home
owner, when the class label is no it's
three as indicated by the green arrows.
This is divided by the number of samples
with no as the class label which is seven.
This fraction, three out of seven,
is the probability that home owner
is Yes given that the class is No.
Similarly, the samples with
the value of Single for
the feature Marital Status when it crosses
Yes are indicated by the red arrows.
And the probability that
Marital Status is Single,
given that the class label
is Yes is 2/3 or 0.67.
Some things to know about the Naive Bayes
classification model are it is a fast and
simple algorithm.
The algorithm boils down to calculating
counts for probabilities and
performing some multiplication, so
it is very simple to implement.
And the probabilities that are needed
can be calculated with a single
scan of the data set and
stored in a table.
Either two processing of the data
is not necessary as with many other
machine learning algorithms.
So model building and
testing of both task, it scales well.
Due today independent assumption,
the probability for
each feature can be
independently estimated.
These means that featured probability
is can be calculated in parallel,
this also means that the data set size
does not have to grow exponentially
with a number of features.
This avoids the many problems associated
with the curse of dimensionality,
this also means that you do not need
a lot of data to build the model.
The number of parameters scales
linearly with the number of features.
The Independence assumption does
not hold true in many cases.
In practice however, the Naive Bayes
classifier still tends to perform very
well this is because even
though Naive Bayes may
not provide good estimates of
the correct class probabilities.
As long as the correct class is
more probable than any other class,
the correct classification
results will be reached.
The independence assumption also prevents
the naive base classifier to model
interactions between features which
limits its classification power.
The increased risk of smoking in a history
of cancer would not be captured,
for example.
The Naive Bays classifier has been
applied to many real world problems
including spam filtering, document
classification, and sentiment analysis.
To summarize, the Naive Bayes classifier
uses a probabilistic framework for
classification.
It applies Bayes Theorem and
the Feature Independence Assumption,
to simplify the problem of estimating
probabilities for the classification task.
In addition to the evaluation
matrix covered n the last lecture.
The performance of a classification
model can also be evaluated
using a Confusion Matrix.
We will introduce the Confusion Matrix,
in this lecture.
After this video you will be able to,
describe how a confusion matrix can
be used to evaluate a classifier.
Interpret the confusion matrix of a model.
And relate accuracy to values
in a confusion matrix.
Let's use our example again of predicting
whether a given animal is a mammal or not.
Recall that this is a binary
classification task, with the Class Label
being either Yes, indicating mammal or
No indicating non-mammal.
Now let's review the different Types
of Errors that you can get with
Classification.
If the True Label is Yes and
the Predicted Label is Yes, then this
is a True Positive, abbreviated as TP.
This is a case where the label is
correctly predicted as positive.
If the True Label is No and
the Predicted Label is No, then this
is a True Negative, abbreviated as TN.
This is the case where the label is
correctly predicted as negative.
If the True Label is No and
the Predicted Label is Yes, then this
is a False Positive, abbreviated as FP.
This is the case where the label is
incorrectly predicted as positive
when it should be negative.
If the True Label is Yes and
the Predicted Label is No,
then this is a False Negative
abbreviated as FN.
This is the case where the label is
incorrectly predicted as negative,
when it should be positive.
A Confusion Matrix can be used to
summarize the different types of
classification errors.
The True Positive cell corresponds to the
samples that are correctly predicted as
positive by the model.
The True Negative cell corresponds to
the samples that are correctly predicted
as negative.
The False Positive cell corresponds to
samples that are incorrectly predicted
as positive.
The False Negative cell corresponds to
samples that are incorrectly predicted
as negative.
Each cell has the count, or percentage
of samples, with each type of errors.
Let's look at an example to see how
a Confusion Matrix is filled in.
The table on the lists True Labels
along with the models prediction for
a data set of ten samples.
We'll summarize this results
in a Confusion Matrix.
First let's figure out
the number of true positives.
We call that a true positive occurrence
when the output is correctly predicted
as positive.
In other words, the true label is Yes and
the model's prediction is also Yes.
In this example, there are three true
positives as indicated by the red arrows.
We enter three and the true positive
cell in the Confusion Matrix.
Now let's look at the true negatives.
A true negative occurs when the output
is correctly predicted as negative.
In other words, the true label is No and
the models prediction is also No.
In this example,
there are four true negatives as
indicated by the green arrows.
We enter four in the true negative
cell in the Confusion Matrix.
What about false negatives?
A false negative occurs when the output
is incorrectly predicted as negative,
when it should be positive.
That is the true label is Yes,
and the model's prediction is No.
In this example,
there are two false negatives as
indicated by the purple arrows.
We enter two in the false negative
cell in the Confusion Matrix.
Finally we need to look
at false positives.
A false positive occurs,
when the input is incorrectly predicted
as positive, when it should be negative.
That is the true label is No and
models prediction is Yes.
In this example there is one false
positive as indicated by the yellow arrow.
We enter one in the false positive
cell in the Confusion Matrix.
This is our complete Confusion Matrix for
this example.
We see that the sum of the numbers
in the cells add up to ten,
which is the number of
samples in our dataset.
Note that the diagonal values,
true positives and
true negatives are samples
with Correct Predictions.
In our example, these values sum up to 7.
Meaning that 7 out of 10 samples were
correctly predicted by the model.
The higher the sum of the diagonal values,
the better the performance of the model.
The off diagonal values capture
the misclassified samples.
Where the model's predictions
do not match the true labels.
In this example these values indicate
that there were three misclassifications.
Smaller values for
the off diagonal cells in the confusion
matrix indicate better model performance.
Note that the diagonal values,
true positives and
true negatives are samples
with correct predictions.
In our example,
these values sum up to 7 meaning
that 7 out of 10 samples were
correctly predicted by the model.
The higher the sum of the diagonal values,
the better the performance of the model.
You may have noticed that the diagonal
values are related to Accuracy Rate.
Recall that accuracy is defined
as the sum of two positives and
true negatives, divided by all samples.
The sum of two positives and
two negatives is the sum of the diagonal
values in a confusion matrix.
The sum of the diagonal
values in a confusion matrix,
divided by the total number of
samples gives you the Accuracy Rate.
Similarly, the off diagonal values
are related to the Error Rate.
Recall that the Error Rate is
the opposite of the Accuracy Rate.
The sum of the off diagonal
values in a confusion matrix,
divided by the total number of samples,
gives you the Error Rate.
Looking at the values in the Confusion
Matrix can help you understand
the kind of Misclassifications
that your model is making.
A high value for
this cell indicated by the yellow arrow,
means that classifying the Positive
class is problematic for the model.
A high value for the cell indicated by
the orange arrow on the other hand,
means that classifying the Negative
class is problematic for the model.
In summary,
the Confusion Matrix is a table
used to summarize the different
types of errors for a classifier.
The values in a Confusion Matrix can
be used to evaluate the performance of
a classifier and are related to evaluation
metrics, such as accuracy and error rates.
They also indicate what other types of
misclassifications the model is making.
Note that in some implementations
of a Confusion Matrix, the true and
predictive labels are switched.
Be sure to review the documentation for
the software you're using to generate
a Confusion Matrix to understand
what each cell specifies.
In this activity, we will be
evaluating the decision tree model
we created in the KNIME
classification hands-on.
First, we will create a confusion
matrix to determine the accuracy
of the decision tree model.
Next, we will use highlighting and
a scatter plot to analyze
the classification errors.
Let's begin.
First, let's open the Classification
workflow that we built in the previous
hands-on.
In the top-left of KNIME
is a KNIME Explorer.
Double-click on the Classification,
under LOCAL.
Next, we'll create a confusion
matrix to analyze the accuracy
of our decision tree model.
To do this,
we'll add the Scorer node to the canvas.
Connect the output of Decision Tree
Predictor, to the input of Scorer.
Double-click on Scorer.
We'll use the default values, so click OK.
Next, run the workflow.
Now, let's view the confusion matrix.
I can see the accuracy as 80.282%.
At the top, I can see that it
accurately predicted 76 values for
humidity_low and 95 for humidity_not_low.
It inaccurately predicted 24 values for
humidty_low and
18 for humidty_not_low,
for an error of 19.718%.
Close this.
Next, we use an interactive table to
look at the values that were incorrectly
predicted.
We'll add the Interactive Table
to the canvas.
We'll connect this to the output
of Decision Tree Predictor,
run the workflow and view the table.
The right two columns have the real value
for low_humidity and the prediction.
For some of these rows, we can tell
that the prediction was not correct.
For example, in row ten, And in row 17.
Let's leave the table view open,
and go back to the workflow.
Next, we'll add the Scatter Plot
nodes to the workflow.
Connect this to the output
of Decision Tree Predictor.
Execute the workflow, and
view the scatter plot.
We'll select row 17, and
choose, Hilite Selected.
Go back to the scatter plot,
and we see this particular value
is highlighted in the plot.
We could choose another
row from the table, and
highlight it again to see
its place in the plot.
Let's choose row ten.
We can do this for
values that were incorrectly predicted,
to find any patterns for further analysis.
In this activity we will use Spark
to evaluate our decision tree.
First, we load
the classification predictions,
created during the last
Spark hands on activity.
We then compute the accuracy
of these predictions.
And then, generate a confusion matrix.
Let's begin.
First, let's open the model
evaluation notebook.
Next, let's execute the first
cell to load the classes.
Then, execute the second cell
to load the predictions we saved
during the previous hands on.
We could then complete
the accuracy of these predictions
by using a multi-class
classification evaluator.
Let's enter evaluator =
MulticlassClassificationEvaluator(labelCo-
l="label", predictionCol="prediction") and
finally metricName="precision" and
execute this.
We can then compute the accuracy by
calling evaluate on the evaluator.
We'll enter
evaluator.evaluate[predictions].
This says that the accuracy is about 81%.
Next, let's use multi-class metrics
to compute a confusion matrix.
Multi-class metrics takes
an RDD of numbers, and
our data is currently in a data frame.
We can access the RDD of the underlying
data frame by using the RDD
attribute of predictions.
If we look at predictions.rdd.take(2)
we see the RDD
is the RDD of rows, or
each row has a prediction and label.
However multi-class metrics
wants an RDD of numbers.
We could do this using a map.
We'll enter predictions.rdd.map and
we'll use a key word,
tuple, and we'll look at the first
two elements in this RDD.
Run this.
We can see now this RDD is just numbers.
Now we'll create a new instance of
a multiclass metrics using this RDD.
Metrics =
MulticlassMetrics(predrictions.rdd.map(tu-
ple)).
We can then display
the confusion matrix by running
metrics.confusionMatrix().toArray().trans-
pose().
We can see these results are similar
to the confusion matrix in nine.
Generalization and overfitting are very
important concepts in machine learning.
We will cover them in
the next three lectures.
After this video you will be able
to define what overfitting is,
describe how overfitting is
related to generalization, and
explain why overfitting should be avoided.
Before we look at generalization and
overfitting, let's first define some terms
that we will need to know to
discuss errors in classification.
Recall that a machine learning model
maps the input it receives to an output.
For a classification model, the model's
output is the predicted class label for
the input variables and
the true class label is the target.
Then if the classifier predicts
the correct classes label for
a sample, that is a success.
If the predicted class label is
different from the true class label,
then that is an error.
The error rate, then, is the percentage
of errors made over the entire data set.
That is, it is the number of errors
divided by the total number of samples
in a data set.
Error rate is also known as
misclassification rate, or simply error.
In our lesson on classification we discuss
that there is a training phase in which
the model is built, and a testing phase in
which the model is applied to new data.
The model is built using training data and
evaluated on test data.
The training and
test data are two different data sets.
The goal in building a machine learning
model is to have the model perform well
on training, as well as test data.
Error rate, or simply error, on the
training data is refered to as training
error, and the error on test data
is referred to as test error.
The error on the test data is
an indication of how well the classifier
will perform on new data.
This is known as generalization.
Generalization refers to how well
your model performs on new data,
that is data not used to train the model.
You want your model to
generalize well to new data.
If your model generalizes well, then
it will perform well on data sets that
are similar in structure
to the training data, but
doesn't contain exactly the same
samples as in the training set.
Since the test error indicates how well
your model generalizes to new data,
note that the test error is also
called generalization error.
A related concept to
generalization is overfitting.
If your model has very
low training error but
high generalization error,
then it is overfitting.
This means that the model has learned to
model the noise in the training data,
instead of learning the underlying
structure of the data.
These plots illustrate what
happens when a model overfits.
Training samples are shown as points, and
the input to output mapping that the model
has learned is indicated as a curve.
The plot on the left shows that the model
has learned the underlying structure of
the data, as the curve follows
the trend of the sample point as well.
The plot on the right,
however, shows that the model has learned
to model the noise in a data set.
The model tries to capture
every sample point,
instead of the general trend
of the samples together.
The training error and
the generalization error are plotted
together, during model training.
What is the connection between
overfitting and generalization?
A model that overfits will not
generalize well to new data.
So the model will do well on just
the data it was trained on, but
given a new data set,
it will perform poorly.
A classifier that performs well
on just the training data set
will not be very useful.
So it is essential that the goal of good
generalization performance is kept in mind
when building a model.
A problem related to
overfitting is underfitting.
Overfitting occurs when the model is
fitting to the noise in the training data.
This results in low training error and
high test error.
Underfitting on the other hand,
occurs when the model has not
learned the structure of the data.
This results in high training error and
high test error.
Both are undesirable,
since both mean that the model will
not generalize well to new data.
Overfitting generally occurs when
a model is too complex, that is,
it has too many parameters relative
to the number of training samples.
So to avoid overfitting, the model needs
to be kept as simple as possible, and yet
still solve the input/output mapping for
the given data set.
We will discuss methods for
avoiding overfitting in
the next couple of lectures.
In summary, overfitting is when your model
has learned the noise in the training data
instead of the underlying
structure of the data.
You want to avoid overfitting so that your
model will generalize well to new data.