It can be said without a doubt,
and the Internet and
the worldwide web changed
everything in our lives.
The worldwide web is indeed the largest
information source there is today.
But what's the data model behind the web?
We will say that it is
the semi-structure data model.
So after going through this video you
will be able to distinguish between
the structured data model that we
talked about the last time and
semi-structured data model.
Further, you will recognize that the most
times the semi-structured data
refers to tree structured data.
And you can explain why tree
navigation operations are important for
formats like XML and JSON.
Let's a take a very simple web page.
Now this page does not have
a lot of content or stylization.
It doesn't even have links to other pages,
but
let's look at the corresponding HTML code.
This code is used by the browser so
that it can render the HTML, and
notice a few things in this data.
The entire data comes within the HTML and
slash HTML blocks.
And we similarly have a body begin and
end, a header begin and
end, a list begin and end and
a paragraph begin and end.
Everywhere here a block is
nested within a larger block.
The second item to notice is that
unlike a relational structure
there are multiple list items and
multiple paragraphs.
And any single document would
have a different number of them.
This means while the date object has
some structure it is more flexible.
So this is the hallmark office
semi structure date model.
Now XML, or
the extensible markup language, is another
well known standard to represent data.
You can think of XML as a generalization
of HTML where the elements, that's
the beginning and end markers within
the angular brackets, can be any string.
And not like the ones
allowed by standard HTML.
Let's see an example
from a biological case.
As you can see, there are two
elements called sample attribute.
They do structurally
different because they
have different numbers of sub
elements called the value.
Another interesting issue
about XML data processing
is that you can actually credit for
the structure elements.
For example, it is perfectly fine to ask,
what is the name of the element
which contains a sub-element whose
textual content is cell type?
As you can see, you'll get two results,
sample attribute.
An experimental factor because sample
attribute has a sub-element called
category and experimental factor
has a subelement called link and
each of these subelements
have the value celltape.
Now we cannot perform an operation
like this in a relational data model.
For example, we cannot say which relation
has a column with a value, John.
The same idea can also be seen in JSON or
the Java Script Object Notation, which
is a very popular format used for many
different data like Twitter and Facebook.
Consider the example here,
all of the format looks different.
We have a similar nested
structure varies that is lists
containing other lists which will contain
topples Which consists of p value ps.
So the key value pairs at atomic
property names and their values.
But one way to generalize about all these
different forms of semi structured data
is to model them as trees.
Let's go back to .xml.
The left side shows an XML document, and
the right side shows
the corresponding tree.
Since the top object of
the root element is document,
it is also the root of the tree.
Now under document we have
a report element with author and
date under it, and also a paper element
with title, author, and source under it.
The actual values,
like is the textual content of an element.
Since a text data item cannot
have any further components,
these text values are always
the leaves of the tree.
Now, modeling a document as a tree
has significant advantages.
A tree is a well-known data structure,
that allows what's called
a navigational access to data.
Imagine you are standing
on the note paper.
Now you can perform a getParent
operation and navigate the document.
Or you can perform a getChildren operation
to get to the title, author and source.
You can even perform a getSiblings
operation and get to the report.
You can also ask a textual query like
which strings have the substring data and
seek their root-to-node path to get to
the path from document to the text nodes.
You can possibly see how queries
can be evaluated on the tree,
now let us take the query.
Who is the author of XML query data model.
In one evaluation scheme we can navigate
up from the text note to title,
to paper, and then navigate down
to author and then to Don Robie.
Well how do we know that we have to get up
to paper before reversing the direction?
Well, paper is the least,
that's the lowest in the tree,
common ancestor of the author note,
and the XM query data model note.
We will come back to semi
structure data in a later module.
In this hands-on activity,
we will be looking at graph data in Gephi.
First, we will import data into Gephi and
then examine the properties of the graph.
Next, we will perform some statistical
operations on the graph data,
and then run some different
layout algorithms.
Let's begin.
We're not running Gephi in the Cloudera
virtual machine, on the Coursera website,
there will be a reading with instructions
on how to download, install, and
run Gephi on your native hardware,
instead of in the virtual machine.
Once you have Gephi started,
let's import the data into Gephi.
We'll go to File Import spreadsheet,
and in the CSV dialog,
we'll click the button with dot, dot, dot.
We'll choose diseasegraph.csv and
click open.
Make sure that as table says
edges table Click next.
And make sure Create
missing nodes is checked.
We'll click finish to import
the CSV file as a graph.
Gephi now shows the graph
in the center pane.
The little black circles
are the nodes of the graph and
the lines between them are the edges.
In the top right we can see that
there are 777 nodes and 998 edges.
Next let's perform some statistical
operations on this graph.
In the statistics pane we
can see average degree.
Let's compute the average degree
of the graph by clicking on Run.
This says that the average
degree is 2.569.
Let's close this,
let's compute the connected
components, we'll click on Run.
We'll leave this as a directed,
since the graph is directed.
Click OK.
It says that there
are 5 weakly connected components,
and 761 strongly connected components.
Let's close this.
Next, let's run some different
layout algorithms over the graph.
The bottom left,
we'll go to choose layout.
We'll choose Force Atlas and click run.
Click stop to stop the layout.
We can see that Gephi has grouped
strongly connected components together
in different clusters.
We can also see that they're parts
of the graph that are not connected.
Let's run a different layout algorithm.
The combo box,
choose Fruchterman Reingold, click run.
After it runs for a few seconds, click
stop, then click the magnifying glass,
center on graph, to see the whole graph.
In this layout,
all the nodes appear to be equally spaced.
But we can also see
the nodes with many edges.
In this hands on activity,
we will be working with Lucene,
a search engine that uses a vector
space model to index data.
First, we will open a terminal window and
change into the directory
containing the data and scripts.
Next, we will index some text
documents and query terms in Lucene.
After that we'll query
using weighted terms or
boosting to see how this
changes the rankings.
Finally, we will show the term
frequency-inverse document frequency or
TF-IDF in terms.
Let's begin.
First, let's open a terminal window by
clicking on the terminal icon at the top
of the tool bar.
Next, let's cd into the directory
containing the scripts and data.
We'll run cd
Downloads/big-data-2/vector/.
We'll run ls to see the scripts.
The data directory
contains three text files.
Each of these text files contains
news data about elections.
Let's index these files by
running runLuceneQuery.sh data.
Next, let's query Lucene for some terms in
these text documents and see the rankings.
Let's query for the term voters.
You can see the rankings and
scores that news1.csv ranked first,
news2.csv was the second ranking,
and the third was news3.csv.
Let's query for delegates.
For this term, we see that news2.csv
was first, and news1 was second, and
news3 did not contain the term at all.
Now, let's query for both terms,
voters and delegates.
In this result we see that
news2 was ranked first,
news1 was ranked second, and
news3 was ranked third.
Now lets use query term waiting or
boosting to increase
the relevance of voters.
I can do this by ensuring
voters carat 5 delegates.
The carat 5 notation is a syntax for
Lucene for boosting.
When we run this, we see that now,
news1 is ranked first,
news2 is ranked second,
and news3 is ranked third.
Notice this is different from the original
query with voters and delegates,
where news2 is ranked first and
news1 was ranked second.
Now let's look at the term frequency,
inverse document frequency or TF-IDF.
We'll enter q to quit this and
we'll run Lucene TF-IDF SH data.
Let's look at the TF-IDF for voters.
You can see that it ranked number 1 for
news1.
Second news 2 and news 3 is last.
Lets try delegates.
Here we see that news 2 had
a higher score than news 1,
and news 3 is not listed because
news 3 does not contain this term.
Hit q to quit.
So the next category of data we discuss
has the form of graphs or networks,
the most obvious example
being social networks.
Now speaking of social networks,
Tim Libzek created a social network
from the Lord of the Rings Trilogy.
This graph represents
the characters' allegiances,
that is who is faithful
to whom in the books.
So the nodes are characters and
other entities, like cities, and
the edges connecting pairs of
nodes represent allegiances.
So after this video, you'll be able to
identify graph data in practical problems
and describe path, neighborhood, and
connectivity operations in graphs.
But this specialization includes
a separate course in graph analytics
that provides a much more detailed
treatment on the subject.
Now what distinguishes a graph
from other data models
is that it bears two kinds of information.
One, properties and attributes of
entities and relationships, and
two, the connectivity structure that
constitutes the network itself.
One way to look at this data
is shown in the figure,
borrowed from the Apache Spark system.
In this representation,
the graph on the left is represented
by two tables on the right.
The vertex, or node table, gives IDs
to nodes and lists their properties.
The edge table has two parts.
The colored part represents
the properties of the edge,
whereas the white part contains just the
direction of the arrows in the network.
Thus, since there is a directed
edge going from node 3 to node 7,
there is a tupple 3,
7 in that part of the edge table.
Now this form of the graph model is
called the property graph model,
which we'll see many times in this
course and in the specialization.
Now representing connectivity information
gives graph data a new kind of
computing ability that's different from
other data models we have seen so far.
Even without looking at the properties
of the nodes and edges, one can get very
interesting information just by analyzing
or querying this connectivity structure.
Consider a social network with three
types of nodes, user, city, and
restaurant, and three types of edges,
friend, likes, and lives in.
The leftmost node, AG, represents me.
And I'm interested in finding a good
Italian restaurant in New York
that my friends, or their friends,
who also live in New York, like.
I shall possibly choose IT3 because
it has the highest number of
like edges coming into it from people
who have a lives in edge to New York.
And at the same time,
can be reached by following
the friend edges going out from me.
Now this shows a very important class
of operations and ground data, namely
traversal, that involves edge following
based on some sort of conditions.
A number of path operations
required some sort of optimization.
The simplest among these is the well known
shortest path query, which is applied to
node networks to find the best route from
a source location to a target location.
The second class of optimization
operations is required to find
an optimal path that must include
some user specified nodes, for
the operation has to determine the order
in which the nodes once we visited.
The classical application
is a trip planner,
where the user specifies the cities
she wishes to visit, and
the operation will optimize the criterion,
like the total distance covered.
The third category is a case where
the system must find the best possible
path in the network, given two or
more optimization criteria,
which cannot be satisfied simultaneously.
For example, if I want to travel
from my house to the airport
using the shortest distance, but also
minimizing the amount of highway travel,
the algorithm must find a best compromise.
This is called a pareto-optimality
problem on graphs.
The neighborhood of a node N in a graph is
a set of edges directly connected to it.
A K neighborhood of N is a collection
of edges between nodes that are,
at most, K steps away from N.
So going back to our mini social
network graph, Bob, Jill,
and Sarah are the first neighbors of AG,
while Max, Tim and
Pam belong to the second neighborhood and
not the first neighborhood of AG.
Finally, Jen is a third level neighbor.
An important class of analysis to perform
with neighborhoods is community finding.
A community and a social network can
be a very close group of friends.
So the graph shown in this
figure has four communities.
One can see in the figure that each
community has a higher density of edges
within the community and a lower density
across two different communities.
Finding densely connected parts of a graph
helps identify neighborhoods that
can be recognized as communities.
A more complex class of operations include
finding the best possible clusters,
which is another name for
communities in a graph, so
that any other grouping of nodes into
communities will be less effective.
Now, as graphs become bigger and denser,
these methods become harder to compute.
Thus, neighborhood-based
optimization operation present
significant scalability challenges.
If we inspect the neighborhood of
every node in a graph, sometimes,
we'll find neighborhoods that
are different from all others.
These neighborhoods are called anomalous.
Consider the following four graphs and
on the central red node.
The first graph is odd because
it's almost perfectly star shaped.
That is, the nodes that the red node
is connected to are almost unconnected
amongst themselves.
That's really odd because it
doesn't happen in reality much.
So it's an anomalous node.
The second figure shows
a neighborhood to which
a significantly large number of neighbors
has connected amongst themselves.
This makes the graph very cliquish,
where a clique refers to a neighborhood
where each node is connected to all other
neighborhood nodes in the neighborhood.
The third figure shows a neighborhood,
where some edges have an unusually
heavy weight compared to the others.
The fourth figure shows
a special case of the third,
where one edge is predominantly high
rate compared to all the other edges.
Connectedness is a fundamental
property of a graph.
In a connected graph,
each node is reachable from every
other node through some path.
If a graph is not connected, but there
are subgraphs of it, which are connected,
then these subgraphs are called connected
components of the original graph.
In the figure on the right,
there are four connected components.
A search gradient like
finding optimal paths
should be performed only within
each component and not across them.
For large graphs, there are several
new parallelized techniques for
the detection of connected components.
We will discuss a map
reduce based technique for
connected components in a later course.
We have discussed quite a few data models,
but
there are many other data models
that have been developed for
various purposes, and we really cannot
cover all of them in a single course.
We'll end these lectures on data models
with an example that may give you
an insight into a class of objects that
define in many different applications.
So after this video you'll be able
to describe how arrays can serve
as a data model, explain why images
can be modeled as vector arrays,
specify a set of operations on scalar and
vector arrays.
Now, we have all seen the arrays.
In the simplest case,
an array is a matrix like this.
Let's call this array A.
The top row in yellow,
gives the column numbers and
the left column, also in yellow,
gives the row numbers.
When we need to refer to a value
of the array as A(3, 2),
we mean the value of the cell in row 3 and
column 2.
This is called indexed structure,
where 3 and
2 are the row and column indices that are
necessary to get the value of a data item.
The area has two dimensions.
So hence there are two indexes.
If these were a three dimensional array,
we would have three indexes.
Now earlier,
we have seen that we can represent the two
dimensional array as a three column table.
One column for the row index,
one column for the column index, and
the last column for the value.
Thus a k dimensional array can be
represented as a relation with k
plus one columns.
The number of tuples in this
representation will be the product of
the size of the first dimension times the
size of the second dimension and so forth.
Then in this case,
the size is five in each dimension.
So there are 25 C column tuples in
a relation representing the array.
A more useful situation occurs
when the cells of an array have
a vectors as values.
As you can see in the 2D vector array
here, each cell has a three vector.
That is a vector with three elements.
Therefore, if we want to
receive a cell value and
treat it like before,
we'll get back the whole vector.
Now, this type of data
should look familiar to you,
because images often have a red,
green and blue channels per pixel.
In other words,
images of vector valued arrays where each
array cell has a three color vector.
We can also think of the array model
in the context of satellite images.
Where there are many more channels
depending on the range of wavelengths
each channel catches.
Let us consider the operations
on arrays of vectors.
Because it is a combination of two models,
one can create different combinations of
array operations, vector operations and
composite operations.
Here are some.
The dimension of the array here,
the first operation, is two.
If we pick up any dimension, say one.
The size of it is also two
because they're two elements,
zero and one in each dimension.
As we saw before, the value of the cell
(1,1) is a vector 16, 301, 74.
While the value of A11 component 2 is 74.
The length of the vector is a square root
of the sum of the elements of the vector.
So length of A11 would come to 310.375.
The distance function can be so
simple like the Euclidean distance
function between two vectors or
the cosine of an angle between them
as we saw in the previous lecture.
But it can also be something more complex,
based on the needs of the application.
Obviously one can also perform operations
like selection over indices so
we can ask which cells had
the zero value greater than 25.
Giving as the result zero one and
one zero.
You will experience some of these
operations in your hands on session.