If you recall, we have previously
discussed that the main categories of
machine learning tasks are classification,
regression,
cluster analysis, and
association analysis.
We have discussed
classification in detail.
Now let's look at the other categories,
starting with regression.
After this video you will be able
to define what regression is,
explain the difference between
regression and classification, and
name some applications of regression.
Before we talk about regression,
let's review classification.
In a classification problem the input
data is presented to the machine learning
model, and the task is to predict the
target corresponding to the input data.
The target is a categorical variable.
So the classification task is to
predict the category or label of
the target, given the input data.
The classification example shown
here is one we have seen before.
The input variables are measurements
such as temperature, relative humidity,
atmospheric pressure,
wind speed, wind direction, etc.
The task for
the model is to predict the weather
category associated with the input data.
The possible values for
the weather category is sunny,
windy, rainy, or cloudy.
Since we're predicting the category,
this is a classification task.
With that context in mind,
let's now discuss regression.
When the model has to predict
a numeric value instead of a category,
then the task becomes
a regression problem.
An example of regression is to
predict the price of a stock.
The stock price is a numeric value,
not a category.
So this is a regression task
instead of a classification task.
Note that if you were to predict not
the actual price of the stock, but whether
the stock price will go up or go down,
then that would be a classification task.
That is the main difference between
classification and regression.
In classification,
you're predicting a category, and
in regression you're
predicting a numeric value.
Here are some examples where
regression can be used.
Forecast the high temperature for the next
day, estimate the average housing price
for a particular region, determine the
demand for a new product, a new book for
example, based on similar existing
products, predict the power usage for
a particular power grid.
This is what the data
set might look like for
the regression task of predicting
tomorrow's high temperature.
The input variables could
be the high temperature for
today, the low temperature for
today, and the month.
And the target is the high temperature for
tomorrow.
The model has to predict this
target value for each sample.
Recall that in a supervised
task the target is provided.
Well, for an unsupervised task the target
is not available or not known.
Since the target label is provided for
each sample here,
the regression task is a supervised one,
similar to classification.
As with classification building a
regression model also involve two phases.
A training phase in which
the model is built, and
a testing phase in which
the model is applied to new data.
The model is built using training data and
evaluated on test data.
Similar to classification, the goal in
building a regression model is also to
have a model perform well on training
data, as well as generalize to new data.
The use of three different datasets
that we have previously discussed
also apply to regression.
Recall that the three
datasets are used as follows.
The training dataset is used to train the
model, that is to adjust the parameters of
the model to learn the input
to output mapping.
The validation dataset is used to
determine when training should stop
in order to avoid over fitting.
And the test dataset is used to evaluate
the performance of the model on new data.
In summary, in regression the model
needs to predict the numeric value
corresponding to the input data.
Since a target is provided for each
sample, regression is a supervised task.
The target is always a numerical
variable in regression.
In the next lecture,
we will discuss a specific algorithm
to build a regression model.
Hello.
Welcome to the Graph Analytics module
in the Big Data specialization.
I'm Amarnath Gupta, a research scientist
at the San Diego Supercomputer Center.
What do I do research on?
Well, a number of different areas,
all generally related to data engineering.
But the area I'm recently very
excited about has to do with graphs.
Now, graphs or
networks has many people call them,
are about studying relationships and
relationship patterns on objects.
I became interested in graphs
when I was a graduate student and
the professor in our artificial
intelligence class showed us how a part of
human knowledge can be represented as
a kind of graphs called semantic networks.
She showed us how even
very simple things like
relationships somewhere in a family can
be represented and viewed as graphs.
Represent your knowledge huh?
Now, that got me really excited.
Someday, I thought this will be a really
interesting topic to research on.
What I didn't realize then is that
in just a few years graphs and
the need to model and analyze them would
become so dominant in both academia and
industry that graphs will
be found everywhere today.
Now we look at Facebook,
LinkedIn, Twitter, and many,
many more companies that
are thriving in the market with data
that are represented, modeled,
and processed as graphs.
Now, even the entire World Wide Web,
if you think about it,
is a giant graph that people analyze.
And that brings us to this course.
Now, in this course, I'll introduce you
to the wonderful world of Graph Analytics
specifically, I'd like
to show how different
kinds of real world data science problems
can be viewed and modeled as graphs.
And how the process of solving
them can apply analytical
techniques that used graph based methods,
that is Algorithms.
This course would have four models.
In model one, we'll introduce graphs and
different applications that use graphs.
In model two,
we'll cover a number of common techniques,
mathematical and algorithm techniques,
that are used in Graph Analytics.
In module three,
we'll look at a graph database.
And through some sort
of a hands on guidance,
we'll show you how to store and
query graph data with the database.
In module four, we'll cover some
strategies of handling very large
graphs and discuss how existing
tools that are currently used by
the community are actually prints.
Thank you for joining this course and
I sincerely hope that you'll find
it both exciting and useful.
Happy learning.
As we saw in these four examples
what graphs are used for
are kind of different but they all show
different viewpoints from which you
can use graphs for your analysis.
Since this course focuses
on graph analytics,
I'd like to briefly recap
what the term means.
Analytics is the ability to
discover meaningful patterns and
interesting insights into data using
mathematical properties of data.
It covers the process of computing
with mathematical properties, and
accessing the data itself efficiently.
Further, it involves
the ability to represent and
work with domain knowledge as we
saw in use case two with biology.
Finally, analytics often involves
statistical modeling techniques for
drawing inferences and
making predictions on data.
With analytics, we should be able
to achieve the goals shown here.
Take a minute to read.
Therefore, graph analytics is
a special case of analytics where
the underlying data can be
modeled as a set of graphs.
So in this video,
we'll going to talk about graph analytics
within the context of this
big data specialization.
So in the previous courses you know about
the three important V's of big data.
So the three well-known V's are volume,
velocity, and variety.
We will also talk about a lesser-known V,
which is called valence.
Okay, what we want to talk about is,
what impact these things
have on graph data.
So for volume, let's take a dataset like
the load network of the United States.
Well, that's a pretty large graph.
So when we say volume,
I mean that the size of the graph
is much larger than what you might have
in the memory of a reasonable computer or
real computing infrastructure.
Now, we will see what impact the size
of the graph has on analytic operations.
What we mean by velocity
when it comes to graphs?
Well, think of Facebook again.
So these little graphs are updates.
So you write a post, then like somebody
else's post, and make a comment.
That's a bunch of updates.
That comes and adds to your graph.
Well, then ten minutes later,
you do something similar, and
that also comes and adds to the graph.
Then your friend does the same thing,
it adds to your graph.
So as time goes by,
you are sending more edges to your graph.
And the speed at which
you are doing this for
at least like Facebook can be really,
really high.
So the rate of update in
Facebook is really high.
This is what is called
streaming edges into graphs.
And there can be multiple streams for
various reasons.
What do we mean by variety?
For graphs, it means that the graph is
collecting data from various places.
And all these different places are giving
different kinds of information to
the graph.
So in the end,
the graph has more non-uniform and
complex information potentially
coming from multiple sources.
That's what we mean by variety
when we refer to graphs.
That picture there, by the way, is
different kinds of protein interactions.
The next one,
the less-known one is valence.
Now, if you remember your chemistry,
this comes from valence electrons,
which are electrons in an atom
which are used for bonding.
The other electrons
are called core electrons.
So the idea is if we increase
the valence of the graphs,
you increase the connectiveness
of the graph.
How, we will see.
Now, graph size clearly impacts analytics.
Why, a, it takes more space, but more
importantly, it increases the algorithmic
complexity of any operation that
you want it to on the graph.
Now, we'll see an example of that,
but what happens as
a result is that the data-to-analysis
time becomes high.
So I put in some data, and
I wanted to do this analysis.
But there is so much data, that my
analysis takes way longer than it should.
Let's give a simple example,
an example we have seen before.
Remember, we had this little graph
from our biological example where we
were asking, find a simple path between
Alzheimer's Disease and Colorectal Cancer.
And in this case, the result is obvious.
Now, let's pause and ask.
There are two nodes that I mentioned,
in this case,
my Colorectal Cancer and
Alzheimer's Disease nodes.
And we are asking,
is there a simple path connecting them?
This is called a decision problem.
I give you a data, and I'm asking does
such a simple path exist or not exist?
But this is actually a very
hard decision problem.
And the computer scientists will tell you
that this is a very complicated problem
because it has a very high complexity.
Let's ask another question.
Well, how many simple paths,
now I want to count.
How many simple paths exist
between these two nodes?
Indeed, it is another
hard computing problem.
And if you really want to know,
the size of the result,
in the worst case is exponential
in the number of nodes.
So if we increase the number of nodes and
edges, if we increase the size of
the graph such a seemingly simple question
can take a very, very, very long time.
So that it's almost practically
impossible to compute it for
a really large graph if we have
no other information supporting.
That's the worst case.
But when we say algorithmic complexity
increases, that's what we mean.
Let's talk about velocity, and
I said our favorite example is Facebook.
So we are adding a bunch of updates, which
means we are adding a bunch of edges.
We are streaming the edges into the data,
and we want to compute a metric.
We want to see what is
the shortest distance
between person a and
person b or item a and item b.
Or I want to know that
Facebook has communities.
Twitter has communities like we saw.
And how many people out there,
in these communities, and
how many such communities are there,
like a Facebook group?
Now, if you want to compute this metric,
and you get this
edges very fast, it is very difficult
to know when you have the answer.
Because you are going to get an increasing
number of edges in the system,
and you keep computing this metric that
you want to find the answer for, and
it will turn out that your continuous
stream does not fit in memory.
Because your memory is limited
compared to the amount of
edges, or edge updates you
are streaming into the system.
So that's what's happened when you
have high velocity information.
Very soon, your memory runs out,
and you want to compute
your answer right now from
the data that you have.
Okay, let's look at variety,
also known as heterogeneity.
There are two aspects of heterogeneity.
One, we have already mentioned, graph data
is often created through integration,
like we saw in the case of the biology.
And therefore, the variety comes because
the nature of data is very different.
Also, they may not be all
the same kind of data.
For example, the data may come
from a relational database,
it may come from an XML database.
It may come from another graph.
It may come from a document.
It may even come from complex
things like social networks,
like citation networks between papers or
patents, between interaction networks,
between web entities,
which are connected through links.
And from human knowledge that has been
represented as graphs through ontologists.
So all of these graphs, the nodes and
the edges do not mean the same thing.
And somehow in there,
you need to capture what it means to have
an edge because that will determine
what you can do with the edge.
A simple example, in an ontology,
is something that says a is a b,
and b is a c, so a is a c.
The a is a c is an inference that you do,
given the other two relationships.
What would be an example?
My pet is a dog, and the dog is a mammal,
therefore, my pet is a mammal.
You want to do inferences for
some edges likes is a.
Now, you need to know this.
You do not do this with the biology
example where you are looking at genes and
proteins because that operation does
not make sense when you have genes and
proteins.
So therefore, every graph may
have a different semantics.
And what happens with variety is
the number of sub-semantics and
the number of valid
operations that you can do.
That changes, and
that becomes more complex.
Now, valence I said,
is about connectedness.
It is also about
interdependency among data.
So if I have a higher valence which means,
I have more data elements that
are more strongly related, and
these relationships can be exploited.
In most cases,
the part where valence becomes important,
is that it increases over time, which
means, parts of the graph becomes denser,
and the average distance
between node pairs decreases.
Let me show you, here is my Gmail.
And I have plotted my Gmail graphs
from 2006 to about two months back.
When I first started using it,
I had these users,
a very few users, and
they are not really related.
Now with time, more and
more people started communicating
with me through Gmail.
And more and more of these people were
also talking amongst themselves and
copying me and responding to me.
By the end, you would see that
you can find dense groups
within my Gmail because
the information and
the connectedness between people have
evolved and become more dense over time.
This is the phenomenon of valence, and
this is very important to study because
you want to study things like, what parts
of the graph have become more dense?
And why have they become more dense?
Maybe something was going on.
Maybe there was an event that
brought these people together,
and you want to analyze that and
find that out from your graph analytics.
That's why you want to understand
the effect of valence.
You also want to understand what do I do
if the graph becomes very, very dense
in a place, so that finding a path through
that dense space becomes very hard.
You will see in a later video that when
this happens, the computer system,
that is trying to process these graphs in
a parallel and distributed way has to do
something special to handle these
increasing density in parts of the graph.
So before we go into graph analytics,
the first question we want to ask is,
what is a graph?
Let's see.
This is a plot of the sales of
some items against time and
it gives you a nice visual representation
of the data, but is it a graph?
While you think about it,
let's try another one.
This is another common visual
representation of data.
If you go to Google and type pie graph,
you will see many results
that look like this.
But is this a graph?
In our research, this is not a graph.
We call it a chart.
Yes, you guessed it right this time.
This too is a chart, and not a graph.
So why do people call them graphs, then?
In a sense, they're abbreviating.
A chart depicts what's called
a graph of a function.
Let me explain.
Look at the two column table on the right.
The first column has information
about product category
with values like furniture,
office supplies, and technology.
The second column represents another set
of values called total containing 1724,
4610, and 2065.
Now we can define our mapping option.
Which means a correspondence
from Product Category to Total.
So we map Furniture to the value 1,724,
Office Supplies to the value 4,610,
and so forth.
If we visually portray this,
we can represent it like a bar chart or
a pie chart.
This is why both the previous diagram and
this diagram are charts and not graphs.
Graph analytics has its basis in a brand
of mathematics called graph theory.
What's more interesting,
however, is that graph theory was
born out of a very practical problem.
The problem started in a very old city
in Prussia which is now in Russia
called Konigsberg.
Even if we look at in in Google Maps
it would sort of look like this.
One of the interesting features of
Konigsberg is that it has two islands and
these islands are connected
by seven bridges.
Back in 1736, the city wanted to create
a walkway, and the criteria was,
this walkway would traverse all
seven bridges such that somebody
wanting to go from one part of the city
to another can cross a bridge only once.
Now this is sort of an urban
planning problem right?
Well in fact, it required
a mathematician to solve the problem.
The mathematician named Euler shown
on the left looked at this and
figured out that you really
cannot create such a walk.
Why?
He said, it cannot be done, because
there are an odd number of bridges, and
proved it mathematically.
From this problem, the whole field
called graph theory emerged.
On the right, you can see Edsger Dijkstra,
a well-known computer scientist who has
developed graph algorithms, one of which
we will study later in the course.
His work has had far further impact on
both the theoretical computer science and
practical applications.
What's the difference between
the mathematics view and
the computer science view?
Let's try to define
the mathematical view of graphs.
We start with a set of vertices.
Here we have a set of six nodes or
vertices.
Now, I'll add another set.
I'll call this the set of edges.
In our diagram there are only four edges,
but
there's something special
about these edges.
Each edge is just not
an ordinary atomic object.
An edge like e1, actually, is one term
from v and then a second term from v.
So this edge, e1, goes from v1 to v5.
Pictorially, we can draw and
arrow from v1 to v5.
Now if I had said v5 to v1,
the arrow would be reversed.
So what do we have so far?
We have a set of vertices and
a set of edges.
That is the mathematical
definition of a graph.
What about the computer
scientist's definition?
Of course a computer scientist needs to
adhere to the mathematical definition, but
they want to represent and
manipulate the same information.
So they need a data structure.
In other words,
something they can operate on.
So what kind of operations would they do?
Well, with a graph,
they can say add edge, or add a new
vertex, find the nearest neighbors of
the vertex where the term neighbor refers
to the nodes connected to the vertex.
We said a computer scientist needs to
represent graphs using data structures.
Here is one that you should recognize.
It's a matrix,
called the adjacency matrix of a graph.
Both the rows and
columns of this matrix represent notes.
If I go from v1 one along the row,
I see that there's one at v3,
which means there is
an edge from v1 to v3.
Similarly there is another from v1 to v5.
Let's look at some operation.
Let's say I first want to
add an edge from v3 to v2.
What should I do?
I'll start from the row v3,
go up to the column v2,
and add a 1 in that set.
So I've added an edge,
which is an operation on the matrix.
Another operation.
I want to get the neighbors a v3.
This will be a little more complicated.
I look at the row v3 and
paint that row and
I'll also look at the column v3 and
paint that column.
If we go down the row of v3,
we'll get v2, so v2 is neighbor.
And if we go down the column of v3,
we'll get v1 and v6.
So v1 and v6 have alternators.
What's the difference?
Since the matrix has the From along
the rows and the Tos along the columns,
following the row v3 gives us
the edges outgoing from v3.
And following the column v3 gives
us the edges coming into v3.
Is this the only
representation of the graph?
No it's not.
Here is another one,
in this representation there
are two kinds of data objects.
No data, which are the blue rectangles and
edge data which are the triangles.
To get a sense of this representation,
look at the note v1 and
follow the top yellow line.
It'll reach v3.
So this link structure directly captures
the graph diagram we created before.
Now, start from v1 again and
follow the blue link and
it will reach e1 and then v3.
So that tells you that e1 is
an edge object between v1 and v3.
Next, let's stand on the edge triangle e1,
and follow the red
dashed line to get to e2, which is
the next edge from the same starting node.
Is this possibly too complex?
Yes it is.
However, as we'll see down the road, many
graph database systems are using this kind
of data structure internally, so that the
database operations become more efficient.