In this video we will provide a quick
summary of the main points from our
first course on introduction to big data.
If you have just completed
our first course and
do not need a refresher,
you may now skip to the next lecture.
After this video,
you will be able to recall
what started the big data era and
the three main big data sources.
Summarize the volume,
variety, velocity and
veracity issues related to each source.
Explain the five step data science
process to gain value from big data.
Remember the main elements
of the Hadoop Stack.
We began our first course with
an explanation of how a lead torrent of
big data combined with cloud computing
capabilities to process data anytime and
anywhere has been at the core of
the launch of the Big Data Era.
This big torrent of big data is often
boil down to a few varieties of data
generated by machines, people and
organizations with machine generated data.
We refer to the data generated from real
time sensors and industrial machinery or
vehicles.
Web logs that track user behavior online.
environmental sensors,
personal health trackers among
many other sense data sources.
With human generated data, we really refer
to the vast amount of social media data,
status updates, tweets, photos and videos.
With organization generated data,
we refer to more traditional types of data
including transaction
information data bases and
structure data often
stored in data warehouses.
Note that big data can be structured,
semi-structured, and unstructured.
Which is a topic we will talk about
more and in depth later in this course.
Whatever your big data application is and
the types of big data you're using,
the real value will come from integrating
different types of data sources and
analyzing them at scale.
Overall, by modeling, managing and
integrating diverse streams
to improve our business and
add value to our big data even
before we start analyzing it.
As a part of modeling and
managing big data is focusing on
the dimensions of scale availability and
considering the challenges associated with
this dimensions to pick the right tools.
Volume, variety and
velocity are the main dimensions which
we characterized big data and
describe its challenges.
We have huge amounts of data
in different formats and
varying quality which
must be processed quickly
veracity refers to the biases,
noise, and abnormality in data,
or the unmeasurable certainty is in the
truthfulness and trustworthiness of data,
and valence refers to
the connectedness of big data.
Such as in the form of graph networks.
Each V presents a challenging
dimension of big data mainly of size,
complexity, speed, quality,
and consecutiveness.
Although we can list some
other v' based on the context.
We prefer to list these five as
fundamental dimensions which
this big data specialization
helps you work on.
Moreover, we must be sure to
never forget the sixth V: Value,
at the heart of the big
data challenge is turning
all of the other dimensions into
truly useful business value.
How will Big Data benefit you and
your organization?
The idea behind processing all
this Big Data in the first place
is to bring value to the problem at hand.
We need to take steps into
Big Data engineering and
scalable data science to
generate value out of Big Data.
We have all heard it.
Data signs turns big data into insides,
or even actions.
But what does that really mean?
Data signs can be taught of as
the basis for empirical research.
Like data is used to induce
information on the observations.
These observations are mainly data.
In our case, big data related to
a business or scientific use case.
Inside is a term we use to refer to
the data products of data science.
It is extracted from
a diverse amount of data
through a combination of exploratory
data analysis and modeling.
The questions are sometimes less
specific and it can require looking
carefully at the data for patterns in
it to come up with a specific question.
Another important point to recognize
is that data science is not static
one time analysis.
It involves a process where models
where you generate give us insights
are constantly improve to a further and
prequel evidence and iterations.
There are many ways to
look at this process.
One way of looking at it
as two distinct activities.
Mainly, big data engineering and
big data analytics,
or computational big data
science as I like to call it,
since more than simple
analytics are being performed.
A more detailed way of looking at
the process reveals five listing steps or
activities of the data science process,
namely acquire, prepare,
analyze, report, and act.
We can simply say that data science
happens at the boundary of all the steps.
Ideally, this process should
support experimental work,
which is constantly iterated and
leads to more scientific exploration,
as well as producing actionable
results during these explorations
using dynamic scalability on big data and
cloud platforms.
This five step process can be used in
alternative ways in real life big data
applications if we add the dependencies
of different tools to each other.
The influence of big data pushes for
alternative scalability approaches
at each step of the process.
Acquire includes anything
that helps us retrieve data,
including finding, accessing,
acquiring, and moving data.
It includes identification of and
authenticated access to all related data,
as well as transportation of data
from sources to destinations.
It includes ways to subset and
match the data to regions or
times of interest, which we sometimes
refer to as geospatial querying.
We divide the prepare data
step into two sub-steps,
based on the nature of the activity.
The first step in data preparation
involves exploring the data
to understand its nature,
what it means, its quality, and format.
It often takes a preliminary
analysis of data, or
samples of data, to understand it.
This is why this primary
step is called prepare.
Once we know more about the data
through exploratory analysis,
the next step is pre-processing
of data for analysis.
It includes cleaning data,
subsetting, or filtering data, and
creating data, which programs can read and
understand by modelling raw data
into a more defined data model, or
packaging it using a specific data format.
We will learn more about data models and
data formats later in this course.
If there are multiple data sets involved,
this step also includes integration
of different data sources or
streams, which is a topic we will
explore in our course three.
The prepared data then would be
passed on to the analysis step,
which involves selection of
analytical techniques to use,
building a model of the data,
and analyzing results.
This step can take a couple
of iterations on its own or
might require a data scientist
to go back to steps 1 and
2 to get more data or
package data in a different way.
So, exploration never ends.
Step 4 for communicating results includes
evaluation of analytical results,
presenting them in a visual way,
creating reports that include
an assessment of results with
respect to success criteria.
Activities in this step can often be
referred to with terms like interpret,
summarize, visualize, and post-process.
The last step brings us back to the very
first reason we do data science,
for a purpose.
Reporting insights from analysis and
determining actions from insights based
on the purpose you initially defined
is what we refer to as the act step.
We have now seen all of the steps
in a typical data science process.
Please note that this is an iterative
process and findings from
one step may require previous steps
to be repeated, but need information,
leading for further exploration and
application of these steps.
Scalability of this process to big
data analysis requires the use of
big data platforms like Hadoop.
The Hadoop ecosystem frameworks and
applications
provide such functionality through
several overarching themes and goals.
First, they provide scalability
to store large volumes of data
on commodity hardware.
As the number of systems increase, so
does the chance for
crashes and hardware failures.
They handle fault tolerance to
gracefully recover from these problems.
In addition, they are designed to handle
big data capacity and compressing text
files, graphs of social networks,
streaming sensor data and raster images.
We can add more data
types to this variety.
For any given data type,
you can find several projects in
the ecosystem that support it.
Finally, they facilitate
a shared environment,
allow multiple jobs to
execute simultaneously.
Additionally, the Hadoop ecosystem
includes a wide range of open source
projects backed by a large and
active community.
These projects are free to use and
easy to find support for.
Today, there are over 100
Big Data open source projects,
and this continues to grow, many rely
on Hadoop, but some are independent.
Here is, one way of looking at a subset
of tools in the Hadoop Ecosystem.
This layer diagram is organized
vertically based on the interface.
Lower level interfaces to storage and
scheduling on the bottom and
high level languages and
interactivity at the top.
The Hadoop distributed file system,
or HDFS, is the foundation for
many big data frameworks since it
provides scalable and reliable storage.
As the size of your data increases,
you can add commodity
hardware to HDFS to
increase storage capacity.
So it enables what we call
scaling out of your resources.
Hadoop YARN provide
flexible scheduling and
resource management over the HTFS storage.
Yarn is use at Yahoo to schedule
jobs across 40,000 servers.
MapReduce is a programming model
that simplifies parallel computing.
Instead of dealing with the complexities
of synchronization and scheduling you only
need to give MapReduce two
functions map and reduce.
This programming model is so
powerful that Google previously
used it for indexing websites.
MapReduce, only assumes
a limited model to express data.
Hive, and
Pig are two additional programming models,
on top of MapReduce,
to augment data modeling of MapReduce,
with relational algebra and
data flow modeling, respectively.
Hive was created at Facebook to
issue SQL-like queries using
MapReduce on their data in HDFS.
Pig was created at Yahoo to model
dataflow based programs using MapReduce.
Thanks to YARNs ability to
manage resources, not just for
MapReduce but other programming models.
Giraph was built for
processing large scale graphs efficiently.
For example, Facebook uses Giraph to
analyze the social graphs of its users.
Similarly, Storm, Spark and
Flink were built for
real time and
In-memory processing of big data.
On top of the YARN resource scheduler and
HDFS.
In-memory processing is a powerful
way of running big data applications,
even faster, achieving 100x better
performance for some tasks.
Sometimes your data processing or
tasks are not easily or
efficiently represented using the file and
directory model of storage,
examples of this include collections
of key values or large sparse tables.
NoSQL projects such as
Cassandra MongoDB and
HBase handle all these cases.
Cassandra was created at Facebook and
Facebook also use HBase for
its messaging platform.
Finally, running all this tools requires
a centralized management system for
synchronization, configuration And
to ensure high availability.
Zookeeper, created by Yahoo to
wrangle services named after animals,
performs these duties.
Just looking at the small number
of Hadoop stack components,
we can already see that most of them
are dedicated to data modeling.
Management, and
efficient processing of the data.
In the rest of this course,
we will give you fundamental knowledge and
some practical skills on how to start
modeling and managing your data, and
picking the right tools for this activity
from a plethora of big data tools.
Welcome to course two of
the big data specialization.
I'm Amarnath Gupta.
>> And I'm Ilkay Altintas.
We are really excited to work
with you in this course,
to develop your understanding and skills
in big data modeling and management.
You might have just finished our first
course, and see the potential and
challenges of big data.
If you haven't it's not required but for
those with less background in
the area you might find it valuable.
>> Let's explain what we mean by
big data modeling and management.
Suppose you have an application
where the data is big in a sense and
it has a large volume, or has high speed,
or comes with a lot of variations.
Even before you think of
how to handle the bigness,
you need to have a sense of
what the data looks like.
The goal of data modeling is to
formally explore the nature of data, so
that you can figure out what
kind of storage you need, and
what kind of processing you can do on it.
The goal of data management
is to figure out
what kind of infrastructure support
you would need for the data.
For example, does your environment need
to keep multiple replicas of the data?
Do you need to do statistical
computation with the data?
Once these operational requirements,
you'll
be able to choose the right system that
will let you perform these operations.
>> We will also introduce
management of big data as it is
streaming from data sources and talk
about storage architectures for big data.
For example,
how can high velocity data get ingested,
managed, stored in order to enable
real time analytical capabilities.
Or what is the difference between
data at rest and data in motion?
And how can a data system enable both?
>> Once you've understood the basic
concepts of data modeling,
data management, and streaming data,
we will introduce you
to the characteristics of large volume
data and how to think about that.
Thus, we will transition from
classical database management systems,
that is DBMSs,
to big data management systems, or BDMSs.
We'll present brief overviews of
several big data management systems
available in the marketplace today.
We are so excited to show you examples
of archived and streaming big data sets.
Our goal is to provide you with simple
hands on exercises that require
no programming, but show you what
big data looks like, and why various
big data management systems are suitable
for specific kinds of big data.
In the end you will be
able to design a simple
big data information system
using this knowledge.
We wish you a fun time learning and
hope to hear from you in the discussion
forums and learner stories.
>> Happy learning and think big data.
This is the second course in the 2016
version of our big data specialization.
>> After listening to learners like you,
we have changed some of the content and
ordering in the specialization.
This course takes you on the first
step of any big data project,
its modeling and management.
>> We hope that this background
on what big data looks like and
how it is modeled and managed in
a large scale system will make you feel
more prepared to take steps towards
retrieving and processing big data and
perform big data analytics which
are topics coming up in the next courses.