Getting started.
Why Hadoop?
We have all heard that Hadoop and
related projects in this
ecosystem are great for big data.
This module will answer the four Ws and
an H about why this statement is true.
Before we dive further into
the details of Hadoop,
let's take a moment to analyze the
characteristics of the Hadoop ecosystem.
What's in the ecosystem?
Why is it beneficial?
Where is it used?
Who uses it?
And how do these tools work?
The Hadoop ecosystem frameworks and
applications that we will describe in this
module have several overarching themes and
goals.
First, they provide scalability
to store large volumes of data
on commodity hardware.
As the number of systems increases,
so does the chance for crashes and
hardware failures.
A second goal, supported by most
frameworks in the Hadoop ecosystem,
is the ability to gracefully
recover from these problems.
In addition, as we have mentioned before,
big data comes in
a variety of flavors, such as text files,
graph of social networks,
streaming sensor data and raster images.
A third goal for
the Hadoop ecosystem then,
is the ability to handle these different
data types for any given type of data.
You can find several projects in
the ecosystem that support it.
A fourth goal of the Hadoop ecosystem
is the ability to facilitate
a shared environment.
Since even modest-sized
clusters can have many cores,
it is important to allow multiple
jobs to execute simultaneously.
Why buy servers only to let them sit idle?
Another goal of the Hadoop ecosystem
is providing value for your enterprise.
The ecosystem includes a wide
range of open source projects
backed by a large active community.
These projects are free to use and
easy to find support for.
In the following lectures in this module,
we will take a more detailed
look at the Hadoop ecosystem.
First, we will explore the kinds
of projects available and
the types of capabilities they provide.
Next we will take a deeper look at
the three main parts of Hadoop.
The Hadoop distributed file system,
or HDFS.
YARN, the scheduler and resource manager.
And MapReduce, a programming model for
processing big data.
We will then discuss cloud computing, and
the types of service models it provides.
We will also describe situations in
which Hadoop is not the best solution.
This module then concludes with
two readings involving hands-on
experience with HDFS and MapReduce.
So let's get started.
MapReduce, Simple Programming for
Big Results.
MapReduce is a programming model for
the Hadoop ecosystem.
It relies on YARN to schedule and
execute parallel processing over
the distributed file blocks in HDFS.
There are several tools that use the
MapReduce model to provide a higher level
interface to other programming models.
Hive has a SQL-like interface that
adds capabilities that help with
relational data modeling.
And Pig is a high level data flow language
that adds capabilities that
help with process map modeling.
Traditional parallel programming requires
expertise on a number of computing and
systems concepts.
For example, synchronization
mechanisms like locks, semaphores,
and monitors are essential.
And incorrectly using them can
either crash your program, or
severely impact performance.
This high learning curve
makes it difficult.
It is also error prone,
since your code can run on hundreds, or
thousands of nodes,
each having many cores.
And any problem related to
these parallel processes,
needs to be handled by
your parallel program.
The MapReduce programming model greatly
simplifies running code in parallel
since you don't have to deal
with any of these issues.
Instead, you only need to create and
map and reduce tasks, and you don't
have to worry about multiple threads,
synchronization, or concurrency issues.
So, what is a map and reduce?
Map and reduce are two concepts
based on functional programming
where the output the function
is based solely on the input.
Just like in a mathematical function,
f (x) = y, y depends on x.
You provide a function, or
operation for a map, and reduce.
And the runtime executes it over the data.
For map, the operation is
applied on each data element.
And in reduce, the operation
summarizes elements in some manner.
An example, using map and
reduce will make this concepts more clear.
Hello word is a traditional
first program you code
when you start to learning
programming languages.
The first program to learn, or hello
word of map reduce, is often WordCount.
WordCount reads one or
more text files, and
counts the number of occurrences
of each word in these files.
The output will be a text
file with a list of words and
their occurrence frequencies
in the input data.
Let's examine each step of WordCount.
For simplification we are assuming
we have one big file as an input.
Before WordCount runs,
the input file is stored in HDFS.
As you know now,
HDFS partitions the blocks across
multiple nodes in the cluster.
In this case, four partitions labeled,
A, B, C, and D.
The first step in MapReduce is to
run a map operation on each node.
As the input partitions are read
from HTFS, map is called for
each line in the input.
Let's look at the first lines
of the input partitions, A and
B, and start counting the words.
The first line,
in the partition on node A,
says, My apple is red and my rose is blue.
Similarly, the first line, on partition B,
says, You are the apple of my eye.
Let's now see what happens in
the first map node for partition A.
Map creates a key value for
each word on the line containing
the word as the key, and 1 as the value.
In this example, the word apple is
read from the line in partition A.
Map produces a key value of (apple, 1).
Similarly, the word my is seen
on the first line of A twice.
So, the key values of (my,
1), are created.
Note that map goes to each node
containing a data block for
the file,
instead of the data moving to map.
This is moving computation to data.
Let's now see what the same map
operation generates for partition B.
Since each word only
happens to occur once,
a list of all the words with one
key-value pairing each gets generated.
Please take a moment to
observe the outputs of map and
each key-value pair associated to a word.
Next, all the key-values that were output
from map are sorted based on their key.
And the key values, with the same word,
are moved, or shuffled, to the same node.
To simplify this figure, each node only
has a single word, in orange boxes.
But in general,
a node will have many different words.
Just like our example from the two
lines in A and B partitions.
Here we see that, you and apple,
are assigned to the first node.
The word is, to the second node.
And the words, rose and red, to the third.
Although, for simplicity, we drew four
map nodes and three shuffle nodes.
The number of nodes can be extended
as much as the application demands.
Next, the reduce operation
executes on these nodes to
add values for
key-value pairs with the same keys.
For example, (apple, 1), and
another (apple, 1), becomes (apple, 2).
The result of reduce is
a single key pair for
each word that was read in the input file.
The key is the word, and
the value is the number of occurrences.
If we look back at our WordCount example,
we see that there were
three distinct steps.
Namely, the map step, the shuffle and
sort step, and the reduce step.
Although, the WordCount
example is pretty simple,
it represents a large number of
applications to which these three steps
can be applied in order to achieve
data parallel scalability.
For example, now that you have
seen the WordCount application,
consider changing the WordCount
algorithm to index all
the URLs by words after a web crawl.
This means, instead of pointing to
a number, the keys would refer to URLs.
After the map, with this new function,
which by the way is called a user
defined function, the output of
shuffle and sort would look like this.
Now, when we reduce the URLs, all the URLs
that mention Apple would look like this.
This is, in fact, one of the ways
a search engine like Google works.
So now, if somebody came to the interface
built for this application,
to search for the word apple,
and entered apple,
it would be easy to get all
the URLs as the word itself.
No wonder the first MapReduce
paper was produced by Google.
We will give you a link to the original
Google paper on MapReduce from
2004 at the end of this lecture.
It is pretty technical, but
it gives you a simple overview without
the current system implementations.
We just saw how MapReduce can
be used in search engines
in addition to counting the words and
documents.
Although it's possible to add many
more applications, let's stop here for
a general discussion on how the points of
data parallelism can be used in
search in this three step pattern.
There is definitely parallelization
during the map step.
This parallelization is over the input,
as each partition gets
processed one line at a time.
To achieve this type of data
parallelism we must decide on
the data granularity of
each parallel competition.
In this case, it will be a line.
We also see parallel grouping of
data in the shuffle and sort phase.
This time, the parallelization is
over the intermediate products.
That is, the individual key-value pairs.
And after the grouping of
the intermediate products,
the reduce step gets parallelized
to construct one output file.
You have probably noticed
that the data gets reduced
to a smaller set at each step.
This overview gave us an idea of what
kinds of tasks that MapReduce is good for.
While MapReduce excels at independent
batch tasks similar to our applications,
there are certain kinds of tasks that
you would not want to use MapReduce for.
For example,
if your data is frequently changing,
MapReduce is slow since it reads
the entire input data set each time.
The MapReduce model requires that maps and
reduces execute
independently of each other.
This greatly simplifies
your job as a designer,
since you do not have to deal
with synchronization issues.
However, it means that computations
that do have dependencies,
cannot be expressed with MapReduce.
Finally, MapReduce does
not return any results
until the entire process is finished.
It must read the entire input data set.
This makes it unsuitable for interactive
applications where the results must be
presented to the user very quickly,
expecting a return from the user.
As a summary, MapReduce hides
complexities of parallel programming and
greatly simplifies building
parallel applications.
Many types of tasks suitable for
MapReduce include search engine
page ranking and topic mapping.
Please see the reading after
this lecture on making Pasta Sauce
with MapReduce for another fun application
using the MapReduce programming model.
Programming Models for Big Data.
We have seen that scalable computing
over the internet to achieve
data-parallel scalability for big data
applications is now a possibility.
Thanks to commodity clusters.
Cost-effective commodity clusters
together with advances in distributed
file systems to move computation to data,
provide a potential to conduct
scalable big data analytics.
The next thing we will
talk about is how to take
advantage of these
infrastructure advances.
What are the right programming models?
A programming model is an abstraction or
existing machinery or infrastructure.
It is a set of abstract
runtime libraries and
programming languages that
form a model of computation.
This abstraction level can be low-level
as in machine language in computers.
Or very high as in high-level programming
languages, for example, Java.
So we can say,
if the enabling infrastructure for
big data analysis is distributed
file systems as we mentioned,
then the programming model for
big data should enable the programmability
of the operations within
distributed file systems.
What we mean by this being able to
write computer programs that work
efficiently on top of distributed
file systems using big data and
making it easy to cope with
all the potential issues.
Based on everything we discussed so
far, let's describe the requirements for
big data programming models.
First of all, such a programming model for
big data should support
common big data operations like
splitting large volumes of data.
This means for partitioning and
placement of data in and
out of computer memory along with a model
to synchronize the datasets later on.
The access to data should
be achieved in a fast way.
It should allow fast distribution to nodes
within a rack and these are potentially,
the data nodes we moved
the computation to.
This means scheduling of
many parallel tasks at once.
It should also enable
reliability of the computing and
full tolerance from failures.
This means it should enable
programmable replications and
recovery of files when needed.
It should be easily scalable to
the distributed notes where the data gets
produced.
It should also enable adding new resources
to take advantage of distributive
computers and scale to more or
faster data without losing performance.
This is called scaling out if needed.
Since there are a variety
of different types of data,
such as documents, graphs,
tables, key values, etc.
A programming model should enable
operations over a particular set
of these types.
Not every type of data may be
supported by a particular model, but
the models should be optimized for
at least one type.
Is it getting a little complicated?
It doesn't have to have to be.
In fact, we apply similar models in
our daily lives for everyday tasks.
Let's look at the scenario where you
might unknowingly apply this model.
Imagine a peaceful Saturday afternoon.
You receive a phone call from a friend and
she says,
she they will be at your
house in an hour for dinner.
It seems like you completely forgot that
you had invited your friends for dinner.
So you say, you are looking forward
to it and head to the kitchen.
As a quick solution, you decide to
cook pasta with some tomato sauce.
You need to take advantage
of parallelization, so
that the dinner is ready by the time your
guest arrive, that's within an hour.
You call your spouse and your teenage
kids to action in the kitchen.
Now, you need to give them directions to
start dicing the ingredients for you.
But in the heat of the moment, you end up
mixing the onions, tomatoes and peppers.
Instead of sorting them first,
you give everyone a randomly mixed
batch of different types of vegetables.
They are required to use their computer
powers to chop the vegetables.
They need to ensure not mix
different types of veggies.
When everyone is done chopping, you want
to group the veggies by their types.
You ask each helper to collect items
of the same type, put them in a large
bowl and label this large bowl with
the sum of individual bowl weights
like tomatoes in one bowl, peppers in
another and the onions in the third bowl.
In the end,
you have nice large bowls with the total
weight of each vegetable labeled on it.
Your helpers are soon done with their work
while you're focused on coordinating their
actions and other dinner tasks in the
kitchen, you can start cooking your pasta.
What you have just seen is an excellent
example of big data modeling in action.
Only it is really the data
processed by human processors.
This scenario can be modeled by a common
programming model for big data.
Namely MapReduce.
MapReduce is a big data programming
model that supports all
the requirements of big
data modeling we mentioned.
It can model processing large data,
split complications into
different parallel tasks and
make efficient use of large commodity
clusters and distributed file systems.
In addition, it abstracts out
the details of parallelzation,
full tolerance, data distribution,
monitoring and load balancing.
As a programming model,
it has been implemented in a few
different big data frameworks.
Next week,
we will see more details on MapReduce and
how its Hadoop implementation works.
To summarize, programming models for
big data are abstractions over
distributed file systems.
The desired programming models for
big data should handle large volumes and
varieties of data.
Support full tolerance and
provide scale out functionality.
MapReduce is one of these models,
implemented in a variety of
frameworks including Hadoop.
We will summarize the inner workings
of the Hadoop implementation next week.
In this lecture we will use
Hadoop to run WordCount.
First we will open a terminal shell and
explore the Hadoop-provided MapReduce
programs.
Next we will verify the input
file exists in HDFS.
We will then run WordCount and
explore the WordCount output directory.
After that we will copy
the WordCount results
from HDFS to the local file system and
view them.
Let's begin.
First we'll open a terminal shell by
clicking on the icon at
top of the window here.
Next, we'll look at the map produced
programs that come with Hadoop.
We can do this by running Hadoop,
jars user jars, Hadoop examples .jar.
This command says we're going to use
the jar command to run a program
in Hadoop from a jar file.
And the jar file that we're running from
is in /usr/jars/hadoop-examples.jar.
Many programs written in Java
are distributed via jar files.
If we run this command We'll see a list of
different programs that come with Hadoop.
So for example, wordcount.
Count the words in a text file.
Wordmean, count the average
length of words.
And other programs, such as sorting and
calculating the length of pi.
In the previous lecture we downloaded
the Works of Shakespeare and
saved it into HDFS.
Let's make sure that file is still
there by running hadoop fs -ls.
We can see that the file is still there,
and it's called words.txt.
We can run wordcount by running hadoop jar
/usr/jars/hadoop-examples.jar wordcount.
This command says that
we're going to run a jar,
and this is the name of the jar
containing the program.
And the program we're
going to run is wordcount.
When we run it, we see that it
prints the command line usage for
how to run wordcount.
This says that wordcount takes one or
more input files and an output name.
Now, both the input and
the output are located in HDFS.
So we have the input file that we
just listed, words.txt, in HDFS.
We can run wordcount.
So we'll run hadoop
jar/usr/jars/hadoop-examples.jar
wordcount words.txt out.
This is saying we're going to run
the WordCount program using words.txt
as the input and
put the output in a directory called out.
So we'll run it.
As wordcount is running,
your prints progress to the screen.
It'll print the percentage of map and
reduce completed.
And when both of these reach 100%,
then the job is done.
Now that the job is complete,
let's look at the results.
We can run Hadoop fs
-ls to see the output.
This shows that out was created and
this is where our results are stored.
Notice that it's
a directory with a d here.
So hadoop word count created
the directory to contain the output.
Let's look inside that directory
by running Hadoop fs- ls out.
[BLANK AUDIO] We can see that there
are two files in this directory.
The first is _SUCCESS, this means that
the WordCount job completed successfully.
The other file part-r-00000 is a text file
containing the output from
the WordCount command
Now let's copy this text file to the local
file system from HDFS and then view it.
We could copy it by running
hadoop fs -copytolocal
out/part-r-00000 local.
And we'll say local.txt is the name.
You can view the results of this.
We're running more local.txt.
This will view the contents of the file.
We can hit spacebar to scroll down.
We see the results of
WordCount in this file.
Each line is a particular word and
the second column is the count
of how many words of this particular
word was found in the input file.
You can hit q to quit
Scalable computing over the internet.
Most computing is done on
a single compute node.
If the computation needs more than
a node or parallel processing,
like many scientific computing problems,
we use parallel computers.
Simply put, a parallel computer
is a very large number of
single computing nodes with specialized
capabilities connected to other network.
For example, the Gordon Supercomputer here
at The San Diego Supercomputer Center,
has 1,024 compute nodes with 16 cores each
equalling 16,384 compute cores in total.
This type of specialized
computer is pretty costly
compared to its most recent cousin,
the commodity cluster.
The term, commodity cluster,
is often heard in big data conversations.
Have you ever wondered
what it exactly means?
Commodity clusters are affordable
parallel computers
with an average number of computing nodes.
They are not as powerful as
traditional parallel computers and
are often built out of
less specialized nodes.
In fact,
the nodes in the commodity cluster
are more generic in their
computing capabilities.
The service-oriented computing community
over the internet have pushed for
computing to be done on commodity
clusters as distributed computations.
And in turn, reducing the cost
of computing over the Internet.
In commodity clusters,
the computing nodes are clustered in racks
connected to each other
via a fast network.
There might be many of such
racks in extensible amounts.
Computing in one or
more of these clusters across
a local area network or the internet
is called distributed computing.
Such architectures enable what
we call data-parallelism.
In data-parallelism many jobs
that share nothing can work on
different data sets or
parts of a data set.
This type of parallelism sometimes
gets called as job level parallelism.
But in this specialization,
we will refer to it as data-parallelism
in the context of Big-data computing.
Large volumes and varieties of big
data can be analyzed using this mode
of parallelism, achieving scalability,
performance and cost reduction.
As you can imagine, there are many
points of failure inside systems.
A node, or
an entire rack can fail at any given time.
The connectivity of a rack
to the network can stop or
the connections between
individual nodes can break.
It is not practical to restart everything
every time, if failure happens.
The ability to recover from such
failures is called Fault-tolerance.
For Fault-tolerance of such systems,
two neat solutions emerged.
Namely, Redundant data storage and
restart of failed
individual parallel jobs.
We will explain these two solutions next.
As a summary the commodity
clusters are a cost effective way
of achieving data parallel scalability for
big data applications.
These type of systems have a higher
potential for partial failures.
It is this type of distributed
computing that pushed for
a change towards cost
effective reliable and
Fault-tolerant systems for
management and analysis of big data.