In this activity we will perform
classification in Spark is in
decision tree.
First, we will load weather
data into DataFrame and
drop unused and missing data.
We'll then,
create a categorical variable for
low humidity days and aggregate
features used to make predictions.
We will then split our data
into training and test sets.
And then create and
train the decision tree.
Finally, we will save our
predictions to a CSV file.
Let's begin, first, we'll open
the notebook called classification.
The first cell contains the classes
we need to load to run this exercise.
Let's run this.
Next we create SQL context and load
the weather data CSV into a data frame.
The second cell also prints all
the columns in this data frame.
Run this.
The third cell defines the columns
in the weather data we will use for
the decision tree classifier.
Let's run it.
We will now use the column name number.
So, let's drop that from the data frame,
df = df.drop Number.
Now, let's revolve the rows with
missing data, df = df.na.drop.
Now, let's print the number of rows and
columns in our resulting data frame,
df.count(), len(df.columns).
Next, let's create a categorical variable
to denote if the humidity is low.
We'll enter binarizer = Binarizer ().
The first argument specifies
a threshold value for the variable.
We want the categorical variable to be 1,
if the humidity is greater than 25%.
So we'll enter a threshold=24.9999.
The next argument specifies the column to
use to create the categorical variable.
We'll input,
inputCol = relative_humidity_3pm.
The final argument specifies the new
column name, outputCol = label.
Now, let's create a new data frame
with this categorical variable.
binarizeredDF = binarizer.transform df.
Let's run this.
Let's look at the first four
rows in this new data frame.
We'll run binarizedDF.select
('relative_humidity_3pm',
'label').show(4).
The relative humidity in the first row
is greater than 25% and the label is 1.
The relative humidity in the second,
third, and fourth rows are less than 25%,
and the label is 0.
Next, let's aggregate the features we will
use to make predictions into a single col,
assembler = VectorAssember( ).
The first argument is a list of
the columns to be aggregated.
inputCols=featureColumns, and
the second argument is the name
of the new column containing the
aggregated features, outputCol=features.
We can create the new
data frame by running
assembled=assembler.transform binarizedDF.
Let's run this.
Next we will split our data
set into two parts, one for
training data and one for test data.
You can do this by entering (training
Data,
testData)=assembled.randomSplit([0.8,
0.2], seed=13234).
We can see the size of the two
sets by running count,
trainingData.count(), testData.count ().
Next let's create and
train the decision tree.
We'll enter dt = DecisionTreeClassifier.
The first argument is the column we're
trying to predict, labelCol='label'.
The second argument is the name
of the column containing your
aggregated features,
featuresCol='features'.
The third argument is
the stopping criteria for
tree induction based on the maximum
depth of the tree, maxDepth=5.
The fourth argument is the stopping
criteria for tree induction based
on the minimum number of samples
in a node, minInstancesPerNode=20.
And finally, the last argument
specifies the impurity measure
used to split the nodes,
impurity="gini", let's run this.
Next, we can create a model by
training the decision tree.
We'll do this by executing
it in a pipeline.
We'll enter pipeline=Pipeline
(stages=[dt]).
We'll create them all by putting
a training data, model =
pipeline.fit trainingData.
Let's run this Now, we can make
predictions using our test data.
We'll enter predictions =
model.transform(testData).
You can look at the first 10 rows
of the prediction by running,
predictions.select('prediction', label')
show(10).
You can see in the first ten rows,
the prediction matches the label.
Now let's save our
predictions to a CSV file.
In the next Spark hands-on activity
we will evaluate the accuracy.
You can save it by running
predictions.select('prediction',
'label').write.save(path='file File:///
home/cloudera/downloads/big-data-4/predic-
tions.csv.
We'll specify the format to use Spark csv.
Format='com.databricks.spark.csv.
Finally, we'll enter header='true'.
Run this to save
the predictions to a .csv file.
In this activity, we will be
performing classification in KNIME,
first we will create a new workflow and
import our weather data.
Next, we will remove the missing data and
then create a categorical value for
the humidity measurements.
We will then examine summary
statistics of the data before and
after the missing data was removed, and
finally build a decision tree workflow.
Let's begin.
First, let's create a New Workflow.
We'll call it Classification.
Next, we'll import the daily weather data,
using the File Reader node.
Configure the file reader node,
to use daily_weather.csv.
Next, we'll add a missing value node,
to remove the missing values
in the daily weather data.
We'll configure missing value to
remove all the missing values.
Next we'll use a numeric binner node
to create a categorical variable for
the humidity at 3pm.
We'll add the numeric binner node,
we'll connect it to missing value.
We'll select the relative
humidity 3pm column.
We'll create two bins,
the first bin we'll call humidity_low.
And that value will go up to 25.
The second bin, we'll
call humidity_not_low.
We'll check the Append new column and
we'll call the new
column low_humidity_day.
Next, we'll examine some summary
statistics, both before, and
after we've removed the missing values.
We'll add the statistics
node to the canvas.
We'll connect the first one to
the output of the File Reader actor.
We'll add another one to
the output of Numeric Binner.
We'll change the name of the first
one to be BEFORE filtering.
And change the name of the second
one to AFTER filtering.
Lets configure the first one.
We'll change the maximum number of
possible values per column to 1500.
We'll also add all the columns.
Let's configure the second statistics now.
Again, we'll change the maximum number of
possible values per column to 1500, and
we'll add all the columns.
Now let's run our workflow.
Let's view both Statistic
nodes to compare the outputs.
In the BEFORE filtering statistics,
we can see that there are missing values.
However, there are no missing values
in the AFTER filtering statistics.
We can also compare the summary
statistics, for different measurements,
to see that they are similar values.
For example,
let's take a look at air_temp_9am.
We could see that most of
the statistics are the same.
As well as the distribution of values.
In the AFTER filtering statistics,
click on the Nominal tab,
and we'll look at the low humidity
day categorical variable we created.
We can see that the samples are equally
distributed between the two values.
Let's close these Statistics views.
Next, let's add a Column Filter node.
We'll connect this to
the output of Numeric Binner.
Double-click to configure the node.
And we will exclude
relative_humidity_9am and
relative_humidity_3pm columns, click OK.
Next, we'll add a Color Manager
node to the canvas.
Will connect this to the output of Column
Filter, double-click to configure it.
We will make sure the humidly_low is red,
and humidity_not_low is blue.
Click OK to close.
Next, we'll add the Partitioning
node to the campus.
We'll connect this to
the output of Color Manager.
Double-click to configure.
We want to split the data
into two partitions.
The first partition should
have 80% of the data.
The second partition should have 20%.
To do this click on Relative[%] and
change this to 80.
We'll make sure Draw randomly is selected.
And check Use random seed and
change the seed to 12345.
Normally we would not
specific the random seed.
However, since we want repeatable results,
we use a specific seed value here.
Click OK to continue.
Next, we'll add a Decision Tree Learner
to the work flow.
We'll connect this to the top
output of the Partitioning node.
Double-click to configure, and
change the Min number of
records per node to 20.
Click OK.
Next, we'll add a Decision Tree Predictor
node to the canvas, and we will connect
the bottom output of Partitioning to
the bottom input of the predictor.
Next we'll connect the output
of Decision Tree Learner
to the top input of
Decision Tree Predictor.
Now let's execute our workflow.
We can view the resulting
classification rules
by right clicking on
Decision Tree Predictor.
And choosing either View: Decision Tree
View or View: Decision Tree View (simple).
Let's do the first one.
This shows the first two
splits in our decision tree.
We can expand each branch
by clicking on the plus.
Let's close this.
Now let's look at the simplified view.
Again, we can expand the branches to
see the splits in the Decision Tree.
Close this,
finally let's save this workflow.
We'll analyze the results of the Decision
Tree model in the next KNIME Hands On.
Save the workflow by
clicking on the disk icon.
Welcome back, we already discussing
Classification models and techniques for
next few lectures.
Let's first define what
the classification task is,
after this video you will be able
to define what classification is.
Explain whether classification is
supervised or unsupervised and
describe how binomial classification
differs from multinomial classification.
Classification is one type of
machine learning problems.
In the classification problem, the input
data is presented to the machine learning
model and the task is to predict the
target corresponding to the input data.
The target is a categorical variable,
so the classification task is
to predict the category or
label of the target given the input data.
For example, the classification
problem illustrated in this image
is to predict the type of weather.
The target that the model has to predict
is the weather and the possible values for
weather in this case is Sunny,
Windy, Rainy, or Cloudy.
The input data can consist of measurements
like temperature, relative humidity,
atmospheric pressure,
wind speed, wind direction, etc.
So, given specific values for temperature,
relative humidity, atmospheric pressure,
etc., the task for the model is to
predict if the weather will be sunny.
Windy, rainy, or cloudy for the day,
this is what the data set might look like
for the weather classification problem.
Each row is a sample with input
variables temperature, humidity, and
pressure and target variable weather.
Each row has specific values for
the input variables and
a corresponding value for
the target variable.
The classification task is to predict
the value of the target variable
from the values of the input variables.
Since a target is provided,
we have labeled data and so
classification is a supervised task.
Recall that in a supervised task,
the target or
desired output for each sample is given.
Note that the target variable goes
by many names such as target,
label, output, class variable,
category, and class.
A classification problem can be binary or
multi-class with binary
classification the target variable has two
possible values, for example yes and no.
With multi-class classification
the target variable has more than
two possible values.
For example, the target can be short,
medium and tall.
Multi-class classification is
also referred to multinomial or
multi-label classification.
Remember though that the target is always
a categorical variable in classification.
Some examples of binary
classification are predicting
whether it will rain tomorrow or not,
here there are two possible outcomes,
yes it will rain tomorrow or
no, it will not rain tomorrow.
Identifying whether a credit card
transaction is legitimate or fraudulent,
again, there are only two possible values
for the target, legitimate or fraudulent.
Some examples of multi-class
classification include
predicting what type of product
that a customer will buy.
The possible values for
the target variables would be product
categories such as kitchen,
electronics, clothes, etc.
There is more than one
category of products, so
this is a multi-class
classification problem.
Another example is categorizing a tweet
as having a positive, negative, or
neutral sentiment, again,
the number of possible values for
the target is more than two here.
So, this is also a multi-class
classification task
to summarize in classification,
the model has to predict the category
corresponding to the input data.
Since the target is provided for each
sample, classification is a supervised
task, the target variable is always
categorical in classification.
In this lecture,
we will look at the decision tree model,
a popular method used for classification.
After this video, you will be able to
explain how a decision tree is used for
classification.
Describe the process of constructing
a decision tree for classification.
And interpret how a decision tree comes
up with a classification decision.
The idea behind decision trees for
classification is to split the data
into subsets where each subset
belongs to only one class.
This is accomplished by dividing
the input space into pure regions,
that is regions with samples
from only one class.
With real data completely pure
subsets may not be possible.
So the goal is to divide the data into
subsets that are as pure as possible.
That is each subset contains as many
samples as possible from a single class.
Graphically this is equivalent to dividing
the input space into regions that are as
pure as possible.
Boundaries separating these regions
are called decision boundaries.
And the decision tree model
makes classification decisions
based on these decision boundaries.
A decision tree is a hierarchical
structure with nodes and directed edges.
The node at the top is
called the root node.
The nodes at the bottom
are called the leaf nodes.
Nodes that are neither the root node or
the leaf nodes are called internal nodes.
The root and
internal nodes have test conditions,
each leaf node has a class
label associated with it.
A classification decision is made
by traversing the decision tree
starting with the root node.
At each node the answer to the test
condition determines which
branch to traverse to.
When a leaf node is reached
the category at the leaf node
determines the classification decision.
The depth of a node is the number of
edges from the root node to that node.
The depth of the root node is 0.
The depth of a decision
tree is the number of edges
in the longest path from
the root node to the leaf node.
The size of a decision tree is
the number of nodes in the tree.
This is an example of a decision tree.
It can be used to classify an animal
as a mammal or not a mammal.
According to this decision tree,
if an animal is warm-blooded,
gives live birth, and
is a vertebrate, then it is a mammal.
If an animal does not have all
of these three characteristics,
then it is not a mammal.
A decision tree is built by starting
with all samples at a single node,
the root node.
Additional nodes are added when
the data is split into subsets.
At a high level, constructing a decision
tree consists of the following steps.
Start with all samples and a node,
partition the samples into subsets
based in the input variables.
The goal is to create subsets of
records that are purest, that is
each subset contains as many samples as
possible, belonging to just one class.
Another way to say this is that
the subsets should be as homogeneous or
as pure as possible.
Repeatedly partition data into
successively purer subsets
until some stopping
criterion is satisfied.
An algorithm for
constructing a decision tree model is
referred to as an induction algorithm.
So you may hear the term tree induction
used to describe the process of
building a decision tree.
Note that at each split
the induction algorithm
only considers the best way to split
that particular portion of the data.
This is referred to as a greedy approach.
Greedy algorithms solve a subset
of the problem at a time, and
as a necessary approach when solving
the entire problem is not feasible.
This is the case with decision trees.
It is not feasible to determine
the best tree given a data set, so
the tree has to be built
in piecemeal fashion
by determining the best way to split
the current node at each step.
And combining these decisions together
to form the final decision tree,
in constructing a decision tree
how is the data partitioned?
How does a decision tree
determine the best way to split
the set of samples at a node?
Again the goal is to partition data
at a node into subsets that are as
pure as possible.
In this example,
the partition shown on the right
results in more homogeneous subsets.
Since these subsets contain more
samples belonging to a single class
than the resulting subsets
shown on the left.
So the partition on the right
results in purer subsets and
is the preferred partition.
Therefore, we need a way to
measure the purity of a split
in order to compare different
ways to partition a set of data.
It turns out that it works out better
mathematically if we measure the impurity
rather than the purity of a split.
So the impurity measure of a node
specifies how mixed
the resulting subsets are.
Since we want the resulting subsets
to have homogeneous class labels,
not mixed class labels, we want the split
that minimizes the impurity measure.
A common impurity measure used for
determining the best
split is the Gini Index.
The lower the Gini Index the higher
the purity of the split.
So the decision tree will select
the split that minimizes the Gini Index.
Besides the Gini Index, other
impurity measures include entropy, or
information gain, and
misclassification rate.
The other factor in determining
the best way to partition a node
is which variable to split on.
The decision tree will test all variables
to determine the best way to split a node
using a purity measure such as
the Gini index to compare the various
possibilities.
Recall that the tree induction algorithm
repeatedly splits nodes to get more and
more homogeneous subsets.
So when does this process stop?
When does the algorithm
stop growing the tree?
There's several criteria that can be used
to determine when a node should no longer
be split into subsets.
The induction algorithm can
stop expanding a node when
all samples in the node
have the same class label.
This means that this set of data
is as pure as possible, and
further splitting will not result in
any better partition of the data.
Since getting completely pure subsets
is difficult to achieve with real data,
this stopping criterion can be modified.
To when a certain percentage of
the samples in the node, say 90% for
example, have the same class labels.
The algorithm can stop expanding a node
when the number of samples in the node
falls below a certain minimum value.
A this point the number of
samples is too small to make
much difference in the classification
results with the further splitting.
The induction algorithm can stop expanding
a node when the improvement in impurity
measure is too small to make much of
a difference in classification results.
The algorithm can stop expanding a node
when the maximum tree depth is reached.
This is to control the complexity
of the resulting tree.
There can be other criteria that can be
used to determine when tree induction
should stop.
Let's take a look at an example to
illustrate the tree induction process.
Let's say that we want to classify loan
applicants as being likely to repay a loan
or not likely to repay a loan
based on their income and
amount of debt they already have.
Building a decision tree for
this classification problem
could proceed as follows.
Consider the input space of this
problem as shown in the left figure.
One way to split this
data set into homogeneous
subsets is to consider the decision
boundary where income equals t1.
To the right of this decision
boundary are mostly red samples and
to the left are mostly blue samples.
The subsets are not
completely homogeneous but
that is the best way to split the original
data set based on the variable income.
This decision boundary is represented
in the decision tree by the condition
Income is greater than
t1 at the root node.
This is the condition used to
split the original data set.
Samples with income greater
than the threshold value
of t1 are placed in the right subset and
samples with income less than or
equal to t1 are placed in the left subset,
just as shown in the right diagram.
The right subset is now labeled as red,
meaning that the loan applicant
is likely to be paid alone.
The second step then is to determine how
to split the region outlined in red.
As shown in the left diagram, in input
space, the best way to split this data
is specified by the second decision
boundary with debt equals t2.
This is represented in
the decision tree on the right
with the addition of the node with
condition debt greater than t2.
Samples with the value of debt greater
than t2 are shown in the region
above the decision boundary.
This region contains all blue samples and
so the corresponding node is labeled blue.
Meaning that the loan applicant
is not likely to repay the loan.
The third and final split looks at how
to split the region outlined in red
in the left diagram.
The best split is specified by
the boundary with income equals T3.
This splits the red region
into two pure subsets.
This split is represented in the decision
tree by adding a node with condition,
Income is greater than t3.
The left resulting node is labeled blue,
and
the right resulting node is labeled red,
corresponding to the resulting subsets
within the red border in the left diagram.
We end with the final
decision tree on the right,
which implements the decision boundaries
shown as dash lines in the left diagram.
These decision boundaries
partition the data set as shown.
The label for each region is determined by
the label of the majority of the samples.
These labels are reflected in
the leaf nodes of the decision tree.
Shown on the right.
You may have noticed that the decision
boundaries of a decision tree are parallel
to the axes formed by the variables,
this is referred to as being rectilinear.
The boundaries are rectilinear
because each split considers only
a single variable.
There are variance of the tree induction
algorithm that consider more than one
attribute when splitting a note.
However, each split has to consider all
combinations of combined variables and
so such induction algorithms are much
more computationally expensive.
There are a few important things to
note about the decision tree classifier.
The resulting tree is often simple
to understand and interpret.
This is one of the biggest advantages
of decision trees for classification.
It is often possible to look
at the resulting tree to see
which variables are important to
the classification problem and
understand how
the classification is performed.
For this reason, many people will start
out with the decision tree classifier
to get a feel for
the classification problem.
Even if they end up using more
sophisticated models later on.
The tree induction algorithm
as described in this lesson
is relatively computationally inexpensive.
So training a decision tree for
classification can be relatively fast.
The greedy approach used by tree induction
algorithm determines the best way to split
the portion of the data at a node but
does not guarantee the best solution
overall for the entire data set.
Decision boundaries are rectilinear.
This can limit the expressiveness
of the resulting model which means
that it may not be able to solve
complicated classification problems that
require more complex decision
boundaries to be formed.
In summary, the decision tree classifier
uses a tree like structure to specify
a series of conditions that are tested to
determine the class label for a sample.
The decision tree is constructed by
repeatedly splitting a data partition
into successively more
homogeneous subsets.
The resulting tree can
often be easy to interpret.
We will start with a very simple
classification technique called k-Nearest
Neighbors.
After this video, you will be able
to describe how kNN is used for
classification.
Discuss the assumption behind kNN and
explain what the k stands for in kNN.
kNN stands for k-Nearest Neighbors.
This is one of the simplest techniques
to build a classification model.
The basic idea is to classify
a sample based on its neighbors.
So when you get a new sample as shown by
the green circle in the figure, the class
label for that sample is determined by
looking at the labels of its neighbors.
KNN relies on the notion
of the so-called duck test.
That is if it looks like a duck,
swims like a duck and quacks like a duck,
then it probably is a duck.
In the classification context,
this means that samples with similar input
values likely belong to the same class.
So, samples with similar input values
should be labeled with the same
target label.
This means that classification
of a sample is dependent
on the target labels of
the neighboring points.
In more detail then,
this is how kNN works.
Given a new sample, look for
the samples in the training data
that are closest to the new sample.
These are the neighbors.
Use the labels of this neighboring points
to determine the label for the new sample.
This figure illustrate how kNN works.
The problem here is to determine if
a sample should be classified as
a blue square or red triangle.
The green circle is the new sample.
To determine a class label for this new
sample, look at its closest neighbors.
These neighbors are the samples
within the dashed circle.
Two blue squares and one red triangle.
The class labels of the neighboring
samples determine the label for
the new sample.
The value of k determines the number
of nearest neighbor to consider.
So if k equals 1,
then only the closest neighbor is examined
to determine the class of the new
sample as shown in the left figure.
If k equals 2,
then the 2 nearest neighbors are
considered as seen in the middle figure.
If k equal 3, then the 3 nearest
neighbors are considered as
in the right figure and so on.
If k equal 1 and only 1 neighbor is used,
then the label for
the new sample is simpler
the label of the neighbor.
This is shown in the left figure.
The label of the new sample is then A,
since that is the label of
its one nearest neighbor.
When multiple neighbors are considered,
then a voting scheme is used.
Majority of vote is commonly used,
so the label associated with
the majority of the neighbors is
used as the label of the new sample.
This is what we see in the right figure.
With k equals 3,
3 nearest neighbors are considered.
With two neighbors labeled as A and
one as B,
the majority of vote determines that
the new sample should be labeled as A.
In case of a tie which could be
possible if the value of k is even,
then some tight breaking rule is needed.
For example, the label of
the closer neighbor is used or
the label is chosen randomly
among the neighbors.
This is seen in the middle figure.
With two nearest neighbors and each with
a different class label, the label for
the new sample is randomly
chosen here to be B.
With kNN, some measure of similarity
is needed to determine how
close two samples are together.
This is necessary to determine which
samples are the nearest neighbors.
Distance measures such as
distance are commonly used.
Other distance measures that can be used,
include Manhattan and hemming distance.
To summarize, kNN is a very
simple classification technique.
Note that there is no
separate training phase.
There is no separate part where a model is
constructed and its parameter is adjusted.
This is unlike most other
classification algorithms.
KNN can generate complex
decision boundaries allowing for
complex classification
decisions to be made.
It can be susceptible to noise,however,
because classification decisions
are made using only information about
a few neighboring points
instead of the entire dataset.
KNN can be slow, however, since
the distance between a new sample and
all sample points in the data must
be calculated in order to determine
the k-Nearest Neighbors.