.
Welcome to module 23 of Database Management
Systems. We have been discussing about application
design and development and this is the third
and concluding module in that regard.
In the last module ah we have discussed about
different aspects of application architecture
ah rapid ah development process ah issues
and performance and security and took a glimpse
in terms of, what is required for ah doing
a mobile app.
In this ah module, we will take care ah case
study in terms of a library information system.
We will try to design the schema for that
as you have seen that ah for a ah database
application design there are frontend designs
there are ah middle tier business logic design
and there will be issues in terms of the database
design.
Since ah we are in the DBMS course, I will
not focus on the whole aspects of application
design, but we will focus specifically on
the database ah aspect. So, we will ah start
with a basic requirement specification for
a library information system and then from
the ah starting from that we will try to extract
different ah entities and attributes and ah
their relationships and we will make a relational
schema and ah use different notions of dependency
and ah how to write queries ah we will look
into those ah aspects and refine that and
finalize a ah schema for this problem. So,
let us work through that . So, the the ah
out[line]- the module ah issue is library
information system.
So, let us start with a basic this is a very
small ah description. So, ah, but yet ah it
will give us lot of food for thought ah in
this work and ah while you actually go through
the rest of the video. I would ah suggest
that you take a print out of this page or
keep this page separately because you will
frequently need to refer to it.
So, let me quickly ah go through this ah we
are talking about an institute library that
has ah over 2 lakh books and over 10,000 members
who can use ah regularly issue the books on
loan and return them on the expiry of the
period or before that and the library needs
a library information system to manage the
books the members and as well as the issue
return process. So, we are just looking into
these aspects not the procurement of books
and organization of the books and. So, on
now what is given every book has it is title
author publisher etcetera a number of different
attributes ah ISBN number accession number
in terms of a book I must ah explain to you
at this stage that ah any book that you ah
that is published has an ISBN number which
is an international number given ah.
So, that you can uniquely identify that book.
So, if we are talking about the database management
book we are following here ah then that has
a ISBN number, but that does not mean ah that
number actually is unique for the book would
not for a specific copy of the book. So, if
you buy three copies of the book and ah put
it in the library, then these three copies
need to be identify separately by another
number which is typically called the accession
number.
So, ah naturally the LIS need that every book
has ISBN number which says which book it is
and the accession number which says which
specific copy it is, because they are may
be multiple copies of the same book in the
library ah on the member side. There are 4
categories of members ah broadly: students
and ah teachers, but amongst students if they
could be undergraduate postgraduate or research
students and the faculty members. The student
ah are specified by their name, roll number,
department, gender, mobile number, date of
birth, and the degree that they are doing
and every faculty member also has a name,
employee id, department, gender, mobile number.
And the date of joining the library ah to
manage these ah members library also issues
a unique ah membership number to every member
and every member has a maximum quota for the
number of books that ah she or he can issue
and the maximum duration for which ah those
books can be retain once issued. So, there
are different specification for at different
categories of member can have different quota
and different duration ah the general rule
as specified by this ah libraries the a book
may be issues to a member naturally if it
is not issued to someone else the book has
to be available also a book may not be issued
to a member if another copy of the same book
is already issued to the same member.
So, you cannot issue two copies of the same
book at the same time no issue will be done
to a member if ah he is kind of a default
that is the time of at the time of issue one
or more of the other books already issued
by the member has already exceeded the duration
of the issue.
So, they are overdue for return in that case
no issue will be allowed no issue will; obviously,
be allowed if the quota x x and ah it is ah
also specified that whenever ah we talk about
name ah every name will have two parts the
first name and the last name. So, this is
the this is the given ah specification based
on this we will need to make a good relational
schema to represent ah the tables and manage
the queries.
So, let us take a ah quick look into some
of the sample queries this is just a indicative
sample. Now, naturally we need a whole lot
of ah you know insert delete update kind of
ah queries for ah adding or removing members
categories of ah members shapes the books
and so, on adding ah or removing or changing
the quota of a category of member the duration
for that also ah we will have queries like
to check.
If the library has a given book with a given
title and if it is ah found then the details
of those ah should be listed or we need to
check if library has a book ah ah given it
is ah author. So, if I say the author it should
be possible to locate a book we should ah
able to check, if a copy of a book if I specify
the ISBN number, then whether it is available
ah with the library for issue. So, there may
be as I said multiple copies of the san book.
So, given the ISBN number it will ah return
all the copies the accession number of all
the copies and their issue status; whether
they are issued or they are available ah it
should be available it should be possible
to check ah the quota available free quota
of a member ah and certainly it should have
ah ah features of issuing a book to a member
and they should check for the rules of the
library as stated it should be possible to
return a book and so, on. So, these are the
typical queries against which in the backdrop
of which we will try to design the database
system . So, what we will do?
We will ah initially start ah with a ah ah
with a specification as ah given. So, I hope
you already have kept a copy to refer to and
ah we will try to extract the different entity
sets and the attributes. Naturally, the first
ah entity said that we extract ah we let us
call it books which is about books where in
the beginning I have given the basic statement
that is given in the. So, ah in the ah specification.
So, from that we can see that ah books will
be an entity set and it will have a attributes
like title author name which is a composite
one, because it will have two parts ah into
that the first name and the last name the
publisher year ISBN number and accession number.
So, these are the attributes available for
books. So, this is ah my first ah first entity
set.
The second entity set ah are students ah.
So, this is the statement about the student
and from that statement, we can easily extract
that entity set here is student and ah the
attributes are ah member number, because certainly
in the context of the library system as we
said the; ah student has to be a member. So,
it should be there will be a member number
which is has to be unique the composite name
the student has a role number. So, ah we assuming
that the role number is ah is a unique field.
So, knows to students will have the same roll
number, then there is department gender mobile
number which could be null the; ah date of
birth degree that the student has done is
doing. So, those are the different attributes
for this entity set. So, we have books we
have students similarly.
We will have faculty again the there is this
process will continue by extracting different
parts ah from the specification. So, these
are statement about the faculty and we know
that ah there will be a faculty entity set
with attributes ah like ah member number name
id and so, on.
So, it should be quite obvious library has
talked of that it can ah each it will issue
unique membership number to every member and
there are 4 categories of member. So, ah let
us we are just making attentive you know suggestion
that there could be. So, it looks like members
are in entity which the library has to interact
with in terms of issue.
So, let us create an entity set members which
has the member number and the member type.
So, which can take different types of undergraduate
post graduate these different ah one of these
four specific values let us say.
The rules have talked about having a quota.
So, every member ah will according to it is
ah member category we will have different
quota. So, to represent so, quota becomes
an entity set. So, we would like to ah represent
that ah for different member type which is
a category; how many number of maximum books
can be taken and what could be the maximum
duration? So, let us say we will put the maximum
duration say in terms of months and with these
three attributes we will have an entity set
which is quota.
Ah Here, I am I am talking about another entity
sets staff if you again carefully read the
specification you will find that there is
no mention of this staff in the ah in the
total of the specification, but ah if we logically
think and this is what we often need to do.
When we deal with a ah practical ah specification
like somewhat like, the one that I have given
here is that we would need to look little
beyond the specification.
So, think about it if I have the library with
books students faculty issue process quota
and all that then certainly they will have
to be some staff of the library; that will
actually do all this ah operation. So, they
will be able to ah log in to the database
and actually issue a book return a book check
for validity and so, on. So, let us assume
that ah we have a ah entity set staff which
ah certainly a staff should have name and
id which id should be unique, gender, mobile
number and date of joining. So, ah this is
kind of a speculative ah ah addition to the
design of entity sets and this must be rectified
from the customer; when ah the opportunity
arise, but something like that must be there
for to make the design complete.
So, these are ah; obviously, the the immediately
visible entity sets that we see. So, the other
part that we will now have to ah check on
is a relationship. So, again we pick up the
relevant statement in this regard books are
regularly issued by members on loan and returned
after a period the library needs an LIS to
manage the books members and the issue return
process.
So, certainly there will have to be a relationship
of issue ah between the student or faculty
in the books. So, we loosely define this relationship
ah on one side there has to be the books and
the other side ah would be the involved entity
set would be either student or faculty. So,
actually ah though ah I am just noting it
here as a as a single relationship, but actually
there is a relationship of issue between students
and books and faculty and books.
So, we will have to see how to handle these
kind of situation now certainly the students
or faculty are identified by the unique member
number of the library that has been given
books as we have said are identified by the
accession number. Again please note that we
are not talking about the ISBN number, because
ISBN number could be same for multiple copies
of the book, but when you issue you issue
a specific copy. So, that accession number
which is a unique for a specific copy needs
to be tracked. So, these are the two attributes,
which will ah certainly be involved in the
relationship and ah then ah you would recall
that often ah relationships of their own attributes.
So, here we have one the date of issue needs
to be recorded, because ah we want to check
conditions like; if the ah borrower ah is
has issued the book and how many for how many
months ah he or she is keeping that book.
So, if you have to check that we need to know
when the book was issued. So, this is a ah
attribute which does not exist in any of the
ah entity sets that are involved in this ah
relationship ah neither in students or faculty
nor in books, but this is a attribute of the
relationship which needs to be specified.
And ah of course, ah it is this relationship
is a many to many relation; because every
student or faculty can issue multiple books
and every book may be issued by different,
but we can we can ah in general ah we we can
be specific to say that this is many to one
also if we want to maintain that at a any
given instant a book can be issued only by
one person. So, if you look at it from that
perspective this will not be many to many
this will be treated as many to one.
So, having ah done this ah finding having
found out this entity an attributes and ah
the relationships. Let us now ah start with
a relational schema.
So, what I have done here; in terms of the
relational schema that for each of the entity
set. I have created a ah relational schema
by the same name and have put the attributes
as identified as attributes of that relational
schema. So, this is a very straight forward
once we have identi[fication]- made this identification
process from the ah original specification.
This is a more straight forward process where
you just convert every entity set into a relational
schema and also we have converted the relationship
ah there was a ah there is a relationship
ah ah called book issue here as you can see
the book issue this also we have converted
to a relational schema involving the two attributes
ah of ah member number and the accession number.
So, let us see how ah this will span out ah
later parts so, having done this.
The next task would be to work on the refinement
of the schema. So, now, it is time that the
relational schema is available the first schema
is available. So, now, we have to apply all
different ah notions of ah the relational
design to refine this schema and finalize.
So, for what will do; we will take every relational
schema and we will try to identify the functional
dependencies and use that to identify the
key.
So, if I look at the books ah relational schema,
then we easily know that ah ISBN number will
uniquely identify the title, author first
name; authors last name, publisher and year.
So, here here also you you may you may just
note that since name is stated to be a composite
ah attribute I have designed here to use two
different attributes the first name and the
last name. So, ah with that we have ah this
functional dependency which tells me that
given ISBN number, I know these details ah,
but of course, ah that does not tell me what
is the accession number because there could
be multiple copies, but another functional
dependency must hold.
Because, every copy of the same book must
have the same ISBN number. So, given the accession
number, ISBN number should be determinable.
So, accession number functionally determines
ISBN number. So, if you ah do the sample computation
on this you will easily ah figure out that
a key of this is accession number. So, this
is what we we currently have this this is
what we have done now. So, you can see that
if there are ah say ah 5 copies of a book
having different accession numbers which are
the key they are has been ah ah number would
ah may may all be same.
So, if I have the same ISBN number I can multiple
ah accession numbers and therefore, there
are different records, but if that accession
number of two books are ah I am sorry the
ISBN number of two books are same then all
of that title, author and ah first name ah
last name all this attributes will be repeated
and if there are multiple copies of the book
then each one of them will have a separate
entry because they have a separate accession
number.
But, ah their ah ISBN number and everything
else will be redundant. So, we can ah easily
see that ah the given ah relational schema
actually has ah redundancy across ah copies
of the book and if we want to look at this
ah from ah formal theory we can easily check
that the keys accession number. So, ISBN number
determining ah title author etcetera that
functional dependency ah violates the voice
code ah normal form actually this is the also
not in the third normal form ah right now.
So, ah we would do well to reduce ah this
ah redundancy and it would be good to normalize.
So, here ah I have not gone through the actual
ah steps of normalization, but I am showing
you more intuitively as to, how you can normalize;
because it is a quite obvious that the accession
number is involved only with the ISBN number
and which keeps track of the copies.
So, we propose to have under normalization
we propose to have ah one ah which is ah let
me just highlight and show you. So, ah book
copies where the ISBN number and accession
number will be maintained. So, for every accession
number we will be able to see the ISBN number
which will tell you which book it is and rest
of the book details will be kept in this say
another new relational schema called book
catalogue which will have all of the earlier
attributes expect the accession number.
So, now, if you ah project the; ah this dependency
on book catalogue the dependency will be fully
projected. So, the whole dependency is preserved
if you project this ah dependency on the book
copies it will also be fully preserved. So,
this decomposition is a ah dependency preserving
and ah you can ah easily check that these
two can be ah ah joint by a natural joint
using ISBN number as the common attribute.
So, if we take the intersection of the two
sets of attributes then ISBN number would
be the attribute and ISBN number functionally
determines ah all attributes in the book catalogues.
So, our lossless join condition r 1 intersection
r 2 determines r 1 here. So, this will also
give me a lossless join and if you check on
each one of these ah relational schema then
ah this functional dependency the left hand
side is a key and ah therefore, book catalogue
is in voice code normal form and book copies
is also in voice code normal form.
So, ah you can you could come to the same
ah result by doing the formal process of functional
ah voice code normal form decomposition, but
I have just shown you here as to intuitively
how you get this. So, intuitively becomes
very clear that you have ah details of the
book that you keep separate in a separate
table, ah because that is not change across
the copies and we have a separate table to
maintain the specific information about the
copies . So, that takes care of the books
ah relationship ah moving on ah let us look
at the other.
So, book issue is a ah relational schema which
comes from the relationship ah between ah
the ah now between what now book issue is
to happen between ah student faculty and ah
books. So, it is I mean we cannot have two
of them ah of ah these entity sets occurring
in the same. So, initially let us just put
that well ah the library has a concept of
a member. So, what if the book issue is a
relation ah simply between the members and
the ah and the books of course, we do not
know the relationship between members and
students or members and faculty, but ah we
can at least ah refine the book issue to be
between member and ah the book and therefore,
ah member number and accession number together
becomes the key which determines the date
of issue this is already in ah ah normal form
as you can see.
Quota is a simple relational schema where
member type determines the max books and duration
and that is the key in normal form ah The
members ah I mean we we have identified something
like a member which should ah list all the
members of the library.
So, existence of a member number in that list
will mean that ah someone holding that member
number is actually a member and it is should
also tell me what type of member ah or what
category of member he or she is. So, member
number must determine the member type and
the member type will be constrained in terms
of poss[ible] 4, 1 of the four possible values
are stated here now of course, ah we will
still have to figure out is to where do we
get this member type from and so, on and that
information is not present here. So, further
refinements will be required in this regard.
Ah let us go to the students ah this is the
whole ah schema that we had done. So, roll
number determines all the; ah attributes specifically
roll number also determines the member number
and member number determines the roll number,
because every student has a unique roll number
and; obviously, has a unique member number
also number will determine rest of the all
attrib. So, member number and roll number
both will determine each other and ah roll
utes.
Which mean that this ah design this relational
schema has two keys the roll number and the
member number ok now ah are we happy with
this design that is a question we need to
ask. So, we can figure out that member number
is needed for issue return or queries book
issue has member number, that is; what we
were thinking of; ah now when we want to deal
with this book issue issuing a book to a student
and returning a book from the student and
so, on.
Is it necessary to have all the students details
with that one that make every record very
heavy and if we want to extra connect with
that ah do some join or if you want to ah
do some query unnecessarily we will have to
deal with very large units of data and as
we will see in the ah next couple of modules
that ah if a record becomes larger dealing
with it become naturally becomes more cumbersome.
So, there is some kind of discomfort at this
ah design similarly a member number is not
here ah it is the student relation. So, it
is coming from the student relation, but in
general in terms of issue it may also come
from faculty relations.
So, how is that handled we do not know ah
then ah issue return also needs the member
type which is implicit here in terms of the
ah field ah in terms of the attribute degree
which tells you that student is a undergraduate
postgraduate or research, but it is not explicitly
maintained anywhere. So, these are the issues
in this ah form of the design that we that
we came.
Ah moving on ah look at the faculty we have
a very similar ah situation as of the student
id determines all attributes of the faculty
member number is also determine from id member
number in turn determines id every faculty
has two unique numbers two keys. And we have
similar type of issues as we have seen in
terms of ah student. So, we will need to do
something ah in terms of this.
So, what can us; ah I mean what kind of issues
we will get into. So, let us consider a query
that ah the query is to get the name of a
member ah of the member who has issued a book
say having accession number ah some accession
number 162715.
Now, if we have to write a select ah query
for this we will need to know whether the
select query should be written on the student
or with the faculty. So, if this member is
a student then we need the first query where
we ah do a join between student and book issue
to find out the ah student member number who
is ah issued that book where the accession
number gives me the particular book issue
record from this result will come. Similarly,
if the ah member is a faculty I need a different
query. Now, it is a problem because if I have
two possible queries and based on the member
number I have to decide which query to to
fire we have not done any mechanism like that.
So, this design has problems.
So, let us see what ah we can d? So, we again
ah go back to the specification and see what
the specification says; it said that there
are four categories of members undergraduate,
postgraduate, research scholar, and faculty
members and least to the the that least to
the specialization of this relationship and
we have already done a members concept members
entity we did.
Which has a member number and the member type,
but now we have just seen that it actually
matters as to whether the member is a student
or is a faculty is is a is a more unique deciding
factor in terms of, how we design our query?
So, we introduce a new attribute which was
not ah specified explicitly say; let us call
it member class which can take only two values
either student or faculty and then retain
the member type. So, what it will mean that
the; if the student class is student then
the member type could be u g, p g or r s and
if the member class is faculty.
Then the person is a faculty than the member
type should be only f c and then also ah maintain
the roll number and id in in this members
table ah. So, the roll number ah; obviously,
if it is if the member class is student then
the person is a student and the roll number
will exist, but the id which is an employee
id will be null and at the same time if member
class is a faculty for a record then the roll
number will be null.
Because, a faculty cannot have a roll number,
but ah the id will be present. So, we extend
the members entity set in relational schema
with these attributes and once we do that
then we kind of exploit a hidden relationship
ah which was not very explicitly stated anywhere
that; now we can say that students is a members
faculty is a members, that is; from the perspective
of ah issuing books and using the library
both students and faculty can be consider
to be members it is kind of a you know virtual
entity that we can see here and certainly
there will be a one to one relationship between
the students and members and faculty and members.
So, let us see what is a consequence of that;
ah in terms of the earlier query. So, we look
at go back and look at the query again we
will see that ah problems have got ah significantly
solved, because we now still have to find
that ah member name and this is the basic
condition which ah say.
But, I am sorry ah this is a basic condition
which say the specify the member number ah
who has issued that book, but the actual problem
of finding the name can be solved here, because
I can I write two queries and take a union
of the first query runs on faculty the other
query runs on student. Now, here since I have
a member class which tell me whether the member
is a faculty or the member is a student.
So, one of these queries will actually return
a null result will not written any record
because it will not match this condition,
but the other one we will ah match and will
give me the record ah give me the corresponding
ah ah names first name and last name of the
member and ah certainly to ensure that when
we are looking at the faculty. We need to
check the equality of member id between the
members ah ah relation and the faculty relation
and while dealing with the student we need
to check for the equality of the roll number.
So, in this way by ah using ah intelligently
using the union feature and the you know nested
ah query feature we can easily write a query
and where implicitly. Now, based on the data
the switching of which table I am I am actually
looking the data from will get solved.
So, with this refinement my members ah schema
now turns out to be member number member class
member type ah roll number and id member number
determines ah everything it member type also
determines member class, because if I know
some member type is undergraduate I know member
class is student and. So, on key; obviously,
is one number.
So having done that, we again go back to the
student and ah faculty, because now we do
not need member number in that anymore; because
these will not directly be involved in the
issue return, because all that you need is
ah just the member number which is already
there in the members. So, now, it is a roll
number which determines everything member
number is no longer used.
And member type and member class which we
have assumed is exist in the in the in the
members ah will have to be derived from the
degree ah value at the time when a new record
is created. So, when a new student record
is created an entry will happen in this relation
as well as a corresponding entry we will need
happen in the members ah relation where the
membership number is given and the membership
type will be derived from the degree similar
ah change will happen in terms of the faculty
as well.
So, after refinement ah now we have ah these
ah ah 8 ah relational ah schema from book
catalogue ah to give the details of every
book book copies which ah keeps the information
about, how many; what are the different copies
book issue; is the basic ah issuing information.
We have quota members has the virtual ah kind
of relation that we have created to support
the notion of members of the library and students
and faculty are related to this members either
through roll number or through id in a selective
manner and staff we have not touched.
So, this is the final relational schema.
In this ah module I have ah shown you illustrated
you that how starting from a very simple specification
you can ah ah reason and ah work through in
terms of creating the entity sets attributes
and relationships and then get into the relational
schema ah look at the ah possible functionality
dependency and refine that and also look into
what ah will be the requirements of doing
your query and come to a final ah refined
schema. So, ah various queries that we had
talked of and others ah can be can now be
coded on this, but I leave that as an exercise
to you please try out coding those queries
and you will be able to ah ah learn in terms
of how to do that well and ah I will try to
also supply some supplementary ah information
on this ah offline.