Welcome to module 34 of Database Management
Systems, in this module and the next we will
talk about Concurrency Control a very key
concept of ah database transactions.
So, in the last module we have talked about
continuing on the transactions, we had talked
about ah recoverability of databases, how
to satisfy the acid properties the basic transaction
in SQL and we have introduced a second form
of serializability in terms of the view serializability.
Now, here in this we will talk more on the
different aspects of concurrency control because,
it is good that if 2 schedules are given,
we can we may try to prove if there conflict
serializable, if their view serializable and
then we can use them, but doing that in general
while the database is in execution is an extremely
difficult problem because, who is going to
give the who is who will be able to give the
all possible different types of transactions
that may happen 100s of them that may be going
on in a in the database at any given point
of time.
So, how do you prove that ah or how do you
know whether they are conflicts serial, or
which of them are conflict serializable sets
of view serializable sets and so, on.
So, we introduce a different kind of need
to have a different kind of mechanism and
that is the mechanism of lock that is used.
So, we will discuss about those aspects issues
and the lock based mechanisms.
So, a database must provide a mechanism that
will ensure all possible schedules are both
conflict serializable, that is a basic requirement
and are recoverable and preferable in a cascade
less manner.
So, that is the basic requirements that we
have seen.
Naturally if we have everything as serial
that will happen by default, but that will
have very poor degree of concurrency and very
low throughput.
So, ah concurrency control schemes will trade
off the amount of concurrency that is allowed
and, the amount of over it.
So, what will I have to be ensured is I should
able to for example, if I say that the the
schedules are always serial then the overhead
of ensuring concurrency is the minimum, but
naturally the benefit is also minimum, we
get a very poor throughput.
The more we would like to allow for more and
more concurrence in the system, but at the
same time we will need to have to see what
is the overhead of that what is the cost of
that what how do we have to ensure those and,
naturally as we I have already said testing
for a scheduled to be serializable ah after
it has happened is; obviously, too late and
the question is beforehand how do I get to
know it in a general setting.
So, we need to have a certain protocol through
which that transactions might be written,
a protocol through which the transactions
must operate so, that we can achieve good
concurrency in the system.
So, here our objective is to develop concurrency
control protocols that will ensure serializability
and if possible cascadeless recovery.
So, naturally what you do you try to see whenever
we have conflict, the basic problem of serializability
is conflict that is what are you are you reading
the right data and, what happens if you inadvertently
make changes in in a data that has already
been read by someone else and so on.
So, the why we need to achieve isolation of
the transactions would be to make the accesses
as mutually exclusive as possible.
So, naturally 1 way it could be to do it using
locks.
So, we by the basic concept of the lock is
you say that this data item is in use.
So, others should not use it.
Now what should be the data item, should it
be the whole database, it can be the whole
database we say this database is in use other
transaction cannot use it, which boils down
to saying almost that you have a serial schedule.
So, at any point of time only 1 transaction
can operate on the database naturally your
concurrency will be very poor.
So, that is not what is ah what is acceptable.
So, we need ah locking mechanisms, or a mechanism
to control exclusivity in terms of holding
locks on smaller items possibly at a record
level at a value level and so on.
So, that gives rise to a whole lot of lock
based protocol some of which we are going
to discuss.
So, lock is a mechanism to control concurrent
access and to start with there are a variety
of locks that exist in a database system variety
of types, but to start with we are talking
about 2 locking modes 1 is exclusive mode,
which is designated as X and other is shared
mode and which is designated as S.
Naturally the exclusive in the exclusive mode,
the data item can be read and written both
and such a lock is obtained ah by doing it
lock X instruction and in the shared mode
the data item can only be read.
So, as you can understand why is it exclusive,
when you do read write because if 2 transactions
try to write the same item at the same time,
then you do not know what is who has been
successful and who is the last right and what
is the actual final value they will become
indeterminate.
But if I have a value and multiple transactions
read that at the same time certainly there
is no problem because, all of them necessarily
will read the same data.
So, that is what is called shared and a shared
lock or a shared mode lock can be obtained
in terms of the lock X instruction.
And transaction when it has a lock it can
unlock that by an unlock on the same data
item.
So, there is a concurrency control manager
to whom the lock requests are made, whether
it is a request to grant, or it is a request
to release and a transaction can proceed only
after the request has been granted.
So, let us look into finer details this is
what is known as a lock compatibility matrix.
So, if there are multiple lock modes which
is what is expected, then you try to see which
locks can be held or operated simultaneously.
So, this is shown in terms of our present
assumption that has shared an exclusive lock
naturally, it transact 2 transactions can
hold a shared lock simultaneously on the same
data item, but all other combinations that
is no 2 transactions can hold a shared and
an exclusive, or 2 exclusive locks on the
same data item at the same time.
So, which means that 2 transactions can read
a value at the same time, but 2 transactions
cannot 1 is reading the value and other is
writing, the value is not possible the reverse
is also not possible and 2 transactions writing,
the value is not possible those are called
said to be the incompatible modes of loss.
So, if the transaction is granted a log, if
it is compatible with the lock that is already
held by another transaction, you cannot get
an incompatible lock granted to you.
And any number of transactions certainly can
hold the shared lock and an item, but if any
transaction wants to have an exclusive lock
on the item, then no other transaction may
hold any lock on that item.
So, if I want to write that as a transaction
I must be the only transaction who is who
has to have that exclusive lock I must be
the only transaction who is trying to write,
but when I want to read many transactions
can simultaneously read.
So, if a lock cannot be granted that if I
want a lock either a shared lock, or an exclusive
lock and if it cannot be granted, then the
transaction has to wait till the all incompatible
locks have been released and, only then this
lock can be requested lock in being granted.
And certainly a transaction who is holding
a lock on a data item can unlock it at some
some point, after it is purpose of accessing
the data item is over and, a transaction must
hold a lock on the data item as long as it
is accessing the item that is the basic protocol.
So, you must request first get a grant of
that lock do the operations that you want
and then you unlock, this is a basic process
that has to happen, usually it is said that
as soon as you are done with the operations
of the data item you mean unlock that, you
may want to wait for a little longer for the
ensuring the serializability these details
we will see subsequently.
So, let us come to an example.
So, here are 2 transactions T 1 and T 2.
So, this is a the 2 transactions T 1 T 2 the
transaction T 1 does this operation it transfers
50 dollar from accountB to account A.
So, it debitsB here credits A here.
So, it transfers and transaction T 2 displays
the total sum of money in the accounts A and
B. So, it reads A readsB displays and say
initially the transaction initially let us
say these accounts have values 100 and 200.
So, what this transaction will do it needs
to do the transfer.
So, it needs to readB debit and write and
what it has to do since it has to read it
must have A shared lock.
Since it has to write it must have a exclusive
lock and, if it has got an exclusive lock
it will also be able to read that data.
So, what it does it performs an exclusive
lock.
So, it requests for an exclusive lock and
only on getting that it can do this and, when
this is over the purpose is over it unlocks
B. Similarly to update a it takes an exclusive
lock on a updates and, then releases a lock.
Transaction T 2 what it does it has to read
and display.
So, it does not need an exclusive lock it
takes the shared lock reads and unlocks, it
again takes a shared lock onB reads and unlocks
and finally, displays the 2 data.
Now, if these transactions are executed serially
that is T 1 after T 2 or T 2 after T 1, then
the transaction T 2 will always display the
value 300 because, 300s is the initial value
that we will be able to see if T 2 runs first
and T 1 300 is all so, the final value because
only 50 dollar has been transferred fromB
to A. So, the sum remains same.
So, you will be able to see that if T 2 runs
after T 1.
So, the consistency of the database is maintained.
Now, let us see let us consider a schedule
written here as schedule 1 and the the transactions
are executing concurrently.
So, then this is a possible schedule and let
us see what will happen.
So, what it does this is where the lock exclusive
lock on B is held and B is updated, then A
is read then B is read display is done and
then this update on a has happened.
And this is where we are showing that how
the grants are happening.
So, as the lock is requested then the the
request goes to the system that a exclusive
lock on B is requested by transaction T 1.
So, that subsequently gets granted and only
when the grant has happened the corresponding
axis can start, but it can be any indeterminate
amount of time between the request of the
lock which is here and, the actual grant of
the lock, but this operation can happen only
after the grant has happened.
So, in every case that is what has to be observed
right.
Now what happens in this schedule what will
be the consequence.
So, in this schedule if we look at the transaction
T 2 will display only 250 dollar, it will
not display 300 dollar why because, if you
if you look at this carefully, if you look
at this carefully this is where B has got
updated.
So, B has become 50 dollar less.
And then the whole of a and B have been read
and displayed.
So, naturally the total sum is 50 dollar less.
So, ah even though we have used a lock it
has not been able to achieve the required
even though, we have used the lock we have
not been able to achieve the required serializability.
And it is possible to create a schedule where
inconsistent data is getting generated T 2
is actually reading an inconsistent data.
So, you have seen inconsistent state in terms
of here.
Why did it happen?
This happened because if we look carefully
this has happened because, T 1 has unlocked
to prematurely T 1 has unlocked as soon as
the update to be was over.
So, it was possible for
T 2 to read that value of B which is not what
is desirable and we will see that we might
want to delay the unlocking till the end,
let us see what happens if we do that.
So, we are here now it is the same transaction
in in terms of the notion, but T 1 has been
made to T 3 here, where you have seen that
unlocking is been pushed to the end T 2 has
been made into T 4, where the unlocking is
pushed to the end.
And now naturally if you look into this, if
you wanted to do a schedule 1 you cannot do
this kind of a schedule 1 that schedule will
not be permissible because, you will not be
able to get the locks, T 4 will not be able
to get the locks that T 2 could get in the
sequence of reads and writes in schedule 1
is no longer possible.
So, whatever way we actually do the schedule
T 4 will always correctly show, that the sum
is three hundred dollar.
So, here we are again showing T 3 T 4 this
is a schedule given schedule 2, which is just
given partially.
And since T 3 is holding an exclusive lock
on B and T 4 is requesting a shared lock.
So, if I hold it this is T 3 is holding an
exclusive lock and T 4 is requesting for a
shared lock.
So, T 4 has to wait for T 3 to unlock B before
it can actually do that operation.
Similarly you will find if you look further
T 4 has already got a shared lock to read
A. And T 3 needs a shared lock on I am sorry
T 3 needs an exclusive lock on A to be able
to proceed.
So, this 1 is here.
So, T 4 cannot go beyond this point because
T 3 has the lock on B and, 1 is this T 3 cannot
go beyond this point because T 4 has that
shared lock.
So, what we situation are we getting into.
So, we are getting into a situation where,
neither of T 3 or T 4 can actually proceed
the normal execution, T 3 is waiting for exclusive
lock on A and which T 4 has and T 4 is waiting
for the shared lock on B, which T 3 already
holds as an exclusive manner.
And this in so, this this is kind this is
what is called deadlock, if you have a studied
operating system, then you have must be knowing
deadlock very well, and there the deadlock
happens 2 different other issues of sharing
resources here it is because of the lock.
So, moment you use locks there is a possible
danger of having deadlock.
And once you have a deadlock there is no other
way than to unroll 1 or more of the transaction,
then start all over again, it has to roll
back 1 of the 2 transactions to be able to
proceed.
AHnd once the transactions are rolled back
the data items that were locked by the transactions
will also be unlocked.
So, please understand this in view of the
earlier discussion we had in terms of transact
TCL commands.
So, when you actually which we are roll back
we had at that point could only say that your
value of the data item in the database will
be rolled back, but certainly as now you can
understand that, if you roll back also the
locks that you have required we also get unlocked
so, that other transactions can get those
locks and proceed.
So, then the data items become available for
other transactions and, that can continue
the execution.
So, if we do not so, so we are saying that
we wanted to use locks to get better control
on the serializability and so on.
And it was partly possible, but then we are
getting into different other kinds of different
problems.
So, if you do not use locking or, if we unlock
data items very early then after reading,
or writing them then we may get inconsistent
state this is what you have seen, on the other
hand, if we do not unlock a data item before
requesting a lock on another data item that
is if we hold it on for a very long time,
then deadlock may occur.
So, if we do it too soon we do not use the
lock that we have a problem of inconsistent
state, if we do it hold it for too long then
there could be problem of deadlock.
Now, deadlocks are necessarily evil of locking,
if you do locking you will always face a deadlock,
ah if we want to avoid inconsistent states.
Now between these two; obviously, we would
prefer deadlock the reason, we will prefer
deadlock to inconsistent state is the fact
that, if we have deadlock we still have the
option of rolling back and we can take different
strategies to decide what to rollback and
how much to rollback and so on whereas, inconsistent
states may lead to real world problems ah
that cannot be handled by the database system.
In fact, in some in many cases I may get into
some inconsistent state which is very difficult
to even recognize that it is an inconsistent
state.
So, we will continue and prefer deadlocks
over inconsistent states and, we will define
we will try to define different locking protocols
a set of rules that the transactions should
follow, while the request and release locks
to make our life relatively easier.
So, locking protocols necessarily will restrict
the set of possible schedules because, we
will put in some discipline in terms of how
we look and how we release them, and the set
of all such schedules is a proper subset of
possible serializable schedules that is easy
to understand.
And ah we will present locking protocols that
allow only conflict serializable schedule
which ensures isolation.
So, let us look at the most widely used protocol
this is called the 2 phase locking protocol
which guarantees conflict serializability,
it does a simple thing it has 2 phases a growing
phase, where it transaction may obtain locks
and may not release any lock.
And a shrinking phase which the transaction
may release locks and may not obtain any law.
So, you are just separating out the you know
the grant or the access of locks holding of
locks and the releasing of locks into 2 different
phases you do not mix them up.
And that is the 2 phrases phases of the locking
protocol.
And this ensures so, we are we will not do
the proof, but you can look it up in the book
or, but you can see through examples that
it can be shown that transactions can be serialized
in the order of the points where they do the
locking.
So, these are known as lock points and, that
is where the transaction actually acquired
it is final block.
So, there can be conflict serializable schedules
that cannot be obtained, if 2 phase locking
is used.
So, what this is saying if you use 2 phase
locking you are guaranteed to have conflict
serializable schedule, but there are conflicts
serializable schedules for which you may not
be able to honor the 2 phase locking protocol.
So, 2 phase locking protocol is kind of a
sufficiency condition.
So, you could also in refine the 2 phase locking
with what is known as lock conversion that
is you can acquire in the in the growing phase,
or the first phase you can acquire a exclusive
lock, a shared lock, or you can convert a
shared lock that you already have into an
exclusive lock which is called the lock upgrade
process.
Similarly, in the shrinking phase you can
release a shared lock release an exclusive
lock, or you are holding an exclusive lock
you can make it a shared lock.
So, you can download.
So, you can understand that upgrade and downgrade
are strategies to ah only use that much of
restriction that you need, to impose on others
and to allow others to access the data to
the based possible way.
This protocol again issuers serializability
and the it certainly depends on the programmer
as to how the programmer inserts the various
locking instructions.
ah
Now, you will have to when you want to do
read or write, you may acquire locks automatically
the database systems will allow that.
So, this is a very simple algorithm.
So, if you want to read a data, I if you have
a lock already on that either shared, or exclusive
you can simply read it, if you do not have
that then if you may have to wait until no
other transaction has an exclusive lock on
that because, you know that read or shared
lock is not compatible with the exclusive
lock.
So, you may have to wait till all are the
in no other transaction the transaction that
was having exclusive lock possibly has released
it and, then take a grant of the shared lock
on this item and, then read it it is a very
simple algorithm to automatically acquire
locks.
Write is little bit more complex because to
be able to write either, you already have
an exclusive lock on D, then you write or
you may have to wait till no other transaction
has any log because, exclusive lock is not
compatible with shared lock or with other
exclusive lock.
So, as long as some transaction has a lock
on D you cannot proceed, but once you come
to a state, that you already if no other transaction
has a lock, then you see whether you yourself
have a shared lock on D, if you have a shared
lock then you upgrade it to an exclusive lock,
if you do not have a shared lock, then you
they take a grant of the exclusive lock and
then you can go and write.
So, it is if you follow the 2 phases these
algorithms become very simple.
And when you commit or the abort the transaction,
then naturally all locks are get will get
released.
So, the 2 phase protocol we have already seen
that does not ensure freedom from deadlock,
you can may follow 2 phase locking protocol
here is an example, but you may still have
schedules which will have deadlocks.
So, this is 1 example you can just convince
yourself.
There is another problem that can happen,
in addition to deadlock this is a code there
is a possibility of what is known as starvation;
starvation, occurs usually it occurs when
the control concurrency control manager is
not a efficient 1.
So, what did we see in terms of automatic
locks in read and write operation is you may
have to wait because, someone else is holding
a lock on an item.
Now holding an exclusive lock on the item,
now it is possible that like the current transaction
there may be couple of other transactions
who are also waiting for a lock on that item
and, when the opportunity comes that there
is no log being held by any transaction, one
of the waiting transactions must be given
the lock you cannot if it is an exclusive
lock you cannot give it to more than 1 transaction,
but say 3 transactions were waiting for the
exclusive lock and one of them get, that and
that transaction can proceed the other transactions
have to rollback because, they are not getting
the lock.
So, now you again start you again come to
the point where you wanted the exclusive lock
on that item and at that time somebody is
holding it and there are other transactions
who are also requesting for exclusive lock.
And when you come back and when finally, the
exclusive lock is released by all other transactions,
then again it is possible that while you are
waiting some other transaction that was waiting
who gets that exclusive lock and you do not
get that so, you roll back and this could
repeatedly could keep on happening.
So, if you have a weak strategy in terms of
concurrency control, you have you will see
that you have had infinite possibilities infinite
occurrences, where you could have got that
exclusive lock, but you are not being able
to get that and therefore, you starve on the
data and this is known as a tower starvation
problem which will also have to be checked
while we do the concurrency control policies.
There is a the potential for deadlock exists
in most locking protocols, as we have seen
and when a deadlock occurs there is a possibility
of cascading roll back because, when it deadlock
happens then naturally you will have to roll
back.
So, you may have to do a cascading roll back
as this example is showing.
And it is possible for a 2 phase locking protocol
have we have in the example is shown here,
where all the transactions are following cascading
roll back has to as following 2 phase locking
protocol, but if T 5 fails after the the read
step of T 7 after the read step of T 7, if
T 5 fails then it leads to a cascading rollback
T 7 T 5 has to be rolled back.
So, T 6 will have to be rolled back, so T
7 will have to be rolled back and so on.
ah
Interestingly there are several other protocols
and particularly 2 more 2 phase locking protocol
1 is called strict 2 phase locking, which
avoids cascading roll back, where a transaction
must hold all exclusive locks till it finally,
commits and aborts naturally you can figure
out that you are making the time for the transaction
to hold lock longer.
So, naturally the level of concurrency will
go down that is all possible serializable
schedules will be smaller, but this guarantees
that you will not have a cascading roll back.
And there is an even stricter rigorous 2 phase
locking where all locks are held till commit
or abort.
In the strict 1 only exclusive locks are held
till commit or abort there is a till the end
of that transaction, but in rigorous 2 phase
locking all locks are held till the committed
abort, in this protocol transaction can be
serialized, in the order in which they do
the commit and in that way this is a serializable
protocol, which also avoids the cascading
roll back up.
Now finally, before you close this module
a quick word in terms of how do you implement
locking.
It is the lock there is a lock manager, which
implements the locking the lock manager itself
runs on a different process to which every
transactions end lock and unlock requests.
And the lock manager maintains a data structure
to maintain what are the transactions, who
are holding different locks on different items
and based on that the grant messages are queued
on that data structure and, these messages
actually release the locks and, otherwise
the transaction has to wait the lock manager
maintains this as a lock table.
And this is typically a in memory hash table
because, it needs to naturally be very fast
and is in the name of the data item being
locked.
So, let us just show you and so, these are
the different this is an instance of a lock
table and, the nodes are different data items.
So, I 7, I 9, 12, I 4, I 44, I 23 are different
data items this is a hash table.
So, you can see that on I 7 and I 23 there
is a collision and there is collate state
chain happening on that.
And then for every item you have you maintain
a list of locks that are granted to different
transactions and the list of requests that
are waiting, the dark blue here shows the
grant and the light blue shows a waiting status
here.
So, it takes it naturally says what type of
lock o'clock is granted and requested and
based on this therefore, when you get a request
to put it in the you come and put it you hash
it to that data item, put that request on
that queue and based on the current status
you can decide, whether it can be granted
or it has to wait.
So, it is added new requests are added at
the end of that queue, it is first in first
out and whenever a release happens, then naturally
a granted node is removed and a waiting node
might get a chance to block that item, if
the transaction reports all waiting, or granted
requests of the transactions certainly will
get deleted ok.
So, this is a simple way to manage the locks.
So, in this module on concurrency control
we have understood the basic locking mechanism
and protocols, we have specifically looked
at the lock compatibility matrix and the strategies
of granting and releasing locks and, we have
seen the consequent danger of having deadlock
and in some cases starvation, which we have
agreed to live with.
So, if deadlock happens we will have to roll
back 1 or more transactions and then restart
again and, but we cannot take the risk of
not having serializable transactions because,
that might lead to inconsistent state of the
database which is not acceptable.