.
Welcome to module 15 of Database Management
Systems. We have been discussing about entity
relationship model and this is the third and
the closing module on this topic .
So, in the last module we have discussed about
E-R diagram and we have also seen how E-R
model can be converted to a relational schema.
In this ah module we will try to go through
a few extended features of E-R model, try
to show some of the more complicated situations
how they can be modeled in the E-R model and
along with that we will discuss a variety
of design issues that will follow .
So, these are the outline . So, we start with
extended entity relationship features . The
first that we note is ah so, far in the entity
relationship model we have talked about relationships
between two entity sets. So, we have talked
about the student attending courses or instructors
advising students and so, on. So, such relationships
are naturally called binary, but it is possible
that more than two entity sets, let us say
three entity sets could be involved in the
same relation and we show an example here
where we have three entity sets instructor,
student and project.
So, the project entity set is a list of projects
ah being done by the students or to be done
by the students. So, the relationship project
guide is a relationship between the guide
who is an instructor, the student who will
do the project and the project that has to
be performed. So, all three together define
this relationship; so, in such cases it is
ah possible in E-R model that we can represent
it conveniently as a non binary relationship.
Now this is an E-R diagram this is called
a ternary relationship R.
Now we have talked about ah cardinality constraints
on binary relationship one to one, many to
one one to many and many to many. And we specified
that ah if we have a binary relationship say
this is one entity set and this is another
entity set and we have a relationship. So,
if we just connect them it means a many to
many relation, but if we have an arrow on
one side entity set then it means on the arrow
side its one.
So, this is ah from entity set E 1 to E 2
this is one to many; we could have arrow at
both ends and; that means, one to one . Now
the question is how will that work out what
will be the meaning of arrow in terms of a
ternary relationship.
Now, in the case of ternary relationship or
this would generalize to relationships of
higher degree whether where more than three
entity sets may be involved. We put a restriction
that we will allow at most one arrow out of
the ternary relationship. So, we could ah
have only if we if we look at if we look at
say this relationship then we could have an
arrow only at this end .
But multiple arrows are not allowed and the
reason is certainly to keep the semantics
of the cardinality meaningful. For example,
if we have a ternary relationship between
A B and C let us say this is a A this is B
and this is C and we have a ternary relationship
between them. And let us say if we have a
more than one arrow; there for example, ah
suppose ah then we have say an arrow to B
and an arrow to C the question is how should
we interpret that?
Should we interpret that ah an entity of entity
set A is associated with unique entity from
B and C together or should we associate, should
we interpret that the entities formed by the
pair a B and the entity formed by the pair
A C are uniquely related. So, there is multiplicity
of interpretation; if we allow more than one
arrow in case of eternity or higher degree
relationship. So, what will follow for simplicity
in this course and that is what is followed
often in practice; is in case of a ternary
or higher order relationship only one arrow
will be allowed in that in it in that relationship
.
Now, let us talk about specialization ah those
of you who have some background of object
oriented systems would be familiar with the
notion of specialization and generalization
in ah object oriented system. So, we say that
ah if we have a certain concept say we have
a concept called person and ah then we say
that a student is a person; what we mean is
a student is a specialization of person. And
person is a generalization of student and
in that process student inherits all the attributes
of person, but in addition the student may
have some specialized attributes.
So, what it means that if you look ah from
from the perspective of such specialization;
say if I draw like this; this is an entity
set A and this entity set B and ah to mark
the specialization we show an arrowhead with
a blank triangle at that end. So, if we by
this what we mean is B is a A. So, B inherits
all the properties of A, but can have some
more properties. So, if you look at all the
entities that A may have you will find that
a subgroup of the entities in the entity set
A have some additional common properties.
So, if A is set of persons and B is a set
of students then A may have entities who which
represent people who are not students; who
are employees, who could be retired and so,
on, but there will be a number of entities.
So, who have the commonality of being student
they are enrolled in certain course of certain
university and so on.
So, in terms of the E-R diagram E-R model
what we do is we try to look at the entity
A and move top down . So, that whenever we
find a group of entities which have certain
commonality; we move them into a lower separate,
specialized entity set and relate these two
entity sets to the specialization relation
.
So, these sub groups form lower level entity
sets and ah as I said that it is designated
in a certain way. And as in the object oriented
system the lower level entity set inherits
all the attributes and relationships of participation
of the higher level entity set . So, here
is an example.
Can say the person at the so, called root
of this hierarchy of specialization; it has
a set of properties ID, name, street, city
and employee is another relationship; another
entity set which is a specialization of person
relation person entity set.
So, employee inherits all attributes ID name
street and city, but in addition the commonality
of the entities in the employee entity set
is a fact that all of them have a salary attribute.
A similar entity set student is a specialization
of person where the again all attributes are
inherited, but there is a common attribute
called total credits which is common for all
the students, but is not available or common
for the persons in general.
And as you can see that it could be hierarchical
it could go further down employee could be
specialized into instructor and secretary.
Again by the rule of ah specialization instructor
will inherit all attributes of employee which
means that it will inherit attributes of person;
which imply has inherited plus the employee
specific attributes salary. So, it will inherit
all five of those attributes and then it adds
another attribute which is specific for the
instructor which says a rank which is another
specific attribute that you have.
Now, when we specialize a certain entity set
into two or more entity sets like we specialized
person in employee and student; then there
could be different situations that could exist
for example, certain entity may be a member
of both employee as well as ah student . If
that happens then we say that their overlapping
entity sets or they could be disjoint where
no member of instructor would be a member
of the secretary and vice versa.
So, we say that this disjointness tell us
that no instructor can be a secretary and
no secretary can be an instructor. Whereas,
overlapping ah specialized sets denote that
well an employee may or may not be a student,
but it is possible that some employee is also
a student and vice versa and that is how we
will represent this . And we will see that
ah when we specialized the ah specialized
entity could be total or they could be partial.
We will talk about that totality and partiality
little later; let us look at how do we represent
this information in the relational schema
because as we have seen that whenever we have
a E-R diagram; it is important to find out
what is the relational schema that will be
corresponding to that E-R diagram or E-R model.
So, here we could do this in two ways one
that we are showing here is form a schema
for the higher level entity. So, form a schema
for the person as you can see here that person
is described in terms of four attributes and
this form a schema for each of the lower level
entity set where you include the primary key
of the higher level entity set.
So, when you are forming the schema of person
of student which is a specialization of person
you include the ID which is the key of the
higher level entity set person. And along
with that you include the so, called local
attributes or attributes which are specific
to this low level entity set in this case
total credit similar thing happens with employee.
Now this representation is in a way optimized
because ah you are representing the information
only once when it is needed, but the drawback
is if you have to find out information about
say employee; then you will not only have
to access the employee entity set or the corresponding
relation in the relational schema, but you
will also have to access the parent or higher
level entity set to get the attribute values
which are inherited. And if you have a multi
level hierarchy as we have shown this could
involve accessing multiple relations to find
information about a single entity in an entity
set.
So, this is an in terms of data representation
this is an optimized representation, but it
has the overhead of having to access multiple
ah entity sets to get information about certain
entities .
An alternate scheme would be that ah based
on the hierarchy of specialization, you assume
all attributes as they are inherited and then
represent every entity set in full. So, when
you the representation of person does not
change, but when you represent student now
earlier you are just having ID and total credit;
now in you include all entities that are inherited.
Similarly, you do the same thing; so, you
have the all entities of the parent to all
attributes of the parent entity set as well
as the local attribute of that specific entity
set. Now this naturally makes it easy to extract
information from a for a single entity set,
but at the same time, you are storing the
same ah data redundantly for people who are
having overlapped representation. So, if we
have as we know student and employee overlapped.
So, the same entity will happen in student
as well as in employee; so, it will the information
of the common attributes name street city
etcetera they will occur in both these tables
in the design.
So, these are two methods and now we have
just given you the relative advantages and
its advantages of the same and based on a
particular situation you will have to choose
what is a good method to represent .
You can look at now you know from the object
based system that if you have a specialization
hierarchy you can think of it as a generalization
hierarchy also.
The generalization hierarchy goes in a bottom
up manner. So, instead of actually ah starting
with an entity set and finding out subsets
of entities which have greater commonality
between them and putting them as specialized,
you could actually group them in terms of
finding out what they share and create a higher
level entities . For example, the way I am
saying is let us say that I have one entity
set which say UG student and have another
entity set in the same university which say
PG student.
So, there are both of them are students naturally
they are disjoint a person cannot be UG as
well as PG student at the same time. And once
you represent that you find that well there
are a lot of information which are common
between these two entity sets like the student
roll number, name and so on so, forth. So,
you could choose that well you instead of
having them as two separate entity sets, you
could extract out the common attributes and
put them at a higher level entity. So, all
that you are doing is instead of going top
down you are going bottom up in the whole
approach.
So, if you do that then there you can easily
see that specialization and generalization
is are inverse of each other and they are
used interchangeably in terms of the relational
entity relationship design.
The other constraint that you can identify,
you should identify is the constraint of completeness
which say that if I have a ah entity set say
a person. And ah then we have specializations
of employee and student; the question is for
a higher level entity set is it necessarily
that every entity will be represented in one
of the or more than one of the lower level
entity sets.
If that is guaranteed that an entity must
belong to one of the lower level entity set
we say that it is a complete specialization.
But if it is that a high level entity is may
or may not be featuring in a entity set, which
is at a lower level then we will say it is
a partially specialized hierarchy. So, the
both of these are are possible depending on
different situation that we have. So, by default
we assume partial specialization and ah. So,
if we want to say a certain specialization
is total we will have to write the keyword
total by the side of the arrow head that is
representing the specialization hierarchy.
You can say that the example I talked of in
uniting unite undergraduate and graduate or
postgraduate students into the entity set
of students, gives you a hierarchy which is
total because every entity in the entity set
student must be either a UG student or a PG
student; it is not possible that I have a
student who is neither a UG student nor a
PG student. So, every high entity at the higher
level entity set ah student must feature in
one of these two specializations.
So, therefore they are necessarily total in
the relationship . So, this is the completeness
constraint that you can think of .
Moving on let us talk about another feature
which is known as aggregation; the situation
is like this we have already talked about
this part of the diagram which is a ternary
relationship which relates project instructor
and student.
Now, let us say once the project progresses
you would need to add evaluation to that.
So, yeah there is another entity set which
represents evaluation and how we are grading
or putting marks and so, on. So, naturally
the evaluation of ah a student will be dependent
on the project, the student and the supervisor
and that will relate to the evaluation. So,
evaluation eval for the relationship is necessarily
a relationship between four entities or four
entity sets so, to say .
Now, the question is how do we represent this
information? The relationship sets eval for
project guide the two that we saw if we just
want to recall once more. The project guide
involves three of the relation entity sets
and the eval for relates to four of the entity
sets. Now every eval for relationship corresponds
to a project guide relationship; that is if
I have an entity in eval for relationship,
I will have a corresponding entity in the
project guide relationship which specifies
the student project and the instructor.
So, but it is other way it is possible that
some project guide relationship may not correspond
to any eval relationship; that is it is possible
that ah there is a allotted project by a student
with a particular instructor which has yet
not been evaluated; the evaluation process
is not complete or the time has not come.
So, if we have to represent the information
only for the eval for relationship; we will
get partial information because it is possible
that some entities in eval for does not have
the eval for information do not feature there,
but need to be preserved because I need to
remember the project guide, instructor, the
student and the project. So, we need to keep
both duplicating the information.
So, we can use aggregation to eliminate this
duplication of information or redundancy of
information. So, what we do is we treat the
first first relationship; the project get
relationship as if it is an abstract entity
and then you allow relationship between two
relationships; this is something we did not
do before relationship so, far has always
been between entity sets.
So, what you can see that project guide relationship
itself as if it is an virtual entity; it is
an abstract entity and then you allow the
relationship between the project guide and
the eval for relationship which relates to
the evaluation entity set this really this
shows I mean I will just show you in the diagram.
So, this is how it will now work out to be.
So, this is the abstract project guide entity
set which is an abstract entity set because
it is actually relationship. And that relates
to eval for which on the other site has the
evaluation. So, what will happen is a student
is guided by a particular instructor in a
particular project will feature in this abstract
entity set; which relates the three entity
sets project student and instructor. And ah
if it has an evaluation then the; this through
this relationship it will be represented and
the evaluation value will exist.
So, we know that if a project is evaluated
then it certainly have a corresponding entity
in the abstract entity set project guide,
but the reverse may not be true I may have
an entity in the project guide entity set
which does not have an evaluation . So, by
using this aggregation model; I can represent
the information of this situation model this
situation more accurately than I could do
otherwise .
So, this can be represented again how to represent
this in terms of the schema? So, what we do
we represent the aggregation we create a schema
containing the primary key of the aggregated
ah relationship. The primary key of the associated
entity set and all the other descriptive attributes
and put them together .
So, in our example the schema would be eval
four and that schema will have these are entities
these are attributes of the aggregated or
abstract entity set which is coming from the
student ah project and the instructor entities
and this is for the evaluation ID. So, we
put this together; so, now, you can see that
all of these are related representing who
is the guide of which student in what project
and if this exists then this gives you the
evaluation.
So, naturally once this has been represented;
the project guide schema by itself becomes
redundant and therefore, it can be removed.
So, this is a process through which we come
to the the decision of actually having this
schema to represent all the required information.
Naturally if the evaluation is not done then
the evaluation ID ah for in eval four will
not exist and that will be a null showing
that it is not present right now ok.
Now, given these basic features as well as
the extended features let me talk about a
few design issues which will ah be required
to see what kind of information that that
the different challenges that we have seen
so, far. For example, we have seen the case
of multivalued attributes .
So, and ah the way we can represent that is
using that multivalued attribute as a separate
entity set like the phone number which also
has the advantage of having its own added
information. For example, once we do this
then not only I can have against the same
instructor ID; I can have multiple phone numbers,
but I can have location for each one of these
phone numbers. And I make use of this relation
relationship that I create which allow me
to represent this multi valued attribute .
So, this is a common technique that will be
used frequently in such cases you can have
entities versus relationship for example,
if we have inform we need to keep information
about registration how students register to
different sections; then we could represent
registration as an entity set and have different
relationships of section registration which
specify how registration is related to section
and student reg; which specify how do the
station is related to students to represent
that kind of information.
We can have placement of relationship attributes
also attribute date we have talked about as
an attribute of adviser to designate as when
that particular instructor became adviser
of a student is a common situation that we
have already seen.
There is also question of the choice being
made between the binary and non binary relationship
ternary or higher degree. Now as it turns
out that it is possible that you could represent
ternary relationships directly or you can
decompose that. For example, a ternary relationship
can be decomposed in terms of two binary relationship;
for example, let us say if we talk about persons
then person every person has parents; so,
he or she has a father and a mother.
Now, if we represent this as a ternary relationship
then the one difficulty that we have that
a person must have both the father and mother
to be represented there. For example, if we
can come to a situation where only the mother
is known, the father is not known I will not
be able to represent that because it will
always have to come as a triplet of three
persons thel the person under consideration
her father and her mother, but if I represent
the person and the father in one relationship;
the person and the mother in another relationship,
then I can take care of the situation where
when one of the parents are known; I can still
represent this.
So, there are certain tradeoffs which can
be done between the choice of binary and non
binary relationships, but; obviously, there
are certain relationships which are inherently
non binary for example, the project guide
example we have seen. The project guide information
cannot be decomposed without certain loss
of information to be represented by say the
instructor and the project and another relationship
between the student and the project it really
that does not represent the same information
.
So, in general you can convert a non binary
relationship by in the binary form by doing
this. So, this is a ternary relationship being
shown and for doing that these are the three
entity sets involving the ternary relationship
and to make decomposite into a ternary relationship;
what we do is into binary relationships we
inject a new entity artificial entity set
E and then we define three different relations
between them.
So, which individually relates to the entity
sets A B and c. So, this is a standard decomposition
and you can easily understand that A B and
C in our earlier example could all be persons
and R A could mean that father of R B could
mean mother of and so, on. So, I can do do
it in decomposite in this manner and represent
that .
Now while we do this decomposition we will
also have to remember in that; we need to
translate all constraints that are present
for the ternary relationship. And often times
it may become difficult to translate all constraints,
it may not be possible and there may be instances
in the translated schema that cannot correspond
to an instance of the original relationship.
So, we will have to avoid we can we will have
to take care of this situation by identifying
attributes. And making use of the weak entity
sets which we have already seen in our earlier
discussions .
So, if we summarize the discussions on the
E-R design decisions; we see that the first
decision that we need to take in case of design
is the use of an attribute or entity set to
represent the object.
So, that is the first modeling that what is
the concept and what is what are the attributes
or what is the representing entity set for
the object that we are trying to deal with
instructor, student project and so, on . And
ah we will also have to see whether in the
real world this actually is an entity set
or it is a relationship set that it is ah
not and concept by itself, but is a concept
which relates two or more entity sets and
thereby becomes a set of representation.
The use of ternary relationship versus a pair
of binary relationship; this trade off will
have to be weighed as a design consideration;
we have to look into the use of strong or
weak entity set. So, we will have to identify
the weak entity sets and see if they should
be represented ah through the identifying
relation ah as against a strong entity set.
We have to identify the specialization generalization
situation where so, that we can get more specific
information and create appropriate modularity
in the design.
We have to look at aggregation which where
we can aggregate entity sets bound by a ah
relationship and create an abstract single
unit which can play a role of an independent
entity set in the whole design .
So, this is ah the basic ah. So, these are
the basic design ah decisions that you need
to make.
And we will certainly come up with lot more
of design decisions as we go along. And ah
before I close in the presentation I have
summarized the different symbols that are
used in the E-R notation. So, I will not these
have already been discussed in depth. So,
I will not go through them one by one, but
I have put them as a list in the couple of
slides.
This is a next slide in that which ah will
be a quick reference for you while you are
initially doing the E-R diagram so, that you
know exactly which symbol to pick up for what
situation .
And ah at the end also there are few slides
which show you that the E-R notation itself
is not a unique one.
There are multiple ways to represent similar
things for example, this is one which is showing
you different composite attributes ah, the
generalization, relationship is shown differently.
So, there are; these are all different styles
of showing ah the constraints that that apply
to a particular ah relationship . And we will
I mean we have included this not because we
will use these alternate notations, but I
have put them because it is possible that
you come across some E-R diagram where these
notations are used and if you come across
and you are not able to identify then please
refer to this slides.
And you will be able to recognize what is
ah what is corresponding symbol that you already
know.
So, in this module we have discussed the extended
features of E-R model and we have deliberated
on certain design issues. And ah we will close
our discussion on the entity relationship
model here and move on to discuss the actual
relational design.