Welcome to module 26 of Database Management
Systems.
In this module and the next 4; that is for
the whole of this week we will talk about
indexing and hashing.
So, this is a quick recap of ah what we did
in the last week primarily talking about application
development and then specifically; we focused
on storage and file structure that is how
a database file can be stored how it can be
organized and in a manner so that, we have
efficient ah representation for that now.
We will move on ah from there to and focus
on the basic feature of a database system,
which is the ability to find information in
a very fast manner the ability to update in
a very fast manner.
And we will see the reasons for which we do
something on the database tables called indexing
and we will talk about ordered index in this
module and about the index sequential access
mechanism.
So, introduction of the basic indexing concepts
and the order indices and we start with the
basic concepts.
So, consider a very simple example, let us
consider an example where there is a relation
faculty which has name and phone number and
additionally.
So, just focus on the middle part the pinkish
part of the table which is table faculty besides
the two attributes I have put a serial number
for the records which kind of can be considered
as internal numbers of the database to identify
each record.
Now, let us say let us assume that we have
to search on names suppose we have a query
that get me the phone number of ah Pabitra
Mitra.
So, you can see that Pabitra Mitra the record
name occurs at position 6.
So, if we have to get the phone number, then
naturally we have to look at all these entries
from one end to the ah other till we come
across Pabitra Mitra match the name Pabitra
Mitra and we can access the phone number .
Now, similarly if we have to search for a
phone number we will have similar situation.
So, if we want to ah get the phone number
of ah the faculty having phone number 84772.
Again we will have to search on the phone
number from one end to the other and find
the name of the faculty.
Now, certainly this will mean that if there
are n records in the database then we will
need or the order of about n by 2 ah comparisons
to be done or accesses record accesses to
be done before.
We can find the desired record which is certainly
ah not a very efficient way of doing things
and you know from your knowledge of ah basic
algorithms that; if we have a set of data
and we want to find a particular one then
we can make it efficient by actually keeping
the data in a sorted manner and doing some
kind of a binary search that is one one possible
mechanism through which you can do that.
So, we can use that same context same concept
now and ah just look at the left side the
blue part of the blue part tableware, what
I have done have collected all the names of
the faculty and I have sorted them in lexicographically
increasing order and with that I have kept
the record number as a pointer.
Now, since this is a sorted array.
So, here I can search for Pabitra Mitra for
the first query in a binary search.
So, at least in the log n order of ah comparisons
I should be able to find ah professor Pabitra
Mitra and get the fact; that it is record
number is 6 navigate to the record number
6 in the table in the middle and take out
the phone number.
Similarly, without disturbing the actual faculty
table I can build a similar kind of ah ah
supportive table on the right the yellow one
where I collect all the phone numbers and
I have sorted on the phone numbers I can again
do binary search on the phone number 84772
and find the phone number ah find the record
number where this phone number occurs and
go and find the name of the faculty.
So, you can see that naturally this gives
us a alternate way of finding out and certainly
you would say that we could have kept the
record sorted on ah name or on phone number,
but certainly if we keep it sorted on name
the first query we will get benefited the
second query will still take a linear time
if we get keep it sorted by phone number the
first query will take a linear time.
So, if we cannot actually keep the data sorted
on both and therefore, this is just an alternate
mechanism called the indexing mechanism through
which even though the original data is not
sorted by maintaining some auxiliary data
we can actually make our search mechanism
more efficient and that is the core idea of
indexing.
So, indexing mechanism is used to speed up
accesses to desired data.
So, as as you have just seen.
So, what we search on is called the search
key and an index file consists of the index
entries as you have just seen it has a search
key and the pointer pointer is the record
number or the internal you know address of
the record where it occurs and certainly I
have shown an example where there just two
attributes in general there will be a large
number of attributes.
So, the entry of every index would be much
smaller than the corresponding record.
So, the overall index file will be a much
smaller one than the original and we can index
it and there are two basic ways to index and;
that is what we will discuss through these
modules one is called ordered index where
this search keys are stored in sorted order
as you have just seen and the other is hash
indices where the search keys are distributed
randomly across different buckets.
Using, concepts of hash function which you
must have studied as a part of your data structure
course .
Now, if we I mean why what should we index
on the basic question is ah should we index
on all attributes should we index on one attribute
should we index on combination of attributes.
So, access.
So, there are certain measures to decide as
to what is a good way to ah index.
So, that will be that will be measured against
the basic requirements of the database that
is I should be able to index in a way.
So, that the access time the insertion time
the deletion time all these should get as
minimized as possible and as you have just
seen indexing might mean maintaining additional
structures.
So, that overhead of space should also be
minimal.
So, with that with indexing we should be able
to do at least certain kind of accesses where
a particular value matches the attribute of
a record or falls within a range of ah values
ah in a record those kind of ah searches those
kind of queries should become very efficient
and these metrics will have to always keep
in mind.
So, let us look at the first concept of ordered
index which is pretty much like what we have
just sent.
So, in a sequentially ordered file the index
whose search key specifies the sequential
order is ah known as the primary index.
So, the sequential ordering is done based
on that primary index it is called also called
the clustering index and please keep in mind
that the search key of a primary index is
ah usually the primary key, but not necessarily
the primary key it could be different from
the primary key also and if I create an index
who search key is ah different from the sequential
order of the file then we say it is a secondary
index and it is also called the non clustering
index.
So, index sequential file is ah ordered sequential
file which is ordered on the primary index.
So, here ah I show an example and this is
ah example of dense ah index file.
So, you can see the blue part is actual table
which has ah different fields the id the name
of the faculty, the department, and the salary
and ah this is ah as you can see that it is
ah completely sorted on the id in the increasing
value of id and on the left the white is basically
just the ids and with every idea we have a
pointer they record the number possibly of
ah the record that it corresponds to here
all the indices that feature in the table
are also put on the index file and therefore,
it is called a dense index you should also
note on the right that the records are interlinked
through a chain I mean kind of they are being
formed in terms of a linked list whose purpose
would be seen later on .
Now, instead of doing id if I want to do a
dense index on department name, then naturally
the sequential file has to be indexed primarily
on the department name and as you can note
that unlike the id which is also the primary
key and therefore, every id value was unique
the department name is not a primary key it
is a different attribute which allows for
multiple ah value ah multiple records having
the same attribute value and therefore, when
we sort we have ah one instance of biology,
but three of computer science ah two of finance
and so, on.
So, when we make the index we made the index
collect all the distinct values of the department
names and for every department name we put
a pointer we put the index marking the first
record in the sequential file with that department
name.
So, you can see that your computer science
points to the record starting with one zero
one zero one and then the; it goes on to the
next two records.
So, now you can understand why we need the
link list; because if we are looking for the
all those teachers all those faculty who are
associated with department computer science,
then I can find it on the index file with
the department name, computer science traveled
to the record first record in that which is
of Srinivasan and then keep going on this
list through the linked list that we have
on write and find the record for Katz and
record for Brandt and till we moved to the
next record for Kim which does not match the
department name anymore.
Now instead of ah dense index we could also
do sparse index.
Tweak parse index it means that instead of
ah maintaining all the search key values ah
that exist in the file we just take a subset
of that and ah we ah maintain those in the
index ah file.
So, here again we are showing a index sequential
structure with id being the primary index
and ah we have chosen three of the ids and
kept them in the index file.
So, in the sorted order.
So, this ah if you want to say look at a record
with search K value K we can find the index
record with the largest key value ah largest
search key value id value which is less than
K and then search sequentially or onwards
because these are all ah linked together in
the sequential manner.
So, naturally compared to the dense index
of sparse index takes ah less space and therefore,
less overhead for maintenance ah when we do
insertion deletion you must have already noted
that ah if I were dense index then every time
I i insert a value it will have to be the
dense index file will also have to change
changes will be required there for insertion
as well as for deletion for sparse index it
will not be required, because it will just
be required when I am actually changing the
record or creating a record which is existing
on the sparse index.
So that way it is it is better than the dense
index, but certainly in ah the dense index
I can go to any record directly from indexing
in the sparse index I need to first index
and then go sequentially.
So, it will be in general slower in terms
of performance and will need to look at this
tradeoff now it is also.
So, these were ah the ways to do the primary
indexing where ah we decide the order in which
we actually keep the record sorted or the
fields on which we do that and the index associated
with it, but ah once since the data can be
ah primarily indexed on one or ah couple of
ah attributes and that gets fixed.
But we may want to search for other values
also to make that efficient we create a secondary
index.
So, here we show an example where the primary
index is id.
So, the whole recall records are sorted in
terms of that and we are creating an index
on the salary.
So, that we can quickly find ah the salary
of ah and given the salary of an employee
we can quickly find the employee or the employees
who get that salary.
So, you can see that for secondary index now
it is quite possible that there are multiple
entries for the same value of salary for example,
if you look at the salary eighty thousand
that is received by Professor Singh as well
as Professor Kim.
So, if you look at the index file of the index
sequence of the ah salary values you will
find that against 80,000 we have two entries
which marked to two different records corresponding
to the faculty who are drawing that salary.
So, secondary index naturally has to be ah
dense and is created when we want we feel
that there is a need to quickly search on
that field or that set of fields and we will
discuss more about those issues later on.
So, indices ah offer substantial benefits
when searching for records, but updating index
impose over it; because if you create an index
whenever you insert a record or a delete a
record or you change the value of a field
which is indexed in a record then certainly
all these indices will have to be also updated
and therefore, while your access time significantly
reduces, because of indexing your ah actual
update insert delete update time will increase
and therefore, ah the indexing will have to
be done carefully.
So, sequential scan using primary index is
efficient, but sequential scan using secondary
index is ah expensive.
So, you will have to bring them in in blocks
and that will require couple of ah millisecond
versus the amount of ah time that you need
in the memory access.
So, these are the factors that we will have
to take into consideration and we will talk
more about those.
Now, if I have a primary index ah then naturally
ah to be able to access the records I will
have to first access the primary index and
then do a search in that and then ah travers
the point at to go to the actual record in
the file.
So, to access the primary record we would
prefer that if the the primary index can actually
fit into the memory.
So, that I can do a in memory search like
we do the binary search in a in an array.
So, because if the primary index is large
then ah that also has to exist in the disk
and therefore, bringing that primary index
into the memory and then searching will add
two additional access cost of the disk and
you have already seen in the earlier modules
as.
So, how these costs are expensive these accesses
are expensive.
So, primary index if it is not in the memory
then we usually have a lot of ah disadvantage.
So, to ah take care of that if you have primary
index actually is large enough.
So, that it does not fit in memory then we
simply apply the notion of indexing once again
on the primary index file itself.
So, we construct a say on the primary index
we construct a past sparse index.
So, which is called the outer index which
is a sparse index of the primary index and
in that index is the actual primary index
file.
So, if now in turn the outer index the sparse
index of the primary index also is too large
to fit in memory then you need to do yet another
level of ah indexing on it and.
So, on till you come to a index of ah list
which fits into a memory can can be directly
accessed.
So, the cost for that.
So, this is what is called a multi level indexing.
Because, you are following multiple levels
for indexing and ah the cost naturally of
update insert delete increases; because now
all of these multiple levels of indices will
have to be updated.
When you do an update.
So, this is ah what is a view of the multi
level index you can see the outer index which
ah is sparsely index and index those lead
to ah different blocks of primary index of
the of the inner index which is the primary
index and then ah you traverse to the specific
block where your record is expected.
So, with this you since your outer index are
in memory.
So, you need to do one disk fetch for finding
out the inner index block which should be
one disk page or disk block one axis and then
based on that to find another access to ah
for the block in which the record exists.
So, with this you would be able to manage
with to block accesses in this case and that
is how the multiple this would not have been
possible if ah in this case you would not
have done the sparse outer index, because
you would have required the different parts
of the inner index of the primary index to
be fetched repeatedly from the disk till you
act could actually find the final result in
that.
So, updating the index particularly if you
ah do deletion then ah the if it is a dense
index then the deletion of the search key
is similar to ah deletion of ah the actual
record in the file because it is dense if
these parts, then naturally you will have
to take care of some of the cases, because
if it falls within a range then ah just deleting
it would not matter, but if it falls on the
boundary where it is actually sparsely indexed
then that will have to be appropriately updated.
Similar thing will have to be taken care of
in terms of ah insertion.
So, first you will have to look up to find
out to where the record needs to be inserted
and then if it is a dense index if the search
key does not appear in the index then you
will have to insert it in case of sparse index
you will have to do the additional care that
ah whether it already belongs to the range
and or whether if it will have to be a new
block has to be created then it has to be
also entered in terms of the sparse index
and ah if you have multi level ah indexing
then insertion deletion will be extensions
of these basic algorithms.
For secondary indices frequently we want to
find ah all records where certain value ah
value in a certain field which is not the
search key or the; of the primary index satisfy
some condition.
And, we can have a secondary index with an
index record for each of this search key values
depending on what we expect what we ah would
think or likely fields on which more search
will be done.
Or more range queries will be done . So, to
ah summarize we have ah taken a brief look
at the ah basic reasons for indexing database
tables which is to speed up the process of
ah access insert and delete and we have seen
that primarily indexing primarily focuses
on ah speeding up the access ah process.
So, in that maintenance of ah indexing whereas,
insertion and deletion might have some additional
overhead, but since insertion and deletion
both inherently needs ah access to be done
because you can insert only when ah you have
ah tried to access and havent found exactly
where the record should occur or for deletion;
obviously, you need to first find the record
to be able to delete it.
So, even though it is focused indexing is
focused on improving the access time it actually
improves the time for access insert delete
all of that, but we will have to keep in mind
that in the process there are certain overheads
of index update for insert and delete that
will have to be kept as a minimal and the
additional storage requirement will also have
to be kept as a least overhead.
So, with this ah we will close this module
we have taken the basic look at the index
sequential access mechanism this is called
index sequential access mechanism associated
with different database index files.