Welcome to module 29 of Database Management
Systems; we have been talking about ah indexing
and hashing and this is a fourth in the series.
Ah In the previous 3 we have talked about
different aspects of indexing and specifically
in the last module, we have introduced the
most powerful data structure B plus tree for
index ah files.
Ah In this module, we will take a look into
a explore into various hashing ah schemes
for ah achieving the similar targets we will
look at static and dynamic hashing. And we
will then compare it between the ordered indexing
ah that we have discussed already and hashing
and we will also understand about what are
called bitmap indices. So, these are ah the
module outline.
So, static hashing I am assuming that all
of you know about basic concept of hashing.
So, it what it does a there is a bucket is
a unit of storage containing one or more records.
So, that is the basic logical concept typically
in physical terms a bucket can be a disk block.
So, a hash file organization ah obtains we
we in a hash file organization; we attempt
to obtain a bucket for a record directly from
its search key value using a hash function.
So, this is where it becomes very different
compared to the ordered indexing ah for which
we we saw all this ah I some method and the
B plus tree where we went through different
index structure, but here we want to make
use of a mathematical hash function. So, that
given the key ideally I should be able to
get the bucket in which that particular record
containing the key exists that is the requirement.
So, hash function h is a function from the
set of all search key values K to the set
of all bucket addresses B. So, it is a mathematical
function and ah it is used to locate the records
for access insert as well as delete records
with different search key values may be mapped
to the same bucket right this is not what
ideally we wanted, but it is possible there
is a entire bucket has to be searched sequentially
once you reach there to look at a record,
we can make use of other techniques there
we will come to that.
. So, let us ah take a quick example hash
file organization of an instructor file using
say department named as key. So, we need to
design a hash function. So, let us assume
that ah on the address space B we have 10
buckets. So, every bucket is ah designated
by a by a serial number bucket 0 to bucket
9 and ah we take department name is a key.
So, it is a is a character string.
So, we take the binary representation of the
ith character and ah assume it to be the integer
I simply every character you take take its
binary representation and think as if it is
an integer. And then as a hash function we
add these integer values of binary representations
modulo 10. So, M hash value of music we take
the binary representation of m which is the
as key code of M capital M; then ah add the
as key code of u the lower case u and so,
on and do that modulo 10 and we get a value
which is 1.
So, naturally since we are doing modulo 10
which is the number of buckets here. So, we
will get a result for the hash function which
is between 0 to 9 which is a bucket address
where it is expected.
So, here we are showing an example. So, you
can ah see ah in the earlier slide we are
showing music is 1 history is 2 physics and
electrical engineering both are hash value
3.
So, you can see here in bucket 2 since history
has ah value 2. So, those records El Said
and Califfieri records go to bucket 2 whereas,
physics and electrical engineering both have
hash value 3. So, that Einstein golden came
all go to the bucket 3 similarly it happens
with the other buckets as well not all buckets
are shown here shown only 8 buckets are shown,
but in this way we can actually directly map
them to the buckets.
And ah ; so, such a hash function would be
really useful now the question is a it is
a mathematical function; so, how good or how
bad it is. So, we will say that the worst
possible hash function is one which maps all
key values to the same bucket. So, that everything
will have to within them serially; so, that
is of no no use.
So, the ideal one would be which will ah distribute
ah the different search keys values in different
buckets in an uniform manner to the from the
set of all possible values. So, that would
be that will be nice to have and ideal would
be that if the hash function is random which
means that ah. So, that each bucket will ah
I mean it will generate from the key value
it will generate the bucket number, it will
generate the bucket address ah in kind of
a random manner. So, that in a random phenomena;
so, that irrespective of what kind of actual
distribution the search keys may have the
buckets over which the distribute will be
more or less the same. So, every bucket will
have same number of records things will be
balanced.
A typical hash function ah performs ah computation
on the internal binary representation of the
search key that is the basic ah that that
is the one that you have just seen. So, if
it is a string then you treat the characters
as ah they are binary representations as integer
do some some modulo a number exactly what
we did in the last case.
Now the question is the buckets have a certain
size we said that a bucket is a is a disk
block. So, ah a bucket can overflow ah because
there may not be enough ah sufficient buckets
to keep all the records. So, it will not fit
in or your distribution could be skewed. So,
there may be many buckets where there are
lot of space left, but some buckets may have
a too many records coming on to it because
of the behavior of the hash function. So,
that multiple records have the same key value
or chosen hash function produces non uniform
distribution and so, on.
So, if that happens then ah the probability
of bucket flow; bucket overflow will happen
and we can try to reduce that, but it cannot
be eliminated. So, all that you do is to have
overflow bucket which is nothing, but having
other buckets connected to this target bucket
in a chain.
So, this is called a overflow chaining as
you can see there are 4 buckets shown here
and bucket 1 we are saying showing are connected
with other two buckets which are the overflow
buckets for bucket 1. So, that this kind of
a scheme is called ah closed hashing there
is an alternate scheme ah called open hashing,
which does not use a bucket overflow and,
but it is not therefore, suitable for database
applications and we will not discuss it here
.
So, hash indices can be used only for file
organization ah I mean not only for file organization,
but they can also be used for indexed structure
creation like we did for B plus tree we can
use the hash indices for index structure also.
So, hash index organizes the search keys with
their associated record pointers into a hash
file structure exactly in the same way its
hashing otherwise.
So, but the you can note that the hash indices
are always kind of secondary indices because
if a file itself is organized using hashing;
then a separate primary hash index on it using
the same search keys are necessary. Because
if if you are talking about primary hash indexing
then ah it will mean that you are taking the
primary search key and creating a hash index
on that, but if the file is hash created by
hash indexing then that already exists. So,
anything that you create in terms of ah indexing
is basically a secondary indexing structure
in a hash organized file.
So, this is ah kind of hash indexing example.
So, here ah I am I am showing the hash indexing
with the ah ID of this ah table and the index
is computed by adding the digits modulo 8
assuming that there are 8 buckets. So, if
you take; so, if you look at bucket 0 then
ah the key that has gone there is 76766 which
is 7 plus 6; 13, 20 plus 6; 26 plus 6 32 modulo
8 is 0.
So, it goes into bucket 0 it happens that
way ah if, but if we look into bucket 4 you
will find that the 4 IDs ah actually all have
ah this value 5 under the hash function. So,
they all need to go to this bucket and therefore,
but the bucket size assumed here is just 2.
So, after the 2 ah indices have gone in there
a overflow chain is created and another overflow
bucket is used to keep the next two ah IDs
there. So, this is how a hash index can be
created .
Now, this is this kind of a scheme where you
you start with a fixed number of buckets and
then you design a hashing function which maps
the search key values to this fixed set of
buckets is known as a static hashing it is
static because you start with a fixed number
of buckets.
So, yeah naturally the question is what should
be this value of B the number of buckets.
Now if it is initially too small ah then the
file keeps on growing the performance will
degrade because you will have too many overflow
chains and if the all advantages of having
done the hashing will get lost. On the other
hand if you take a too large a B then ah you
will unnecessarily allocate a lot of space
anticipating growth, but it may take a very
significant amount of time to utilize that
that space or also it is possible that it
the database at at certain point of time grew
to a large size and then it started shrinking
and then again space will get wasted .
So, static hashing ah has has these limitations.
So, naturally what you will have to do is
to periodically reorganize ah the file with
a new hash function which is ah certainly
very expensive because it changes the positions
of all records. So, it disrupts the normal
operation; so, it would be better if we could
allow to change the number of buckets to to
be changed dynamically at the as the database
grows. So, if the database grows it can use
more and more buckets and if we could adjust
this in the hashing scheme ah inherently;
then it will certainly be better as a solution
. So, that gives rise to what is known as
ah dynamic hashing.
So, it is certainly good for databases that
regularly grows and shrinks in size, allows
the hash function to be modified dynamically
ah. Of the different dynamic hashing schemes
I will discuss ah the extendable hashing which
is a very popular scheme . So, let us see
what how it works. So, it at the hash function
will generate the value over a large range
say typically a B bit integer say 32 bit integer
now .
So, what you have is is you have generated
a value which is hash value which is say over
32 bits, but what you do at any time you use
only a prefix of that; you only use a part
frontal part of that to index the table to
the bucket address and ah the length of that
prefix is i bits; then naturally it could
be at least theoretically it could be 0 that
is you do not use any prefix and it could
be up to that you use all the prefixes.
And ah so, therefore, if you are using i bits
then the bucket address table the possible
you know bucket addresses that you could have
is 2 to the power i initially you keep that
as 0 .
So, then the address table will actually point
to different buckets let us ah start moving
to an example and see what is happening.
So, this is ah the general ah scheme. So,
you have ah a hash prefix which is using i
number of bits and therefore, different values
of i number of bits. So, there will be 2 to
the power i entries naturally you have different
buckets here, but you may not actually have
all 2 to the power i buckets ah you may have
less than that as it is shown here that bucket
2 and bucket 3 exist, but ah bucket 1 is ah
a holder for both this ah prefix 0 0 as well
as prefix 0 1.
So, and on on top of ah every bucket you have
a a a kind of ah bucket depth given. So, it
is a number of bits ah that you need to ah
explore in the in the representation in the;
so, that you can distinguish the different
records of that bucket .
Naturally the maximum value of any of these
i is ah the the i here, but it could be less
than that. So, I am I am sure this is this
probably is not making much sense immediately.
So, let me move to my detailed discussion.
So, what I was saying that each bucket j stores
a value i j. So, this is ah the all the entries
that point to this bucket has the same value
on the first i j bits. So, this i j bits are
are identical. So, all of them have come to
this bucket. So, how do you look at ah the
bucket that contains the search key K j? So,
it compute the hash function which is X user
prefix i bits of X as a displacement into
the buckets address table and follow the pointer
to the appropriate bucket.
Now if I have to insert ah a record with a
search key K j; you will follow that same
procedure as a lookup and look at the bucket
j and then you will have to look for making
some space. So, let me do something. Let me
before going through this ah statement of
the algorithm. Let me just go through an example
first and we can come back to this ah formal
statement.
So, what we are trying to do is ah ah there
is ah the department names ah which we are
using as a key to do this hashing index and
they are represented in terms of the binary
representation. So, this is ah this is ah
the hash of that department name and hashed
into ah you can you can easily see this is
ah 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8 . So, this is hashed
into 32 bit number .
Now what do we do? So, initially we start
with. So, this is ah this is all the different
ah hash values that you can see I am sorry
ah this is ah all the different hash values
and this is the table that I need to actually
represent ok . So, initially there is nothing.
So, I try to ah I will try to insert Mozart
Srinivasan and these 3 records here. So, let
me try that .
So, if I look at Mozart then Mozart is from
the department of music. So, and ah Srinivasan
is from computer science Wu is from finance.
So, let us look at this. So, Mozart is from
music Srinivasan is from computer science
and ah Wu is from finance. So, these are the
3 now if we look into the prefixes of their
hash values; you can see that ah their hash
values are 1 1 and for music it is 0 right.
So, if I use a hash prefix which has just
one bit and naturally therefore, I have two
entries 0 and 1 then music with the value
0 maps to this bucket where I entered the
record for music. And computer science and
finance the records corresponding to them
has a hash value prefix 1. So, they both map
to discipline this is how it can get started.
So, you you find out while inserting you find
out where is Mozart and based on that you
create this.
Now, let us try to ah insert Einstein . So,
to insert Einstein what ah do we find? So,
what all ah we we already have? We have music,
we have computer science, we have finance
and ah now Einstein comes in ah Einstein is
from physics. So, what would happen when you
try to insert Einstein? You already had computer
science with 1 as 1 prefix and finance with
1 prefix.
So, you had ah in in bucket two ah corresponding
to 1 you already have 2 records that bucket
is full assuming that it can take only 2 records.
So, now, you get another which is value 1;
so, its value is 1. So, what I need to do?
I need to actually expand this now how do
I do that? I cannot expand this because there
is no more space left. So, all that I need
to do is to actually expand the bucket address
table.
So, earlier if I if I just ah if I just go
back. So, if I just go back earlier we had
only two entries because we are using only
1 bit in the prefix and with that I could
not have inserted Einstein oh is from department
of physics which also has a 1 bit prefix which
is 1 it was. So, I need more space; so, I
have increased the prefix level to 2 going
here and now naturally I have if I have increases
to 2; now I have let me erase this ah these
entries and now I look at for music I look
at 2 ah for physics 1 0, for finance 1 0,
for computer science 1 1.
So, now, I find that after I have moved from
looking at 1 bit of prefix to 2 bits of prefix
now finance and computer science which was
earlier together because I was looking at
1 bit now becomes different, but finance and
physics both come to the same ah 1 0.
So, in the hash bucket address table 1 0 you
have financial physics ah coming in with Wu
and ah Einstein records and ah computer science
which has got 1 1 the Srinivasan record goes
to a new bucket which comes from 1 1 here
. Now the interesting fact is what happens
to Mozart who which was there if you if you
remember the earlier structure this is we
had only 1 here. So, this was going to Mozart
this was 1 and Mozart was here because ah
music had a prefix 0; now music has a prefix
0 0.
So, what he would have expected? You would
have expected that therefore, ah since 0 0
has come and 0 1 has also come in. So, you
would have expected that ah to have another
bucket here which 0 1 is, but then you observe
that actually that would be a quite a wasteful
to do because you do not actually have a record
which has a prefix 0 1.
Out of ah these two which are we are looking
at two prefixes, but you do not really right
now need to look at both the prefixes you
can still resolve just by based on the first
prefix 1. So, you do a simple trick you do
not change the prefix level of the particular
bucket you say it is 1. Because it is you
just need to look at one bit to be able to
come to the records in this bucket and the
globally it has changed to 2 bits prefix,
but locally you keep it as 1.
And with that what you have? You have 0 1
which has a bucket address table entry actually
does not have a bucket because there is no
records for that. So, you let that point to
the same bucket. So, this is a very critical
observation that these numbers are basically
the local depth; the local ah information
of how many bits in the prefix you need to
look at to be able to resolve for coming to
this bucket for the records that you currently
have.
Whereas this is the global one this is a global
maximum that you have. So, naturally local
depth cannot exceed the global depth, but
if it is equal then you have a unique mapping
from the bucket address table entry to the
bucket, but if the local depth as in here
is less than the global depth; in terms of
the number of prefix bits you are looking
at then multiple bucket address table pointers
actually end up in the same bucket and that
is the main principle of this algorithm we
can just ah continue further inserting gold
and ah said into this .
So, as you ah try to insert gold and ah said
gold is also from physics which we already
had. So, physics ah and said is from history
which we did not have. So, history finance
computers let me let me just mark them by
the side. So, you have now computer science,
finance, history, music and ah physics.
Now, you will ah find that you need to ah
you now have physics is 1 0 and you have two
records ah for that and ah music is continues
to be 0 0 ah; obviously, ah history is 1 1
same as ah computer science. So, that has
to go on this and finances on 1 0 now, but
what happens is when you try to do this; you
could not have inserted more records because
you have run out of space in the buckets.
So, again you have run out of that; so, you
need to expand in terms of the number of bits
that you look at.
So, you increase that to 3 and now you have
0 0 0 to 1 1 1, but as I have explained not
all buckets really need to look into. So,
many bits Mozart ah this bucket continues
to ah B with a local depth of 1 because if
you look into all these 4 ah different ah
cases; then music is the only one which has
a prefix 0, everyone else has a prefix 1.
So, if I know that it is 0 then it comes to
only this bucket and nowhere else consequently
all these 4 bucket address pointers actually
go to this bucket table.
Whereas ah these two for physics I have 1
0 and ah for finance we have ah 1 0 here and
these come to . So, physics now is looking
into 3; so, it is 1 0 0 finance is into 3
it is ah 1 0 1. So, both physics and finance
go to different buckets; now coming to computer
science it is 1 1 1 and there is no. So, computer
science is 1 1 1 and there is no 1 1 0 . So,
the 1 1 0 bucket address table pointer continues
to point to the same bucket and the local
depth value is just 2 less than 3 in the global
table.
So, this is the basic ah process of ah doing
dynamic hashing. So, I will not ah; so, the
whole example in terms of this table I have
ah given here worked out. So, you can just
go through every step and try to convince
yourself.
This is an interesting case that happens here
where again you come to computer science ah
professors to be entered. So, at level 3 of
prefix you have all of them have prefix 1
1 1. So, you would have required to split
or increase the prefix level globally the
prefix level to 4, but assuming that there
is an upper bound on the number of prefix
levels; you can do which decides the size
of the bucket address table ah. If that is
given to be 3 you certainly cannot increase
it further; so, all that you will have to
do is actually do a kind of an overflow chain
here as well.
So, all of them are 1 1 1 here which brings
you to this you cannot find it you go to this
and all 1 1 ones in future will have to be.
So, it is a its kind of a tradeoff between
what is the ah size of the global depth, how
many prefixes globally you would like to look
at what is the size of every bucket that you
will have to ah maintain and what is the kind
of chaining that you will have to accept because
of that. So, this is ah what happens ah particularly.
So, you can continue in this way and this
is a final table where all things have been
hashed well. So, this is the basic extendable
hashing scheme it has ah in this the performance
does not degrade with the growth of the file
and there is very minimal ah overhead of the
space. But it does have ah disadvantages for
example, there is a extra level of indirection
to find the desired record because it the
hash then come to the hash bucket address
table and then go to the bucket ah bucket
address table itself may be very big because
it is exponential in the size of the number
of beds.
So, it could be larger than memory if that.
So, much of you know a contiguous allocation
may not be possible. So, you will need to
have another possibly a B plus tree structure
to locate the desired record in the bucket
address table first. And then changing the
bucket address table ah will become a quite
an expensive operation. So, the growth will
become.
So, there are several disadvantages that also
this scheme has. So, another alternate is
to use a linear ah hashing allows incremental
growth of his directory at the cost of more
bucket overflows of course, . I would quickly
try to compare the two ah major schemes that
we have ah discussed.
The ah ordered indexing ah and the hashing
now naturally ordered indexing has suffers
from the cost of ah periodic reorganization.
And ah because ah the indexing will have to
be maintained the hashing is better in terms
of that relative you will have to look at
the relative frequency of insertion deletion
that decides much of the cost between going
between these two schemes.
You will have to see is it desirable to optimize
average access time at the expense of worst
case access time. For example ah there could
be several ways to organize; so, that your
average become your worst case may be really
really bad, but as long as your averages is
very good you should be happy about it. So,
those kind of hashing schemes should be more
preferred. So, you also depends on ah the
kind of ah expected type of query.
So, for example, hashing is ah better in terms
of retrieving records which have a specific
value of the key because you can directly
map from that key to the bucket. And ah if
range queries are common then ah as we have
seen ordered indices would make it make much
better sense because in terms of the ordering
you can quickly get all the required records
at the same physical location nearby physical
location.
If you would ah like to understand as to what
the industry practices are it is very mixed.
And if you just look into 3 of the very common
ah database systems PostgreSQL does support
hash index, but recommends does not recommend
it because of the poor performance oracle
supports static hash organization, but not
hash indices SQL server supports only B plus
trees no hash index space scheme. So, of course,
you can see that there as ah the community
is mixed in terms of ah it is a reaction to
whether its ah indexing or hashing, but hashing
powerful at least in in limited ways is a
powerful technique to go with.
Ah The last two that I would like to just
quickly remind ah I mean ah take you through
is what is known as bitmap indexes. Bitmap
indexing is a very simple idea. So, what you
it is a special type of indexing which is
designed for querying on multiple keys; the
basic idea is that ah if let us assume that
all records in a relation are numbered from
0 to n and ah let us say that you are talking
about attributes which can take very small
number of distinct values.
So, bitmap indexing is not for any attribute.
So, consider attributes such a very small
number of distinct value say gender which
has two possible values or few possible values
the country state. So, take those or or maybe
you can you can nominally bucket a range of
numbers source income level 5, 6, 10 income
levels. So, small range of possibilities and
bitmap is simply array of bits. So, take an
array of possible ah ah array array for the
records and for the possible values you mark
1 or 2 0.
So, this here is an example showing it. So,
we are showing bitmap index for gender. So,
you have a array for m the male gender and
f female gender and if you look into the record
076766 has ah male under m ah gender m. And
ah therefore, in the male gender bitmap ah
index the first bit is 1 in f it is 0; so,
actually m and f are are complimentary.
Similarly, for the income levels you have
ah 5 different bitmaps encoding; the 5 different
ah possible levels in the income that you
can have.
Now the big advantage of bitmap indices are
doing different queries on ah multiple attributes.
And for example, the often queries have intersection
union and they can be simply computed in terms
of bitmapped operations. So, if you have two
different ah values to be two conditions to
check in terms of bitmap indices; then you
can just make there and and whatever ah satisfy.
So, say if you are looking at males at for
example, here males at income level L 1, then
you can you can just take the ah bitmap for
ah gender and ah bitmap for income level and
do the ending and you get that the first record
has value 1.
So, that is ah answer and you can quickly
come to that . So, ah bitmap indices generally
very I mean naturally they are they are they
are small in compared to the relation size
ah because you are doing bitmap indexing only
if the attribute can take small number of
distinct values.
Ah Of course, the deletion has to be handled
ah properly look at this and ah should keep
bitmap for all values even if there are null
values you must keep that otherwise you will
lose lose track of that. And ah there are
several ah efficient implementations ah some
information I have given, but ah is we do
not want to go in much ah depth here.
But several compression techniques. are are
possible in terms of bitmaps; in the next
module I will talk little bit more about how
to use that ah. In this module to summarize
we have ah talked about various hashing schemes
static and dynamic hashing, compared the order
indexing with hashing and introduced the notion
of bitmap indices.