Welcome to module ten of database management
systems. We have been discussing about intermediate
level features in SQL; and this is a second
and closing module on that. So, we have in
the last module talked about join expressions,
views and transaction in a bit.
In this module, we will try to learn SQL expressions
that are responsible for maintaining in the
integrity of the database. We have talked
about integrity a little. We will now see
how explicitly integrity can be checked and
how different kinds of integrity can be ensured
through SQL. We will also talk about more
data types. We have seen the basic primitive
data types, and we had promised that we will
talk more about the data types including user
defined data types here. And finally, we will
talk about a very important aspect of authorisation
as to who can do what in a database in through
SQL.
So, this is a module out line. We start with
integrity constraints. Integrity constraints
guard against accidental damage to the database
that is there are certain real world facts
that must be ensured in the database all the
time. For example, in bank accounts, we have
a minimum balance that need to be maintained;
for a particular customer, we might want that
the customers phone number must be present.
We may have certain age bar in terms of entering
into certain memberships or certain employment
and so on. All these kinds of real world constraints
need to be represented and maintained in the
database and that is the purpose of the integrity
constraint.
And we will first look at the issues of integrity
constraint for a single relation, and we have
seen the use of not null and primary key.
We will also talk about what is unique and
we will see how actually general constraints
can be checked in terms of a check clause
with a predicate P.
So, not null we had seen this before we can
while creating the database table. Create
table we can specify a field to be not null
and then in that case null values will not
be allowed in those fields. So, they will
must be some value given. You can say one
or more attributes to be unique. If you specify
them to be unique; that means, that in any
instance of the table in future that cannot
be two tuples which match in all of those
attribute. So, if you say A 1 to A m are unique;
that means, that if we have two different
tuples in the table anytime in future. Two
different rows in the table t 1 and t 2 then
across A 1, A 2, A m they must differ in at
least one attribute value. So, uniqueness
is a basic requirement for being a candidate
key, but they are, but still permitted to
be null which in contrast to what is the true
for primary key already you know that primary
key values cannot be null, but uniqueness
allows a null values, but they have to be
different.
The check clause is where you say check and
then you put a predicate. So, the idea is
like this suppose I know that I have specified
and attribute called semester. It is a varchar
6 which means that it can have a string maximum
of length 6, but naturally I can write anything
there I can write morning in that field. I
can write welcome in that field and so on,
but those are not valid names of semester.
So, I want that in my design semester must
have any of these values only.
So, we say semester in. So, I have listed
the values that are allowed in is a set membership.
So, it says the semester in so which means
the value of the semester is be one of this
fall. And this whole thing now becomes the
predicate P which on which I give a check
which means that whenever I am creating once
you have created the table when I want to
insert or update the values in the table,
the records in the table then e the value
of semester has to be always within this.
Otherwise, the check integrity constraint
will fail, and the update or insert will not
happen and an exception will be raised. This
is the basic idea of check constraints.
Now, let us move on to more involved integrity
check which goes beyond one table. So, let
us suppose that we are talking about the instructor
table we have the instructor table. An instructor
table has a department name. Similarly, we
have a department table which naturally has
a department name. Now, we know that this
is the key in the department table and therefore,
here it is the foreign key.
Now, while we are inserting records in the
instructor table how do we guarantee that
the record that we insert has a corresponding
entry in the foreign key table that is difference
table. So, it is when we are inserting and
in a faculty in the saying that the faculty
belongs to biology department there needs
to be a biology entry in the department table
as well. So, this is known as a referential
integrity that is once you refer from one
table to the other that reference must also
be a valid one; otherwise, all your computations
will go wrong.
So, this is a for saying it formally there
are two relations and one relation as a primary
key which is used in the other relation as
a foreign key then there is a referential
integrity that needs to be maintained.
So, here we are just showing the effect of
that. So, we have created a table this is
the first one is what you have seen earlier
creating the table course and that table course
needs the name of the department. So, we are
specifying that it references the department
table. Now, if it references the department
table it must ensure the referential integrity.
So, this just says that this refers to the
department table, but I can be more specific
to say what will happen if the integrity gets
violated. For example, I have created this
and the course table has an entry, which has
a department name say biology. Naturally,
biology department should have the entry there
should be an entry in the department table
with this department name biology for this
to be valid.
Now, say for some reason the biology department
is abolished and that particular record from
the department table is removed, naturally,
the course which is referring to biology in
terms of its department name that particular
record will become invalid. So, we can say
that on delete, what you should be doing,
one most common action that we specify in
referential integrity is cascade that if the
referred entity is deleted then the referring
entity should also be deleted. So, if you
delete the biology entry from the department
table, then all courses which have biology
through references to department as their
field value should also get deleted.
Similar thing can be there on update also.
For example, biology department say tomorrow
changes the name to bioscience. Now, if I
have a referential integrity put on the course
table as on update cascade, then as I change
the bioscience the name to bioscience. All
records in the table course, which had the
department name as biology will necessarily
get updated. So, this is the way to maintain
referential integrity. Cascading is one of
the most common way to handle this, but there
could be other ways to take action also that
could be no action that you say ok, I do not
care. Let that happen in that case some, because
of the violation that could be some exceptions
thrown or even say that if this happens then
I will set that field to null or I will set
that field to some default value and so on.
So, this is how the referential integrity
has to be handled. There could be integrity
violation during transactions also. This is
an example of a self-referential table which
of persons which where every person's entry
needs the name of the mother and the father
which are also entries in this table. So,
necessarily if you are entering a person record
you need this feels to be populated and that
can be populated only if those records already
exists. So, there is some order in which you
have to enter the records or you have to set
them as null and then update them in future
and or some ways to say that well do not check
this integrity now. We will talk about this
integrity at a later point of time. So, these
are the issues that necessarily you will have
to be addressed.
Let us move on and look at the SQL data types
and schemas. So, in addition to the data types
like char, varchar, int and all that you have
an explicit date data type which gives you
a year, month, date kind of format with a
four digit year, because date is very frequently
required. You have a time type to give you
hour, minute, second time format. You have
a timestamp, which is date and time together
and you have what is known as interval where
you can do a date or time difference between
two different dates, two different time, two
different time stamps and so on. So, these
are the common added built in types which
makes it very easy to handle the temporal
aspects in SQL queries.
In addition, the next that you can do is you
can create an index. So, let us look at this.
So, this create table definition you understand
well by now. You can I can do this, I can
say create index and give a name for the index
and specify which field on which the index
should be created. So, here we are saying
that the index should happen here. This is
the name of the relation, this is the name
of the attribute name of the field. Now, this
does not change any data neither does it change
any schema, but it creates certain additional
structure. So, that it becomes easier to search
this particular table using IDs.
So, if I have a query like this that I am
trying to find out all information about a
particular student then as we have said that
by default the different entries the rows
of a relation are unordered. So, the only
way to find out this particular row and in
fact, whether it actually exist would be to
go over all the relations one by one. But
if we index it, then it creates some kind
of an efficient data structure through which
it can be searched out very efficiently very
easily with a later module we will talk about
index in. But just to give you the idea that
this is similar to finding out a value in
an unordered array if you are thinking of
C.
In contrast, I can we all know that this can
be done, but takes a whole lot of time it
takes order in time. But I could keep those
numbers in terms of a some binary search tree,
balanced binary search tree like red black
tree or two three four tree kind of, where
the search can be conducted in a login time.
Or I could keep it in terms of some efficient
hashing mechanism where the search could happen
in terms of an ordered one time also. So,
index is has a has a lot of importance and
we will talk about that more, but this is
how you create index in SQL.
You can have user defined types, you can say
create type and use some specific you know
sub types of a type as and give it a name.
So, you send numeric 12, 2. So, which is the
12 digit number with two decimal places of
precision you can call it dollar and then
use that as a type name. So, type name doing
this helps in to visit make sure that wherever
you actually have to conceptually refer to
dollars you are talking about dollars it is
easier to understand and you are making sure
that everywhere the same numeric precision
is used.
You can also actually go further and create
domains which is very similar to create type.
But domains are more powerful in the sense
that in a domain. You can also add constraints
like not null and you say that this is person
name see say that this once you have set that
this person name is 20 characters long and
it cannot be null then you do not specifically
have to every time. You define a field based
on this domain type you do not have to specifically
say that it is not null. You could also create
a specific constraints in terms of the check
clause and make it easier. So, now if you
say degree level you do not have to put check
clause explicitly in the SQL query, because
it is already specified in the created domain.
SQL supports certain large-objects which are
either called blobs if they are binary, or
called clob if they are character objects.
The only the major difference in terms of
the large object types are they are not stored
as a part of the table. They stored elsewhere
and you actually maintain a kind of a reference
a pointer to that large object. So, this is
very useful in terms of handling photos, videos
and no big binary files, character files also.
Let us move to authorization.
Next, authorization is the process by which
you restrict different users to be able to
do different kind of operations. You recall
in the early modules on database overview.
We mentioned that there could be several types
of users for a database. There could be absolutely
application users who may necessarily do not
feature as a part of the database development.
But there could be application developers
expectedly most of you would become application
developers or there could be intermediate
higher level of analyst who design databases,
design constraints, decide on indices and
so on and that could be database administrator.
And also in terms of different application
programs and programmers there is a need to
separate out who can access which part of
the database. For example, if you look at
a add a banking system, then while I am by
net banking application is accessing different
information about my account, one part I need
to ensure that I can only access my account.
And also what the database system needs to
ensure is that a net banking application should
in no way be able to access the information
about the specific employees, because, in
the same database information about the bank
employees will also be there. It should not
be possible for possible to access information
about different physical information about
the branches as to where, how many square
feet of area that branch has and so on and
so forth.
So, we need to put variety of restrictions
and as we will see that authorisation or this
process of restricting or allowing different
access and different authority to operate
is decided based on two different factors.
One is what you want to do, and two is who
wants to do that. So, what and who, so we
identify different operations or different
operations on certain tables or operations
on certain attributes as what needs to be
done. And on the other side, we will identify
who in terms of specific individual user IDs
or groups of user IDs or roles that exist.
So, here we will just try to show you how
we can do that in SQL. So, the first part
of the authorisation is being able to do different
things with the database that means, the instances
of the database. So, there are authorisations
to read insert, update and delete. So, read
is where you can access the data, but you
cannot modify; insert is when you can add
new data, but you do not with insert rights
authorisation, you cannot update an existing
data, you can only insert data. You can have
update rights, where we can change make modifications,
but you may not be you are not allowed to
delete data, and you can that would be delete
right where it allows you to delete data and
my new this authorisations or not these are
all independent authorisation.
So, you may have I mean certain authorisations
may need certain other authorisations to be
present. For example, if you are updating
naturally evenly to read, but it is these
are all independent authorisations, and you
may have one or more of them to be able to
do the appropriate actions. Similar set of
another set of authorisations will exist,
if you want to for those want to modify the
database schema, naturally, this is primarily
for the applications and application programmers,
and this primarily would be for the analysts
that you can index the different table you
can do. You can have authorisation for resources
which mean you can create new relations, create
new schemas, you can alter schemas, you can
drop schemas and so on. So, these are the
different kinds of authorisation that are
possible.
So, let us see how it works the authorisation
is specified in terms of a statement called
grant. So, you grant an authorisation to a
privilege list and on certain relation to
a group of users. So, grant what kind of authorisation
you are granting that is the privilege less
list on what relation on view you are granting
that is on condition and to whom are you granting
those. So, user list could be a specific user
ID or you could say public which in this case
everybody will have that or this could be
a role which will see, what a role is.
Granting a privilege on a view does not imply
granting any privileges on the underline relation,
please mind this one, because, you have seen
that a view can be formed from multiple different
relations. So, if somebody has been granted
a particular privilege say read privilege
on a view, then it does not mean that the
corresponding underline relationship, you
been granted a read privilege on faculty relation
that we faculty view that we did that does
not mean that the user will automatically
get a read privilege on the underline in structure
relation. So, that has to be kept in mind.
The grantor of the privilege must already
hold the privilege that is you cannot grant,
naturally, grant will be done also by somebody
in some of the users you may be, so that user
who is granting must also have the privilege
same privilege on the specific item. So, you
cannot grant privilege on something, some
relation or view on which you yourself do
not have that or it has to be the database
administrative who naturally has privilege
for everything.
The privileges on SQL there is a select privilege,
which is so you know this is the privilege
list. Select privilege which basically means
read access. So, it is saying select privileges
is read access on instructor and these are
the different users. So, this is how typically,
you can have insert to ability to insert tuples,
the update privilege this should be easy to
understand now delete privilege. So, only
thing is read is a called select here, so
these are the different privileges that you
have in a SQL. And you have one all in compressing
privilege which is called all privileges so
as a short form of allowing all these allowable
privileges.
Certainly, if you can grant an authorization,
then needs to be a reverse process that is
if we want to withdraw authorization of certain
privileges on certain items for certain users,
so that is known as a revoke statement. So,
we can revoke it the structure looks exactly
similar to the grant. So, you revoke a privilege
list, select, insert this kind of on certain
relation and view from a set of users. So,
you can say that revoke select on branch from
this. So, once this is done, then U 1, U 2
and U 3 will not be able to read the branch
relation or the branch view. The privilege
list may be all to revoke all privileges.
So, instead of revoking select insert, separately,
you can just say all and revoke all of that.
The list of revoking can include public which
means all users lose that privilege and or
though those were granted. If the same privileges
granted twice, now it is possible that a user
gets privilege granted to him or her by two
different granting authorities, then the if
ones is one of them is revoked the other will
still continue to remain. So, every privilege
that is granted needs to be explicitly revoked
that is a basic meaning.
So, all privileges that depend on the privilege
being revoked are also revoked. So, some privilege
which is dependent on some other privilege,
if you revoke the update privilege then this
select privilege will remain. But, if you
revoke the select privilege then if you also
had the update privilege that will certainly
get revoked, because if you cannot read then
naturally you cannot change.
The SQL also allows you to create certain
roles. Roles are kind of like virtual use
that so, we all say that we all play certain
role. So, I have an entity as an individual
say I may be user called P P B, but I have
a role as an instructor, I have a role as
a say the head of the department, I have a
role as a chairman of committee and so on.
So, often times it becomes easier to grant
privileges to different roles. You do not
really care immediately about who that individual
could be who that particular user could be
who has that privilege, whoever plays that
role gets that privilege, whoever becomes
the director of IIT Kharagpur has the privilege
to appoint faculty members it is of that kind.
It does not specifically. So, role is of that
kind of a concept. So, you create role we
are saying that role is the role instructor
is created.
And then you are saying that you grant instructor
to Amit which says that Amit now plays the
role of instructor. So, any privilege that
the instructor role has Amit will enjoy that.
So, let us see more of this the privileges
can be grant to roles. So, earlier we said
it could be public, it could be users, but
now you are saying that it could be two roles.
So, here this role was creates and the privilege
is being granted to that. And since Amit plays
that role it will mean that Amit with this
grant select on takes to instructor, Amit
will actually get a privilege of select on
takes relation that is the kind of derived
structure that roles give you roles can be
granted to users as well as to other roles.
So, roles are becoming like virtual users.
So, you can create role teaching assistant
and grant teaching assistant to instructor,
which means that if you do that you are granting
this. So, it means that any privilege the
teaching assistant will have the instructor
will get those privileges, because, you have
made in instructor to also play the role teaching
assistant mind you instructor itself is virtual
entity. So, if Amit is an instructor by this,
then Amit plays this role and this role plays
teaching assistant role and this teaching
assistant role has certain privileges, so
naturally through this chain process Amit
will get those privileges. So, in an instructor
inherits all privileges of teaching assistant.
So, this is what exactly, what I was talking
of you can have a chain of roles create a
role dean new one, you have created, then
grant instructor to dean grant dean to Satoshi.
So, which means that once you grant dean to
instructor, so anybody who plays the dean's
role will get all privileges of instructor.
Here you are saying that Satoshi is going
to play the dean role. So, the Satoshi in
terms of chaining gets all the privileges
that instructor has.
So, once this has been done, then you can
have authorization on views as well. So, you
have created a view here. So, this is the
view created the geo instructor the Geology
instructor. And on that view particularly
you have given the privilege to the geo staff.
So, a geo staff member would be able to access
this view. And if this query is fired by a
geo staff member, which I am assuming is a
role then this view will get executed and
the results of all instructors in the department
geology will be update. But, what if the geo
staff does not have permission on instructor,
does not matter that is the beauty of the
whole thing. The geo staff may not have permission
to do select on instructor, but the geo staff
has permission to select on geo instructor.
So, the geo staff will be able to execute
this view, but the geo staff will not be able
to do a select on from the instructor database
instructor table.
There are several other authorization features,
the references a privilege to create foreign
key. So, we talked about basic read, write,
data manipulation privileges, but there could
be other privileges like whether you can create
a foreign key, whether you can transfer of
privilege. So, whether you can give one privilege
to the another, so whether you can cascade,
whether you can restrict and so on. So, transfer
of privileges is also privilege. I am naturally
will have to think of this is an authorization.
So, actually what we can authorize is also
a privilege that needs to be authorized. So,
these are the derived privileges that I have.
So, in summary, we have learnt about SQL expressions
to deal with integrity constraints. We are
familiarized with more data types particularly
user defined types and domains creation of
index and we have discussed about authorization
in SQL. Each one of them particularly authorization
has lot more details, but at this intermediate
level we just wanted to get a basic idea about
authorization to be able to deal with that.
So, with this we close our discussion on the
intermediate level SQL features. In the next
module that we start next week, we will talk
about some of the advanced SQL features.