Welcome to module 8 of Database Management
Systems. We have been discussing basic SQL
queries and this is the third and closing
part of that introductory discussion that
we started in the 6th module.
So, just to quickly recap, this is these are
the things that, we did in the last module
completing the understanding of basic operations
the null values and aggregate functions.
In the current module, we want to understand
a feature which is very very important in
SQL query forming it is called the nested
query or more formally nested sub query. In
SQL and we would like to understand the process
of data modification.
And those are the two things that are outlined
here. So, let us start with nested sub queries.
A sub query is necessarily a select from where
expression that is nested within another query
this is. So, these are the key things where
expression. So, it is nothing new over; what
we have already learned? But it is a part
of another query it is nested within another
query and that is the reason it is called
a sub query. So, it by itself is not the result
this will be used, this is a select from where
expression that will be used in a nested form
in another some other queries to actually
generate the result.
So, that is a nested sub query. So, the nesting
can be done in one or more of the three clauses
that a select from where SQL query has an
attribute can be replaced a relation can be
any valid sub query or a sub query could form
the part of a predicate in the where clause
all of these are possible. So, we will discuss
them one by one. So, first we will start by
discussing how sub queries work in the where
clause.
The common use for you having sub queries
in the where clause is to perform different
kind of tests for membership comparison cardinality
and so, on. So, let us look at this; you have
already seen this query before find courses
offered in fall 2009, and in fall in spring
2010. Earlier we have shown different ways
of coding this, now we are showing yet another
way to be able to code this in SQL.
So, first from the beginning certainly we
need the courses. So, the select clause is
trivial it has to be the distinct course id
is certainly the information will come from
section which has information about offering
of courses as we have also seen already ah.
So, those two are no brainer. Now let us see
what how do I find courses that are offered
in fall 2009 and in spring 2010. So, again
the first part, the courses offered in fall
2009 is coded in this part; in part of that
where clause predicate when he says semester
has to be fall and here is 2009. So, this
part is also done.
Now, we need to ensure that whatever I mean
e e if I assume that after this this part
were not there, then this will only give me
courses which are offered in fall 2009, but
we want the courses that are in fall 2009
and in spring 2010. So, we do something interesting
what I do is we write a separate query here
which is courses that are offered in spring
2010. Select course I d just in the same way,
select course I d section semester year. So,
this particular query will give me the courses
offered in spring 2009. So, what do we have
in one part? I have so, if you look at this
part this courses that happened in fall 2009;
if we look at this part courses that happened
in spring 2010 good.
Now, what I want I need that the; it I am
interested in the courses that happened in
both. So, for a course that exists here I
want to specify that that course Id that course
Id must be present here. So, what I am checking
for? I am checking for a set membership; this
is a set right. So, I am trying to check,
whether that course Id which is being selected
in the first part exists in in is another
keyword. In this particular, this particular
relation that is specified by the second part
of this query which is courses offered in
spring 2010.
If it is if the course Id is present, then
that course must have been offered in both
the semesters if it is not present, then it
is offered only in fall 2009, and not in spring
2010 and certainly the courses that were not
offered in fall 2009, and only offered in
spring 2010 will feature here, but they do
not exist here. So, they will never come up
for tests. So, as a result what I get finally,
is the effect of computing courses that are
offered in fall 2009 and in spring 2010 this
part of the query which I used as a part of
the where clause is my nested sub query.
And in this case as we have seen it is used
for set membership and this is a basic idea
of using nested sub queries; that is a nested
sub query will always give you a relation.
So, you try to put that relation in the right
context of the where clause from clause or
select clause, and then make use of it in
building up your logical.
So, let us run through some examples this
is, what you are saying is is earlier one
was the courses offered in both here we are
trying to do kind of the difference saying
the courses offered in fall 2009, but not
in spring 2010 certainly we easily get that
by changing the membership to negation of
the membership earlier it was in now you do
not in you will simply get that it is up to
you to take some examples and convince yourself
that this kind of a nesting will work ah.
We find the set of the find the total number
of distinct students, we have taken the course
section taught by the instructor Id some Id
is given. So, again we form a nested query
here is a nested query, which tells me the
courses taught by this particular teacher
10101, and then we check set membership. In
terms of this course Id section Id that is
fields of the takes relation to see that,
whether that particular tuple can exist in
the course offered by the specific teacher;
if it does then take out that I d which is
which will turn out to be the student Id.
In this case because that is the text relation
has the student I d take out the student I
d and count it as distinct. So, this can simply
give you the answer to this squared; obviously,
[laugher] we we agree that this can be written
in a simpler form also, but we are including
it here just for the sake of illustrating
the feature ah.
There is another clause called the some clause
look at this fine names of instructor; salary
is greater than that of some which means at
least one instructor in biology department
and we have already seen this coding before.
Now, we can do this in terms of the nested
query by using again this is certainly the
salary of instructors in biology department
and we are doing greater than sum; that means,
that the salary here being checked must find
at least one record here. So, that it is greater
than that salary value. So, it is greater
than some is a nice way to find existential
records using the nested sub query.
The logic of some clause I have detailed out
here. So, we will not go through each one
of them in this discussion. I leave it unto
you to study and convince yourself, that you
understand the semantics of some. So, similarly
we have an all clause which say that if we
want to say, they find the names of all instructors;
whose salary is greater than the salary of
all instructors in the biology department
in case of sum we can write or we will write
all and it will check every salary will check
with the whole set of salaries in this sub
query. And only if that is greater than that
particular record that particular name will
be included in the result. Otherwise it will
be excluded from the result.
Similar to some there is a basic semantics
of all which is also worked out here and I
leave that to your study at home. You can
test for empty relations by using the existing
construct. So, if you say exists r, then that
is a predicate which mean that r is not empty;
if r is empty then exist is false and not
exist is the negation of exist. So, it can
be used to specify the query like find all
courses taught both in fall 2009 and spring
2010. So, all that you have to do earlier
you did it by set membership.
So, now you are trying to do this by this
exists. So, you are saying that this is again
the same query which gives you the courses
that are in spring 2010 and also in this fall
fall 2009 and you check whether this relation
whether this particular nested query is an
empty one or not if it is an empty one, then
exist will fill and the whole where clause
will fail, if it was not an empty one then
you have found such an entry it was offered
and therefore, it will get included.
So, these are just different ways of expressing
similar things, but what you should note is
the nested sub query is a very convenient
way to frame up the logic in multiple different
ways that you would like to do. So, these
are the different names given the correlation
name and the correlated sub query incidentally;
the nested query is often referred to as the
inner query and the query in which the nesting
has happened, is known as the outer query
ah
Here is another example which illustrate the
use of not exist; so which I leave it for
your own study. We can check for uniqueness
that is; test for absence of duplicate tuples
by using the unique keyword. So, we can you
can see here that here is a nested query and
using unique to find out all courses that
were offered at most once in 2009. So, if
it a course was offered more than once, then
naturally multiple records will feature and
the result the unique will fail unique will
be true only if; there is only one entry which
shows that it is offered at most once in that
semester.
Now, I move on. So, we have been discussing
about sub queries in the where clause; now
we move on to sub queries in the clause. So,
as we have already seen a nested sub query
is a relation. So, it can naturally be used
in the place of any relation that we have
in the clause. So, we are trying to find out
average instructor salaries of those departments
where the average salary is greater than 42,000.
So, look at this is a nested sub query. So,
where what is been found here this will compute
the average salary department wise average
salary which we have already seen group by
department name and then you do average on
the salary and you give it a give me that
field a new name.
So which means that; this is equivalent to
having a relation which has two attributes
depth name and everyday salary. So, from that
you are now trying to do the selection and
what is the condition that the average salary
has to be written. So, you already have that
as a part of the field the average salary.
So, you just need to put that in the where
clause and you have only those coming out
of this particular relation where average
salary is greater than 42,000 to be selected
in this select query. So, these will feature
in the output of this selection.
So, that is how you can very easily use a
nested sub query in the; from clause and for
this we did earlier. We solve this problem
using the having clause, but they here we
will not need we did not need the having clause
to do this there is this is another way. So,
here what we have done is the same; if we
if we look into the nested sub query. This
is actually the same all that we have done
we have given it a new name by the renaming
feature, and then this as if becomes a relation
and on that the computation is done rest of
it is similar.
There is a clause that provides a way of computing
a temporary relation and that can be subsequently
used.
So, let us look at example. So, we are trying
to find all departments with maximum budget.
So, this is my basic value we want to find
department name, department dot name, that
is; a departments name from the department
table and the budget must be same as maximum
budget. So, for that I need to know the maximum
budget that exists across the department.
So, look at what has been done here we have
a nested query which aggregates the maximum
budget from the departments.
So, this gives you the value of the maximum
budget. We make that into a temporary table
max budget with an attribute value. So, this
is renaming. So, you cannot see the renaming
is being used in very interesting ways. So,
this is my nested query that gives me a relation
and this is my definition of the relation.
So, max budget now is a temporary relation
a relation that I used subsequently in my;
from clause and with allows me to do that
this relation will not be available.
Otherwise after this query this relation will
not exist this is just a temporary one computed
for this query. So, this gives me the budget
value this gives me the department and department
specific budget, and this condition tells
me that I can choose all the departments which
has the maximum budget very nice way of using
this.
So, with clause can be used in even more involved
way again this is an example which is more
complex use and I leave it to you to practice
study and understand we move on to sub queries
in the select clause finally, ah. A scalar
sub query is one; where there is a single
value is expected. So, we can very easily
use that in the select. So, what if you look
at this part which is the sub query? So, you
are saying list all departments along with
number of instructors each department has.
So, this condition tells that the from the
instructor; we are taking out those that department
name where the instructor works to count them
and then you form that in as a new attribute
mind you in while we were using this in the
from clause.
We were treating that as a relation because
nested query will give a relation, but here
in the select clause the entities are attributes.
So, this as is renaming of attribute which
means, but this is a relation that is why
this notion of scalar sub query is required
that is they though this is a relation what
does the relation compute it computes a single
value. So, that value we are putting as an
attribute named num instructors.
So, we have department name and the number
of instructor, then for each and every department;
that we actually have from the department
list. So, it is a very interesting way of
using this nested sub query in terms of the
select clause naturally; since thus in the
select clause I cannot have I mean every entry
in the select clause has to be an attribute
pure relations are not possible.
So, if the sub query returns more than one
table which cannot be conceived as a as a
as one or more attributes, then it will be
runtime error that will not be allowed; because
we do not know how to handle multiple tuples
in terms of a select clause ok. Next we move
on to discussing the modifications to the
database, how do we modify the database?
So, we will look into some of the ways of
changing the records or removing records from
that earlier. We saw a delete of record which
removed all records from a relation, but now
we will see selective deletion insertion and
update of values.
Now, deleting all instructors are easy delete
from instructor all records sorry this and
this becomes an empty table, but suppose we
want to delete all instructors from the finance
department, then like we do in the select
from where we again use the where clause as
a predicate and say that delete from instructor,
but you do the deletion provided this condition
is satisfied that is; department name is same
as finance. So, it is very similar to the
select from where, but the effect is unlike
select from where where no tables change in
the database here.
The table is actually changing; because these
instructor records are deleted whose department
name was finance. The third example shows
delete all tuples in the instructor relation
for those instructors, associated with the
department located in the Watson building.
So, it Watson building may have multiple departments.
So, all instructors who worked on those departments
which are located in the Watson building that
will go. So, you do this is again you are
using nested query.
Now, you know how to use a nested query. So,
you use nested query which will give you the
names of departments, which it gives you a
relation with a single attribute with names
of departments housed in the Watson building,
then you use the set membership to check whether
a particular department belongs to that set
if it does then it is in Watson building;
otherwise, it is not in Watson building if
it does belong to the Watson building then
this where clause becomes true and the corresponding
instructor record is deleted and that is of
this whole different kinds of selective deletion
can happen.
Delete all instructors whose salary is less
than the average salary of instructor. Again
this is; so, you compute the selection sub
query which computes the average salary and
check if the salary is less than the average
salary and delete that sounds straightforward,
but just where you I just wait just wait I
mean did we do it do a right thing an average
salary is computed by taking the sum of all
salaries in the relation. And then dividing
it by the number of relations this has to
be the average salary certainly if I remove
a record then the average itself will change.
So, if I write the query in this manner then
what I am saying on the face of it looks correct,
but then actually can it be correct because
the moment a condition is satisfied and that
record is deleted this average value itself
has changed. So, that is not. So, that will
depend then the result will depend on the
order in which the deletion is happening,
but that is not what was meant what was meant
is take all the records for the present find
out the average find out all records which
have a salary less than that average and remove
them.
So, this initially you know easy trivial looking
solution is not actually correct. So, you
will have to do the solution in two stages:
first compute the average salary, find all
tuples to delete? Next delete all tuples found
above without recomputing. The average in
the present solution the average is recomputed,
which is the wrong thing.
So, again I will leave that for you to solve
we move on to looking at modifications in
terms of insertion. So, we had seen this earlier
we can add a new tuple by inserting to then
the relation names, and then you save values
and the tuple of values. We can specify the;
if we if we do not remember the order of attributes
in the relation. Then we can also specify
the order in which we are spaced actually
giving the information.
So, you are saying insert into course and
what we have done here is we have actually
specified the order in which that tributes
occurred and that order and the order of values
must be the same. In the first case this order
of values is decided by the order of the attributes
that exist in terms of the create table. Add
a new tuple to student with total credit set
to null that is I do not know; we were adding
a student initially does not have a credit
right. The credit is a nullable field the
credit will be earned after the student has
gone through the courses and all that. So,
if I do not know the value of a field then
I can write n u l l null which is a special
value designating unknown for at the time
of insertion.
And all instructors to the student relation
with total credit set to 0. So, I can also
combine insert with select. So, we are taking
the first part this part is selection which
generates a whole lot of records having ID,
name, department name and the total credit
set to 0. From the instructor and insert them
into the students. So, these will get instruct
in inserted into the students select from
where statement is evaluated fully. So, this
first select from will be done before any
of its results are inserted in the relation.
So, that is the basic condition that SQL guarantees;
because if that were not the case then such
situations will become circular and will cause
problem.
Updates can be done based on particular values.
So, you can update a table based and what
it means that? It you could update the values
of specific fields.
So, here in the in the first case; we are
giving trying to give a 3 percent salary raise
for salaries which are more than 100, 1,000
and some 5 percent raise for salaries which
are less than equal to 100, 1,000 and mind
you this order in which you do the update
is important, because if you do the later
update first then someone who was what qualified
in the later part was less than 100, 1,000
with the increase will become more than 100,
1,000 and will also qualify for the second
one. So, that will become wrong. So, update
often is dependent on the order.
And therefore, you have yet another ah feature
to take care of this when you have a specific
order to do things it is called the case.
So, you say when salary case is a new keyword,
when is a key word when salary is less than
equal to 100, 1,000, then this is how you
hike otherwise this is how you hike. So
It can it looks more like the; if statement
of c c plus plus you can do updates with scalar
sub queries. We have seen scalar sub queries
already. So, you can use a scalar sub query,
again I would not go through that details
please study and you will be able to understand.
So, these are different examples. So to summarize,
we have introduced a very powerful feature
or in SQL query known as nested sub query,
where we can write a select from where expression.
As a part of the where predicate or as a relation
in the from clause or as one or more collection
of attributes in the select clause and it
can be used in several other places also.
We have seen the ways to perform data modification
in terms of deleting inserting and updating
records. And we have also seen how nested
sub query often may be very useful not only
in terms of performing a query, but also in
terms of performing certain data modifications
.