welcome to module two of database management
systems in this module we will ah talk primarily
about the introduction to the data d b m s
ah this discussion will span two modules that
is the current one module two and the next
one that is module three ah just to quickly
recap in the last module we have discussed
about why we need databases and we have introduced
you to different aspects of the course in
view of this in this module we would familiarize
you with basic notions and terminology of
a database management system just at an introductory
level we will try to understand the role of
data models and specific languages for database
systems and we would also outline the approach
to database design so the module outline would
be like this and ah as we go along you will
be able to follow which particular aspect
of this outline we are discussing about
so to start with we talk about levels of abstraction
a database system like any other system is
conceptualized in terms of three levels of
abstraction and the lower most level is the
what we say is a physical data level or the
physical level which describes how a record
is actually stored so thats about the physical
storage in the system at the next level we
talk about it we say it is a logical level
which describes the data stored in databases
and its relationship amongst the data so you
can any data that is stored you can think
about it as a record so if we here we are
illustrating the record of an instructor who
teaches a course so as you know the record
is a collection of multiple fields ah of different
types so here we have field to describe the
i d identifying number or shrink of an instructor
we have the name of the instructor the name
of the department the salary and so on so
this logically says this is the entity this
is a record or this is the structure of a
record that i want at a at a logical way
so this call in contrast to the physical level
logical level is not concerned particularly
with how that these data how this string the
number and all that will be actually stored
and how these multiples of hundreds and thousands
of records will actually be stored so that
they can be efficiently used but we are just
concerned with the logical view that i should
be able to deal with records as they are ah
as a third level which is it can say the topmost
level is called the view level where the application
program tries to view the data and when the
application program tries to view the data
it deals with the the details that it needs
to and rest of the details are usually hidden
from this view for example if here we talked
about the university database in the last
module so if you are talking about the university
database and then you are a student and you
are when you access the database you should
be able to see what all courses you are enrolled
in or where is that course being held who
is the instructor of that course and so on
but you should not be able to access or see
the view of what is the instructors salary
or for that matter what is a ah what are the
grades that are obtained to by different students
in different courses and so on whereas an
instructor may be able to view the performance
of the students in multiple different courses
particularly the ones that he or she is involved
in evaluation and but she again may not be
allowed to check the salary of other instructors
so view level is is a is a high level where
of abstraction where you try to ah provide
the information about the data in terms of
what the application needs what the users
of that application need but you do not actually
deal with the details of all the records that
the logical level has so these are three levels
form the basic structure of a database system
architecture of a database system as you can
see the physical level using that a logical
level of records are formed physical level
typically is in terms of database files is
binary in nature the organization of those
files the logical level deals with the records
and the different fields of the records the
schema of the database and so on and the view
level is something which is constructed from
the logical level in terms of different views
that the different applications need i am
i am sure at this stage you may not understand
the whole of these levels and their implications
but this is just to give you an idea of the
existence of three levels and the need to
deal with the three levels and as we go along
we will see that we will refer to these levels
more and more and discuss about the specific
aspects of those next
let us talk about schema and instance we will
very regularly keep on referring about schemas
an instance the schema is in s in very simple
terms say if we talk about first a logical
schema it is a is a way a certain data ah
needs to be organized it is a plan for organizing
data so if we if you can draw a parallel then
say when a building is constructed a plan
is prepared and according to that plan several
buildings in a in a say residential complex
may be constructed so there is a difference
between the plan which gives you the layout
of where different rooms should be where there
is a staircase where is the courtier and so
on and the actual building when or the group
of buildings which are constructed so the
schema primarily talks about what is the plan
to organize the data so if we talk about a
customer schema it has multiple different
fields it should talk about the name of the
customer i d of the customer its account possibly
the other i d the mobile number and so on
so the fact that these the fields need to
be ah need to be present for describing a
customer forms a customer schema whereas when
we talk about a specific schema of account
ah that the customer holds with a bank ah
then we need the account number account type
interest rate minimum balance the current
balance and so on these are the fields of
information that we need and we need to know
what is the type of every such field and all
those and those kind of information from the
schema information and again ah in line with
the abstractions of physical logical and view
as we did schema also can be at a logical
schema which is corresponding to the logical
level of abstraction and we may also have
a physical schema which tells actually how
the data is ah physically organized in the
database what are the different database files
how they are indexed and so on
so all these information which we can say
is kind of a metadata information these are
this is not actually that it is not the customer
schema is not saying who the customers are
the account schema is not saying what are
the accounts what is their balance but it
is saying that if a customer needs to be defined
then what is the information that you need
to know what is the information that you need
to manage if an account need to be described
then what is the different fields that are
important so this schematic or this metadata
is called the schema of a database now based
on this schema specific instances of databases
happen instances when you actually have populated
different records according to the schema
now naturally once the schema is fixed your
records will need to have values in all of
those fields that the schema has and every
value must be of the type that the particular
field is specified with so i have just shown
here certain sample instance of customer schema
where you can see three customers with their
name customer i d account number other i d
and mobile number these are all fictitious
data of course but this is just to give you
an idea of how this customer instance would
look like similarly we have shown what is
a accounts instance so you can see that there
is a ah some kind of a relationship that you
can see between these instances for example
the first customer i d ah on the customer
instance can be seen as a first i am sorry
the first account i d in the customer instance
can be seen as a first entry first record
in the account instance and so on
so the when we actually populate the schema
with different records and this is what keeps
on changing so certainly when we do operations
on the database then certainly very regularly
new records will get added some records might
get deleted from this instance and fields
of certain records may keep on changing for
example in an accounts instance very regularly
whenever a transaction is done the account
balance will get changed maybe at a certain
time the bank might decide to change the interest
rate for a certain type of account then the
interest rate field will get changed new customers
may come into the customer instance and so
on so instances keep on regularly being updated
manipulated added deleted updated but the
schema remains unchanged so change of the
schema is very rare in a database and needs
to be done only when the database is designed
or when it is being upgraded because once
you change the schema it changes the way you
look at the whole world you look at the whole
database scenario so if you are changing the
schema at a at a logical level then naturally
the ah your view will also get affected because
you are using this these a schemas to decide
how you would like to ah present a transaction
application to the user or for a balance check
application to the user and so on but of course
what do you would want is between the ah physical
schema and the logical schema we normally
would want certain independence what it means
is the logical schema is what you need to
deal with because it is linked with the ah
view that you have at a higher level of abstraction
on the other end the logical schema is based
on the physical schema physical schema is
how you are actually organizing the information
in the in terms of the binary files the database
files
now certainly you want that that logical ah
um ah schema not to change because if it changes
then at a view level all your applications
will have to change but it is quite possible
that your physical schema the way you have
organizing files and so on might need a change
because maybe it is just that you had designed
the database for ten thousand records and
you already have nine thousand records and
you would like to expand it to maybe hundred
thousand records and the physical this system
needs to be ah different you you may need
to reorganize the files and so on you may
need to index it in a different way and all
this but you would like to do that change
in the physical level without requiring any
change at a logical schema so this property
of a database schema is very required which
we say is a physical data independence or
the ability to change the physical schema
without actually affecting the logical schema
or the view level so that will be a critical
factor that will have to keep in mind so next
is ah data models so um ah data models are
a collection of tools that describe the data
because we are talking about a database system
so certainly the main focus here is to be
able to model that it to be able to represent
the data so that talks about relationships
between data it talks about the meaning of
the data the data semantics it talks about
data constraints for example it is a account
balance ah we just refer to account balance
in the account schema in the instance
now the question is will can the account balance
be negative the answer is yes or no if the
bank mandate that i can only withdraw as much
money up to which i have deposited then account
balance cannot be negative but if the bank
is giving me the facility to overdraft then
i may be able to draw more money than i have
actually deposited so my account balance might
note negative in some banks it could be that
the bank says that well there is a minimum
balance so minimum balance is five thousand
so which means that my account balance cannot
go below five thousand rupees the bank will
not allow those transactions so these are
examples of different constraints that might
exist in the real world and therefore will
be required in terms of the data model representation
so there are several data models that exist
today ah the most widely used the most popular
and most powerful in terms of a certain section
of database applications which we are we are
commonly interested in is a relational model
and that is what we focus in this course we
will have a major discourse in terms of the
relational model and a lot of things will
be developed based on that but it is not easy
to directly design a database in terms of
the relational model because you first need
to understand the real world ah in which the
design is happening
so we normally start with a less formal model
known as the entity relationship data model
or an e r model e r diagram these are commonly
called so ah if you recall your knowledge
about object oriented systems and if you happen
to know u m l you already know about e r models
and corresponding class diagrams that that
result so we will talk briefly about your
model and show you how to do modelling on
the real world in terms of the ah yeah diagrams
but then they are not actually models which
the database systems directly used they are
subsequently converted to some relational
or other model and which the database systems
will use next is a object based data models
you all would be knowing familiar with the
fact that ah objects give a better power to
represent the system which objects are not
like simple strings or numbers or characters
like that they are encapsulated concept of
an entity which can be manipulated in a certain
way so like in the real world you have several
objects it would have been nice to have similar
objects in the databases so ah quite a few
database system have been designed used which
are object based database systems so there
are models for those however we will do little
of that in this course because it is little
bit advanced in notion the other model which
has become very popular is called the semi
structured data model it is primarily in terms
of x m l um i am sure all of you would be
familiar with the basics of x m l which is
extensible mark up language in which you can
create use tags and use different mark ups
to describe the data you can say this is the
field and this is the value kind of and this
is become a very nice way to represent the
data and x m l or the semi structured models
are particularly useful today to exchange
data between different systems i may be ah
using a my s q l kind of database system my
friend may be using an oracle system and we
need to exchange data tables between these
two ah these two systems will represent the
data in the in physical schema which are not
may not be compatible
so we can represent both of them in terms
of x m l models convert the data so i convert
the data into x m l give it to my friend and
my friend can import from that x m l into
the database so it is a x m l is a data model
which is frequently used in terms of data
exchanges then there are several other models
like the network model hierarchical model
which used to be very popular in the early
days of database systems before relational
model came into force ah they are they still
exist in terms of the some of the databases
and some of the newer emerging big data databases
actually we have started using this old concept
in a new way again so this is a overall set
of data model so here i am just showing an
example of a relational model data which is
simply looks like a table so you can see that
on top row in the blue e are the names of
the different fields which describe the schema
it says that it has an i d it has a name it
has a departments name it has salary they
are trying to describe a a particular instructor
and then a whole lot of records rows in that
table which are every row individually is
a particular ah data entry or a record so
columns are attributes and rows are records
that the relational model described ah some
more of that the instructor table along with
the department table so the table below describes
details of a department
so that has its own schema and the individual
records we have of course in similar instances
already in terms of the customer and accounts
instance that we have just discussed a couple
of while ago ah let me introduce these two
terms d d l and d m l d d l talks about data
definition language so what the concept were
is what we are trying to say is certainly
we have a schema and we have instance so we
need certain language constructs to be able
to define a schema and certain other language
constructs to be able to manipulate the data
in that schema or they are basically manipulate
the instances so d d l is the language or
part of the language which is used to define
and manipulate the schema of a database that
is why schema is is a way to define a database
so it is called a data definition language
so you can define that i have i will am going
to have a table ah called instructor which
will have four different fields each having
certain types of data so it says that the
i t will be a i d will be a five character
data the name would we would have a variable
length because you cannot say that the name
will be of a fixed length but it will be a
variable length that is what varchar is but
the length will not exceed twenty and similarly
salary will be a numeric data with up going
up to eight figures and having a ah decimal
part having two parts
so this way of defining the schema in terms
of the different attributes and their types
or columns in the table or trying to define
the structure of that table is a main issue
of the data definition language so the data
definition language compiler who generates
a set of tables in the data dictionary where
the data dictionary ah basically contains
metadata as i said the schema is is nothing
but a metadata about the database tables so
which will have the database schema it will
have different integrity constraints it could
say that well ah the account balance cannot
be negative or account balance cannot be less
than the minimum balance so these are different
integrity constraints it could say that this
is the primary key we will talk more in more
depth in terms of what is key and it could
also specify the authorization as to who is
allowed to access which part of the data and
so on that is these all are part of the schema
definition and forms the d d l of the language
in contrast the data manipulation language
is a language for accessing and manipulating
the data organized so it is for access update
addition of new records deletion of existing
records and so on and very commonly we will
refer to the data manipulation language as
a query language because this is what you
want to know what exists in the database so
the query language will be designed they are
designed primarily in in one of the two ways
one group of languages is known as a pure
language they are more mathematical in nature
they have a formal basis that can you can
prove that whatever do you do in these languages
are correct and will give you the correct
result
so they are different ah languages based on
the relational model they are called relational
algebra tuple relational calculus domain relational
calculus and so on of these three we will
in this course deal only with relational algebra
there are mathematical proof which show that
whatever you can do in relational algebra
you can do it in tuple relational calculus
and vice versa similarly whatever you can
do in relational algebra you can do in domain
relational calculations one in one sense that
these languages are equally powerful the same
thing can be done in any one of them but we
will just take the simplest of them and study
here in terms of the relational algebra but
these are more mathematical representations
are not easy to write as a program so normally
we will use certain commercial query language
which is called s q l for most of our applications
and we will do the coding in that so s q l
which is a most widely used commercial language
and mind you this is not a turing equivalent
language which means that everything that
can be that need to be computed cannot be
computed in s q l there are certain computations
which s q l cannot do ah it is a limitation
is a restricted language so of an s q l is
used in conjunction with some common high
level programming language like c or c plus
plus and so on
so whatever is there can be done in s q l
in terms of data manipulation will be done
in terms of the relational model but there
could be additional logic that needs to be
built in in terms of the ah high level language
so application programs are typically written
through them so we can do this through a process
of embedding that is put in s q l as a part
of a c program or use certain ah libraries
which can actually take a query from c and
fire it on the s q l database so we will see
how to do this in in the course of time ah
coming to the database design aspect ah the
this is a process through which the databases
need to be designed and certainly the first
part of the design is the logical design where
you want you need to identify what are the
schemas and you know what are the constraints
that apply what is authorization required
and first set of decisions those are related
to the business as we say business means it
is basically comes from the domain so it is
if i am doing a university database the business
decisions will come in terms of you know i
have courses students instructors and the
instructor teach courses can an instructor
teach multiple courses can a course be taught
by multiple instructors these kind of business
decisions are are critical for the database
design and then there is a whole set of computer
science decision or the data based decisions
ah to decide as to if this is the kind of
business information that you want to keep
in the database then what is the kind of relation
what is the kind of schemas that we should
use what are should be the attributes which
attribute should be of what type what should
be strain what should be numbers and so on
so these are formed the basis of the physical
logical design and of course we then need
a physical design which decides on the physical
layout of the data what are the different
database files how they should be indexed
and so on so here we are showing an example
table so it has multiple fields it shows the
instructors expanded form of the instructor
table you saw earlier it is expanded with
the departments name and the building in which
it is housed so if you look carefully that
this is this certainly comes from the business
decision that you need to know the department
to which an instructor belongs and certainly
you need to know the building in which that
that department exists so knowing the department
of the instructor and the building of where
that department is are critical but the question
is is this a good design is this so we will
discuss as to when why this is a good this
may not be a good design to represent the
data so in this module we have taken you through
the basic notions and terminology of database
management systems highlighting primarily
the levels of abstraction the schema an instance
the basic data models the languages that you
need d d l d m l and the commercial s q l
language and we have also tried to give you
a glimpse of the approach that is required
in terms of the database design will elaborate
on this more in the second part of our introduction
to d b m s which will be taken up in module
three