Bottom of Form
Welcome to module 38 of database management
systems, in this module and the next we will
talk about query processing and optimization
of that in the current module we will talk
about query processing.
So, in the last ah module we had done talked
about ah database recovery.
And ah now we will try to understand the overall
flow of processing queries. So, if I fire
a query like ah select from where how will
that actually access the database ah files
the b trees and indexes and so, on and compute
the result is what we would like to discuss.
And a query can be processed in multiple ways
giving rise to different kinds of costs in
terms of the time required for processing
that query. So, we will define certain measures
of query cost and then we will ah take a quick
look into a set of sample algorithms for processing
ah simple selection operation, sorting, joint
operation and few of the other operations
like aggregation.
So, first let us so, these are the ah topics
to talk about and first we will take a look
at the overall query processing algorithm.
So, this is the flow so, this ah is a way
the a query will get processed. So, here what
you have is ah this is where the input query
comes in naturally it is written in terms
of a in terms of SQL which is kind of a programming
ah language.
So, you need a parser and translator. So,
the it is parse translated and it is translated
into a relational algebra expression as we
have shown at the very beginning discussed
at the very beginning that SQL is basically
ah derived or developed based on relational
algebra. So, corresponding to every SQL query
there is a one or more relational algebra
expression. So, you express in terms of that,
then you optimize you try to see how ah the
relational algebra expression can be made
efficient and ah to optimize this we might
use some information about the statistics.
Statistics in terms of we might use ah the
information past history information of ah
say what is ah the what are the attributes
on which more often the ah where conditions
are port we might want to use statistics like
how many ah tuples actually exist in the relation
right now and so, on. And based on that we
will decide on an execution plan, execution
plan is how we actually want to what are the
actions that we actually want to do in terms
of accessing ah the the different indexes
and the different ah b plus tree nodes to
evaluate the query and that is the job of
the ah evaluation engine is you can see that
it will access the data for that and finally,
out of that the query output will be generated.
So, in the this module and the next we will
ah take a quick look into so, it is ah glimpses
of these steps one by one and try to understand
how query processing and optimization can
happen.
So, beyond a parsing and translation there
is evaluation as we have ah talked of.
Now, if we ah take in terms of ah say a query
a where ah select from where clause has been
translated. So, for example, if ah this is
ah we can we can simply write out say if we
have select and what are we selecting here?
We are selecting salary and where are we selecting
it from? The from is instructor and under
what conditions are we doing that? Where,
where is salary is less than 75000.
So, if you had a query like this then you
know then it will be ah it will get translated
to some kind of a relational ah algebra expression
like this where you do a selection on the
ah salary and then you do ah you do a projection
on the salary and you do a ah selection based
on that condition. Now, it is ah also clear
to say that ah this particular relational
algebra expression can be equivalently written
by swapping that these 2 conditions, that
is we can first do a selection and then do
the projection they are actually equivalent
and that could be multiple equivalents.
So, we ah know that given a query there could
be multiple relational algebra expressions
and then the relational algebra expression
the operations can be evaluated also in one
of the by using one or more different algorithms.
So, basically what you have you have different
options given a SQL query, you have different
possible relational algebra expressions that
are equivalent given every relational algebra
expressions you have ah different strategies
different algorithms to actually execute and
evaluate that. And ah we would like to based
on these we would like to annotate the expression
we would like to mark out as to whether ah
from the above to say whether we first project
on salary and then do the selection or we
first do the selection on salary less than
75000 and then project.
And with that annotation we will build up
a total evaluation strategy which is known
as the evaluation plan and ah for example,
here we can have different strategies like
we can use an index on salary and ah if you
use that that will be ah it will be pretty
efficient to find ah tuples which satisfy
salary less than 75000 or ah we can ah scan
the whole relation and discard all those instructors
for which salary is greater than equal to
75000. So, there could be different ways in
which we can do this evaluation and that is
what optimally has to be decided in every
case.
So, in terms of query optimization out of
all these equivalent evaluation plans we try
to choose the one that ah gives some minimum
cost the lowest cost ah evaluation.
So, the cost will have to be estimated based
on certain statistical information from the
ah database catalog for example, number of
ah tuples in the relation, the size of the
tuples, ah the attributes on which frequently
condition are tested and so, on ah. So, this
is what ah we would ah in totality try to
understand out of that in this module we will
first define what is the measures of cost
and look at the algorithms for evaluating
some of the relational algebra operations
and then you can combine them to do bigger
operations and in the next module we will
talk about optimization.
So, first let us see how we define the cost
because if we want to say that ah we can do
it you say in 2-3 different ways, evaluate
the same query in 2-3 different ways then
we must assess as to what is the best way
of doing it the best way is whatever gives
us the least cost.
So, measures of cost will be in in absolute
terms it is in terms of the elapsed time how
much time does it take and there could be
many factors which ah ma dictate that because
in terms of evaluating this we will have to
access the disk. So, access time of the disk
will be involved, the computing time in CPU
may be involved even some network communication
may get involved.
So, out of these if we assume that there is
no network communication cost ah just for
simplicity that is everything is connected
to a very you know high speed ah network then
between the disk cost and the accesses and
the CPU processing cost the disk access is
a predominant cost. Because ah ah and it is
relatively easy to estimate that because as
we have looked at the storage structure we
know that ah it is a ah typically a magnetic
disk which where the head has to move to the
correct cylinder to find the block where the
records can be ah located. So, there is this
process is called the seek.
So, we will need to ah find out how many estimate
how many seek operations we need and multiply
that by the average cost of seeking a block.
Similarly, while we are reading that we need
to estimate how many blocks to read and average
ah cost to read a block, number of blocks
to write average cost to write the block,
cost to write the block is ah usually greater
than the cost to read actually often when
we ah write a write some data after writing
we also usually read it back to make sure
that the right was successful.
So, these are the typical cost factors that
will dominate. So, if we say that ah if we
just count the number of block transfers and
the number of seeks and ah if ah the time
to transfer one block is t T and time for
seek is ah one seek is t S, then the cost
of transferring b blocks doing and doing S
seek will be given by this expression you
can easily understand that.
So, every block transfer is t T and the b
blocks being transferred. So, this is the
transfer cost and if there are S number of
seeks and every seek time is t S, then this
is the seeking cost and adding them together
we get the total cost of ah seek and transfer
ah. For simplicity we will ignore ah the CPU
cost and we will also for now ah not consider
the cost of finally, writing the result back
to the disk we will simply ah check as to
what will it take to actually compute the
result.
So, there are also it has to be noted that
there are also several algorithms to reduce
the disk I/O ah we can do that by using extra
buffer space for example, one block has been
read in and we are just using one record of
that if in the next operation we have to use
some record which is already existing in that
block and ah if that block is maintained in
that buffer then we do not need to go back
to the disk and actually read the ah block
once again.
So, the more of the buffer space that we can
ah provide naturally the performance would
become better, but certainly; that means,
that the memory required for keeping the buffer
would be higher and ah it is also often ah
difficult to decide as to ah I mean estimate
a query as to if I am looking for a particular
block whether it is already there in the buffer.
So, that the I/O can be avoided or ah it needs
to be actually read back from the disk, but
these are some of the you know cost measures
that ah are used ah in a more sophisticated
cost function, but we will simply use the
seek and read cost from the disk in terms
of blocks to estimate our ah cost of the different
operation. So, let us ah look at ah sample
algorithms for ah different basic SQL operation.
So, the first and most common SQL operation
is selection as you all know.
So, the selection for selection we discuss
in multiple algorithms for different ah situations
the first ah algorithm is here we are calling
it as algorithm A1 is a linear search. So,
what we do we just ah need to do some selection.
So, we scan the say we are looking for a result
ah of couple of records and or a single record
then we just scan the file from one end to
the other we look for all the records and
ah check whether they satisfy the selection
condition.
So, the cost ah for that would be ah ah b
r block transfers if there are ah if ah b
r is a number of blocks containing records
from relation r then b r blocks have to be
read and one seek has to happen. Now, if the
selection is on a key attribute ah and we
can stop find on finding the record and on
the average we can expect that ah we will
be able to find it by having read half of
the record. So, b r by 2 block transfers plus
1 seek so, if I if I write it in the notation
that we had used earlier this b i by 2 into
the transfer cost plus one seek cost.
So, this should give us the cost of the ah
finding out the particular record from any
ah file ah if we are doing a linear search
if we are doing a linear scan. So, the advantage
of this is it can be applied irrespective
of the condition, ordering of the records
ah whether or not the index is available and
so, on.
So, this could be the fallback ah in any case
when we want to do that and ah just you may
note that ah in memory when we search we say
that we will keep the data sorted and binary
search ah is efficient, but that is not the
case for us ah here because as you know the
data is not stored sequentially it is in terms
of a tree structure. So, when the index is
available we will do the index based search
otherwise ah we will have to do some kind
of a linear scan alone. So, this was the first
algorithm that ah we can think of.
Now, if now let us assume that it is the situation
is such that we have some index on the b tree
b plus tree that we are using to going to
do the selection on and let us assume that
h I is the height of that b plus tree. So,
the second algorithm ah is is good if we are
using a primary index and we are looking for
equality on a key that whether it matches
certain key. So, what will have to do we we
know that in b plus t ah if the if the height
is h I then we will be able to find the leaf
node surely by h I number of ah block transfers
because ah we will be a h I is the height
of the tree.
So, this is a number of ah nodes ah the number
of blocks that we will need to read. So, if
each one of that will take a transfer time
plus a seek time because they are not consecutively
located. So, everything they will have to
be ah will need to seek them. So, that will
be h I times t T plus t S and we will need
one additional block transfer to actually
get the data ah get the record read it. So,
that will give us cost that we have shown
here ah.
In a variant of this algorithm A3 we may be
using a primary index, but we are looking
for equality on a non key. So, if you are
looking for equality on a non key since is
a non key then certainly in the result ah
we may have multiple records, but the records
will be on consecutive blocks because we are
using a primary index.
So, if b is the number of blocks containing
matching records then ah we will ah need to
have say this is a cost to find out the the
first one and ah then they from consecutively
they are on. We will need to locate the next
record and the b blocks for transferring all
the matching records this is the kind of cost
that will need to go through natural you can
see that in these cases all these cost expressions
are better than what we were getting in terms
of doing a linear search.
If we look into a few of the other situations
for example let us say instead of primary
index if I have a secondary index and you
are looking for a equality or non key ah ah
then you can retrieve a single record if the
search key is candidate key. If it is a candidate
key then we know that even though it is not
a primary key, but certainly 2 tuples can
never ah match on them and still exist. So,
it is a candidate key we will need to have
we will get only a single record and ah therefore,
this is a cost expression that you will get,
but if it is not a candidate key then there
could be multiple records ah that will have
to be finally, retrieved.
So, if there are n records then first you
will need h I to locate ah the first record
and ah times of course, h I times the transfer
plus seek cost and if there are n records
then you will need to ah every time each one
of them because they are on secondary index
and non key. So, you have to retrieve them
one by one and every time you will need a
search you will need seek and transfer time
and this can as you can understand could be
quite expensive if n turns out to be large
which will often be the case ah.
We can implement different this is a very
common selection condition where ah we have
these kind of conditions that we are selecting
on ah less than equal to or greater than equal
to kind of condition.
So, ah we can implement this using a linear
file scan or by using indices in in a certain
way using indices we will certainly have a
better performance. So, ah if we have a if
we have a primary index and we are using comparison
then what we will we can certainly decide
is we need to find out the first tuple which
matches this condition that is ah a is greater
than equal to v and then once we have found
that in a primary index ah the following ones
will all be ordered in that manner. So, I
can scan sequentially from there and ah get
them.
So, finding the first one will give me ah
finding the first one will give will take
this cost because I am doing a search on the
primary index and then if there are b blocks
containing the result records then this is
the cost that will need. Whereas, ah we can
do something different also we can just start
ah sequentially based on the primary index
from the beginning and ah check for the till
we get a tuple which is greater than v and
then we ah do not use the index we can simply
ah we know because these are all ordered in
terms of the primary index. So, that will
be the ah search result that can be easily
produced. So, here we are using a linear scan
and that itself will give a good result.
But if we are doing a similar operation based
on a on a secondary index we are doing composition
on a secondary index then we will again use
the index to find the first index entry greater
than equal to the key value and then scan
the index sequentially.
So, we will get a cost which is similar to
what we saw earlier and ah in the other condition
we can just scan the leaf pages of index finding
the pointers to record still the first entry
so, we are doing more a sequential one. So,
in either case retrieving records that are
pointed to requires I/O for each record because
they are on a secondary index. So, they are
not necessarily consecutive and residing on
the on the same block. So, they may be all
distributed across different blocks and ah
in such cases it may turn out that actually
is doing a simple linear scan may turn out
to be cheaper.
Often we have ah select conditions which are
conjunction. So, it could be conjunctive select
and may be using only one index in that case
it depends on if there are n conditions then
we will need to depending on the combination
of this condition theta n and the algorithms
that we have seen here we can evaluate as
to which strategy will give that ah least
cost for this condition ah.
So, we will do the access based on that and
then once we have accessed that tuple then
we will try out the other conditions on the
tuples that have been fetched into the memory
buffer. You can also do conjunctive ah selection
using composite index we can there are depending
on the attributes involved in theta 1, theta
2, theta n we may have a multi key index and
that decision of course, as to whether I have
a multi key index or what is that multi key
index is of course, dependent on the earlier
statistics.
But if we have some multi key index which
are appropriate composite index then we can
use that and more directly get the result
which will be more efficient. Or we can do
conjunctive selection by intersection of identifiers
which require indices with record pointers
and will use corresponding index for each
condition and then fetch the records which
is simple to understand.
Disjunction ah this that was conjunction if
we want to do disjunction then ah if we have
all conditions all of these conditions have
index on them if it is available index then
we can do something better. Otherwise if we
do not have that then it is better to do a
linear scan because the conditions all triples
which satisfies theta 1 will be there in the
result, those which satisfy theta 2 may or
may not satisfy the others will also be there
and so, on.
So, what we can do is ah if we have index
on each one of these based on each one of
these conditions then they can use corresponding
index for each condition get the results and
take their union and then fetch these records.
So, these are ah some of the so, I i just
gave you a quick outline in terms of some
of the different ah algorithms that selection
could use. Negation of a condition could also
be done, but ah it usually requires a linear
scan on the file that is there is not much
optimization that you can think of here. The
next operation which is often required may
not ah be explicitly, but in terms of doing
other operations is sorting.
So, if we may build an index on the relation
then we can use that index to read the relation
in sorted order, this is what we have already
discussed that ah b plus tree in the in order
traversal will always give you the sorted
order. So, that may lead to one disk access
for each ah tuple ah at times. Now that if
the relation can totally if all the records
can totally fit into the memory then we can
use some in memory algorithm like quicksort,
but often that will not be the case relations
are much bigger.
So, what will have to do is will have to take
ah recourse to external sort and merge ah
strategy which is a very old strategy, but
very effective.
So, just to illustrate that suppose ah sorry
so, suppose these are this is the initial
relation so, what we do certainly we cannot
ah read that whole relation in terms of memory
ah into a memory. So, what we do we ah take
different parts and say we are taking in groups
of 3 just for illustration and ah make them
and sort them in memory. So, take them so,
take that money records which you can fit
into the memory and sort them.
So, once you have sorted them then you can
these are 2 sorted ah sub lists of the original
set of records. So, now, you can merge them
according to the merge strategy so, this is
the sample merge saw strategy and again you
write this back you do the similar things
again here write them back. So, now, you have
2 bigger ah short sorted lists so, so these
are called runs. So, the first step creates
the runs and now after you have done merging
once you get longer runs then again you merge
them into a bigger run and depending on the
on the actual size of the file and the size
of the memory that directly fits in you might
ah be doing multiple such runs till you get
to the sorted output.
So, ah that is a very external ah sort merge
is a very effective strategy that the databases
ah will always use and the efficiency of that
or the cost of that depends on the size of
the memory in terms of pages as to what can
ah fit a a complete one run data. So, this
is ah whatever I have described is simply
given here in steps of algorithm.
So, that is a sort that is that here is a
merge so, you can go through that and convince
yourself that this is what algorithm is actually
doing.
And there are 2 cases you have to consider
whether your data fits into the memory otherwise
if your it does not fit into the memory then
multiple passes are required and these are
the steps of the algorithm that will be followed.
Now next to sorting certainly we have often
talked about that join is a very required
operation in ah relational database in terms
of SQL.
So, let us see what will it take to do a join
so, first we ah talk about ah so, the join
could be done in several ways nested loop
join, block nested loop join, indexed nested
loop join, merge join, hash join. So, these
are different ah strategies of doing join
we will just illustrate the algorithms for
the first 3 strategies.
So, nested loop join what we are trying to
do is very simple we have 2 relations we have
2 relations here ah r and s and we have a
condition theta and we are doing a theta join.
So, what needs to be done in terms of theta
join in the relational algebra what do we
do we do a Cartesian product and then in the
Cartesian product we check out this theta
condition.
So, the basic Cartesian product is all records
of r will have to be matched will have to
be connected to all record of s. So, that
naturally can be done using a nested for loop
so, for each tuple ah in our you try out each
tuple n s take the t r, t s pair and if they
satisfy the condition theta then they go to
the output otherwise you leave that otherwise
ah you discard that and here we say r is the
outer relation and this s is the inner relation.
So, naturally since you have to examine every
pair this could be quite expensive to perform
and the cost may be quite high.
So, if we ah look at what could be the possible
cost. So, if n r is the number of ah records
in relation r and b r is the number of blocks
in which they exist then for every record
you have to actually ah access all the blocks
of the other ah every for every tuple of relation
r you have to actually access all the blocks
of relation s. So, you get this and you have
to access all the blocks of relation r.
So, this is the kind of block transfer that
you will get you will require and naturally
you will require so many seek because every
time you have to find out you have to go and
seek for that. So, one optimization that is
very common is what you can do is if if the
smaller relation can entirely fit into the
memory then you do not need to do this repeated
ah read for that both the relations.
So, if it ah fits into that then the cost
will significantly reduce to b r plus b l
block transfers because you want the smaller
one has already fit. So, you just need to
access one relation once you need to read
the smaller relation and put it in the memory
and then you just need to read the other relation
one after the ah other. So, b r blocks of
that and so, you are seeking only twice one
for reading r, one for reading s there is
a 2 seeks.
So, here I have just ah shown a simple example
of ah computing the join of student and takes
let us say student has 5000 records and ah
spread over 100 blocks takes relation has
10000 records spread over 400 blocks then
if you apply the ah formula above you will
find that ah if student is the outer relation
you have so, many block transfer and so, many
seeks. Whereas, if takes is the outer relation
then you have so many block transfers and
so many seeks.
So, you can ah understand you can see here
that ah if you make student as a outer relation
then you have much larger number of block
transfers though you need to do less number
of seek, but ah taking ah, but using takes
as a outer relation you have much less block
transfers, but more number of seek usually
seek is less expensive than ah less costly
than the block transfer.
So, will possibly in with this kind of a statistics
if it is available then we will possibly take
takes as outer relation and ah student as
the inner one ah. You can refine this ah.
Strategy by doing a block nesting that is
ah instead of ah taking every tuple of the
relation you can take every block of the relation.
So, for every block of relation r you try
to match with you try to combine with every
block of relation s and then within every
block of relation r the block b r you take
tuple and within b s you take t S and then
you do whatever we are doing earlier, but
naturally you get a much ah better ah performance.
Because you are now optimizing based on the
block reads only you are not reading every
tuple every time you need. So, I will not
go through ah ah this ah you know simple algebra
to show that if you have a ah memory size
of M ah M blocks that your cost will significantly
decrease and, but the larger the M your cost
will come down by a factor of this M. So,
block nested loop join will usually be far
more efficient than the simple nested loop
join.
The third strategy which we will use very
often is efficiently applicable if you are
ah if your join is an equijoin or a natural
join as we have seen that we often need to
do a natural join. So, there are 2 attributes
between these 2 relations on which ah during
join the values that they match are retained,
the values that they do not match are ah not
retained in the natural join.
So, if we now assume that we have an index
available on the inner relation then every
time we go with the outer relation will be
able to access the inner relation very efficiently
because for each tuple in the outer relation
the index to look up the tuples in nests will
satisfy the condition will be found very efficiently
because they are index. So, they will occur
if through the index I can find them in terms
of the consecutivity.
So, ah there the cost in that case will turn
out to be very simply the cost of ah the b
r which is ah the outer relation ah the number
of blocks in the outer relation the seek and
transfer cost of that and then the number
of record times, the estimated cost of a single
selection using the join condition. So, we
often use the nested loop join when we have
to do equal join or natural join .
So, here is an example with the same students
and takes ah ah example. So, it is shows that
the cost of block ah nested join if you work
out for the block nested join then you have
so, many 40,100 block transfers and 200 seek.
Whereas, if you do index to one on the assuming
that the smaller relation the inner relation
has a index then you have 25,000 block transfer
and seek. So, ah this will turn out to be
a naturally more efficient way of implementing
the join.
So, these are there are several other strategies
particularly hashing based strategies, merging
based strategies which we are not discussing
here, but there are different strategies through
which you can do join in more and more efficient
manner.
Couple of ah other operations which are often
required is duplicate elimination because
ah if ah they we know that there are duplicate
records cannot be kept, duplicate in the sense
the records which match in the ah in the key
field and the duplicate will often happen
in terms of the result, they will happen in
terms of when we do projection, we will need
to do aggregation set operations outer join
and so, on. So, the first 3 we will quickly
out like.
So, duplicate ah naturally can be very easily
eliminated through sorting, they can be done
through hashing also because if we sort they
will come on side by they will come consecutively
after the sort, if we hash then they will
necessarily hash to the same value which becomes
easier to check whether they are identical
or not. If whenever we are doing projection
we can project on each tuple and then you
can ah perform a duplicate elimination to
actually get to the final result. Aggregation
ah group that is whatever you do group by
kind of.
So, aggregation ah is certainly will be efficiently
done if you have again done sorting because
if you are grouping by something then if you
have sorted on that those elements will come
together and or if you are hashing then they
will also come together. So, you can easily
do the computation on that.
And what you can do is instead of for example,
you are doing a count or you are doing a minimum,
maximum, sum this kind of all of these are
ah associative operations. So, you can ah
do it in parts that if you have done ah in
this sorted order, in the hashed order if
you have done the sum of 10 records then you
can actually do not need these 10 records
when you do the sum for the next 10 records
and so, on. So, in this manner the aggregation
can be efficiently implemented. So, we can
ah for average keep sum and count and divide
the sum by count at the end and so, on.
So, we have ah in this module we have just
given a very brief outline of ah what is what
are the steps involved in query processing
and what are the measures that ah define a
query cost typically and we have been talked
about some of the simple algorithms for selection,
sorting, join and ah aggregation operations.
In the next module we will talk about ah elementary
optimization strategies for processing of
queries.