Welcome to module 20 of database management
systems. We have been discussing about relational
database design, since the last 4 modules
and this will be the concluding part of relational
database design.
In the last module, we have seen some very
key concepts of relational design, that of
normal forms third and Boyce Codd normal form
specifically and how to decompose into them?
And how do we get benefit in terms of doing
this kind of decomposition? In removing the
anomalies by reducing the redundancy in the
design.
In view of that in the background of that,
in this module will we would try to understand
a new kind of data dependency, an additional
kind of data dependency, which is called multivalued
dependency. Which can occur when an attribute
can have can take multiple possible values,
which we had eliminated in the first normal
form together and based on that, we will define
4th normal form and decomposition into 4 NF
and then we will summarize this whole set
of discussions of relational database design,
and talk little bit about what happens, when
you have temporal data in your system .
So, these are the ah outline points, based
on our objectives and we start with the discussion
of multivalued dependency. Consider a situation
like this. So, here we are trying to represent
an individual instead of persons with 3 attributes,
man which is an may be id or name of that
person, phones and dog like. So, the idea
is that the here persons and they can have
1 2 3 any number of phones, which is true
for all of us and then a person may have any
number of dogs that he or she likes. So, both
of these phones and dog like D P and D attributes
can take multiple values and ah. So, ah if
we if we if you look at the ah 1 NF normalized
form here. So, in 1 NF what we do? We create
separate rows for them. So, we have created
separate rows for M 1 ah against P 1 and P
1 or P 2 in phones and similarly for D 1 and
D 2. So, once we have done that then we have
here, we can see I have highlighted with yellow,
you can see the different redundancies that
are arising.
Because since I have phones and dog liking
ah attributes. So, it is possible that if
phone takes 2 values and dog like takes 2
values, then actually 4 different combinations
of them are possible. But in reality, it may
be in reality it may be actually these 2 are
true, that M 1 has phone P 1 and likes dog
D 1 M 1 has ah phone P 2 and ah likes dog
D 2, but you could also have such redundant
tuples coming in, because there they are now
valid.
So, this is the situation which we try to
ah try to capture, in terms of what you see
here multivalued dependencies, where which
is row shown in terms of double arrows as
you can see here. So, man I say determines
multi determines phones man multi determines
dog likes. So, there are 2 different multi
valued dependencies in this case. So, this
multi valued dependency adds a new source
of redundancy in our data, and that is very
real in in various models of our system.
So, let us move on . So, this is just ah another
example, we have 2 different ah relations
student give the student id and name, courses
giving course id and name and the corresponding
functional dependencies in them, you can see
2 instances of that. But if we ah as as such,
there is no relationship between student and
course, but if we choose to keep them in a
single relation, say student course which
I have shown on bottom right here. Then there
will be you can see lot of ah redundancies
coming in, because ah since I they can be
in terms of all different combinations. So,
S 1 has in name A may be taking course C 1
having name C, but again the the S 1 having
name A could be taking course C 2 having name
B, you just do not know which one is is correct.
So, you can see that here again you have 2
multiple value dependencies, one where SID
multi determines CID and SID multi determines
C name. So, these are the 2 different multiple
values that you can, find against the SID
and this is ah. So, if 2 or more multi valued
dependencies exist in a relation, then while
we convert the we we convert multivalued attributes
into single valued attributes, then the multi
value dependency will show up. So, that is
the basic problem, that we would like to address.
This is another example of 2 relations, ah
where the id and child are together, when
id and phone number are together. So, naturally
ah if I combine them into a single relation,
you have a set of possibilities of multiple
different tuples. Because given an id there
could be multiple children, there given an
id there could be multiple phone numbers.
Mind you, this relation of ah isn't info is
still in Boyce Codd normal form, because there
is no dependence there is no functional dependency
that holds on this relation. So, the key of
this relation is the union of all the 3 attributes
and therefore, that being the key and no functional
dependency holding on it, naturally vacuously
makes it Boyce Codd normal form, but you can
still see that there are redundancy in that
is data.
So now, let us define multivalued dependency
in a formal way and ah . So, we say that ah
alpha multi determines beta, naturally alpha
and beta both have to be subsets of the given
set of attributes. When we say that? When
there are for all pairs of tuples t 1 and
t 2 such that they match on the fields of
alpha, this till this point it looks like
functional dependencies. There exists 2 more
tuples t 3 and t 4 such that this condition
sold, what are the conditions? Look carefully
here we say that all of them match on the
alpha attributes which is fine, then you say
that t 3 matches with t 1 in the beta attributes
and t 3 matches on the remaining attributes
with t 2. Similarly, t 4 matches with t 2
in the beta attributes and t 4 matches with
t 1 on the remaining attributes.
So, let us look at an example, gets confusing.
So, here is course ah book and lecturer ah.
So, it is a relationship of university courses
known naturally, every course has multiple
recommended books and every course has been
taken by multiple different lecturers from
time to time. So, course can have multiple
books. So, there is a multivalued dependency
here, it can be taught by multiple lectures.
So, there is a multivalued dependency here
and therefore, I can have an instance of ah
this particular relation and I am just showing
you, how to test for the multivalued dependency
course multi determines book. So, these are
the 2 4 tuples I have marked t 1 t 2 t 3 t
4 if you look into the first condition. So,
this is your alpha I am checking for. So,
this is alpha this is beta. So, this is beta
ah and this is ah. So, to say R minus beta
minus alpha ok.
So, the first condition that all these tuples
will have to match on alpha yes, they do,
all 4 of them have AHA here. So, that is fine
take at the second condition t 3 on beta is
Silberschatz and t 1 on beta is also Silberschatz.
So, they match and t 3 on the remaining attributes
remaining attributes are, if I take out beta
if I take out book it is AHA it is course
and the lecturer that is remaining. Now it
already matches on the course. So, I do not
have to check for that, but. So, I can just
check for whether it matches on lecturer,
between some checking for this rule, whether
t 3 and t 2 match yes t t and t 2 match, they
have the same name for the lecturer.
Look at ah the next one which is ah t 4 and
t 2 match on beta, t 4 and t 2 match on beta
yes, they have the same name of the book,
and whether t 4 and t 1 match on the lecturer,
this rule t 4 and t 1 match on the lecturer
this rule. So, it also satisfies. So, I can
say that this relation has ah holds the multivalued
dependency course multi determining book.
In a similar way you can ah you can ah mark
your t 1 t 2 t 3 t 4 on this and check for
course multi determining the lecturer, actually
we will we will soon state that if course
multi determines book, then it is trivial
that course will also multi determine lecturer.
So, this is ah just to ah tell you if you
have ah 3 non-empty sets of attributes Y Z
and W and then we say, Y multi determine Z,
if and only if there are these are the possible
relations. That I can have Y 1 and Z 1 W 1
in a relation and Y 1 and Z 2 W 2 in the relation,
then I can have Y 1 Z 1 with W 2 and Y 1 Z
2 is W 1, that is you can basically take the
cross of these ah to other 2 attributes and
those are r tuples, possible tuples in your
relation and ah.
So, you can you can naturally if you read
it in little in a different way, then you
can observe that since the behavior of Z and
W are identical they are switchable. So, if
Y multi determine Z, then you can you have
ah Z Y multi determining W and vice versa.
So, this is ah what is a core observation
in terms of the multi value dependencies?
So, this is ah in terms of our example, you
can now clearly understand that id multi determines
child name and id multi determines phone number,
in the earlier example that we took and ah.
So, we can also note that if there is a functional
dependency, Y functionally determines Z then;
obviously, Y will multi determine Z, that
is that is just quite obvious.
. So, we have to ah we can make use of multi
value dependency to specify, further constraints
to remove ah redundancies and defining what
is legal in a relation. And ah if a relation
fails to satisfy a given multivalued dependency,
then we can construct a relation r primed,
that does satisfy the multi valued ah dependency
by adding tuples to that r right?
Now, once having defined the notion of multi
valued dependency, we next proceed to check
how do we reason about that. So, I would remind
you about functional dependencies, and the
different rules of ah ah functional dependencies
ah Armstrong's rules, that we had introduced
the all of these of augmentation transitivity
and all that.
So, in terms of ah functional dependencies
we have 3 rules, commonly called the cat rules.
Which purely involve the functional dependencies,
first is a complementation which is a kind
which we have just ah discussed shown, that
if X multi determines Y then X multi determines
R minus X union Y with multi determines the
remaining set of attributes.
Augmentation, that is I can augment any multivalued
dependency with left and putting attributes
on the left and right-hand side, as long as
I put all attributes that I put on the right-hand
side, I put them on the left-hand side. I
may put more attributes on the left-hand side,
but all attributes that I put on the right-hand
side here Z must be a subset of the attributes
that I put on the left-hand side, that augmentation
is possible. Transitivity is ah manifesting
in a little different way, if X multi determines
Y and Y multi determines Z then, X multi determines
Z minus Y.
So, these are the these are the 3 rules which
are basically these 3 are rules that, involve
only multi valued dependencies and the other
2 rules, actually involve the relationship
between multi value dependency the replication
rule and the coalescence rule, which are between
the multi value dependency and the functional
dependency. We are not going going ah deeper
into that further, or trying to take specific
examples and show how they work. I just want
you to know that such rules exist through
which, you can define similar algorithms for
multivalued dependency also, as we did for
functional dependency like as you can understand
the most critical algorithm to define would
be the algorithm of closure, which can again
be used in the situation where I have functional
as well as multivalued dependency.
So, just ah we will keep that, in little bit
advance space of this course. So, just know
that such things exist, but we are not going
into the details of that. Finally, for a multivalued
dependency where, X determines Y we call that
MVD to be trivial. If either y is a subset
of X which is the notion we used for functional
dependencies or there is a second condition
here, that the union of the X and Y that left
hand right hand side gives you the whole set
of attributes, otherwise a it is a non-trivial
multivalued dependency and we have to repeat
the values. So, these are the 2 conditions,
if they satisfy then we know that we have
a trivial multi value dependency and we do
not want to deal with that.
So, there is little bit of ah references to
the theory given here, ah I have mentioned
that there are closure algorithms ah. So,
that given a set of dependencies I will now
generalize and set dependencies, which means
that there could be functional dependencies,
always lies multivalued dependencies. Even
a set of dependencies you can define a closure
of all of these functional and multivalued
dependencies together, that are implied by
the given set and ah we can have all those
ah parallel definitions of ah closure of the
dependencies, ah the minimal cover canonical
cover and so on.
So, I just want ah you to note that these
things have been defined and the existent
theory, but will be beyond the current course
that we are pursuing. So, it is ah now that
we have is we have seen a another additional
source of ah redundancy in our data, in terms
of multiple values and ah in terms of the
multi value dependency that hold.
So, we would now like to look into if such
dependencies exist, then how do you decompose
a relation to satisfy that the redundancy
caused by such dependencies are not affecting
us. So, such a normal form it is beyond the
third normal form is called to be said to
be a 4th normal form or 4 NF. Where you say
that a relation is ah in 4 m NF if, every
multi value dependency alpha multi determining
beta, in the closure of the set of dependencies
is either trivial, trivial means that left
hand side is a subset of the right-hand side
or the union of the left and right-hand side
gives you the whole set of attributes.
So, it is either trivial every dependency
is either trivial, or alpha left-hand side
is a superset of the schema R, you can very
well relate that this is just a little twist
on the definition of the Boyce Codd normal
form, where the second condition was identical
and only thing in the first condition instead
of MVD, you had a functional dependency. So,
when we have this, we say we are a relation
would be in the in the 4th normal form. Naturally,
if a relation is in 4th normal form, it is
trivial that it will be in the Boyce Codd
normal form, but the reverse will not be necessarily
true.
So, again the same set of ah concepts that,
ah if I have a set of dependencies and you
have a decomposed relation then smaller relation,
then I can ah project that set of ah dependencies,
in in terms of a particular subset of the
attributes and here is the condition that
is given.
So, the decomposition algorithm into 4 NF
is exactly like the decomposition algorithm
of the Boyce Codd, normal form BC NF. Only
difference being that, now you may be doing
this ah crucial step of ah to a decomposition,
for every multivalued dependency also earlier
we were doing this only for the functional
dependency.
So, now if there is any offending multivalued
dependency, which is not satisfying the phone
in a form. We can decompose the relation in
terms of R 1 and R 2, as in here which is
exactly like the Boyce Codd normal form and
then the rest of it is simple. If ah ah if
it is ah you know by by this another important
point, that you that you must note is in this
process you actually guarantee lossless join.
So, this also continues to be in lossless
join, with every decomposition and then you
keep on repeating till all dependencies in
f, in your set has been ah dealt with the
attributes in R 1 and have converted them
into the 4 NF form. So, you have a total 4
NF decomposition happening.
Ah let us ah take a ok this here, is the like
before here is a formal algorithm for those
who would be interested, to ah formally study
the steps. Ah here I am just showing examples
of 4 NF decomposition. So, we started this
discussion with a person ah relational scheme,
having man phone and dog likes MPD, I have
added I have just modified and I have added
another attribute address. So, that in addition
to the multi value dependencies, I can also
have a functional dependency. So, we have
2 multivalued dependencies like before, man
multi determining phones and man multi determining
dog like, but now we have a functional dependency
man determining address the key continues
to be MPD.
So, all of these dependencies ah will violate
the 4 NF, because none of them satisfy the
either of the condition, that none of them
are trivial and on for none of them left hand
side is a super key because a key is MPD.
So, you can see that in on instances of this,
ah relational schema you will have multiple
redundant records, in the actual instance.
So, on the right ah we normalize we normalize
by taking f D 1, take the union of man and
phones, that gives you the first relation
and then the rest of it. Then again you split
based on f D 2, you have the second relation
in the decomposition man and dog like and
the third one gets generated as a byproduct
of that, which is man and address.
And you have 3 relations now, which together
represents the original relation each one
of them is in 4th normal form. Actually, what
happens is, when you when you have decomposed
then, f D 1 in ah this has ah has ah become
a a relation where, the multivalued dependency
man multi determining phones can be checked
in terms of a functional dependency itself,
and ah that that is what gives you the multi
value dependency. And since it is multivalued
so, man and phones together ah continues to
form the key, similarly in the second one
the man and dog like is the key. Because you
just have the multivalued dependency and given
the same man, you will have multiple dogs
whom he or she likes, but in the third one
in the person address where you have man and
address you have only man as the key, because
man is a functional dependency that holds.
So, this is a simple illustration of ah decomposition
into 4 NF, here is a little more elaborate
one, again this is a we have ah I have worked
through the steps. So, there are 3 multivalued
dependencies and you can see that, A multi
determining B is not does not is not who does
not hold the condition of 4 NF. So, you have
to decompose, you decompose get R 1 which
is in 4 NF and the remaining R 2 which is
also not in 4 NF. So, decompose in R 3 which
is in 4 NF and R 4, we can R 4 is not in 4
NF you decomposER 4 into R 5 and R 6 and ah
work through that, and you will be able to
see that R 5 is in 4 NF and R 6 also is in
4 NF, which gives a complete multivalued decomposition
of this whole set.
Naturally with that, ah we will conclude our
discussion on the decomposition process, there
are there would be some more aspects to look
at and there is lot of more ah normal forms
that exist. But this is for all practical
purposes, ah a database is normalized, when
it is represented in terms of the third normal
form. And I have discussed still I have discussed
the 4th normal form, because in some places
people prefer to represent also in 4th normal
form.
So, that they guarantee that they have even
less redundancy in the data, but ah leaving
that, let us quickly take a round in terms
of the what we have done so far and what is
a basic overall design process that we should
be following.
So, again to remind you the goal for our design,
is to have a relational database which is
in BC NF or 3 NF has a lossless join due to
the decomposition, and dependency preservation.
If we cannot ah achieve that, I am I am sorry
earlier what I meant is BC NF or 4 NF not
BC NF and 3 NF. So, the idea would be I have
a decomposition in BC NF and 4 NF lossless
join and dependency preservation which may
not be achievable. If I cannot achieve that
then I go I have to sacrifice either, the
lack of dependency preservation. So, dependencies
will have to be checked using natural joint
or, I will allow a little bit of redundancy
and use the third normal form where I have
the guarantee.
Now, at this point you must wonder and note
that SQL, the language in which we are doing
the creation and update and the query processing.
That SQL does not provide any directory of
specifying or checking any dependency, other
than the functional other than the ah functional
dependency, that checks the super key. Super
key is the only functional dependency ah that
SQL would check, no other functional dependency
or multivalued dependency and other type dependencies
are can be specified or checked in SQL. You
can do that using assertions, in the in the
while discussing SQL I were talked about assertions
we can do that using assertions, but that
too is very expensive to test. So, it is not
ah not usually supported by any of the databases,
which are widely used because that slows down
your every process very, very much.
So, you can understand that in terms of your
design goals, you have ah to do a very good
job to make sure that, your functional and
multivalued dependencies are accurately expressed
in the design and accordingly the schemas
are normalized in in the proper ways satisfying
BC NF for 4 NF or 3 NF ah normal forms. But
because, while you will actually have instances
there will not be a practical way, to see
if you are violating any one or more of these
ah ah rules of dependencies that you have
set.
So, as I mentioned there are actually these
are not the only forms, there are various
other normal forms as well and ah fifth normal
form 6 normal form and so on, but it is very
rarely these are very rarely used . It is
not ah easy to decompose into these normal
forms, and by this decomposition does not
give you enough returns in terms of the reduction
of redundancy and removal of anomalies, that
people often would have motivation to do them,
but you should know that such normal forms
exist.
So, in the overall process if we look, at
I mean what we have been doing is ah there
are several tracks that we could be taking
one possible thing is, the whole set of attributes
have been generated while we have converted
or relation has been generated. When you have
converted the entity relationship diagram,
the UML or the ER diagram into a set of tables,
That is how we got our ah set of attributes
or the relational schema R, it is also possible
that we just started with a single relation
containing all attributes, ah which is called
the universal relation? And then ah normalization
will break them into smaller relations. It
could have been or could have been the result
of some add of design of relations also, and
then you convert them.
So, there are possible all different possible
tracks that can happen. So, if we have taken
the ER model track, ah then frankly speaking
if the ER model is carefully designed, then
every entity defined in that ER model will
have only the dependency which are the determining
super key.
So, ah just just recall the employee department
building kind of situation we discussed earlier.
So, an employee entity has attributes department
name and building, and there is a functional
dependency from department name 2 building.
So, what it means that in the entity relationship
diagram itself we didn't do a good job. If
we had done a good job then we would have
identified that the department itself is an
entity and therefore, would not feature as
an attribute on the employee. So, it would
have been I mean right there, we would have
if we had called it as a separate entity,
then that is equivalent of what we are doing
now taking the relation and then breaking
it down through decomposition.
So, functional dependencies from non-key attributes
of a relation ah ship are possible ah, but
are rare. So, ah mostly the relationships
are binary, and if you do a careful design
of the ER model then many of these deep exercise
of ah normalization you will not have to go
through.
It should also be kept in ah your view, that
ah at there times when you want to de normalize
want to use denormalized relations, because
ah if you have normalized and the only way
to get back ah the original view is to perform
join. So, if we of course, if you have prerequisites
and if you want to say, view or print ah prerequisites
with that title hm title and course id ah
naturally you will have to take a join with
the course, which is expensive.
So, one option could be first alternative
could be that, you use a de normalized relation,
where the course prerequisite is actually
included in the course and you you know that
will have you know violations of some of the
normal forms. Because, ah there are there
are ah functional dependencies between them,
but that will certainly lead you to first
a look up, because you have them in the same
table you do not need to perform join. But
you need extra space exact extra execution
time for update, because you have redundant
data you have redundancy while programming
on that coding on that, because of this redundancy
there could be possibility of error, because
any of these anomalies can happen and your
code will have to now take care of that.
So, it does help in certain way in terms of
getting a better efficiency, but it there
is a there is a cost to pay in a different
way also the other alternative could be you
can have a materialized view, which is actually
the joint and course of prerequisite. In terms
of performance it has a same benefit or or
the costs as you say, but ah only thing is
you will not need to do that extra coding.
So, it is better from that perspective.
So, always keep the issue of de normalization
in view, and we do a careful design that if
it is very frequent that, you will have to
compute a join then, you might want to sacrifice
some of the redundancy some of the you know
possibilities of having anomaly, and still
have a you know ah de normalized design in
your database.
There are several other issues of design,
which do not get captured in what we have
designed. For example, let say very regularly
we are we have ah returns, income tax returns
to submit and we will be maintain ah income
tax return tax your sales tax return and on
all that, and you maintain your accounts book
of transactions debit credit accounted and
so on. Now naturally, these are all bound
in terms of one-year effectivity.
So, when they come when in the next year comes,
then you need a a separate you know set of
records to be done for that year. So, how
do you. So, if you if you have such a table
where you along with the company idea of year
and amount and then how do you take care of
this situation, because one way could be that
you have all all of these you take out year,
from the attribute and you have separate table
in every year. So, you will have to create
new table and remember their name. So, if
queries which ah run across year will be difficult
to do.
The other way could be that, you every new
year you start renaming you know you do a
year where where your earnings from different
years are shown on different columns. So,
you are basically every year you have the
result in terms of a different attribute.
So, that also is not a very good solution
for a database ah it is something which is
with the spreadsheets will will often use,
but ah in terms of data which has a certain
format and needs to be you know redefined
from scratch, at a at a different time frame
in a different way, then you will come across
these issues.
Ah let me close ah with just pointing out
that, if we have a one kind of data that we
have not looked at which are temporally in
nature, that is all that we have ah said is
the attributes and their values. So, if we
put at value to an attribute then that value
is taken to be the truth for now, and for
the past and for the features. So, if that
value changes, then you completely erase that
in the database.
So, for example, today I stay at a certain
address, tomorrow I may take up a different
quarter my address has changed. So, in our
design if if there is against my employee
id there is an address given, then once I
change my quarter my address will change it
will not be possible to recollect, what address
I resided in in say 2017.
So, temporal data of ah such kind, temporal
data I am sorry just of ah such kind ah have
an association with an interval. So, a snapshot
often does not solve the problem. So, ah you
have ah you have to decide, how you do that?
Whether ah you can you would like to put some
attributes, which specify the timestamp or
you would like to I mean really have ah multivalued
attributes, denoting the different time frames
where they are ah they may have taken effect,
there is no accepted standard . And the fact
that, if you if you know that it keeps on
changing with time then your original dependencies
might get affected they will they will change
as well. So, these are the things that you
will have to take care ah.
This is another style, that many a times when
you have to say that ok. This course ah with
this title existed from this semester, a different
semester the title may have changed. So, you
can put a start and end attribute with which
specifies what is the time for which the remaining
attributes made sense a good design, but these
also have issues because, ah if you do this
kind of temporal intervals, then how do you
make sure that ah between 2 records the intervals
are not overlapped. So, you are not saying
that at the same time this course had them
X this of course, also had name Y. So, they
have to be disjoint. So, how do you check
for this ah ah this consistency of data, there
is no easy way to do that.
So, um the foreign key references and all
those. So, handling of temporal data is another
aspect which will have to be looked into very
carefully, in the design and you will need
to do some kind of design compromise and implementation
has to take care of those issues.
So, to summarize ah we have ah ah taken a
full look into the multivalued dependencies
and tried to understand what happens, when
your attributes get multiple values. Learn
the 4th normal form for that and the decomposition
into that, and most importantly we have tried
to summarize the core database design process.
That we have been discussing ah for the last
4 modules, this is the 5th one including this
and we have understood that and we have talked
a little bit about the temporal data and with
this we close our discussions on the relational
database design, and from the next module
we will move on to other aspects of the database
systems.