Welcome to the Module 17 of Database Management
Systems. From the last module, we are discussing
Relational Database Design. So, this is second
in the series of 5 modules which we will discuss
this .
We have already seen ah basic features of
good relational design. We have studied about
first normal form atomic domains and got introduced
to functional dependencies.
So, we will develop further on that to see
how decompositions into good design can be
done by making use of the notion of functional
dependencies and we will more formally introduce
the theory of functional dependencies.
So, that is all that we discuss in this. So,
decomposition using functional dependencies
is the first thing that we look at.
The first normal form of relations which ah
were studied, we look at its Boyce-Codd Normal
Form. So, normal forms are ah kind of set
of properties which is satisfied by a relational
schema and if they are satisfied, then we
have certain guarantees in terms of what can
or cannot happen in that relational schema
design. So, Boyce-Codd is a simplest kind
of ah beyond 1NF is a simplest kind of normal
form and a relational schema is said to be
in Boyce-Codd normal form if with respect
to a set of functional dependencies, all functional
dependencies in the closure.
So, in respect of F, we compute F plus which
is a closure and if I have a dependency alpha
determines beta, then naturally alpha will
have to be a subset of R beta will have to
be a subset of R, but what is important is
every functional dependency in the closure
set must either be trivial that is right hand
side is a superset of the left hand side or
the left hand side set alpha must be super
key. So, only those kind of ah functional
dependencies are possible. No other functional
dependencies are possible. If that is satisfied
by the relational schema R, then it is said
to be in the Boyce-Codd normal form .
So, if we look at ah inst department schema
of the combined relations we saw last time,
then we will know that certainly this is not
in Boyce-Codd Normal Form because ah this
functional dependency holds in this schema
where it is neither a trivial dependency and
nor department name is a super key. So, this
is not in BCNF.
So, if a relational scheme is not in BCNF,
then the question naturally is can I make
it into BCNF. So, then that process is the
process of decomposition. So, what you do?
You divide the set of attributes into two
or more at sets of attributes. So, here ah
let us say that ah we have a relational schema
which has a non-trivial dependency, alpha
determines beta where alpha is not a super
key. So, with respect to this functional dependency,
the relational schema is not in BCNF, then
we can decompose R by two sets. One is alpha
union beta take the union of these two attribute
sets and remove beta minus alpha from R, take
the difference of beta minus alpha and remove
that from R. The resulting pair of relations,
relational schemas will be in Boyce-Codd Normal
Form with respect to this particular functional
dependency .
So, let us ah see an example. So, if alpha
is department name beta is a pair of attribute
building and budget, we have department name
functionally determines building budget. So,
alpha determines beta and we have already
seen that ah it does not hold. It is not satisfied
by the inst department. So, you replace it
by taking alpha union beta. So, alpha union
beta is this ah set of relational ah this
relational schema and you do R minus ah beta
. R minus difference of beta minus alpha beta
minus alpha. Naturally if this is beta and
alpha, then beta minus alpha is necessary
building budget because if the department
does not occur in beta.
So, this set is building budget and if I remove
it from R which means that id, name, salary
and department name are retained, but building
and budget gets removed. So, I get another
relational schema which has these four names
and it holds the ah functional dependency
id determinant. So, even now if I look into
this schema R1 and this schema R2, there are
different dependencies that hold on R1 and
with respect to that dependency R1 is in BCNF
because department name is the super key,
is the primary key and with respect to this
dependency, R2 is in BCNF because id is the
key.
So, I can see that ah the original combined
relational schema was not in BCNF with respect
to this functional dependency, but when I
do this decomposition, I get two schemas which
are each in BCNF normal form. So, this is
the basic process and we will see ah depending
on the normal form and different notions of
functional dependencies, we will see how these
ah conversions can be done, but this is a
basic approach of converting a schema into
a normal form .
Now, ah the question is if ah the constraints
including the functional dependencies if we
look at, then functional dependencies will
have to be checked on different instance.
Now, in general it is ah difficult to check
a functional dependency alpha determining
beta if the attributes alpha and the attributes
of beta or the attributes of beta are distributed
between multiple relations because naturally
how do I check if they are true, how do I
check that two tuples which match on alpha
is indeed matching on beta unless I perform
a costly join operation. So, there objective
is to be able to come to designs where it
is sufficient to test only those dependencies
on individual relations of the decomposition
and with that I must be able to ensure that
all functional dependencies hold. So, it is
a very interesting situation.
So, we are saying that we will decompose,
get into a number of relational schema. Every
schema will have a number of dependencies,
functional dependencies and those functional
dependencies if they involve only the attributes
of that relational schema, they can be tested
very easily and if these functional dependencies
together mean ensure that all functional dependencies
hold that is if the closure of this set of
functional dependencies is same as the closure
of the earlier set, the original set, then
we say that the decomposition that we have
achieved is dependency preserving because
ah I can actually effectively compute. This
is dependency preserving because I can effectively
compute whether every dependency is satisfied
by checking on every individual relation , but
the unfortunate part of the reality is that
it is not always possible to achieve a Boyce-Codd
Normal Form Decomposition which also preserves
the dependencies. See if there are in some
cases will be able to do like the example
we saw ah just now the instructor and department,
but it is not always possible. So, we usually
need another weaker form, normal form which
is known as a third normal form and ah we
will subsequently look into those.
A third normal form is ah again a relational
ah schema is there and for all attribute,
for all dependencies that belong to the closure
of the functional dependencies, this following
conditions must hold either alpha, determines
beta is trivial which is a condition which
BCNF or alpha is a super key of R which is
also a condition that we say an effort or
each attribute in beta minus alpha that is
right hand side difference. The left hand
side is contained in a candidate key for R.
It is not very obvious as to why we need that.
That will unfold slowly. This is the condition
we did not have in BCNF. So, naturally you
can see that based on the first two conditions,
you can always say that if a relational schema
is in BCNF, it necessarily is in 3NF, but
not that if .
There could be some schema which is in 3 NF
because of the third condition where there
exists a functional dependency. So, that beta
minus alpha is contained in a candidate key
for R, but it is not in the BCNF form and
also you can ah note that the attributes of
ah that are contained in beta minus alpha
must be in some candidate key, not necessarily
in the same candidate key. If they exist in
some candidate key, then itself 3 NF condition
will get satisfied . So, if a relation is
in BCNF, it is in 3NF. We have already seen
that. So, third condition minimally relaxes
BCNF to ensure that we have a dependency preservation.
We will see this more later. So, I am just
introducing the concept of a relaxed normal
form here.
So, what is a goal of this normalization is
if tosummarize let R be a relational scheme,
F is a set of functional dependencies, we
need to decide whether the relational scheme
R is in a good form which means that ah it
should not have ah unnecessary redundancy.
It should be impossible to ah acquire information
by doing lossless join. So, in case it is
not in good form. We can convert it by decomposition
into N relational schema, such that each schema
is in good form. The decomposition has a lossless
join, so that I can get back the original
relation from this and preferably the decomposition
should preserve that dependencies. So, that
is what we will target henceforth .
So, when we do that let us quickly evaluate
as to we have seen BCNF. So, how good really
BCNF is. So, if I have something in BCNF should
I really be very happy always. So, let us
look at a relational schema. This is an information
relating the idea of a person, the name of
the child and the phone number and ah naturally
the person, the instructor may have more than
one phone and may have multiple children.
So, this is a possible instance that you can
see though all of these belong to the same
instructor. He has naturally you can see that
two children and there are ah this is here,
this is here. So, this is here and this is
here. So, there are two different phone numbers.
So, naturally you have four possible combinations
that you need to look at
So, now there is no non-trivial ah functional
dependency in this ah relation. So, since
there is no non-trivial functional dependency,
this relation naturally is in BCNF form because
that is the existence of non trivial dependency
is what makes a schema not conform to the
BCNF form. So, there is no such. So, this
is in BCNF form and ah now, if you look at,
but what did we see the key thing that we
saw if we just go back, the key thing that
we saw that there is ample redundancy of data,
the same data is entered multiple times. So,
the consequence of that could be insertion
anomaly. If we want to add a phone number
to the same instructor, then we need to add
two tuple because the instructor also has
two children. If the instructor and three
children will need to add three and unless
this is maintained always, then we will have
difficulty.
So, the redundancy consequences anomaly that
we are getting into , so it could be better
to decompose this to say that I make this
orthogonal. I keep the child information with
id and I keep the phone number information
in the id separately. So, if I do that, then
I can decompose it in this manner and if I
decompose that, this have just shown that
if you are dividing that table in two parts.
So, naturally these are not required, ah neither
are these required. So, these are the entries
that I get and you can convince yourself that
you can actually do a lossless join to get
back the information .
So, BCNF not necessarily give you good designs
and we will see later on that there are other
normal forms which can be used to improve
on BCNF .
Now, let us for formally getting into how
do we convert decompose relation into a third
normal form and how we assess that we need
to understand more of the functional dependencies.
So, we will consider now a little bit of formal
theory on them and then, develop algorithms
that can generate lossless join decomposition
into BCNF and 3 NF and we will also create
algorithm to test if decomposition preserves
the dependency .
So, just quickly to recap we have already
introduced the closure set of a functional
dependencies. It is all dependencies that
are logically implied by it. Now, the question
certainly is how do I give a set? How do I
compute this closer set?
So, to do this we make use of three rules
known by Armstrongs Axiom named after the
person who first observed them. So, the first
rule is reflexivity which says that if beta
is a subset of alpha, then alpha determines
beta. Always alpha functionally determines
beta. So, this is basically reflexivity you
can see is a different way of saying ah specifying
about trivial dependencies. Next comes important
thing augmentation which says that if alpha
determines beta, then gamma alpha where gamma
is some set of attributes in R.
Then, gamma alpha will functionally determine
gamma beta which is very easy to see because
alpha determines beta means two tuples who
match on alpha will necessarily match on beta.
Now, if that happens and whatever is gamma
if two tuples match on gamma and alpha, then
certainly they will match and gamma and beta
because alpha determines beta tells me that
they will match on beta and gamma is the same
set of attributes. So, augmentation also is
easy. Then, we have transitivity which we
earlier saw also if alpha determines beta
and beta determines gamma, then obviously
alpha determines gamma.
So, these are the foundational rules observed
which can be made used to compute the closure
of the set of functional dependencies. Now,
these rules as they say this is more for ah
you know understanding the theory better.
These rules are sound as well as complete.
Soundness mean that if I use these rules repeatedly
in a set of dependencies, then it generates
functional dependencies all of which actually
hold. So, it will never generate a functional
dependency which is not correct, which will
not hold and the second it is complete which
means that if I keep on using these ah rules,
then all functional dependencies that can
at all hold will eventually get generated.
So, that is a very strong result and that
is what leads to say the following example.
So, when we are trying to ah compute the functional,
the closure of the function set of functional
dependencies here. So, there are six attributes
in the set. There are six different functional
dependencies and ah we identify some members
of the closure. For example, ah we can see
that A functionally determines B and B functionally
determines H. So, transitivity clearly show
that A will functionally determine H, very
clear. So, in the closure that must be there.
Similarly, we can see that A functionally
determine C. Now, if we augment it with G,
that is put G on both sides, then AG functionally
determines CG and we know that CG functionally
determines I. So, if we combine these two
by transitivity, then we can get a new functional
dependency which has AG functionally determines
I. So, in this manner you can do the next
one also and you can try to infer several
other functional dependencies that can be
inferred by different applications of the
armstrongs axiom, the three rules in any multiple
different ways.
So, to get the closure what we need to do
is, now very simple is certainly we will have
a repetitive algorithm to get the closure.
The first algorithm will start with the set
of functional dependencies that we have. So,
the closure must include the given set of
functional dependencies. So, F plus must have
F. So, let us start with initial value of
F plus as F, then for every functional dependency
is F plus. This is what we keep on repeating.
Look at the outer loop, every functional dependency
that we have. F plus now will apply reflexivity
and augmentation and add the resulting functional
dependency in F plus. It is possible that
the same functional dependency gets generated
and added multiple times does not matter.
F plus is a set. It will naturally eliminate
duplicates.
Then, for each pair of functional dependencies
because reflexivity and augmentation applies
to one functional dependency only, but transitivity
applies to two functional dependencies. So,
for every pair of functional dependencies,
we check whether they can be combined by transitivity.
If they do, then the transitive closure of
the transitive functional dependency that
arise out of that is also added to F plus
and mind you more and more functional dependencies
you add, there are more and more opportunities
to apply the Armstrongs Axiom rules and newer
functional dependencies will continue to get
added, but eventually you reach a point where
F plus does not change any further and when
that is achieved, we know that the functional,
the closure of the functional dependencies
have been obtained and that is our final set
.
We can also observe that ah based on the rules
of ah Armstrong, the Armstrongs Axioms we
can also generate lot of derived rules. Some
of those are shown here. For example, if A
determines, if alpha determines beta holds
and if alpha determines gamma, that also holds,
then alpha determines beta and gamma together.
This is called the union set. So, if there
are two functional dependencies which are
the same left hand side set of attribute,
then we can take the union of their right
hand side attributes and that functional dependency
will hold. Ibviously, it is trivial to prove
this.
If alpha determines beta gamma, then alpha
determines beta holds and alpha determines
gamma holds. This is called decomposition.
So, kind of the other side of the union which
also is trivial because alpha determines beta.
Gamma says if two tuples match on alpha, they
match on beta as well as gamma attributes.
So, obviously you take the first part, you
get alpha determines beta. You take the second
part of the observation, you get alpha determines
gamma. So, that is a composition rule. The
third is interesting. It is called the pseudo
transitivity which says that alpha determines
beta if that holds and gamma beta determines
delta if that holds, then alpha gamma will
determine delta which is not difficult to
get because if this holds, then I can augment
gamma on both sides. I get beta gamma and
then, I have given ah beta gamma determines
delta. So, if I combine these two in terms
of transitivity, I get alpha gamma determining
delta.
So, this is called pseudo transitivity because
here you are adding another attribute in the
transitivity. So, often times it becomes easier
to make use of these additional rules to quickly
get to the closer set .
So, given a set of attributes we also compute
the closure of a set of attributes. This is
a second concept we have seen how to give
the set of functional dependencies, how to
compute the closure of the functional dependencies.
Now, we are given a set of attributes and
we want to define the closure of this set
of functional, this set of attributes under
the set of functional dependencies and as
ah the closure of functional dependencies
F is denoted by F plus, the closure of a set
of attributes alpha under F is denoted by
alpha plus. So, this set of closure attributes
of alpha is a set of attributes that are functionally
determined by alpha under F. So, all set of
attributes that are functionally determined
by alpha under the set of functional dependencies
is member of alpha plus.
So, the following simple algorithm can compute
the closure naturally. Initially let us say
the result is the final closure set. So, initially
we can say that result can be initialized
with alpha because certainly the whole of
alpha would necessarily belong to alpha plus
by the reflexivity condition, then for each
functional dependency beta determining gamma,
we check if beta is a subset of the result.
If beta is a subset of the current set of
attributes that form result which mean that
alpha functionally determines beta, it will
have to because result is the set of all attributes
that alpha functionally determines. So, if
beta is a subset of the result, then necessarily
alpha functionally determines beta is a consequence
of this and we know that this is their beta
functionally determines gamma combined by
transitivity.
So, I know alpha functionally determines gamma.
If function alpha functionally determines
gamma, then it must get into the result and
this is exactly what the statement is saying
that take result and add alpha, add gamma,
the set of attributes gamma to the result.
How long should you do that? Naturally you
will do that as long as over a full iteration
of functional dependencies in F, if there
is no change to the result, then you know
that all future iterations will have no change.
So, you reach a fixed point and you declare
that the closure of the set of attributes
have been obtained.
Now, this closure information is very ah interesting
and we just show an example here based on
the same set of attributes and same set of
functional dependencies.
So, we are trying to find the closure of the
set of attributes AG. So, AG plus initially
it will be AG. Now, ah since A functionally
determines C, so given that I can say that
C will get included in this set in the same
iteration. If I look at A functionally determines
B, so B will get included in this set. So,
after this first iterative loop I will have
the result as ABCG. If ABCG is there and I
am looking at the next iteration, then CG
functionally determines H. So, H comes into
the set because CG is a subset of that I comes
into the set because CG functional determines
I and at this point, it eventually ends in
this case. In this particular example, you
can see that all attributes have got included.
So, you can see that it immediately gives
you another information as a byproduct of
the closure that closure of AG is all attributes
which mean that AG is a key. It has to be
a key because AG functionally determines all
attributes now.
So, what is the meaning of AG plus being this?
So, if the meaning of this is AG functionally
determines the set of attribute ABCGHI, right
, so we will see that this closure set has
a lot ah of valuable information in this.
So, we can say that AG is a candidate key
and ah because of this, we can also check
whether AG is a super key or not. All that
we need to do is drop some member from AG,
we drop G and check whether a functional determines
R which means we check whether A plus is equal
to R or not. We check we drop a from a g and
check whether G functionally determines R
which means G plus has to be equal to R and
by that we can easily determine whether the
set of attributes is a key or not .
So, there are several ways. The attribute
closure can be used as we have just seen.
It helps you determine whether something is
a super key. We can check for ah ah testing
functional dependencies because if we have
to check whether a functional dependency alpha
determines beta hold, all that we will have
to do is to compute the closure of the set
of attributes alpha that is alpha plus and
check whether beta is a subset of that. If
it is, then certainly holds. If it is not,
then it does not hold. So, it is simple and
useful test that can be made use of. So, it
can also be used in computing the closure
of F that for example, for every subset gamma
of R, if we find gamma plus that is a closure
of the set of attributes of gamma and then,
for each subset of gamma plus, we know that
there is a functional dependency gamma determining
S which is just is the same statement being
made in you know or in different forms and
ah the closure of attributes is a very nice
concept which ah help you play around in this
multiple ways and we will see subsequently
many of the algorithms for normalization.
How they make effective use of this closure
set, notion of both closure of ah functional
dependencies and in very practical implementation
algorithms, the closure of attributes. So,
to summarize this module, we have discussed
ah issues for, issues in the good design in
the context of functional dependencies and
in the process, we have also extended the
theory of functional dependencies and we will
continue it this in the next module to get
more insight into the algorithms that actually
work with the functional dependencies .