.
Welcome to module 24 of database management
systems ah in this module and the next we
will take a look at the storage and file structure
of database systems. So, we will start with
the storage.
So, specifically we want to look at various
physical storage medium because. So, far we
have been ah talking only about the logical
layer of the database design and now we want
to actually look at the in physical terms
how the data will be stored ah what could
be the physical storage medium for high volume
fast reliable inexpensive options for databases.
ah We would like to understand the structure
and basic functionality of ah magnetic disks,
because they are they are most widely ah used
we will try to take the glimpse about ah RAID
which is a ah kind of a good option in terms
of reliable ah databases and also look at
ah options for the tertiary storage.
So, these are the ah topics that we will quickly
cover in this. So, first let us take a overview
of the physical storage medium I am sure all
of you have ah known all or parts of this.
So, this is, but this is more for completeness
to look at from the perspective of a database
application. So, some of the the classification
of storage media done on different factors
the factors includes speed which is the first
thing the how fast the data can be accessed
the cost per unit of data you can say the
ah ah rupees per bit or rupees per byte or
rupees per kilobyte something like that.
So, which is a cost per unit of data the reliability
that is the if ah we will the data get lost
if ah power fails or if the system crashes
and ah or if this physical you know failure
of the storage device and so, on. So, what
is the reliability on that; and broadly as
you ah all know we can differentiate storage
into volatile storage which loses contents.
When the power is switched off and the non
volatile storage which ah are secondary and
tertiary storage ah where the data will continue
to stay even when power is off even ah you
have some parts of the memory which may be
battery backup which also will be non volatile.
So, in terms of the physical storage ah certainly
the ah absolute starting point of the storage
is ah registered in the CPU; we are not talking
about that because they are primarily meant
for temporary computations. So, in terms of
data the first possible level is the cache
which is the fastest and most costly form
of storage it is volatile in nature and is
managed by the computer ah system hardware.
So, cache ah typically is a ah fast ah semiconductor
ah memory that ah exist between your ah ah
main memory and ah the disk system and it
is very fast to work with then comes the main
memory which is ah which has fast ah access,
but ah compare to ah cache it may be ah may
be much bigger, but overall it is too small
to store an entire database, but ah I mean
every ah ah regularly the size of this main
memory is increasing. So, ah the capacity
of couple of gigabytes are common these days,
but ah still it is small compare to the requirement
of the databases and main memory typically
is ah volatile. So, if the power goes up the
system crashes all the data is lost.
Ah
we have flash memory where ah the data can
survive ah ah across power failure; itcan
be they had data can be written at a location
only once ah, but ah you can erase and write
it again.
So, it is not ah not like in the main memory
where you can read write read write like that
here you can write and then if you want to
write again then you will have to erase and
write it. So, ah the read is very fast in
case of flash memory which is ah almost as
fast as a main memory, but writes a slope
particularly when you have erase and write
it will be a [slo/slow] slow process ah all
the kinds of ah USB keys ah pen drives ah
digital phone ah memory that we are often
using are actually flash memory.
Then you have the magnetic disk where the
data is stored on ah spinning ah disk and
ahit is typically written and read magnetically.
So, this is the primary medium for long term
storage of large volume of data. So, data
needs to be moved from disk to the main memory
and written back for permanent storage. So,
it is ah ways slower compare to the main memory
and ah , but ah it is ah has a kind of direct
access which means that it is possible to
read ah data on this disk ah in any arbitrary
order in compare to magnetic disk.
Which is the serial device here it is a it
is kind of a I can do things in parallel at
random in in any order capacity is ah go up
to tens of ah terabytes ah ah easily and it
can survive for failure and system crashes,
ah ah because it will the magnetic recording
will still be there if the disk itself fails
then it will the data will get distract, but
such a situation is usually rear.
We have ah different ah optical storage devices
ah CD-ROM, DVD and so, on the juke box systems
and which are also non volatile and data is
[ridd/written] written optically here, ah
that is by using a laser light on the spinning
disk use a typically ah optical storages are
removable ah media.
Then you have the tape storage which ah usually
is a largest volume of storage, but it is
as a name suggests it is a tape it is a linear
device. So, access can only be sequential.
So, if you want to read the 6th record you
have to skip of a record 1 to 5 ah, but it
can be a very high capacity usually it is
ah ah slope.
But ah very large in volume and tape juke
boxes ah can support hundreds of terabytes
or even multiple of petabyte ah. So, that
is ah for offline storage.This is a big medium.
So, his is the ah basic storage ah hierarchy.
So, we broadly classify them in to three groups
primary storage which is volatile and very
fast cache and main memory is within that
or secondary storage which is an online ah
store ah which is non volatile and moderately
fast and tertiary storage is called the offline
store which is non volatile and slope. So,
flash memory and magnetic disk are secondary
storage they are non volatile and moderately
fast and they are online. So, they exist with
the system whereas, optical disk and magnetic
disk can be removed and taken elsewhere.
So, let us quickly take a look into the magnetic
disk this is how a typical magnetic ah disk
ah looks like; these are the different ah
cylinders ah these are the different ah disks
that we have and these are all different read
write head.
So, as you can see all of them can ah can
work along a ah path ah backward forward like
this and ah they can come and parallelly all
of them parallelly can read from the different
ah disks and this disks keep on spinning to
help you look at the data anywhere on the
disk. So, that is a typical ah structure of
a magnetic.
Disk if you look specifically into. So, this
is this is the structure we saw and if you
specifically look into one particular disk
then the disk is radically divided into different
ah sectors ah portions. So, these are these
are all separate ah portions and you can at
a time the head can read one such ah sector.
So, these are called the geometric sectors
and ah the whole of the ring that you can
see the cylindrical ring that you can see
is called a track. So, this is a track sector
the orange one is a track sector and ah often
we take multiple sectors from a particular
track and combine them into one unit this
is called the block of data and we will often
talk about the block of data.
So, here at the typical numbers of how these
ah sizes of this different ah units ah turn
out to be. So, the early generation where
ah of disk were susceptible to head crashes,
but ah now a days it is moved it quite ah
stable there are disk controllers which regularly
check ah and manage the; ah read write into
in terms of the sectors naturally the. So,
many heads being in parallel the data can
be written on to multiple sectors at the same
time and so, ah for doing that.
We we the we will see what is the mechanism
for that; and we also have disk subsystems
where if you need a large ah ah a volume of
data to be managed which is larger than a
single disk. Then you can connect multiple
disk and through a disk controller you can
actually read write data on to them and there
are different such disk interface standards
that you may have heard of.
We will just mentioned that these are the
typical ah storages ah the san and are the
typical storages. So, if you come across these
terms ah we will not go into details of that
that takes us into a different course of hardware
ah discussion, but these are the very common
storages for database disk systems.
Now basic question is ah for doing this ah
read write on the disk what kind of ah performance
measures we should ah look at. So, one ah
main measure is access time if I want to access
a record ah from the disk, then how much time
ah shall I need. So, this is based on two
major components one is a seek time now naturally
as we have ah seen ah that the disk platter
as a whole ah range of ah read heads which
are positioned.
So, to be able to get the data the platter
has to the head has to move forward or backward
to the right track on which the data is there.
So, this time it takes to go from current
position to the correct track where, I find
the data is called the seek time. Now, even
when it is come to the; ah correct position
in terms of the correct track it may not actually
be on the correct sector.
Because, it is at the whole track is a is
kind of a circle. So, it may be at one part
of the circle and the actual data may be in
a sector which is in a different part of the
circle. So, the disk will have to rotate.
So, that the correct sector comes under the
head which is already positioned through the
seek. So, the time to seek plus the rotational
latency the time it takes the for the sake
ah sector to be access is gives the total
access time and then comes the ah other measure
which is the data transfer rate as to you
using this then ah what is the rate ah how
many ah megabytes and so, on can be transferred
at from this. So, it that depends on a ah
besides the access time you will have to see
[wh/what] what is the rate at which the disk
can be copied from the magnetic medium to
the ah semiconductor medium and transferred.
Ah the other performance measure that we are
concerned with in the database system is known
as MTTF which is mean time to failure. Because,
database systems as you know are dealing with
persistent data. So, data has to exist and
therefore, the disk on which we keep the data
must be very very reliable. So, meantime to
failure is ah ah conceptually that if you
consider two failures of the database ah of
the disk ah to consecutive failures then what
is the time the time elapse between them the
average of the time that has elapse between
them now ah. So, if we say the ah it is typically
now mean time to failure for this magnetic
disk that we use today at typically 2 to 5
years.
So, the probability of the failure of a new
disk is ah very very low. So, it is kind of
a theoretical MTTF ah we which will be said
like this which which; obviously, in terms
of hours it it does not really make a make
a physical science. So, what it in technical
in in more practical terms, what it means
that ah if you are given thousand relatively
new disks then ah on average one of them will
fail every 1200 hours.
So, this is what ah is a. So, MTTF ah certainly
ah decrease it will it will ah decrease as
a disk becomes old. So, it decreases with
age. So, they will start failing sooner than
it is to do.
Now we have to ah basic objective is to transfer
the data at a fast rate. So, ah what we try
to optimize is a; what is called a block the
contiguous sequence of sectors from a single
track which I mentioned earlier. So, this
is what ah we will be read at one go. So,
once you access the data one block will be
read ah block size can ah range from ah 512
bytes to several kilobytes. ah If the blocks
are smaller than naturally will need more
transfers from the disk if the blocks are
larger then ah you might waste ah lot of space
because ah your part of the block will not
can be used with the data. So, with all that
consideration the typical blocks size that
ah use today is 4 to 16 kilobytes. So, you
will see that in in all our subsequent discussions
particularly with the access and the file
organization and the indexing we will consider
that a block is one unit.
Which can be fetched in one go and that determines
the the size of ah the basic information node
where the information about the ah ah records
will be maintained.
Ah this is the more details in terms of ah
how you move your disk head. So, I think will
will skip this this is more advance material.
So, to optimize the the block ah access ah
we need to organize the blocks ah corresponding
to how the data will be access. So, ah certainly
if ah the related data are kept in nearby
blocks then naturally you are ah disk head
and ah the rotation will have to be mean will
get minimized. So, ah the basic idea is store
the related information in nearby cylinders
in the nearby ah cylindrical practice, but
ah as you keep on using you may start with
that, but as you keep on ah using for various
types of insert delete and overflows that
ah keeps on happening. So, the data gets ah
very fragmented which means that the data
gets spread over a whole lot of widely separated
cylinders and so, on.
So, the time to actually seek the data increases.
So, we can correct that by doing ah what is
called a defragmentation process. So, by defragmentation
what you do is your data which is got ah distributed
all over the disk you try to bring them together
again to logically continuous ah physically
contiguous blocks. So, that their access time
can improve. So, ah databases often will periodically
defragment the file system.
ah The other way look at the optimize ah block
access ah is ah by using buffers. So, idea
of the buffer is suppose ah you want to write
some data to the disk. So, naturally for writing
the data also you will need a seek time you
will need the rotational latency then we will
have to data do the data transfer. So, if
you are ah trying to do some ah write ah you
have you can take another option that you
actually write that to a buffer ah a buffer
which ah is ah in the memory in the it is
a in the a semiconductor buffer ah ah where
you can very quickly write and then ah when
you have enough data in the buffer then you
can take them in a single go to the disk.
And write that or when the disk is not actually
doing something ah ah some access you can
use those cycles to write that now naturally
if you write things onto the buffer ah then
ah it is possible that while your buffer has
some data which has actually not been written
to the disk if the power fails then ah you
will lose that data. So, parts of the data
which you think have been written actually
have not gone to the disk. So, to ah take
care of that often non volatile ah memory
ram are used which are [ba/battery] battery
backed up or flash memory.
So, that even if power fails the ah right
buffers will not be lost. So, we say that
use non volatile buffers and ah ah other ah
option that is used often is you maintain
a log disk a log disk is ah nothing, but when
you are writing ah to the disk you make a
sequential log of the updates that you are
doing. So, this kind of is a report. So, you
are saying that I have written ah this data
to this block written this data to this block.
So, if there is a failure, then ah if you
can go through the log and you can actually
retrieve ah the information of what was lost
how far it it actually worked correctly and
ah you can ah ah used exactly like the non
ah volatile ram and using the log you can
find out. So, you are keeping a kind of a
general link system you are keeping information
of this is what I did this is what I did.
So, the all this write ah information are
maintained in terms of the log.
Ah You can use ah flash storage ah nowadays
the NAND ah based flash storage is are very
common. So, here are some details on that
ah let us move on to ah understanding. So,
we we just took a a look into the basic ah
storage hierarchy and the use of ah magnetic
disks and ah what are the parameters that
control the performance in terms of the read
write in terms of the disk ah RAID is ah um
a ah the full ah form is redundant array of
independent disks.
So, the disk organization that manage a large
number of disk, but ah the view that you get
you do not get to see the multiple disk you
get to see a single disk.
So, ah by this you can create very high capacity
and very high speed and ah. So, because you
have multiple disks. So, ah you organize a
data in in such a way that when you are writing
or you are reading actually you can parallelly
read or write from multiple different ah disks.
So, that not only increases capacity, but
actually increases a throughput and you can
get ah high reliability also by storing the
data redundantly; that is keeping multiple
copies and that is what ah RAID is often ah
quite known for.
So, originally when ah RAID was ah originally
designed ah actually the I in red stood for
inexpensive. So, it was kind of a disk array
which was ah inexpensive to afford, but now
it is ah not ah particularly the expenses
is not the primary factor for which we do
go for red, but we go for red for the high
capacity high speed and high reliability.
So, the I is now interpreted as independent
array.
So, we can improve. So, now, the main issue
in red is to improve reliability. So, the
main the key idea is ah have redundancy to
improve ah the reliability that is stored
the data in multiple copies and can ah rebuild
from the copies once a disk has failed. So,
we earlier looked at the MTTF mean time to
failure. ah Now, we are look at ah another
parameter which we say is a mean time to data
loss. So, which depends on mean time to failure,
because if you are if you are failed then
you have lost the data, but when you have
failed you have a possibility. Now, to recover
the data to repair it; because you have redundant
copies.
So, mean time to data loss it depends on the
MTTF plus the mean time to repair how quickly
can we use your redundant copies and get back
the original data. So, mean time to data loss
is the actual key factor which ah needs to
be minimized and for this ah red does ah a
mirroring or shadowing that is ah for every
disk there is a duplicate there is a clone.
So, it the logically you have one disk, but
physically you have actually two disk. So,
every write that you do is carried out to
both the disks and when you read the read
happens on either of the disk usually it it
ah switches between the disks. So, if one
of the ah disk in the pair would fail, then
the data can still be recovered from the other
and the data loss would occur if a disk fail,
but the mediate disk also has to fail before
the system has been repair.
So, if one of the disk fail you get the data
from the middle disk you continue to do that
from the mirror disk you restore the ah the
other disk you may be replace and put a new
one mirror it again and. So, on, but you can
restore that. So, in between this time if
the mirror disk also fails; then you have
actually lost data, but the probability of
that is very very small. So, mirroring gives
a at the expense of ah naturally having lot
more of ah redundant storage ah the mirroring
can actually give you a much higher reliability.
That we ah expect today another ah [sa/some]
some of the other techniques ah which improve
ah reliability is ah ah bit level and byte
level ah block level ah striping techniques.
So, what ah you in the basic bit level striping
what you do is a say every byte has 8 bits.
So, when you are writing a byte you do not
write all the bytes to the same disk you write
them to multiple disks. So, you take an array
of 8 disks. So, write bit I of each byte to
disk I it is. So, did interesting concept
you have fragmenting it in a very peculiar
way.
So, you have 8 disks and every byte ah first
ah byte first bit is written to one disk second
byte is second bit is written to the second
disk, third bit is written to the third disk
and so, on. And when you ah access you can
ah access from all these 8; now naturally
which means that ah ah this ah will decrease
your ah throughput to some extent, because
ah you have to collect from all of that reconstruct
ah. So, bits levels striping is not ah much
in use any more instead you have block level
striping where ah with end disk a block I
of a file goes to the disk ah i mod n plus
1.
So, circularly. So, the first goes ah if you
have say five disks in the first block goes
to disk one second to disk two-fifth to disk
5 and the 6th again back to disk 1. So, the
ah request to different blocks can run in
parallel and ah reside on different disk and
if they can easily utilize this parallelism
to improve the throughput.
At the same time improve the ah reliability
now how do you improve the reliability. So,
for improving the reliability you use the
basic ah you know error correcting coding
ah concept you just use a bit level ah that
again two options one is you can do a bit
inter lift parity which means a single parity
bit is ah used which is good for error correction.
Usually, we know that if we use a single parity
bit we can know a single error we can detect
a single error, but here with a single bit
you can correct the single error also because
you know in case of a failure you know which
particular disk has ah failed. So, then you
can ah exalt with a ah data from the other
disk and [re/reconstruct] reconstruct the
error bit.
So, the other is naturally block inter leaving
of the parity which ah uses block level striping
and keeps a parity block on a separate disk
for corresponding blocks from n other disks
and you can reconstruct in a very similar
manner. So, by using block interleaved parity
with block striping you can really have a
higher throughput with a better reliability.
So, it is a win win situation now naturally
ah when you ah ah go for red ah you will ah
find that ah there are different levels ah
ah of read that are available today goes up
to level 6 right. Now, and ah the factors
that certainly has to be considered is ah
I mean different RAID at different kind of
cost the what is the performance ah what is
the performance during failure; that is performance
during failure is is typically the MTTF and
performance during rebuilt is a mean ah time
to ah ah to [da/data] data loss. So, including
the rebuilding and so, on. So, based on these
factors different rate levels can be ah looked
at RAID 0 is used only when data safety is
not important. So, that is not very common
ah the RAID level 2 and 4 are never used ah.
Because, ah they are they got subsumed in
level 3 and 5. So, you can ignore that ah
level ah three is also not used anymore, because
ah it ah used bits striping and ah naturally
we talked of that that is not ah that is words
compare to the block striping which level
5 uses and ah level 6 is also really used.
Since level 1 and 5 ah adequately support
all applications. So, ah the conclusions simply.
Is that ah you either use ah RAID level 1
or you use RAID level 5. So, RAID level 1
gives a better right performance, than RAID
5 and ah it is ah certainly ah ah level. So,
therefore, level 1 is preferred for high update
environments such as log disks and so, on
whereas, ah ah level one has higher ah storage
cost than than ah 5 also and ah level 5 is
preferred for applications that has low update
rate and large volume of data. So, if you
have ah very high update you go for level
one rate. So, which will ah give you which
will cost you more, but ah if you have a level
5, then you will be able to ah get a low update,
but have large amount of data stored reliably
ah with less amount of money invested into
that and ah.
So, these are ah the RAID levels ah then ah
of course, finally there are different ah
tertiary storages ah compact disk CD-ROM ah
we all are familiar that DVD ah the record
once versions where you just record and ah
use that particularly for different kind of
distribution these.
Ah storages are used there are magnetic tapes
which are ah very large volume and ah provide
a high transfer rate and they are ah go currently
they go into different ah couple of orders
of terabytes ah ah even petabytes in size
ah, but ah the tapes are not ah really very
expensive. So, we can use them ah to hold
ah really really large databases they are
good for Backups and so, on ah, but ah the
tape drives are quite expensive. So, that
will have to keep in mind.
So, ah to summarize ah we have looked at ah
different physical ah storage media. So, this
was ah I mean besides all the details in the
discussion the key take way point ah for us
here is ah to understand that ah ah primarily.
We have a a memory which is expensive and
ah which is small in size very high speed.
So, all operations that we need that need
to be done ah we will finally, have to happen
when the once the data is in memory and ah
on the other side we have all the persistent
data in a in some kind of a magnetic disk
ah in certain structure and ah that is ah
that can support large ah storage it is persistent
it is reliable, but ah it is relatively slow
to access and ah ah. So, it needs to be used
in a intelligent manner and one point that
you have specifically noted that there is
some ah unit for every disk system there is
some unit called a block or disk block which
is a basic unit of data that will be transferred
every time you access the disk. So, you are
if your design is aligned with a size of the
disk block which is couple of kilobytes ah
then it will be ah easier to be able to design
more optimal ah ah physical storage for your
files and you can speed up the whole process
of search and update that you want to do in
the database.