.
Welcome to module 32 of database management
systems, from the last module we are discussing
about transactions and transaction management.
And we have technical look into the basic
concept of a transaction the transaction state
and the issues.
In concurrent execution and in this module,
we will look try to understand, what are the
very specific issues that happen when 2 or
more transactions work concurrently we have
seen that now it is possible that they execute
in a schedule, which would not let us preserve
the acid properties.
So, we want to introduce the very basic concept
of making sure that such concurrent execution
schedules are acceptable, and those are the
notions of serializability. And we will ah
analyze different conditions called conflicts
that need to be honored to attend the serializability
of the schedules.
So, serializability is the main topic to discuss.
So, to understand serializability we make
a basic assumption, we make an assumption
that every transaction by itself preserves
the database consistency. That is, it starts
in a consistent state of the database. And
through the execution of it is instructions
in the order given it leaves the database
in a consistent state, that is satisfied in
each and every transaction. So, we can conclude
that, if we see really execute a set of instruction
set of transactions, then the consistency
of the database will always be preserved.
Now, the problem happens, and as we have seen
in the last module, that problems happen when
possibly concurrent transactions happen. And
we may execute may be executing the instruction
in an order which leads to the violation of
acid properties, the consistency in particular.
So, we say that a concurrent schedule is serializable,
if there is a there is some serial schedule,
you say what is the serial schedule serial
schedule is where the transactions are executed
one after the other.
So, if you have 2 transactions in in the concurrent
system, then if I do T 1 then I do T 2 it
is a serial schedule. If I do T 2 and then
I do T 1 it is a serial schedule as well.
So, if I have a concurrent schedule, like
few refer back to the last module schedule
3; where the instructions of T 1 and T 2 are
interleaved, then it is it will have to be
equivalent to a serial schedule either T 1
after T 2 or T 2 after T 1. Different forms
of schedule equivalence is uh is used one
is called conflict serializability, and the
other is called view serializability. In the
present module we will first discuss conflict
serializability.
Now, we make now a transaction may have all
varied kinds of instructions, but we make
an assumption that we will ignore anything
other than any instruction other than the
read and write instruction. Because ah other
operations like we saw an operation where
an account is debited by 50 or account is
credited. So, you subtract 50 you add 50 you
multiply by point one or things like that
are all operations that happen in the local
buffer in the memory, and never temporary
in nature and mostly they do not affect the
state of the database, because you have read
the data do the changes write it back. So,
it is a read and write that actually are important
for that maintaining the consistency after
database. So, that simplifies our process
of analysis to a good extent.
So, this is so, we assume that between every
read and write or read and read write and
write and so on, the database the transactions
may be doing arbitrary computations, which
are all in the local buffer and do not affect
the state. So, we can make this assumption
that our shift schedules consists only of
read and writing.
Now, we say that suppose Ii and Ij, 2 instructions
for belonging to transaction Ti and transaction
Tj. So, there are 2 transactions Ti and Tj,
Ti has an instruction Ii Tj has an instruction
Ij and we say that I and Ij this instruction
will conflict, if and only if there is some
item Q, that is some data entity Q; which
both Ii and Ij are trying to access. And at
least one of these instructions try to write.
So, these 2 instructions from true transactions
are trying to manipulate the same data item,
and at least one of them is trying to write.
If that happens then we say that Ii and Ij
these 2 instructions are conflicting. So,
you can naturally enumerate the 4 possibilities,
if both of them are reading their own conflict.
If it is read write, write read, write write
All of them are cases of conflict.
So, naturally intuitively, you can figure
out that since the write changes are value
that if there is a conflict between these
2 instruction, then there must be a fixed
temporal order between them. So, if Ii and
Ij are consecutive in a schedule and they
do not conflict. Then we can interchange the
temporal order of Ii and Ij, that will also
not make a difference, because they do not
conflict. But if they conflict I cannot make
the change in their ordering.
So, that gives rise to the notion of conflict
serializability. So, we say if a schedule
S can be transformed into another schedule
S primed by a series of swaps of non-conflicting
instructions, then S and S prime that conflict
equivalent. So, what are you saying? That
we have 2 one schedule S, and we will swap
non-conflicting instruction, possibly since
non-conflicting instructions that ah occur
side by side. And if by doing this, if I can
create the schedule S primed, then I will
say S and S prime that conflict equivalent.
But if S and S prime are such that, I cannot
transform S into S prime by just swapping
non-conflicting instructions, then they are
not conflict equivalent.
The second definition to keep in mind is a
schedule S is conflict serializable, if it
is conflict equivalent to a serial schedule,
what is the serial schedule? Just to remind
you serial schedule is one where the transactions
are happened one after the other in a serial
manner. So, all instructions of one transaction
complete, then all instructions of the second
transaction complete, then all instructions
of the third transaction complete and so on.
So, if a schedule is conflict serializable;
that is, if in a schedule. I can swap non-conflicting
instructions. And make it into a serial schedule,
then I will say that the given schedule is
a conflict serializable schedule ok.
So now let us it is time for a number of examples
to understand this better. So, we had seen
schedule 3, will have to refer to the earlier
module 4 schedule 3. Sir, no not I am sorry
this is the the this is just abstracted form
of that; not the actual one because in the
in the earlier schedule 3 we had shown all
the complete other computations also, but
the read writes are the same.
Now, that this ah schedule 3 can be converted
to so, this is where you have schedule 3,
and you can easily see that the part of transaction
T 1 then a part of transaction T 2. So, schedule
3 is not a serial schedule, but if you can
swap non conflicting instructions, then you
are able to convert this into this schedule
which if we are calling a schedule 6. Where
all instructions of T 1 is followed by all
instructions of T 2 which is a serial schedule.
So, since this can be done, we will say it
is conflict serializable schedule 3 is conflict
serializable. And just to see how how that
happens. So, you start here let me erase this
marks and start here. So, here if I look into
these 2 instructions, which are the consecutive
instructions in schedule 3 I can swap them;
that is, I can do read B first and then do
read A, I can swap read B and write A read
B, and write A can be swapped.
Once I have done that, then I can swap read
B with read A. It has become before right
I can swap it with, because read B and write
A, or write B read B and read A these do not
conflict their non-conflicting instruction.
Why read B an righty and non-conflicting?
Because they are not reading and writing to
the same data item. Why read B and read A
are non-conflicting, they are accessing the
same data item, but both of them are read
there is no right. So, I can swap so, this
is the second one I can. So, once I do that
read B will come here, and write A read A
write A will come down.
Then again, I can see that write B can be
swapped with write A. Both are rights, but
referring to different data items. Similarly,
write B then can be swapped with read A, because
they are again referring to different data
items. So, I can do this and then these will
also come up. So, I will eventually after
these 4 swaps, this whole schedule 3 will
transform into this serial 6, and we get a
serial schedule.
So, we will say that schedule 3 is conflict
serializable. That is the basic concept that
we are trying to establish here ah.
Just as very simple example suppose you had
2 transactions T 3 and T 4, and you have this
situation. Now is it conflict serializable
it is not. Because to make it conflict serializable.
I need to either swap right Q of T 3 with
right Q of T 4. Which is not possible because
these are conflicting instructions, they both
access the same data item Q and they both
are right.
The other option is I could swap read Q in
T 3 and write Q in T 4, that they are also
conflicting because they access the same data
item and one of them is right. So, I cannot
do either of this swaps which mean, that I
cannot find a conflict equivalent schedule
for this schedule; either to T 3 T 4 or to
T 4 T 3. It is not this schedule is not conflict
equivalent to either one of them.
So, this schedule is not conflict serializable,
this is the core concept. So, if you if you
go through different examples and try to understand
this at the very beginning, then in terms
of the transaction management the whole study
of transaction management you will have very
easy progress.
So, let us let me show you number of other
bad schedules, and let me a little bit more
complex examples.
So, consider 2 transactions transaction 1
here. Update an account, where the account
id is 31414 a specific account and balance
is debited by 100. So, it is debiting 100
from the balance. Where in the transaction
2, you update accounts where balance is changed
to balance times 1.005 which means that we
are giving a point 5 percent ah interest,
and here there is no where clause. So, transaction
2 actually changes does this balance change
in all the accounts, whereas, transaction
1 makes this debit in only one account.
Let see what will happen in terms of them.
So, let us first try to write out transaction
1 and transaction 2, the first in the read
write Abstracted form. So, transaction 1 it
is working only on one account let us call
it account A. So, what does it do? It has
to set the balance to debit 100. So, it has
to read so, this is r 1 by r 1 A, we mean
that it is read the subscript here refers
to the transaction number.
So, r 1 stands for r stands for read, 1 stands
for transaction 1. So, it is read by transaction
1. And what are we reading? We are reading
the account balance A, let us arbitrarily
we are calling it A. And then what we will
have to do? After having debited that locally
we will have to write it back so that the
change has happened. So, r 1 A followed by
w 1 A is transaction 1 which is being shown
on the left. So, I have shown you from the
actual sql statement, how can you make an
abstraction of the read write that we use
in terms of reasoning about the serializability.
In contrast, if you look at transaction 2,
naturally transaction 2 does not have a where
clause. So, it performs this balance update
on each of the accounts. So, it will also
perform this balance update on the account
A or account balance a rather, that we assumed
in the transaction 1. So, we model that by
saying that naturally for changing the balance
from balance times 1.005, we need to read
A if the read is done in transaction 2. So,
that is r 2 A and write it back. So, that
is w 2 A and then I assume that B is some
other account. There may be one more account
there may be 100 thousand more account, but
so far as serializability are concerned, these
are all other different accounts from A. So,
we symbolically just consider one; that is,
some other account B other than the balance
a and naturally to do the change here or do
the update here will have to read B r to be
and w to B. So, these are the 2 transactions
in the simplified form that we have to analyze.
Now, let us consider A so, we have between
transaction 1 and transaction 2 we have 6
instructions. So, we produce a schedule 6,
where these 6 instructions are interleaved.
And we satisfy the basic constraint that the
instructions of every transaction occur in
the same order in which they existed. So,
r 1 precedes ah w 1 ah r 1 precedes w 1 in
this schedule. R 2 A precedes ah w 2 A, w
2 A precedes r 2 B, r 2 B precedes w 2 B and
so on. So, their original ordering is maintained,
but we have an interleaved ah schedule called
S. And then on the on the write if you if
you look at here on the write this is schedule
S.
So, in the write we are saying, that let us
say that a starts with 200 dollar, and B at
the beginning is 100 dollar. So, what will
happen you will read? You will read here this
is the first thing r 1 A. So, 200 is read
then r 2 A. So, what happens if r 2 A is read
Again 200 is read. And then you do w 1 A.
So, what is w 1 A? W 1 A is the right of the
transaction 1. So, transaction 1 writes after
debiting this balance this is the intermediate
computation.
So, when transaction 1 writes, it writes based
on the value that it had read in r 1 A; which
was 200 then 100 debited. So, it writes back
100. Then the next is w 2 A. So, w what will
w 2 A ah do w 2 A will write back the write
back w 2 A is here, will write back the result
of the computation in transaction 2 based
on what it read in the r 2 A. R 2 A had written
had read 200, we hear and therefore, if you
multiply 200 by this factor it becomes 201.
So, w 2 A will write 201.
So, naturally E as w 2 A has changed the value
of a after w 1 A naturally the final value
of a will be 201. Then you have r to be w
to be which reads 100 makes this balance change
by 1.005, it becomes 100.5. So, this is what
we will have when actually this schedule completes.
So, if I mean just this look at what has happened,
it has I have debited 100 dollar from account
A which was transaction 1, bar and here I
had started with 200 dollar. But at the end
what I have according to the schedule is account
A has a balance which is 201 dollar. Whereas,
it should have had a balance which should
have been 100 dollar, the balance in account
B is fine. But it shows that 101 dollar more
in account A. So, naturally the bank is going
to get bankrupt very soon if such scheduled
are allowed.
So, this schedule is an incorrect inconsistent
schedule, it is a bad schedule , let us take
other examples.
Now let us ask ah what is the ideal schedule,
what is is ideally what should happen. Ideally
naturally we can have we will have serial
schedules, there are 2 transactions. So, there
are 2 possible serial schedules that can happen
that is first T 1 happens, then hole of T
2 happens. I am sorry, first T 1 and then
hole of T 2 . Or first hole of T 2 and then
T 1 . And if you go through the steps, assuming
that a initially is 200 dollar and B is 100
dollar, these are the possible results that
you see naturally. As I had mentioned earlier
also, the different ordering different schedule
might give you different results, but both
of them are correct, because any one of them
will happen, but both are consistent. Either
debit has first happened, then the interest
rate or interest rate it has first happened
and then the debit.
So, either of these schedules are acceptable,
but what we got as a schedule S in the last
case are not acceptable. So, we will call
it you will serializable, if it has the same
effect, as some of the one of the 2 schedules
that we have here. Then we will say that is
it this is serializable schedule . So, again
we create another example schedule T here.
So, what we do? We take the schedule S which
we saw was bad, and we interchange, these
2 we do w 2 for a first and w 1 A next.
Now, you see very interesting things will
happen. So now, you focus on this part, on
the left part of schedule T where we are assuming
that A and B both have 100 dollar to start
with. And then go through these steps r 1
is in transaction 1 r 2 is in transaction
2, then w 2 happens so, the interest is credit
100.5. And then ah then what has happened?
W 2 after that w 1 A so, whatever was written
here is debited and written back. So, whatever
was read there is 100 dollar. So, you debit
100 dollar it becomes 0.
So, a has become 0, and then you have the
B which goes goes on correctly. So, things
look like that it appears that we are we are
perfectly ok. So, by the first example the
outcome is same as a serial schedule one.
And so, we we might just think that things
have been good, but this is just incidental
based on the particular values. Now let us
consider another execution by the same schedule
which makes use of this this value 200 and
100.
Now, as it with 200 and 100 and we do w 2
followed by w 1. So, when r 2 A is followed
by w 2 r 2 A 100 read 200 and that 10 ah 1.005
or that kind of interest is given then it
becomes 201 . And then r 1 then you have w
1. Now what does w 1 A changes? R 1 had read
200, and from that you have subtracted 100.
So now, you have as w 1 A, you have 100 input.
And from this you have B certainly does not
change.
So, if you look into that, now you can see
that he has a value which is 100; which certainly
if you if you look back. So, 200 and 100 are
the values that we had assumed here, and you
can see that in neither of the schedule a
can have a value, which is 100 dollar as we
have found here. It can either be 100.50 or
it can be 101, but you have got a value 100.
So, even though with some data, a schedule
might look like serializable, but it actually
is not and it needs to be properly established
that serial is serializable.
So, neither S naught T are serializable , yet
another schedule U this again. So, you can
see that ah transaction 1 is happening instruction
of transaction 1 is happening somewhere in
the middle ah. With transaction 2, and this
is what you you get. So, if you if you look
back as to ah earlier case . You you will
find that this is same as scheduled 201. So,
this is same as scheduled 2.
So, again my the data it looks like that this
is correct, but we have to actually establish
that this is correct. So, we can establish
say that by proving that schedule 2 is, I
am sorry, schedule 2 is conflict serialize,
schedule U is conflict serializable to schedule
2. How we do that? We keep on swapping the
non-conflicting instructions. This is one
we start with, and we swap w 1 with r 2 B
this is possible they are referring to 2 different
data items. Then we swap w 1 with w 2 again
different data items. Then we swap r 1 with
r 2 again different data items and also, they
are both of them are read. And finally, we
swap r 1 with w 2 r 1 A with w 2 B and we
get this, and now you can see that this is
transaction 2 followed by transaction 1 which
is scheduled 2. Which is indeed a serial schedule
and we have been able to transform schedule
U into a conflict equivalent schedule 2 which
is serial.
So, we will say that while our earlier attempts
on schedule S and schedule T were not serializable
schedule U is serializable.
So, naturally all serializable schedules are
are they conflict serializable. No, for example,
here I have given. So, here what we are trying
to highlight is a schedule may be serializable,
but it may not be conflict serializable. So,
conflict serializability is a stronger notion.
So, here I have given a small example which
I leave to you to go through in detail and
understand where it is not possible to show
that it is conflict serializable in the sense
you cannot there are 3 transactions here w
1 w 2 and w 3. And you cannot swap non-conflicting
instructions in this schedule and convert
it into a serial schedule.
So, serial schedule here will mean, T 1, T
2, T 3, T 1, T 3, T 2, T 2, T 1, T 3 like
that. Any of the 6 possibilities, you cannot
convert this in a conflict equivalent manner
to any of those 6 serial schedules. But this
actually is a serial schedule, because very
interestingly even though there are multiple
rights, but in between there are no reads.
So, you can you can easily reason, that the
values have actually not changed ok. So, this
is on the basic notion of serializability.
Now, the question naturally is how do I detect,
if a schedule is serializable. So, the process
is to construct a what is called a precedence
graph. So, if I have a set of transactions,
then I construct a graph is a directed graph
where the vertices are the transactions their
names. And we will draw an art from T I to
Tj, that is my graph means there will be an
edge is a directed edge. If these 2 transactions
Ti and Tj are conflicting. So, if Ti Tj conflict
there will edge between that. And the edge
will be from Ti to Tj, if Ti access the data
item which conflict with Tj. So, if Ti is
a head is earlier, then we will draw the art
from Ti to Tj, otherwise it will be from Tj
to Ti. And we may also annotate label the
arc by the item on which item that is being
accessed.
So, this could be A so, possible what is called
the precedence graph. So, it is a schedule
is conflict serializable, if and only if it
is precedence graph is acyclic . Naturally,
if there is a cycle then; that means, that
any of the like like we have here, if there
if it is a cyclic like this then it is possible
that I can actually do a topological ordering
of these nodes, and we can find a serial schedule.
But if it has a cycle then naturally, Ii cannot
put any of the transactions on the cycle at
the beginning and put the others on the later
part things will; obviously, always conflict
.
So, we can easily these are details of the
algorithms, cycle detection can be done very
easily. Either in n square time in a simple
manner or when n plus E time where E is a
number of edges. So, the precedence if the
precedence graph is acyclic the serializability
order will be obtained by simple topological
sorting. I am not discussing what these algorithms
are I would expect that you know if you do
not please look up in algorithms book.
So, to test for conflict serializability.
The steps will be built the directed graph
. Then go through each operation of the shall,
you look at each each operation read or write.
If the operation is a write, then find so,
it if it is wi X, then find what is happening
with data this data element X in different
transactions that exists later on that instructions
exist later on.
If there is some rj X or some wj X, either
in in this was in transaction I/, in transaction
some transaction j if there is a read X or
if there is a right of X, then there will
be a directed graph age from Ti to Tj. This
is what I said earlier. On the other case
if your operation is of the from r ij if it
is a read operation then all that you need
to look for is only a right on this X on the
different transaction. And then you will have
a naturally if you if your current operation
is read and you do not find a write there
may be other reads on X then you do not add
any conflict edge.
So, on this graph the schedule is conflict
serializable if it is acyclic, and we will
do topological sort to get that as I have.
So, here what I have done is I have actually
taken a little bigger example, where you can
see that at the at the beginning here. I have
given a schedule which has ah 5 transactions.
And it has A B C D E, 5 different data elements,
and variety of read write happening on them.
So, based on that, you start with an empty
graph having so, your graph will have 5 notes
because these are the transactions. And then
you go through the schedule, you start with
the very first one w 1 A. So, a is the data
item you are looking at and then you see who
is doing it. So, you you see that well a is
read by a is here read by T 2.
So, there is a conflict. So, you will add
an edge T 1 T 2 so, this this edge gets added.
Then is to have r 2 A, and you find ok look
for A, A, A, A, A, A there is no A so, there
is no subsequent right. So, there is no new
edge then you have w 1 B, w 1 B and if you
look for you have r 4 B. So, r 4 that this
transaction 4 is reading it later on. So,
w 1 A B subsequently read 5 T 4 so, there
is a conflict. So, you add the edge T 1, T
4, T 1, T 4. You proceed in this way, you
can work it out in full. And when you come
to the end you have constructed this particular
graph which is the precedence graph. And you
can very easily see that this precedence graph
is acyclic there is no cycle here. And therefore,
the original schedule is serializable. And
what is that what is the order in which you
you find out what is the corresponding serial
schedule for that you do a topological sort.
So, by topological sort which will mean this
have no predecessor. So, any one of them can
be the first node other one can be the next
node. So, it could be T 3 T 1 or T 1 T 3.
So, let us say T 3 T 1 then T 3 T 1 has happened.
So, I can put any one of T 2 or T 4 after
that. Here I put T 4 then T 2. So, up to this
and then finally, T 5. So, this is one possible
ah serial schedule to which this given schedule
is conflict serializable. And so, the actual
serial schedule. So, if you if you do this
schedule, you will get a result which is a
result of this serial schedule which is T
3, T 1, T 4, T 2, T 5. It is also actually
this channel is conflict serializable to several
other trade rules because you can do this
topological sorting in in various different
manners, you could have started with T 1 and
then do T 3 and then do the rest. You could
have done T 3, T 1, and then instead of doing
T 4, T 2, you could do T 2, T 4.
So, you will get a number of, but having one
equivalent serial schedule. One conflict equivalent
serial schedule is enough to prove the serializability
of a schedule. Now ah so, based on that you
say that this particular schedule is conflict
serializable . And it will be safe to execute
the interleaved instructions of the 5 different
transactions in this manner in the schedule,
and we will always have a consistent result
.
So, here in this module, you have understood
the issues that arise in terms of concurrency
when 2 or more transactions work concurrently.
And very specifically we have learnt about
different forms of serializability. In this
module we have talked of conflict serializability,
view serializability we will take up later
on. And we have seen an algorithm, simple
algorithm, based on the a cyclic precedence
graph, which will allow you to ensure that
a given schedule is conflict serializable
or not .