Welcome to module 35 of Database Management
Systems. ah We have been discussing about
concurrency control, this is a second and
concluding module on that . So, in the last
module we have talked about the basic issues
in concurrency control; and particularly talked
about log based protocol, and how to implement
locking in very simple terms.
As we have seen that deadlocks of the perils
of locking I mean we cannot do without locking
and and certainly if we lock then deadlocks
are inevitable almost to happen. So, here
first we try to understand how since dead
locks are inevitable. So, there has to be
mechanisms to detect deadlocks and recover
from them. And also we would like to look
at if it is possible to create strategies
which can prevent deadlock from happening
at all. And so after having studied that we
would like to understand take a look into
a simple time-based protocol that can avoid
deadlock.
So, deadlock handling. So, system is deadlock
if there is the again just to recap the simple
idea is if there is a set of instructions
such that every transaction in the set is
waiting for another transaction in the set
and therefore none of them can actually proceed.
So, deadlock prevention protocol ensures that
the system will never enter into the deadlock
state. So, the question is can we make some
strategy. So, why are we getting into the
deadlock, because ah transactions are making
requests for different locks and those are
granted. And then some more requests come
and we come to a state where a is waiting
for b, b is waiting for c, c is waiting for
a kind of a situation and we get into a deadlock.
So, can we have strategies so that the the
requests and releases are done in a way, so
that the deadlock will not happen at all.
So, I mean fortunately such number of such
strategies exist. For example, one strategy
which is called a predeclaration which required
that each transaction locks all debt items
before it begins its execution that can be
shown that that ensures that you will never
have deadlock because where in very simple
terms you will not be able to start before
you have got all the locks. And once you have
got all the locks naturally you have every
access to all possible data items and therefore,
you will be able to proceed. Naturally, the
flip side of this is this will delay the beginning
of the transactions to a great extent in many
cases, and particularly will bring down the
level of concurrency that you can have.
The other which is smarter is what it does
is imposes a kind of partial ordering of all
the data items that a transaction and all
the data items that exist. And it requires
that the transaction can lock the items in
only in that specific order. So, the important
thing here is a is a partial order among the
data items. And the fact that you locked data
items in that order that is specified by the
partial order, you cannot lock out of order.
And if you can do that then it can be shown
that the deadlock will get prevented. We cannot
we do not have time to go into the details
of how that works, but I just want you to
know that such strategies of prevention exist.
So, the other possible prevention schemes
that we will we would like to look at little
bit more depth is the fact that I can use
timestamps for the transaction. And use those
timestamps that is which will tell me which
is an earlier transaction in which a later
transaction for preventing deadlock and several
strategies for that exist. We will discuss
two of them. First is what is known as wait
and die with scheme, which is non-preemptive.
Non-preemptive means that well in this no
one preempts anyone else.
So, what do you do in wait and die, the older
transactions because you assume that every
transaction has a timestamp. So, smaller the
timestamp, older is a transaction. So, older
transaction may wait for the younger one to
release the item. So, if two transactions
are are conflicting then the older one will
wait; and the younger transaction will never
wait for the older one, they are rolled back
instead.
So, if there is a conflict, then the younger
one in that will always roll back, and the
older one will wait. So, a transaction may
die several times before acquiring the needed
data item kind of starvation may happen, but
certainly there will not be a deadlock. Because
my a waiting on b, and b waiting on a, cannot
happen because out of a and b one must be
older has to be older, and that only will
wait, the other one will abort, abort and
roll back on.
The other is a preemptive scheme where which
is called wound and wait scheme, where the
older transaction wounds up or forces a rollback
of the younger transaction instead of waiting
for it that is why this is preemptive. So,
the older transaction is preempting the young
that transaction to continue to wait and forces
it to roll back to abort and that, but the
younger transaction may wait for the older
one. So, by doing this preemptive one also
it is possible to have a fewer roll backs
than the other scheme. So, it is a preemptive
scheme, but it the advantages it might allow
you fewer roll backs to happen. And with these
two kind of timestamp based schemes it is
possible to actually prevent deadlocks and
for that reason these kind of schemes are
often preferred in many context.
So, both in wait and die, and wound and wait
scheme, the rollback transaction is restarted
with its original timestamp. This is a very
very important point to note. When you restart,
so your rollback so you have to restart that
transaction you restart the transaction you
do not put the timestamp of when it is being
restarted, you put the timestamp of its original
time. The time when it was started and had
to be aborted and rollback. So, the older
transactions have precedence over the newer
ones and that starvation will get avoided.
So, now what becomes you are you are actually
a new candidate because you have been rolled
back in and started again, but you carry your
older timestamp. So, your your precedence
has gone higher because in wait and die, and
wound and wait in both actually the older
one has a precedence. So, by carrying your
older timestamp, you inherently bring in a
higher precedence in the system. And in this
way there is a precedence based ordering that
will naturally always happen. So, this will
not only avoid deadlock, but this will also
ensure that starvation is avoided. So, very
simple and nice scheme. ah .
So, in this you usually have time out basically
my transaction waits for a lock only for a
specified amount of time. If the lock has
not been granted within that time the transaction
is rolled back and restarted, and therefore,
the deadlock is not possible. It is simple
to implement, but starvation can happen in
the timeout based scheme .
And it is also difficult to determine what
is a good time interval to wait. If you wait
too short, then ah you will spend a lot of
time in the in the rollback and restart. If
you wait for too long, then your throughput
will go down because several transactions
are basically waiting on logs. So, theoretically
it does avoid deadlock, but ah in terms of
starvation and in terms of the practicality,
this there are critical things to decide on
this .
The second issue in terms of deadlock that
we must be able to answer is well hundreds
of transactions are going on in the system.
Now, how do you know that a deadlock has happened?
Because if a deadlock has happened and if
you are not using a preventive scheme to ensure
that the deadlock will not will never happen
theoretical proof. If you are allowing say
two phases are locking kind of protocol where
deadlocks can happen then you must know what
the must be able to detect that a deadlock
has happened and then take care of it to rollback
the transaction.
So, for doing this, we again create a graph,
which is wait for graph which is very similar
to the precedence graph we saw earlier which
the nodes are the transactions and the edges
are ordered pair of transactions. So, what
do you you put an edge from T i to T j, you
put this edge in what it means is T i is waiting
for T j.
So, if we have a a conflict, then certainly
one transaction is holding the lock and other
is other has requested for that lock. So,
what you do you put an edge for from the one
that is waiting for the lock to the one that
is already holding the lock for for the release
of the lock, and in this way the graph gets
built up. So, ah naturally when T i requested
it item currently being held by T j, then
the edge T i T j is inserted in the in this
graph. And when the release happens then this
edge is removed because T j is no more holding
the item that T i had actually required.
So, this is how this is kind of a dynamic
graph the wait for graph is a kind of dynamic
graph which will regularly keep getting updated.
Now, naturally from the description of this
graph, you can understand that a deadlock
if a deadlock has to happen then this graph
must have a cycle. So, if at any instant the
graph has a cycle then there is a deadlock;
otherwise the graph will grow and shrink grow
and shrink it will keep on happening that
way.
So, it is important to ensure that this graph
remains a cyclic which now this is dynamically
happening hundreds of transactions, transactions
are getting created, they are getting committed,
aborted, they are requesting logs they are
releasing logs and so on. So, how do you ensure
that the graph at every stages is remaining
a cyclic or a cycle has happened and therefore,
a deadlock is actually happening.
So, what you will need to do is periodically
run another process which invokes the deadlock-detection
in the graph that is it looks for the cycles,
and the cycle is there, then you have to do
some strategy to roll back about one of the
transactions, and break the cycle and then
so that the other transaction can proceed.
So, these are examples of the wait for graph.
For example, here on the left as you see if
you if I if I may point out in the left, if
we see that T 17 is waiting for T 18 and T
19, T 18 is waiting for T 20. So, eventually
and T 20 is waiting for none. So, at some
point of time T 20 will be done and when that
is done then T 18 would be able to proceed.
And if T 18 is able to proceed then T 19 would
be able to proceed, and then T 17 would be
able to proceed.
So, there is no possibility of a deadlock,
whereas in here if you look in the graph on
right, then you can see that between these
three ah they are waiting on each other. So,
no matter how long you wait this will this
deadlock will never be broken, and the deadlock-detection
system has to detect this cycling and decide
to ah abort one of these transactions and
so that the rest of the transactions can can
progress. So, this is a sample deadlock-detection
ah mechanism.
So, when the deadlock is detected there has
to be a recovery. So, trump transactions will
have to be rolled back to break the deadlock.
And so there is a there is a strategy required
to select which transaction must rollback;
naturally that should be done based on the
minimum cost that is you do not want because
if you roll back then the recomputation naturally
because you have to restart and do that transaction
again. So, you have to in terms of rollback,
you have to determine how far to rollback
that transaction. There can be a total one,
so that you roll back the whole transaction
abort and then restart it or you can roll
back to a previous point, we discussed notions
of safe point in the transaction program.
And so it is be more effective to roll back
transaction only as far as necessary to break
the deadlock, you may not need to roll back
everything. Maybe this is this transaction
is participating in the deadlock, because
it is holding some exclusive lock which it
took three instructions before. But before
that it has done 300 instructions it is not
necessary to rollback the whole of the 300
instructions, you can just roll back up to
the point where it took that exclusive lock
which is creating the problem. So, that those
are some of the strategies which can improve
the throughput and minimize the possibility
of starvation. Ah
Starvation will again happen if the same transaction
is chosen as a victim to be rolled back every
time, which the possibility exists. And so
the number of roll backs is also usually kept
as a cost factor. So, when you roll back a
transaction, you also keep a number saying
that how many times this transaction has been
rolled back. So, higher that cost becomes
then you would like to avoid doing the rollback
for that transaction because so that it does
not wait infinitely in terms of (Refer Time:
14:45) starvation. So, these are some of the
simple strategies that roll back the deadlock
recovery can be done.
So, having talked about the the prevention
detection and recovery from deadlocks let
us quickly look at a simple time-based protocol
in contrast to the two phase locking protocol
we had earlier. This protocol does not lead
to deadlock. So, what you do in here is each
transaction is issued a timestamp when it
enters the system. So, hold at the transaction,
less is the value of the timestamp so that
is a simple. So, time goes in the increasing
order.
Now, the protocol manages a concurrent execution
such that timestamps determine they themselves
will determine the serializability order,
they will determine in which order the transaction
should occur. And for that for each data item
two timestamp values are maintained; one is
a right time-stamp on the data item queue,
another is a read timestamp. So, this is the
latest read write and read times for the data
item. So, w timestamp Q is the largest time
stem of any transaction that executed a write
Q successfully. So, naturally what it means
the largest timestamp means the latest write
that has happened. Similarly, it keeps it
latest read.
Now, using that you build up this protocol,
so it is again looks only at conflicting read
and write operations, and they are executed
in timestamp order. So, let us suppose that
let us consider the case of read. So, a transaction
T i has issued a read. Now, if that the timestamp
of T i is less than equal to W-timestamp Q
which means that W times stamp Q is the latest
write. And T s T i is a timestamp of the transaction.
So, the transaction is older than the latest
write. So, the transaction T i needs to read
a value that was already overwritten because
the latest write has happened after the transaction.
So, this read operation can be rejected and
T i will be rolled back.
If it is in contrast, if the timestamp of
the transaction is greater than the latest
right time W-timestamp Q then the read operation
is executed and since we are doing a read
operation. So, this becomes the latest read
operation and therefore, the read timestamp
R timestamp Q is set to the maximum of the
current read timestamp and the timestamp of
the transaction. Mind you here we the timestamp
one confusion that may come to your mind is
are we looking at the exact time when the
read has happened or when the write has happened,
no, we are all of this reasoning is happening
with the timestamp of the transaction.
So, whenever it started. So, it is a older
transaction and newer transition that we are
reasoning with. So, when you update R-timestamp
then you are the R-timestamp already has a
value which is the timestamp of the latest
transaction that has read that value and TS
T i is the timestamp of the transaction that
is read it now. So, it is not always that
since this read is the last read you will
update this. So, by by the sense of latest
what I mean is the latest in the sense of
the timestamp of the transaction that is reading
it. So, you will compute that in terms of
finding the maximum of the current read timestamp
and the timestamp of this transaction .
Write is a little bit more complex, but we
can reason in the same way. So, if T i issues
a write Q. And if the timestamp of T i is
less than R-timestamp that is if this transaction
is it is less so it is older than the read
timestamp that is it is older than the transaction
that read Q last, the youngest transaction
that read the value of Q. So, then the value
Q that T i is producing was needed earlier,
it is trying to write, but already a newer
transaction has used the value. And the system
assumed that what the T i was supposed to
write was not available was not produced,
hence the write operation is rejected T i
does not should not write this and T i will
be rolled back.
Second case if the transaction T i has a timestamp
which is less than the write timestamp. So,
which means that this transaction is older
than the transaction that has done the last
write. So, T i is attempting to write an absolute
value of Q, and hence this write operation
is again rejected and T i is rollback. Otherwise,
in other cases, the write operation is executed
and the write timestamp will be set to the
timestamp of this transaction which has written
it. So, this is a very simple protocol for
read and write.
And here is an example shown in terms of ah
this protocol. For example, this wanted to
do a read and this so this is this is the
that this is a time where where the the transaction
had started so and this was the write that.
So, when this read is happening this is the
so this is naturally this is at hold at transaction
than T 3. So, this at this point, the right
timestamp is that of T 3 and this is an older
one, so it was trying to read that, so this
was aborted.
Similarly as you see here if I clean and start
again if we look at write W this is trying
to do read and T 4, so read will this read
has a timestamp which is of T 4 which is later
than the timestamp of T 3. So, this gets aborted.
So, you will need to spend a little bit of
time to convince yourself that this will never
actually ensure never actually lead to any
deadlock, and it is a very effective serializable
and simple strategy to ensure serializability
while it avoids the deadlock.
At all the timestamp ordering protocol itself
guarantees the serializability, so the transaction
with the smaller timestamp will lead to transaction
with larger timestamp, because those are the
more recent transaction. So, since the ordering
is always in this manner, there cannot be
any cycle in this precedence graph, because
if they are recycle then naturally, somewhere
you are you will be coming from newer to an
older transaction which is not allowed in
this protocol.
So, there cannot be a cycle and so this ensures
that there cannot be deadlock in this time-based
protocol, but the schedules that they produce
they may not be cascade free. And actually
examples can be shown that they may not even
be recoverable there may be some irrecoverable
schedules that get produced through this time-based
protocol.
So, to summarize we have tried to take a look
into explaining what are the different ways
to prevent ah deadlock. Some of the strategies
and specifically we focused on the time-based
strategy. So, there are some strategies which
are based on the order of accesses the data
items ordering of data items and so on. And
we have specifically focused on time-based
strategies. And from that there are multiple
time-based strategies which can prevent deadlock.
And in case the deadlock has happened then
we have discussed a simple wait for graph
data structure and algorithm to be able to
detect that the deadlock has happened. And
if once this has been detected, we have talked
about basic strategy to recover from that
that is how do you decide what are the what
is a good candidate victim transaction which
should be rolled back, which should be aborted.
And on that study we have presented a simple
time-based protocol which maintains the timestamp
of transactions to decide the ordering in
terms of read and write and deciding as to
whether you should continue doing a read or
write or you should abort the read and write
attempt. And thereby ensuring that deadlocks
do not happen in the system though there may
be other problems in in this in terms of having
ah cascading rollback or having some irrecoverable
schedules at times.