Welcome to module 40 of Database Management
Systems.
Ah this is for course summarization, this
is the last module of the course ah.
So, I would just start with ah doing a quick
recap of what all did we cover and what we
expectedly learnt.
Ah in the week 1, we talked primarily of Introduction
to Database Management System and the Relational
Model which is the foundation of a database
system.
In week 2, we started off with query language
SQL at an Introductory level and then at an
Intermediate level which are really really
the first ah major ah aspect of a database
particularly relational database that a student
must master.
In week 3, we continued with the advanced
SQL and did the aspects of modeling from specification
in terms of Entity Relationship Model.
In ah week ah the next week, we did the design
issues which was really the involved part
and ah possibly the most important aspect
of the relational database design beyond ah
query coding query being able to write queries.
So, this is based on dependency and different
normal forms and I am sure you have spent
a good time on mastering these.
We followed up in week 5 with application
design and discussing aspects of ah storage
structure, how will actually the ah items,
data items be stored in the different ah memory
and disk structure.
In the following week, in week 6, we discussed
about indexing and hashing to for making the
accesses really efficient.
Ah in week 7, we did another critical aspect
of ah database systems that is how to make
transactions work concurrently.
So, we defined transactions and define what
is Concurrency and then we took in 2 different
critical aspects of Serializability that it
is possible that we can execute transactions
in a manner so that their instructions are
intermixed, but then even in that case, they
actually produce a result which is as if these
transactions could have been executed in the
serial order and ah we talked about the issues
of ah recoverability in this respect and we
specifically looked at different protocols,
particularly 2 phase locking protocol for
managing this kind of concurrency and the
evils of deadlock that may happen when you
do it concurrency and how simple protocols
like time based protocol can handle that.
And in the current week, we have ah dwelt
with different strategies of recovery, particularly
log based recovery and we have touched upon
query processing and optimization.
So, this is you have got a very first level
overview of this course.
Ah this is in a limited time and with limited
number of assignments.
So, ah you will just get a first level idea,
this is not to make you really an expert of
database systems, but this will certainly
get you started well in terms of the database
management ah programs, in terms of you are
ah taking up advanced courses later on or
in terms of actually taking up a job in different
database area.
So, given that ah given that in this current
module, I would discuss about ah few things
beyond the the textbook actually, the space
of databases RDBMS bases are quite crowded,
the lot of RDBMS bases you will see.
So, I will just take a quick look in terms
of the common RDBMS systems and there had
been a number of queries on the forum and
ah in the live session about that ah.
I will also touch upon ah we would like to
discuss about non relational database systems
which was not a part of the ah curriculum
that we did here, but will just present a
brief overview and then finally, I would like
to conclude with what should be the road forward
from you ah, presenting you a kind of a skill
profile matrix so that what skills you must
pick up to actually get get a job off certain
profile and ah what are the companies that
you might look at working for.
So, starting with the common databases, there
are several relational database systems.
So, in this slide you summarize basically
the what are the different aspects of ah relational
database systems which you have been discussing
so far.
So, this is just a summary of that.
Now, these are the common database systems.
So, ah I have chosen the ones which are ah
most widely used, most easily accessible and
kind of ah large companies use them, large
databases exist on them.
So, there are primarily 2 classifications;
one is a set of database systems are commercial
Oracle from the Oracle corporation, Sybase
from Sybase corporation which is now SAP AG,
DB2 from IBM ah, SQL Server from Microsoft
and the recent entrant to that who is making
a regular ripples is Teradata which is a you
know joint ah database systems from Caltech
and ah certain group of Citibank.
So, I if you are working for a company who
subscribes to any of these database ah software,
then you should be able to ah use them and
understand ah what all you can do, but if
you are working with smaller companies or
you are working as a student, then you will
need to use ah some of the database systems
which are free or are on the ah GPL licensing
or open source.
So, most prominent amongst them is PostgreSQL
which is from a Postgres global development
group.
So, these are ah non commercial ah the software
in the sense that you do not need to pay for
them and they are on the GPL and some of some
part of that would be open source as well
and a very commonly used is my SQL which is
is ah was originally from a Swedish company
called ah my SQL AB, but now it is acquired
by Oracle corporation, but it still ah does
not you do not need to pay for that.
So, these are the databases and systems to
primarily look for and besides that there
are some other database systems which use
ah certain object oriented features on top
of the relational features.
So, ah if you look in through these, then
in most cases you will find in terms of the
gross functionality of ah the kind of SQL
that you can write, a large subset of the
SQL that you can ah write on databases maintained
through this database systems will be same.
So, what you have learnt here would be applicable
irrespective of which database ah which of
these database systems you are using, but
ah of course there are specifics which would
be different ah amongst them.
So, ah in the next couple of slides, ah I
have 4 on each ah one slide, I have given
a brief background about the particular database
system.
So that you know you know how stable, how
old or you know ah what are the basic nuances
of that database system for example, Oracle
started in 77.
So, you can say, it is a it is a 40 year old
database system.
The latest version is 12 ah C and these are
the different supports that it has.
Ah Sybase also started in 1987.
So, that is almost ah 30 years, but ah it
is less you know less vibrant right now, the
last stable released happen in 2014 about
nearly more than 3 and a half or 4 years ago
and ah, but Sybase is a has been a very good
database systems for ah programming through
API's and it has really good support for that.
DB 2 is also a very old possibly the oldest
surviving database systems which started in
1970 ah.
So, when when almost the ah E. F Codd of the
Boyce Codd normal form published ah the data
manipulation schemes from IBM.
So, ah this is also a widely used, last release
2016.
Ah Microsoft ah the started database systems
in 1989, last release happened last year and
that is very widely used if you are particularly
on windows system ah.
It is one of the most popular one in terms
of the windows ah operating system.
Teradata is ah relatively new.
It was released in 1984 and it is, but it
is it is one where lot of new developments
are still happening and new experiments keep
on happening and the current version is a
Teradata 15.
And ah in terms of the ma free or open source
GPL ah databases Postgres ah started in 1988
about 30 years back and as I said, this is
ah this is ah has a release even half of this
year.
So, it is a very vibrant system.
MySQL probably most widely used amongst the
free community among ah the open source community
also where the first internal release happened
in 1995.
The recent releases happened this year.
So, these are the common ah database systems
that you will come across.
So, I mean given the organization that you
are working with, first find out which database
system it uses and then look into the specific
manual for that and specific ah features.
Beyond these a ah Relational Database Systems
also, there are certain database systems which
use ah Object oriented notions in that.
So, if you are familiar with object orientation
then you would have understood that the relational
approach ah does not make keep things object
oriented because you are always flattening
out in terms of attributes and you are trying
to look at the attributes ah, but it went
for example, when you want to model the same
thing in terms of a C plus plus or java program,
you would like to look at a course as an as
an object, as a class you would like to look
at instructor as a class, you would like to
look at teaches as a as a kind of class ah
and their instances.
So, ah there has been attempts to make ah
give a object orientation ah kind of layer
on top of relational databases or define things
in that way.
Objectivity DBO 2 objects store are some of
the examples, but unfortunately this is have
not been as popular as a regular relational
databases.
So, ah if you happen to use any one of them,
then you should be ah cause a cautious that
you know ah you really know why you are using
it and you would be able to go a long way
in terms of that.
Now, when you ah come across a particular
system that your company or your university
needs to use and you would like to choose,
then it will be good to look at the different
aspects of that system.
These are here are some of the parameters
on which these database systems vary in a
in a minimal to a very large extent, in terms
of what operating systems it supports, what
are the fundamental features, what are the
limits for example, every database sets a
number of limits in terms of the index size,
in terms of the table size and and whole lot
of that.
How are the tables and views created what
the kind of restrictions you have that, what
kind of indexes has support the capabilities
the data types, the the different databases
support.
We have talked about a very limited set of
data types in terms of SQL, but in in an actual
commercial or even ah you know open source
database, the data types could be wider than
that what kind of other objects partitioning
access control mechanism.
Access control is very important for ensuring
security and finally, what kind of programming
language support do you have.
Because as we have seen in the application
development module, that it is not enough
to just have a you know the database firing
SQL queries, no application user will actually
fire SQL queries.
The application user needs and in GUI possibly
or a text interface through which it will
put queries in a different form and that needs
to be processed by taking it to the ah database
engine.
So, you need possibly an interface which is
in terms of C, C plus plus, Java, Python,
this kind of programming language.
So, how do you connect to or embed such embed
your relational query into different languages
that differ between different database ah
systems.
So, these are the parameters that you must
look at.
In the next ah series of slides, which I will
not you know discuss really because the these
are more like data.
But here after given a compilation of different
you know on different aspects, how do these
common database RDMS systems agree or differ.
So, this is like a slide which shows what
are the operating system support for different
databases.
So, if you are for example, working on android,
then you can easily make out that you do not
have a choice to use SQL server or to use
Oracle, but you can use ah Sybase.
But you can use Postgres and MySQL actually,
if you look into ah these two columns, right
most columns which are for the open source
databases, you will find that they have the
widest choice in terms of operating system.
In many aspects you will find that ah these
free database systems have a better you know
options for you; obviously, when it comes
to you know really the core, core of database
systems in terms of really really supporting
very large databases, really really supporting
very fast operations, really really supporting
very secure applications, you might need to
only work with commercial software because
they offer that, but otherwise for a large
number of common you know medium scale or
low cost applications the ah free database
systems, Postgres and MySQL are really good
options there are different such features.
The basic features are compared to here.
At compile different limits of different database
systems here.
So, you can see in terms of maximum row size,
columns per row and and so on and so forth,
how do they differ.
So, if you are making a choice in terms of
what database I will use.
You can use these information.
This talks about tables we use the type systems,
what kind of typing is used.
The different data types that are used are
given here.
The index mechanisms are ah discussed here
the capabilities of the database, what it
can do overall.
Ah other kinds of objects that it supports.
Ah the different partitioning mechanism.
Ah the access control which is critical for
ensuring good security and good management
of that database are given here.
So, these are ah kind of the different across
different features, this is ah parameters,
this is how they compare.
So, ah well this is for your you know reference
only, this is this is not ah for your assignment
or examination, but I just wanted to have
a view that with all the ah theory and you
know a small hands on that you have seen ah,
when you go to the real life what are the
expected things what are the expected system
this will have to work with.
Now let us just ah move on and let us let
me just briefly talk about the a group of
database systems which are non relational
and of course I would warn you that the basis
for these DBMS is are not covered in this
course, is beyond the course, but just for
your information and to keep in ah keep you
in in tune with what is happening frequently
around the industry today.
So, the non-relational database systems have
arisen from what they all have must have heard
of is is the whole aspect of Big Data.
Big Data as a name suggests is is certainly
voluminous data, complex data and now the
question that you might have is if I i have
done a good relational design, if I have a
good RDMS, can I not handle big data.
The question here really is, big data is not
only about ah volume, the volume is only one
aspect which is really really large.
So, ah big data typically are characterized
by certain Vs.
So, these are not any very standardized characterization,
but these are more commonly accepted once.
So, one is volume, that the quantity of data
when a for a big data situation has to be
very very large . Now again what is a very
very large is again again a subjective question,
some you can say that a million record is
large, someone else would say no no million
record is small, it is actually ah 10 million
is large; some might say that it is a database
need to be petabytes to be large and so on.
But these are all subjectivity, but it is
large has a voluminous existent in certain
sense, there has to be different variety different
types of data.
So, all that we have seen in the relational
database is basically your you know strings
and numbers if you look at it in different
ways we are seeing, whatever we have dealt
with in all these through all this 39 modules
so far, they are primarily about strings and
numbers, but nothing else we have not, but
big data can be about ah free text, it could
be about natural language comments your ah
regularly ah writing comments on on your Facebook.
So, those Facebook comments are phrases and
if I want to make certain query based on that,
if I want to make a query that ok ah, how
many ah Facebook users has commented on the
success of Virat Kohli as a captain of India
if I want to ah make such a query, then the
question is how do I do that?
Because it is not something where you have
a at the information in a very structured
way this is no there is no relational schema
which says that well the values are put in
terms of Virat Kohli having done very good,
moderately or marginally or you know the captain
Indian captains are successful, not successful
and so on.
These are this happen in terms of various
texts, phrases, clauses that we write.
So, variety is a major issue then, it could
have word your images video.
So, big data includes all of that.
The third V is about velocity that the processing
speed may need to be really really fast, often
in big data often ah we say that the processing
has to be real time which means what is real
time.
Real time is is basically that ah from the
time I fire the query and to the time I get
the result, there is a fixed time limit within
which it has to happen.
So, if I if I if I really want to do a ah
railway reservation that also is a kind of
real time, but that is not very critical because
it is ok if I get the reservation done in
one minute, it is also ok, if it takes 5 minutes,
it is good if we can happen in 10 seconds,
but I do not ever need it in in say 20 millisecond.
So, but in when you talk about real time,
it could really be about getting all these
processing done in millisecond, microsecond,
nanosecond and so on.
And those kind of real time systems with a
large volume of varied data, it is a big challenge.
So, those are the challenges of big data,
then there could be variability inconsistency
of the data that you are because ah maintaining
integrity is a big problem; there could be
issues in terms of quality of the data that
is called veracity.
So, actually these things characteristics
that I have put, there are lot of debates
in terms of that or many people take these
3 and say that there these are the 3 V s of
big data.
There is a 3 main characteristics, but off
let more and more people are also considering
variability and veracity are as the characteristics
of big data.
Now as it ah happens, is if you look into
these ah requirements and what you have you
have a fairly good idea of relational databases
now what they can do, how to design them,
how to query them, how to implement them,
you will understand that it is not easy to
meet these requirements using the relational
model.
So, we need their non-relational databases
to effectively support big data.
That is that is a one major reason that you
need big data.
So, that in non-relational databases certainly
as the name suggests, do not follow relational
model, they offer flexible schema design.
The schema may itself change while the database
is evolving which is not the case in the relational
schema is fixed, only the data can change,
but here the schema itself can change.
It may be able to handle unstructured data,
make natural language comments like images
like audio coming in which do not fit nearly
into your you know table structure ah, some
of the other feature sites they are typically
open source because you know still in an experimental
stage ah and ah needs to be scalable and some
of the popular ones are ah, these are the
names you must have heard about at least some
of them like MongoDB like Cassandra ah like
HBase and so on.
Now again again in terms of the non relational
database, it ah does differ in terms of all
non relational database error are not of the
same type, there are there have been 4 different
styles or strategies to actually ah generate
realize these non relational databases, they
are called key value store graph, store columns
stores and document store ah.
They are also known as no SQL databases.
I, I personally find the name no SQL a little
misnomer ah, it it no SQL does not mean that
ah you are strictly prohibited from not using
SQL in these databases.
But I would rather like to read it more as
no SQL means that it is not only SQL like
in a relational database, you can use only
SQL and solve problems; here you need to do
lot of other things beyond that.
So, here is a quick comparison between the
relational and the non-relational ah, in terms
of the flexibility of the data model ah, relational
is very structured when on relational has
to have ah handle unstructured data, semi
structured data and therefore it has to be
ah flexible in terms of the data model, cost
complexity and speed ah faster less capable,
but cheaper and less complex, but in non-relational,
you are talking about much more database operations
highly complex ah in internal structure usually
costlier, performance and scalability ah certainly
non-relational ones need to be better scalable,
consistency have a very strict consistency
rules in relation, but in non-relational ah
you use some kind of you know eventual consistent
system.
So, maybe not always not everything is consistent
in that way, enterprise management and integration
ah, relational fits very well into because
it is been around for as as you have seen
the little bit of history of all these ah
common databases, it is more than 40 years
that they have been around.
So, they easily fit into the IT stack whereas,
ah non-relational is still on the in the in
the agile form of development that is becoming
more and more common it fits into the cloud
based development and so on.
So, these are some of the distinctions that
exist.
And these are the different types of no SQL
databases, there is a key value store strategy
ah Redis and MemcacheDB follow this strategy,
graph store is used by orient DB and Neo4J;
column store is used by Cassandra and HBase
document store, MongoDB, Couchbase, they use
document store.
So, these are I am in this is not just about
going a deeper into what they are or how they
are distinguished, I just want you to have
an idea that ah well.
These are different from the relational databases
they can do lot of structured, handling of
unstructured data they can actually use a
scalability of volume a variety which is relationships
cannot do and, but they have there are different
principles for actually implementing them
and there is a deeper.
So, if you are interested, you can take specific
courses which deal with the big data and and
prepare yourself for the bigger ah challenges
ahead.
I have also done similar to the relational
database, I have presented here a tentative
comparative study between these different
ah non no SQL databases in terms of what is
the context in which you use them.
Or ah now now while you are doing this unstructured
data handling, there will be lot of data which
is also structured.
So, how do you, along with this know SQL,
how do you handle the relational data with
these?
Databases what how do how do the performance
compare between these different no SQL databases
and based on all that you can make some judgment
and it is it is very important to ah in today's
time ah naturally knowing relational databases
the foundational ones are very important,
but it is always good to look forward be with
the time and I will urge that if you have
started growing interest in handling of data
ah do take specific courses on big data and
ah no SQL databases.
I will end this discussion with a very simple
ah skill job profile matrix which Will give
you some idea in terms of ah, it will you
can use it for a certain kind of self-assessment
as well.
So, let me just explain the the structure
of this matrix, what I have tried to do is
here ah I am sorry.
Here on the left, I have given different typical
job profiles this is if you look into LinkedIn,
Naukri and all that you will find ah these
kind of profiles being.
So, then at the lowest level there are application
programmers ah for which typically 0 to 4
years of experience are asked for.
Then the next level, this is so, this is your
kind of your career progression also.
If you if you choose to ah take up databases
as your primary job profession, ah this next
level is a senior application programmer which
ah requires 2 to 6 years of experience depending
on the organization and depending on your
skills ah.
Then you move on to database analyst or architect
which you happen in 4 to 8 years of time and
ah on a little different track ah because
these are these are primarily in terms of
application development and hierarchy on that
and ah the other is an administrator track
who actually administers the database in an
organization, controls all the all that is
happening in different database applications,
typically 8 to 10 year's experience is required.
And ah some of that, so this these are the
about actually in terms of ah you know profiles
that are related to applications and this
is a profile which is related to, if you really
want to become a database engineer in a sense
that you want to you know ah make changes
in Oracle, you want to make changes in say
MySQL, you want to make changes in say MongoDB
or say that relation will say the Sybase.
So, if you want to become a database engineer
who changes the database system itself or
develops the database system itself, then
this is the kind of background you will need.
There is a kind of number of years, you would
need and of course it is not a single grid
there are multiple grades, you know junior
and mid levels in here and those kind and
last which have shown in different color are
the whole set of profiles which relate to
programming the big data, analyzing the big
data and so on.
We are at present, it is companies are typically
asking for 0 to 6 years of experience depending
on ah actual skills that you have.
On this side, I have shown a whole grouping
of skills, this is the first basic level that
you must understand specs and schema, without
that you cannot do any of this and you must
have a skill for ah coding in inquire in SQL,
the DML part significantly ah, without that
as you can see you cannot pick up any of these
profiles whereas, if you go a little if you
go little senior you know gaining experience
and you should be able to analyze specs that
is, you should be able to design schema do
normalization and get into this.
So, at at at a very initial level, you ah
may not be expected to do all of that schema
design and normalization by yourself, but
it would be good to be able to do that, but
well there will be seniors to help you, but
if you once you become a senior application
programmer that becomes onward that becomes
a critical skill to have.
Then ah the next level would be in terms of
application or database architecture management
deciding on how to index, performance optimization.
So, between between these two, there will
be certain overlaps a senior application programmer
in addition to doing this might do some of
these optimization techniques depending on
how competent he or she is ah.
Or some ah database architect may focus only
on this, but but these are the typical skills
that you need.
But to be a database administrator, you need
all of these skills , but you are specifically
administering a certain ah organizations enterprises
whole database system.
So, it is just not one database application,
but a whole lot of databases and whole lot
of user groups, security, network connectivity
and all that.
So, that needs ah certainly bigger experience
it can, you can see that experience level
is much higher and the skill sets ah.
If you want to become a database engineer,
that is not focus only on the application
side, but also have ah some more ah understanding
in terms of actually doing working in the
internals of the database systems, then you
need whole lot of additional skills like ah
good knowledge and algorithms, in architecture,
in compiler all of that ah; only then and
coupled with coupled with all the database
knowledge, then you will be able to work as
a database system engineer.
And in the emerging areas of what is ah big
data where, you need to have now of course,
the I am saying this is 0 to 6, it could be
0 to 8 kind of, not more than that because
it did not exist ah quite a long time ago
ah, but you need to have a basic level of
at least this much of the relational database
understanding and knowledge, but what is critical
is a whole set of other skills like, you must
be aware with big data the data mining, warehousing
strategies machine learning or is often very
useful in this kind of big data applications
ah, python programming, tensor flow all these
become critical.
You have to be a good programmer in any case
I mean not only just an SQL program and you
might have to be a good program and in C or
C plus plus or python of these, but that is
it that is a very very emerging area.
So, if you can acquire a little bit of besides
database you know he said that the basics
of the database along with that if you pick
up few basics or from here, you will be able
to enter into the space and that will give
you a very very bright future ah in in in
my view otherwise you can focus on the application
programming stat as I have mentioned.
So, this is the basically skill profile matrix
ah that you have ah mapping that you have
that you can focus on.
So, ah finally, before I close here a glimpses
of companies that are in the very active in
the RDMS space really really any big organization
you talk ah about ah, they have consultancy
projects, product development different ah
database management back end services and
so on.
So, DB application development, I have listed
some around 20 companies, but there are really
100s of them almost.
Any big organization in any area you think
of, they require databases.
So, in terms of beta based application programmer
and senior programmer and to some extent architect,
you have a wide range of jobs available which
you may just grab; if you have been able to
study write the basics of the database.
The second group of companies which I show
here, these are system development companies
who are actually working on the new DBMS products
and services around that.
So, these are companies like Oracle, Teradata
or Microsoft and so on, naturally these are
big companies and you need ah more lot of
more skills besides the database like I said
algorithms programming and all that to crack
a job here and here are some of some companies
which I have mentioned, but there are many
others who are focusing on the big data space.
So, I have tried to you know these may not
be absolutely accurate because you know these
are all collected from different sources,
but these are the different companies and
the kind of non relational database that they
are focusing with working with.
So, if you pick up certain skills in those
in a certain non-relational no SQL database,
then you can target the corresponding companies
better or other companies and you can see
that all.
You know new generation companies, the companies
were working for products for the next ah
10, 10, 15 years are in this space.
So, there are whole lot of opportunities for
you all if you if you prepare a little hard,
then you will I mean job will run after, you
will not have to run after the job.
So, ah with that I conclude this course a
couple of final words ah the the hygiene words.
Read the DBMS textbook thoroughly and solve
exercises.
There is no shortcut to that, there is no
other way to master the horse other than this
you must practice query coding as much as
you can, practice database design from specification.
We are releasing a tutorial on this where
for a hospital management system we are showing
from the specification how you can do the
initial schema and the refinements ah and
ah finally, how can you implement it using
my SQL.
So, do similar practices very heavily ah.
Keep in mind the database the knowledge of
database system alone will not be good enough
to get a good job, get a good placement.
So, develop good knowledge in programming
data structure, algorithms and discrete structures;
these are the minimum required around the
database systems which will really make you
powerful and if you need ah we are there to
help you ah.
As long as the course is on, the forum would
be on.
You can post in the forum beyond that also
if you need help ah, please ask for it mail
us and wish you all the very best with your
course in your examination and the future
course of your profession in life, all the
very best.