welcome to database management systems in
this course we will have forty modules each
module would be of about half an hour so this
is the first module where we would talk about
the overview of the course
so we will discuss the importance of database
management systems in modern day applications
and will familiarize you with different aspects
of the course so this will be the outline
first we will try to explain why we need databases
and then we will run through a k y c on the
course prerequisites course outline the textbook
and the t s who will help us in this course
so first why do we need databases a database
management system contains information about
a particular enterprise so it deals with collection
of interrelated data we have a set of programs
which access and manipulate that data and
together a d b m s presents an environment
for convenient as well as efficient use of
data of the enterprise under consideration
so there could be different database application
actually if we look around in the world that
we are living today every aspect of our life
has been touched by certain database application
some of the very common and wide applications
will include banking we are doing net banking
very regularly net banking is a highly distributed
database application that allow us to do different
kinds of retail as well as corporate banking
we have we perform different kind of booking
reservation railway reservation airline reservation
hotel reservations all of these are
now possible over internet as well these are
all big database applications when we are
attending colleges universities the students
courses teachers course enrolments performance
of the students and different courses examination
all ah are parts of huge university database
applications there are different cells applications
online retailing applications like i am sure
all of you ah have been using some of the
amazon flip kart e bay snap deal all these
are online retail database applications which
allow us to order to select items to make
payments and to track the deliveries of different
items that we have ordered there are database
applications in terms of manufacturing production
systems inventory management any big factory
of manufacturing need to use a huge database
application to manage the supply chain the
inventory the orders everything there are
database applications in human resources applications
like ah linkedin are huge human resource application
of database the social media applications
all involve different kinds of database applications
so in this database management system course
we are going to understand how such applications
can be designed developed and managed over
a period of time database applications are
typically characterized by the fact that they
are very large if we have a relatively small
set of data then possibly will be able to
manage it in terms of using an excel sheet
or a couple of excel sheets but soon when
it goes beyond a certain size we need a database
application so the fact of being large is
a critical factor of any d b m s
so with all this we as we observe the database
says cover all aspects of our life and hence
understanding d b m s s is a critical requirement
for any computer science information technology
student so if we talk about a specific ah
database example say ah university database
then will have several application programs
which will allow us to do several required
applications like when new students join we
would need to add the students we will need
to add new courses when courses are floated
the will need to add new instructors when
faculty join will need to do allotments will
need to do registration of students for courses
will need to conduct examinations will need
to assign grades to students when they are
graded for different courses and compute their
g p a and so on so all the activities that
a university has to deal with are application
programs of varied kinds that the university
database need to work with in the earlier
days before the days of databases ah typically
such applications used to be managed through
file systems we all know that all our system
has a file system where different files text
as well as data files can be stored and information
can be written in these files in a certain
order and just to quickly recall file systems
typically have ah a large number of sequential
files which can be written and read in a certain
order and some random access files where you
can ah reach a particular point in the file
to do certain access operation certain manipulation
operations
so in the earlier days it was a collection
of file systems which managed large enterprise
data as is required but over time it was observed
that the file systems to store data to manage
data has a lot of drawbacks for example if
you look at in a file system there is often
a lot of data redundancy and inconsistency
ah these are terms which we will loosely define
here and as we go across along the course
will understand these terms better but redundancy
just to explain redundancy is a concept where
the same data is written at multiple places
in different forms and that may give rise
to several forms of inconsistencies because
if you write the same data in multiple files
because you need to ah deal with ah many of
these aspects so there is a file for students
there is a file for teachers there is a file
for ah particular courses there is a file
for enrolment and so on several data items
may be ah redundantly copied in multiple files
and once that is done then we can it is very
easy to get inconsistent in terms of the data
because you may update the data in one file
and may forget to update the data in another
file
so that is one of the first problems with
using the file systems then this difficulty
in accessing the data because as i said the
data is the files often are sequential in
nature even if they are random access then
every task might need to use data from multiple
files and opening those files and reaching
to the appropriate point of access is a non
trivial task then there is issues of data
isolation because there are multiple types
of files there are multiple formats used therein
very importantly there are a lot of integrity
problems the database any database ah application
need to have a lot of integrity for example
if you want to withdraw money from an account
bank account then certainly the balance needs
to be positive you can you draw only that
much amount up to that much amount which is
which exists in the in the account so any
application will need to check for this so
if you use a file system based application
to store the data then at every point wherever
you are updating the balance you will need
to make such checks which make the application
quite complicated and often creates the possibility
that certain integrity checks may be missed
out so it is hard to code these new constraints
over a period of time then there are issues
of atomicity of update what atomicity means
is the ability to do certain operations in
a in a in a single as a single unit so what
you want is ah either that operation happens
or the and and if it happens then it happens
in full in totality whereas otherwise it may
not happen at all for example consider that
there is a funds being transformed from one
account to another so this means the account
from which the funds are being transferred
needs to be debited certain amount and that
same amount has to get credited to the accounts
to which it is being paid
now if for some reason of failure or because
of the fact that there was link issues or
something if you are not able to um ah make
this whole transfer then it is possible that
you have already debited the account but you
have not been able to create that account
now this will be a a major cause of inconsistency
in the in the database so what what you want
is if the transfer can happen then it must
happen in totality that is what that debit
and the credit must happen together or nothing
should happen at all so these are there are
several examples of requirement of automaticity
for a update which is critical for maintaining
consistency of the data the other aspect which
has become very very deeply required in every
aspect of database is concurrency of access
if there is a database then certainly there
is not a single user there are multiple hundreds
of users you think about net banking you think
about ah railway reservation multiple users
are trying to make bookings in multiple ah
trains from varied stations to vary stations
in different classes and so on so all of this
must go on at the same time that is what is
called the concurrency of update
so it is quite possible that while you are
trying to update you check the um ah but availability
on a certain train on a certain date that
you intend to travel at the same time someone
else may be checking for the berth availability
on the same train on the same date and there
could be conflict of concurrency because there
may be one berth available and you are trying
to book that you have seen that one berth
is available so you go ahead and book it try
to book it and there is another user who also
saw that one berth is available and that user
makes payments and tries to book that so concurrency
needs to make sure that both of these users
should not be allowed to make the booking
to the same berth because then that will be
a disaster so uncontrolled concurrency can
add to several inconsistencies in the application
then certainly there are you all would be
very familiar that today we are living under
a whole lot of security threats
so there has to be ah proper security that
it should be possible to ah um access the
data by a user to the extent the user is allowed
to do that ah so as a user you should be able
to access certain parts of the data the manager
of the system the administrator should be
able to access a bigger part of the data possibly
so security is hard to provide in terms of
a file system based applications to store
data so all these with we conclude the data
based systems had those which provide solution
to take care against all those above problems
and ah we are trying to learn how to do such
things so moving on ah i would quickly take
you through ah familiarizing with you with
the ah overall ah plan of the course so what
we we first i talk about are the course prerequisites
ah these prerequisites are kind of certain
elementary level knowledge in computer science
and related discrete mathematics that you
should have you should be that would make
it easier for you to understand and follow
the course otherwise if you find at any stage
that you are finding any of this aspect difficult
to follow in the course then i would advise
that you ah go back to some of the background
material and try to study them
so i have tried to list down ah this prerequisite
topics one certainly is the set theory because
that is the basic premise on which databases
are designed on so starting from definition
of the set membership concepts of subset superset
power set different operations of union intersection
complementation difference cartesian product
de morgans law all these basic set theory
you should be very familiar and conversant
with if you are not i have mentioned one moocs
course ah um this is a past course but you
can access the videos and the contents ah
which has a very nice discussion on these
aspects of set theory which you may refer
to ah moving on the next which goes on top
of the sets are the concept of relations and
functions we all know that a relation is a
um ah subset of a set so if i have a set a
then i can define a binary relation over that
set a which is basically the pair of elements
from set a or in other words the relation
binary relation is a subset of the cross product
of a with itself where the domain and the
range are related together so there are concepts
of the image of a domain the pre image of
the range the inverse relation and several
basic properties of relations like the relation
being reflexive symmetric antisymmetric transitive
total relations and
so on you should be familiar with these otherwise
you will find difficult to ah follow major
concepts in the database systems because this
tribal system primarily the one that we are
going to ah take you through in this course
is relational in model so it is heavily based
on relations and functions and you should
understand one specifically a relation becomes
a function and when what is meant by functions
being injective subjective bijective what
is meant by composition and inverse of functions
and so on again if you need you can refer
to this moocs course on discrete mathematics
to brush up your knowledge about relations
and functions we also need you to have a basic
understanding of the propositional logic which
is truth values true and false and the different
operations of conjunction disjunction negation
that is and or not ah what is meant by implication
what is meant by equivalence you know that
given two variables which have or two propositions
which can take a value true or false the conjunction
of them can be represented in terms of a truth
table where we say that only when both these
propositions are true then the resultant conjunctive
proposition becomes true otherwise a conjunctive
proposition is false
so you should be familiar with these ah concepts
if you are not please brush up your ah ideas
about propositional logic we need a little
bit of predicate logic as well a predicate
logic in contrast to propositional logic deals
with quantification that the knowledge of
existential and universal quantifier when
you say that whether certain proposition predicates
hold for all values in the domain or for some
value in the domain whether there exists some
value for which it holds or whether for all
values it holds and based on that predicate
logic is build up we do not need very advanced
concept concept here just basic level familiarization
will help and the same moocs course on discrete
mathematics would be of your help in case
you need to ah brush it up further on ah aspects
of computer science certainly you need a ah
good familiarity with the data structures
are a list particularly binary search tree
what is called a binary search tree what is
meant by a height of a binary search tree
when we say that a binary search tree is balanced
what are the ways and conditions of balancing
is particularly um ah the b trees for organizing
good search trees hash tables what is hashing
we need you to be familiar with with this
concept because the databases will be heavily
designed based on the concepts of b trees
and hash tables and so on
ah there are courses on design and analysis
of algorithms fundamental of algorithms have
mentioned two excellent courses in moocs from
which you can brush up if you need to ah certainly
you need certain familiarity with common algorithms
particularly i had mentioned sorting and searching
algorithms because these are critical for
database applications and again ah the um
the same moocs courses would be of your help
and it will be good to have familiarity with
programming in c because several of the applications
need some application high level application
programming to be performed and we would assume
that those aspects we described in c because
that is a fundamental and most commonly known
language ah besides these prerequisites which
i have marked as essential ah because they
will certainly be required for the major parts
of the course it will be good if you have
some familiarity with object oriented analysis
and design and some language which is more
heavily object oriented object aligned in
nature like c plus plus or java so um again
some moocs courses the related moocs courses
are mentioned here in case you need to brush
up moving on this is your course outline so
as i said the course comprise forty modules
so it is divided into eight weeks so this
plan is given based on what we do in different
weeks from week one to week eight so as the
course unfolds you will be able to ah you
will you will take will take you through these
modules on these topics and on the right you
can find that i have marked that the initial
part of the course which we cover from week
one to first half of week five is primarily
meant for application programming which is
a which it means that the database system
has already been designed and basic premises
the schemas and constraints have been set
up but
now you want to write different data query
different data manipulation applications and
that is where the large volume of database
engineers work so they are called application
programmers so that is the i should say the
first level in terms of a database understanding
and you must target to become a master of
application programming to get started with
the other half of the course which start from
the middle of week five with the storage and
file structure and goes on till the next is
meant for the analysts who are responsible
either for designing a particular database
which the application programmer can use ah
tune that for performance ah index it properly
design queries to be efficient so these kind
of analysts will be involved the more with
the understanding of the second part of the
course and the second part of the course would
also be useful for the database a d b m s
designers if you want to really become an
advanced programmer we want to work on database
engineering in terms of creating database
management systems not merely creating databases
or database applications then you need to
have a good initial command over the ah second
half of the course so ah while you prepare
for the course where you go through the modules
please keep this in mind that your familiarity
with the application programming must be at
the highest level and in the later parts will
be relatively little advanced but they are
required for good design and ah good development
of consistent ah efficient system in in future
ah we will follow a textbook this is um as
you can see this is a sixth edition that i
am following in this course it is called database
system concept by ah silberschatz korth and
sudarshan this is kind of a classical book
in database systems ah ah current version
actually is the seventh edition
so if you get access to the seventh edition
you can use that as well but whatever we are
following in this course sixth edition is
good enough so i advise the that you try to
get a copy of this book to yourself ah so
moving on ah we have different three t as
we will help you in this course srijoni majumdar
ah himadri bhushan bhuyan and gurunath reddy
so these are their emails i have also put
their mobile numbers however i would advise
that unless you are really stuck avoid calling
them on the mobile because they are research
students as well ah busy with their own work
as well but they can certainly put all your
questions on the forum which will be promptly
responded by some of these t as or by myself
and in case you would have very specific follow
ups to do you can write email to one or all
of these t as
so this is about the course overview so in
this module we have discussed about the importance
about database management systems in the modern
day applications and we have tried to familiarize
you with different aspects of the course and
i reiterate that please ah give due consideration
to the prerequisites as mentioned we have
ah floated in an assignment called assignment
zero where there are questions on different
aspects of these prerequisites please try
to solve that assignment and see your ah performance
ah this assignment i would like to mention
that this assignment will not go in the final
evaluation of the performance of the course
this is just to give you an idea for self
assessment of your preparedness for this course
so if you find that on questions on certain
topics say on relation function or on data
structure if you have not been able to answer
the questions well then it will be good to
check back and go through the prerequisites
once more but please keep in mind that database
management system is a ah course which depends
on these background knowledge quite heavily
so if you have gaps in understanding those
topics then all through the course you will
get into several difficulties in understanding
and problem solving so that is about our first
module so from the next module we will start
introducing the database management system
enjoy the course and try to learn try to become
a good database engineer