.
Welcome to module 14 of database management
systems.
In the last module we will started our discussions
on the entity relationship model, we will
continue that in this module as well, and
actually conclude it in the next module.
So, these are the items that we had discussed
in the last module.
In the present one, we will first illustrate
the entity relationship diagram notation;
that graphical notation for E-R model, how
nicely this can be shown in terms of certain
diagrams.
And then we will explore how E-R models can
be translated to relational schemas, which
is a basic step of the logical design . So,
these are the topics.
So, we start with the E-R diagram.
Naturally the first thing to represent in
ah an E-R model is the entity set.
Every entity set is represented by a rectangle.
On the top, we write the name of that entity
set.
As you can see examples here the instructor.
And student are the 2 entity sets and below
that we write the names of the attributes
that are involved.
And we underline the attribute or attributes
that form the primary key of that entity set
.
A relationship between ah 2 entity sets is
represented by a diamond, and 2 connecting
lines to the 2 entity sets.
So, here it says that advisor is a relationship
between entity set instructor, and entity
set student.
Trying to convey the real-world situation
that students are advised by the instructors
or students have instructors and so on .
As we had mentioned that relationships could
also have attributes.
So, if the advisor relationship has an attribute
date then it will be tagged to the adviser
relationship with the attribute coming as
a within a rectangle and attached to the name
of the relationship by a dotted line.
So, this shows that advisor is the relationship
between instructor.
And student and the adviser relationship has
an attribute date .
It is possible that ah the relationship that
hold between 2 entity sets can be can use
entity sets which are same.
That is, it is possible that a set is related
to itself.
So, as an example we show, the entity set
course which has a relationship prereq, prerequisite
which takes a course id, and relates it to
another course id called the prerequisite
id.
Because obviously, if a course has a prerequisite.
Then that prerequisite itself is another course
id which must occur in this table itself.
So, in this case, if you can see that unlike
the earlier ah case the prereq id is not actually
a field of this ah relation course.
So, we say these are rules.
So, we say the rule that prereq relate from
the course relation to itself are course id
and prereq id; where in the actual table both
of them relate to course id, but prereq will
pair them to show which course has what prerequisite.
And we often need this kind of; we have ah
seen ah similar instances of this while we
treated dealt with the recursive queries in
databases.
The source destination of ah aligns problem
that we discussed has similar kind of relationship
structure.
So, you can think about a relationship flies
from the set of ah source to this set of destination,
and basically this these 2 sets the places
source places in the destination place are
necessarily the same set the same relation
. There could be a constraint on the cardinality.
So, the line that links the relationship diamond
with the rectangles of the relations rectangles
of the entity sets.
Those lines could have an arrow at the end
or may not have an arrow at the end.
So, if it has got an arrow, then it means
that suppose it has an arrow it means 1.
And if it does not have a arrow if it is simple
then it means many.
So, using this rotation we can designate one
to one one to many these all different kinds
of cardinalities that we had discussed.
So, for example, if we are showing this ah
arrow on both hands, both ends of this relationship
advisor then, it means that it is a one to
one relationship.
Because there is an arrow here.
So, this is 1 . There is an arrow here.
So, this is 1.
There is an arrow here.
So, this is 1; which means that a student
is associated at most with at most one instructor.
And it also means that and an instructor is
associated with at most student.
This may not be a reality this usually is
not the reality, but this we are just showing
this as an example.
So, if the student instructor relationship
advisor relationship is one to one, then this
is how we will denote it .
If it is one to many . So, which side is 1,
this side is 1 and this side is many.
So, it is one to many from instructor to student;
which says that every student has at most
one instructor.
And an instructor may have several students.
It could be null also it could be none also.
So, for an instructor here there are many
students, but for a student here there are
only at most one instructor.
So, it is one to many and this is how we designate
a similar thing will happen, if I read the
same relation in the other direction.
So, instructor to student was one to many.
So, student instructor also drawn in the same
way, because this is ah this is the one side,
this is the one side and this is the many
side.
So, if the situation is the same.
So, if we read from the student instructor,
then it is also designates the many to one
relationship.
And finally, we can have a many to many relationship,
where there is no arrow at either end which
means that an instructor is associated with.
Several possibly none no student why the advisor
relation and the student may also have several
instructors by the advisor relationship.
Now, we can you can certainly figure out that
in the particular case of student instructor
scenario of providing advice, one to one as
well as many to many are not the usual real
world scenarios, but these are we have just
using to show you how to model this usual
scenario would be from instructor to student
it is one to many relationship .
A relationship could be total or it could
be partial.
If you if one side of the relationship, or
whichever side of the relationship is total,
then we draw a double line.
So, you can you can see here in the diagram
we are drawing a double line, which means
that in the advisor relationship the involvement
of the student is total, which means that
every student must feature in the advisor
relationship.
Or in other words every student must have
an advisor.
But it is partial on the instructor side because
every instructor may not have a student .
So, this double life shows that reality . Some
entities may not participate in any relationship
is a partial .
Now, this ah constraints the cardinality constraints
can be made more precise by actually using
numbers.
You can actually say on the 2 sides of the
relationship, that at the minimum how many
entities should relate, and at the maximum
how many entities can relate.
For example, if we are saying that we are
on the right-hand side here, if you see we
are saying that it is maximum minimum is one
maximum is one which what does it say it says
that every student the minimum is one.
So, every student must feature in the advisor
relationship.
So, in real world, every student must have
a an advisor, must have an instructor.
It says maximum is one; which says that every
student can have at most one instructor.
So, this one to one one, dot dot one says
that every student must have at least one
instructor, every student must have at most
one instructor.
So, together it says that every student must
have exactly one instructor.
Whereas if I if we see on this side, it says
that 0 dot, dot, star, star stands for no
limit.
It can be anything any number.
So, the minimum is 0 which means that an instructor
may not have a student.
And star says that if the instructor can have
any number of student.
Naturally 0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 2, or 200.
So, any instructor can advise any number of
students.
So, these kind of precise number constraints
can be put in addition to the one to many,
or one to one, many to many kind of notations
in the diagram.
So, when we do that we have the precise cardinality
of the complex relations that exist .
Next, we take a look into the handling of
the complex attributes.
The first you remember that, the first kind
of complex attribute is 1 which is composite.
Say, name which has first name middle name,
initial middle initials and last name.
So, when we have that, then the way we represent
is at the actual name of the attribute is
at the outermost level.
And it is composites are written with certain
shift on the left.
So, these all say that these are composites
of name.
So, if this says that street city state zip
are composites of address, and further indentation
say, that these are composites of street.
So, this is how graphically we show that how
complex attributes feature .
Now, let us go back to discussing the weak
entity sets.
In the E-R diagram, a weak entity set is represented
by a double rectangle.
You remember the section is a weak entity
set.
And why is it so?
Because the same course may have 2 different,
I am sorry, 2 different courses may have the
same section id semester and year that is
2 courses 2 or more courses may run sections
by the same name in the same semester and
the year.
So, a section cannot be uniquely identified
by these 3 attributes.
It needs a relationship with the identifying
entity set course to be specific the course
id so that the entities here in can be uniquely
specified.
So, since this has happened.
So, we designate that by putting this double
rectangle around the weak entity set section
. We underlined the discriminator of a weak
entity set with dashed line.
So, you remember these are the discriminators.
Because given the identifying attribute in
the identifying set.
These are the attributes which distinguish
different tuples of section.
So, they are not shown with solid underline,
they are shown as dotted underline, dashed
underlined.
So, that you can make out that this is a weak
entity set and these are the discriminators
.
The relationship set connecting the weak entity
set to the identifying strong entity set,
is also so, this the moment you have weak
entity set.
You know that there has to be a relationship
to the strong entity set which identifies
it.
So, that relationship set course which say
, course id against this minds that is designated
with a double diamond.
So, that you know that this is the identifying
relationship between a weak entity set and
the corresponding strong entity set . And
once that happens in the primary key becomes
the discriminators of section the weak entity
set, and the primary key of the identifying
a strong entity set the course.
So, that forms our final primary key for this
entity set section.
My new course id is not a part of this relation,
but it actually plays the role through this
section id as a key for the section relation
without which the section entities in the
section cannot be uniquely identified.
So, having said that this is a the E-R diagram
of the university enterprise.
Some of the points that you could take a look
at.
This is the weak entity set we have just seen.
This is the relationship to the identifying
strong entity set . This is a prerequisite
multi role relationship.
Ah this we can see is a is a total involvement.
So, worry why is it a total involvement, because
every section must have at least one teacher.
So, there cannot be a section which does not
feature in the teacher's relationship.
Similarly, every section must get a timeslot
where the classes for that section is held.
So, every section must feature in the sec
timeslot.
So, these are the similarly, it must get a
classroom.
So, these are all different total involvements.
That we total roles that we can see we can
see some of that elsewhere as well.
For example, you can see it here, we can see
it here, because in between instructor and
the department the inst department relationship
. Certainly, every instructor must have a
department.
So, it is total, but it is not the same for
the department, every department will not
have instructors.
So, these is how if we can you can go through
carefully.
And for example, this is another which is
total, which means that every course need
a department you cannot run a course which
does not have a department.
So, this is how we can see that how the E-R
diagram that the first conceptual level diagram
of a very simple university enterprise is
being designed following the notions and symbols
of E-R model that we have already developed.
Next comes the part where, from this model
which is primarily diagram based we have to
really go to the relational schema, which
is names of relations and attributes which
is ah pretty much a straightforward job.
So, entity sets and relationship sets have
to be represented in terms of relational schema.
What is the beauty of the E-R model?
And the relational schema is that that, when
you reduce the entity relationship model to
relational schema both entity sets and relationships
sets.
Both of them turn out to be relational schemas
. And so, that the database finally, can be
represented simply as a set of schemas each
one of which must have a set of identifying
primary key.
So, let us look into that.
So, on the strong entity set, that reduces
to schema with the same attribute as student.
So, student has id name and total credit.
So, which we saw earlier.
Now this gets converted to a schema with id
being the primary key.
The other case of weak entity set, section
which had the 3 discriminators, and through
set course relationship was identified from
the strong entity set.
Course borrows the primary key of the course
to be defined in terms of this relational
schema one moment . This borrows ah the primary
key from here and becomes.
So, you can see that in the E-R model, the
section did not have course id as an attribute,
but while we reduce this to the relational
schema through this sec course relationship,
we have borrowed this primary key from course.
The primary key of course, the course id and
added that to section to make it a complete
relational schema .
Next comes the representation of relationships.
So, we are showing a relationship advisor.
So, which relates instructors to students.
So, naturally every instructor is identified
by id every student is identified by id.
Since both of the attributes have the same
name id.
We are calling them as s underscore id, and
for the student and I underscore id for the
instructor.
So, the advisor relation is basically a pairing
of these 2 ids.
Which gives rise to a relationship which looks
like this relationship schema which looks
like this.
So, it can in general say that if we have
a relationship ah in the E-R model, which
we want to represent in the schema then we
will take, we will create a schema which has
the primary key of both the sets, and put
them together.
And if the names clash we will just change
the name with the name of the relation, and
that will give us the schema for the relationship
in this case the advisor.
So, you have seen how to represent entity
sets, weak entity sets and relationships ah
let us look at how do we deal with composite
attributes.
Because so far, we had assumed that the relational
schema has attributes, and every attribute
has a domain.
The type from where it is values come.
So, if I have a composite attribute, where
every attribute has a set of components.
Then the easiest way to handle this is to
what is known as flatten the composite attribute.
So, flattening basically is for example, if
I take a name it has 3 components.
So, each one of them I can call by given new
name name underscore first name name underscore
middle initial name underscore last name . By
prefixing with the attribute name, I make
the names of these components necessarily
unique.
Now after I do the prefix thing I might figure
out that actually prefixing is not required
first name itself is a unique.
Because it does not occur anywhere else if
it is then I can I may drop the prefix name.
But in general, I can take the attribute name
prefix on the component, and just flatten
them out make them all attributes each separate
attribute.
So, here when we ah flatten out we will have
ah first name, middle, initial, last name
as you can see these flattened out from here.
Then we have street number, street name, apartment
number, flattened out from the street.
Subsequently, we have city state zip flattened
out from here.
So, all of them flattened out has become separate
attributes.
And flattening is a very straightforward mechanism
by which you can convert complex composite
attributes into the regular schema design
.
Getting to little bit of issue if you have
a multi valued attribute.
Multivalued attribute is one where one attribute
may have multiple values at the same time.
And the example we talked about is ah a phone
number.
I may have multiple phone numbers.
So, certainly against an attribute I can keep
only one value.
So, if I if my attribute is multiple value.
Then the basic idea is to use a separate schema
to maintain this multiple values.
For example, if I have to maintain multiple
phone numbers of an instructor.
I may have a separate I may decide to have
a separate relation . Which relates the key
of the instructor relation, and the attribute
that I want to ah maintain multipally.
So, in this relationship in this relation
inst underscore phone against the same id
I can have different phone numbers.
So, there will be different records which
match on the id, but do not match on the phone
number which gives me the different values
that the phone number can take.
And then this inst phone in conjunction with
the instructor relation will actually denote
the multi valued phone number attribute.
So, this is just an example showing that for
one primary key of an instructor 1 to 2 2
2 2 and there are 2 phone numbers.
So, this will basically mean you have 2 tuples
in the new relation.
So, with that we can ah handle multiple multivalued
attributes also.
Some of the relationships that we may have
modeled, which we have done ah in ah doing
the database E-R schema could have redundancy.
For example, take a case here we have the
instructor.
And we have the student advisor relation is
incidental here, and we have department.
So, we want to say that the instructors belong
to certain departments.
Every instructor belongs to one department
which is the totality of the relationship
here.
Similarly, every student belongs to a department,
totality of the relationship on this side.
And inst dept inst dept in that context is
a relationship which is between instructor
and department.
Similarly , so, we can there is certain redundancy
in this, because ah we can get make this simpler
if we just take the primary key of this relation
and put in here.
If we do that then basically this become redundant
these are no more required.
So, all that you are saying is the instructor
has a dept name field which says which department
does it belong to.
So, if there is a choice between whether you
will keep such relationships or you will actually
reduce the redundancy in the schema, and involve
the primary key of the other relation into
your primary table which is instructor or
the student here . So, instead instead of
creating a schema for relationship set inst
department.
You will simply add a department name.
So, mind you this is at the at the E-R model
level you did have a separate relationship,
but while you reduce it to your relationship
relational schema you are reducing that relationship
by including the dept name as an attribute
in instructor.
So, that is called the reduction of schema
which is often used.
Ah for one to one relationship.
So, this is this, was ah this is ah good if
you have many to one relation.
Because this was possible, because every instructor
has one department.
So, if you just include the department name
with the instructor.
Or every student has one department ah.
So, it is possible that way, but if you have
a one to one relationship, then naturally
you can do the similar reduction by I by choosing
the either side as the many.
You know, because because the the unique side
has to come on the many side.
The unique side here . This is the unique
side here.
Because every instructor has a unique department,
and this is the many side here.
So, the unique side has to attribute has to
come in here.
The unique side primary key has to come in
here.
So, instead of ah so, you can apply the same
principle to a one to one relationship by
treating any one of them as a many side, and
add the extra attribute on the other side
to get rid of this additional schema.
The schema corresponding to a relationship
set linking a weak entity set to it is underlying
strong entity set is certainly redundant,
we have already seen this.
So, this ah is made redundant by including
the primary key of the identifying relation,
identifying entity set in the weak entity
set . So, that is another reduction of schema
that can be done.
So, to summarize we have in this module illustrated
the entity relationship diagram, which are
very nice ways of graphically representing
what we see in the real world.
So, it has graphical representation of entity
sets, attributes the key attributes primary
key attributes the weak entity sets, and the
relationships along with the cardinality information.
And then we have shown that using certain
reduction rules how we can easily reduce this
entity relationship diagram or entity relationship
model into the traditional relational schema.
And we have seen that both the entity sets
as well as the relationship sets become relational
schemas.