Welcome to module 28 of Database Management
Systems.
We have ah been discussing about indexing
and hashing.
This is the the third module; in that continuation.
ah
In the last module we have taken a quick look
at the balanced BST and specifically a and
different kind of inline data structure called
2-3-4 tree, which can be of ah very good use
in terms of understanding B plus tree, which
we want to ah study in this module and we
will also take a quick look at the B tree.
So, now, B plus tree is the main data structure
ah is or one of the main data structures to
be used for index files.
So, B plus tree has ah now; what we have seen
we have seen the ordered indexes.
We have seen the index sequential files, where
you could ah keep the index file in a sorted
manner in the primary index you could build
secondary index on that and so, on, but ah
that is not an efficient way of doing things,
because the performance keeps on degrading
as ah the file grows.
Since many overflow blocks will get created,
because ah certainly if you if you are growing,
then naturally you have created say sparse
index on uncertain values and if ah there
are more ah records in that bucket.
Then naturally you need to have linked buckets.
So, periodic reorganization of the entire
file becomes required which is a very costly
affair.
In contrast advantage of B plus tree is ah
it automatically reorganizes itself in in
small bits and pieces with local changes and
so, on; whenever insertions and deletions
happen and the reorganization of the entire
file is not required for the purpose of maintenance.
Of course, there are a little bit of ah disadvantage
the extra insertion and deletion overhead
exist for the small ah you know micro reorganization
there is little bit of space over it, but
in the face of the advantage that we get ah
it outweighs the advantage is outweighs the
ah disadvantages and B plus trees are used
quite extensively.
So, just recall ah the notion of ah 2-3-4
tree that we had ah discussed and ah look
at this diagram.
So, 2-3-4 tree ah have ah different types
of node 2, node 3 node and 4 node.
So, we said that there could be a node which
can be only partially filled and ah it has
a different number of children pointing to
the; ah conditions of how different keys are
ordered in that particular node.
So, here we I show an instance of a ah B plus
tree, which is basically trying to represent
ah this ah file in terms of the creating indexes.
So, if the index is actually based on the
name.
So, this is the root node that you have and
for an instance; we are taking a structure
where every node can have ah 3 data items
and 4 links and ah it could be it could be
ah more it could be less, but this is just
for an example.
So, as you can see; so if we have this link,
then on the left of ah Mozart, then it means
all keys which are less than Mozart will be
available on this link below; the link that
ah exists here is for all keys which are greater
than Mozart and less than right.
Now there is nothing.
So, those will occur here.
So, as you can see that Einstein gold brand
all these will come on this length Srinivasan
Singh wu all this come on this side the Mozart
itself comes on this side.
Now, if I look at ah this node the next level
loads.
Now this link has values which are less than
Einstein as you can see this has values which
are between Einstein and gold.
So, Einstein and l set these are values which
are more than gold.
So, this is this is a and as you can as you
can see that ah though all all nodes are shown
to be of the same type as we had mentioned
at the end of the 2-3-4 tree discussion, but
it has variable number of ah entries.
So, the number of ah links are between n by
1 and n.
So, n here is ah 4.
So, you have at least either at least two
entries or maximum up to 4 entries that can
go on here .
So, this is the basic observe definition of
a B plus tree.
All paths from root two leaf are of the same
length.
This is again something you you should observe
here, because if you if you see all of these
paths all of them have the same length here
then the length is 2.
So, that is a basic property of 2-3-4 tree
generalized into B plus tree.
So, each node ah that is not a root is a leaf
level has between n by 2 to n children.
Leaf node has n minus 1 by 2 to n minus 1
value.
And the if the root is not a leaf, then it
has at least 2 children and if the root is
a leaf ah there is no no other nodes in the
tree then it can have between 0 to n minus
1 values which are quite obvious.
So, naturally a typical node will look like
this, where ah the pointers and key values
alternate starting with a pointer P 1, then
keep K 1 and so, on and ending with a point
at P n.
And the search keys are strictly ordered K
1 less than K 2 less than K n minus 1 these
are facts that we have seen for 2-3-4 tree.
So, for a leaf node ah the the pointed Pi
points to the file record with the search
key Ki and ah if there are two ah leaf nodes
Li and Lj and i is less than j, then Li search
key values are less than or equal to the Lj
search key values.
So, this is the basic ordering that we had
ah seen in 2-3-4 tree, that is what is getting
generalized for a non leaf ah node.
Similarly ah all search-keys in the subtree
which P 1 points to a less than K 1, then
for all that P n points to are greater than
ah K ah n minus 1.
And in the other cases they are between the
two consecutive ah key values that exist between
the pointers.
So, this is a this is an example of a simple
ah case which is n where n is equal to 6.
So, since the inter-node connections are done
by pointers, "logically" closed blocks are
not "physically" close.
So, that is a that is a key idea there is
a key observation about the B plus tree.
So, 2 ah nodes the records which are logically
closed are may not actually be physically
close, because the pointers actually define
the closeness in terms of the ordering of
the values.
So, B plus tree contains relatively small
number of levels, we will see what what that
level would be?
So, what will happen; if the level below root
root has two two values at the most at least
and ah the below that will have n by 2 values,
because every ah node has to be at least half
field.
We have said every node we will have to have
n by 2 lengths to n links it cannot be less
than that less than n by 2 link.
So, the next level as n by 2, then the next
level has 2 into n by 2 into n by 2 and so,
on.
So, every time ah you you every level you
go down you can basically ah increasing by
a factor of n by 2, which as as you all know
simply means that the number of levels or
the height is ah log K to the base n by 2,
where K is a number of ah search key values
that exist on the tree.
So, larger the end smaller is this ah value.
So, larger the node size is smaller is a is
a height and therefore, the number of ah insertion
ah number of ah you know access operations
that need to be performed.
So, insertion, deletions to the main file
can be handled efficiently as the index can
be restructured in logarithmic time as you
have just seen.
So, search should be very simple, because
ah its just an extension of what you did in
2-3-4 trees.
So, algorithm is given here I will skip it,
because we have already done this in detail.
Now, ah what we introduced I started saying
that there are no duplicates.
So, the keys follow strict ordering, but the
whole assumption will also hold good, if you
allow the equality between ah the consecutive
keys, but only difference is there could be
multiple keys which are all equal; and if
that happens then ah you have to use the same
key value present at the two leaf nodes and
the parent will also have the same leaf node
same value.
So, for ah doing in the case of such duplicates
will have to a little bit modify the procedure
for doing the search and say printing all
values and so, on.
So, you could go through that.
. So, if there is a key search-key values
in the file, then let us see what the cost
is coming to actually, then the height of
the tree is not more than log key to the best
n by 2.
So, if ah we say that the every node.
So, how large would be the node.
Now again I would remind you that we are moving
from 2-3-4 tree, which was a in memory data
structure to a external data structure.
So, our main cost is a disk axis.
So, what would you like to make this node
size, if we make the node size ah too small,
then there will be too many nodes and every
node ah will have to be accessed?
So, as you can see this is log to the base
n by 2.
So, we ah benefit by making n larger larger
the n this log value or the height will be
less, but can I make n arbitrary large then
n will not fit into one disk block.
So, it would it cannot be accessed in one
fetch from the disk to the memory.
So, we would typically like to make it is
customary to make the node as the same size
as the disk block, which is typically say
4 kilobyte or 8 kilobyte like that and ah
ah therefore, ah the if that is a size then
ah it the n will be typically around 100,
because if 4 kilobytes is a is a total space
and if I assume that 40 bytes per index entry,
which is very typical, then n would be about
100.
So, if I assume that my index file has actually
1 million ah search key values to look for,
then I will need 1 million to the base 100
by 250.
So, 1 million log 1 million to the base 50
which is approximately 4 node accesses in
a lookup table.
So, that is amazingly fast if you contrast
this with binary balanced binary tree which
will be log ah 1 million to the base 2.
So, which would be about 20 nodes ah accesses
20 ah disk accesses for this lookup.
So, this is ah the co reason that ah B plus
trees are preferred and and with this if even,
when you have couple of ah million records
in a in a table you can actually manage with
a very small number of node accesses for the
lookup, which makes the realization of algorithms
possible in the next couple of slides.
ah I have discussed about how to update B
plus trees talked about the insertion and
the deletion process.
I will skip them in the in the presentation,
now because as we have discussed the ah process
of insertion in depth in terms of the 2-3-4
tree the only difference here is that this
is ah in a generalized framework, but follows
exactly the same idea of node splitting and
keeping in mind that in case of 2-3-4 tree
you move from 2 to 3 and 3 to 4 node here.
All that you will have to remember is you
always make sure that ah you have every node
half filled, because n by 2 is a minimum requirement.
So, you keep on inserting in a node till it
becomes full, when it becomes full you cannot
insert any more you divide it and split it
into two nodes.
So, that each one of the them become at least
half filled and that is the simple ah logic
and rest of it you can ah figured out by following
on the 2-3-4 tree insertion.
So, this is the first algorithm.
Then we have shown here the strategy to splitting
the node, which I have just ah you know discussed
and the same ah notion of propagating ah the
the middle element of the split continues
here go to next and here the examples shown
in terms of the B plus tree.
Before and after insertion of a certain key
you can go through that and convince yourself.
There is some more steps in the algorithm
ah please go through them carefully and try
to understand.
The whole process and then this is the basic
algorithm written in in a very cryptic pseudocode,
I should say you should refer to the book
actually 2, 4 ah and study the whole pseudocode
to understand the algorithm better and ah
work through ah examples as well.
Similarly, examples of deletion ah in B plus
tree; so the ah trees are shown before and
after deletion of ah Srinivasan, then ah if
we delete like that.
Now in case of ah in contrast to splitting.
Now I will have merging of nodes ah which
will start happening there are some more steps
in the deletion shown here, please go through
them and work this out they should not be
you should not have any difficulty in understanding
them given your background in the 2-3-4 tree.
So, more steps in the deletion.
So, this is the deletion process in terms
of ah algorithmic steps and what you need
to do for deletion.
So, this is all detailed here just . So, B
plus tree file organization is ah takes care
of the degradation problem.
In terms of the index files which ah would
have happened, if we were used pure ordered
indices like, the index sequential access
method for storing the index files.
So, that is now taken care of and even the
data File ah degradation problem can also
be solved by using B plus T organization..
So, it can be used for both maintaining the
B the index as well as the actual data file
and the leaf nodes in the B plus tree file
organization stored the records ah instead
of ah pointers.
So, you finally, have the records there and
the leaf nodes are still required to be half
full since they are records, but since records
are larger than the maximum number of records
that can be stored would be less than the
number of pointers in a non leaf ah node insertion
and deletions are ah handled in the same way
ah as in the B plus tree index file.
So, here all all that we are explaining that.
So, far we have not explained the whole B
plus tree in terms of index file ah organization
and we are saying that you can do the same
thing with the data file and only at the leaf
level you will have to actually keep the data
records ah for ah maintenance.
So, this is ah showing some instances of the
ah B plus tree organization.
So, there is a couple of other issues the
record relocation and ah secondary index,
if a record moves all secondary indices that
store record pointers will also have to be
ah updated node splits in B plus tree file
organization is very expensive.
So, what we do is?
We use primary index search key instead of
record pointer in the secondary index.
So, in the secondary index we do not actually
keep the direct record pointer instead, we
keep the search-key of the primary index and
we know that the primary index can be very
efficiently searched.
So, what happens is when in the secondary
index when you have been able to actually
find that you do not get a pointer directly
to the record, but you get the search key
through which you can use the primary index
and actually go to that.
But with that you get yourself get rid of
the requirement of maintaining different secondary
index ah structures and ah getting into several
record relocationess problems.
There are ah your indexing also may need to
take care of other issues of string ah your
variable length string could be keys which
are variable fan out ah and so, the general
strategy in handling indexing with string
is to do a kind of what is known as prefix
compression.
So, you kind of find out what is the shortest
prefix which can distinguish between the strings.
So, if you have Silas and Silberschatz then
you can easily make out that Silb would be
a separating ah string between these two.
So, Silb will match with Silberschatz, but
or not will match with the first one.
So, you do not need to look beyond that so,
we can just keep enough ah characters to distinguish
entries in the subtree separated I by the
key values and keys in the leaf node can be
compressed by sharing common prefixes.
So, that is a very common strategy ah next
let us just take a quick look into the B tree
index file which is ah another alternate possibility
the basic difference between a B plus tree.
And B tree allows search key values to appear
only once, if you if you remember in the B
plus tree your search key values where which
occurs in an internal load keeps on occurring
at multiple ah node levels also B plus B tree
does not allow that the search key non leaf
nodes appear nowhere else in the B tree.
So, if it does not then naturally the question
is when where will the actual record value
ah we found out for this key.
So, what you do is in the node itself you
introduce another ah field after along with
the key which is the; ah pointer to the actual
record.
So, as as you can as you can see here let
us ah get back.
So, as you can see this is this was a general
ah structure of the B plus tree node.
And, now what we are doing is we are putting
in separate pointers ah along with the key
which will actually maintain the data for
that key which will be pointers to the actual
record, because this earlier in B plus tree
all ah records.
Finally, appear in terms of the leaf level
nodes only they are their pointers come in
the leaf level whereas, here the there is
no repetition of the search key along the
structure.
So, they come wherever there.
So, let me just ah show you an example.
So, if you look into this ah carefully.
So, this is ah what you have seen is a B plus
tree.
So, you can see that Mozart happened here,
it also happened here and this is the leaf
level.
So, from here actually you get pointers to
the; to the record for Mozart.
Similarly, Einstein happens here and it happens
here ah Srinivasan happens here in.
So, there are multiple times there happening
this in contrast is a B tree representation
where Einstein, if it happens then alongside
with it the pointer to the Einstein's record
exists, if brands happen here along with it
the brands record exists and Einstein would
not happen anywhere else in the tree.
So, you do not have the second instance of
the Einstein or this instance of the Mozart
in the B tree.
So, naturally that is the basic optimization
that ah B tree does?
. So, it is advantages it may use ah less
notes than the corresponding B plus tree sometimes
it is possible to find the search key value
even before reaching the leaf node.
So, search could be efficient, but it does
have a lot of ah disadvantages, ah because
ah what happens is only small fraction of
all search key values ah are actually found
early non leaf nodes are larger.
Now, because you you have ah pointers to the
data as well.
So, the fan out gets reduced which means that
the number of children you can have is gets
reduced.
So, ah though you are expecting to get a benefit,
because you are not having to go to the leaf
every time, but you pay off because your fan
out gets less.
So, if your fan out get less naturally the
tree has a greater depth.
Now, because you can you are fanning out less
number of children at every node.
So, it has a greater depth.
So, eventually your cost increases the naturally
the deletions insertions are more complicated
than in B plus tree and implementation is
more difficult.
So, typically the advantages of B tree do
not outweigh the disadvantages.
So, it is not very frequent that you will
use b trees ah, but they they are use at times,
but thats not a very common thing and we stick
to B plus tree for both of the data file as
well as index file ah storage . So, in this
module you have understood the design of ah
B plus ah index B plus tree index files in
depth for the purpose of data base persistent
store and ah I would again remind you that
ah whole discussion of how B plus tree is
organized and how operations of access insert
delete are done in B plus tree.
I have introduced them in ah keeping in parallel
with the simpler in memory data structure
for this which is a 2-3-4 tree discussed in
the last module.
So, while ah ah going through the insertion
deletion ah processes of B plus tree, if you
have difficulty following I would ah request
that you go back to the 2-3-4 tree that is
kind the the simplest situation that can have
that can occur and ah understand that and
then you come back to the specific ah points
in the B plus tree algorithm and also always
keep in mind.
When you refer to 2-3-4 tree for understanding
also always keep in mind that in case of B
plus tree all load types are same and the
basic requirement is every node must be at
least half full all the time except of course,
for the root.
And ah in addition we have also familiarized
with B tree and reason that ah B tree possibly
is not a very powerful is not powerful enough
it does not give enough advantages so, that
to we would like to use it in place of B plus
tree.