Welcome to module 6 of database management
systems, this is the starting of week 2. In
week 1 we have done 5 modules, after the overview
of the course, we have primarily introduced
the basic notions of DBMS and we have discussed
about the relational module, the fundamentals
of it.
In this background, in this week we are primarily
focusing on the query language the structured
query language SQL. So, all the 5 modules
will relate to discussions on query language
and this module 6 7 and 8, the 3 modules will
introduce SQL at a first level and the last
2 modules 8 and 9, I am sorry 9 and 10 will
discuss about intermediate, that is somewhat
advanced level of features in the SQL.
The objective of the current module is to,
understand the relational query language and
particularly the data definition and the basic
query structure, that will hold for all SQL
queries, particularly this the modules this
week would be important for writing any kind
of database applications, squaring the database
to find information from the existing data
and to manipulate it. So, please put a lot
of focus in the whole material of this week
and practice them well, to understand the
basic issues of database systems, in depth
in a well oriented manner. In this module
we will first talk about the history and then
we will see how to define data and start manipulating
them.
SQL was originally called IBM sequel language
and was a part of system R, it was subsequently
renamed as structured query language and like
any other good programming language that we
have, SQL also gets standardized by ANSI and
ISO and there have been several standards
of SQL, that has come up with SQL 92 in the
most popular one, and the commercial system,
most of them try to provide support for SQL
92 features, but they do vary between themselves.
So, it is possible that the examples that
we show here, may or may not all of them execute
in the system that you are using. So, you
will have to look at what standard your system
is actually following.
So, the first what we will talk about is a
DDL data definition language, as we had discussed
earlier this is the features to create that
schema the tables in a database management
system.
So, it allows for the creation or definition
of the schema, for each relation that we have
in the database it specifies the domain of
values associated with each attribute of the
schema and it also defines a variety of integrity
constraints, later in the course we will see
that, it also has to specify other related
information like indexing, security authorization,
physical storage and so on.
So, first the domain of possible values. So,
we have already specified that, every domain
in SQL is more of an atomic nature. So, they
are more like the primitive or built in data
types of languages like c, c plus plus, java.
So, the common domain types are character
which are basically strings of character,
having a certain length then you can have
variable character string which means that
the length here specifies that, the maximum
length that the string can take, but a string
could be shorter than that integer; obviously,
then small integer, which in a system may
give a smaller range of integer values.
Then there is a numeric type which is often
very important, which says what is the precision
of the numbers that are to be written in this
format stored in this format. So, d basically
gives that precision value and p gives the
size, then you can have real and double precision
numbers you have can have floating point numbers
and so on, and there are some more data types,
which we will discuss later in the course.
Given all these domain types; so, what we
will try to do is, here is a schema for the
university database, which has multiple different
relations designed in that showing the attributes
and marking out, what are the keys? And what
are the foreign keys? So, we would take examples
of some of these and try to code them in the
SQL.
Now, to create a table this is how you go
about, the SQL keywords create table is the
basic command. So, with the create table you
have to specify a name, here the name that
is given is in terms of this name r, which
is the name of the relation and then you provide
a series of attributes, separating by comma
A I are different attributes and for every
attribute, there is a corresponding type domain
type specified. So, is it says that A 1 is
of domain type d 1, A 2 is of domain type
d 2 and so on. And all of these attribute
descriptions, are then followed by a series
of integrity constraints. It is possible that
a create table may not provide any constraint,
but often you will have a number of constraints
to work with. So, here is one example.
So, in this we are trying to code the creation
of this instructor table, as you can see it
has 4 different fields ID name, department
name and salary and for each one we have specified
the domain type. So, ID is char 5, this means
that the identity of this table instructor
will be strings of length 5 whereas, the name
or the department name are strings, but they
have a maximum length 20, but they could have
be of variable length where a salary is of
numeric type having specification 8 2. So,
it can have 2 decimal places and be of size
8 maximum. So, this is the basic form of definition
that we have for creating a table, defining
a table or defining a schema.
Now, we can add a number of integrity constraints
to the create table, 3 integrity constraints
we will discuss here, one is not null, one
is primary key and other third is foreign
key. So, not null we specify whether a field
can be null or not, primary key as we have
seen will specify the attributes which form
the primary key, and the foreign key will
specify the attributes which reference some
other table and our key in that table. So,
here is an example, in the instructor relation
here we have we had seen this part, the attribute
what we have added here is, this not null.
So, we say the name is not null which means
that, in the instructor table it is not possible
to insert a record, where the name of the
instructor is null that is unknown, but it
is possible if the same thing is not said
about department name same thing is not said
about salary. So, it is possible that these
could be null.
Now, we additionally say that primary key
is ID. So, this field ID is a primary key
and it is a property of SQL create table command
that, if an attribute is referred as a primary
key, then it cannot be not null. So, you do
not need to specify that is here you do not
need to write not null, because it is a primary
key it will be known to be not null, because
certainly we have discussed that key is the
distinguishing attribute in a database a table.
So, it cannot be null.
So, it will not be able to distinguish similarly,
we have finally we have the third integrity
constant which is foreign key which says that,
it is referencing this table department and
the foreign key of this is here, the depth
name this particular field is a foreign key,
which is a key of the department table. And
so, we will be able to refer this, from this
table as a foreign key and we know that it
will be key in the department table. So, these
are the ways to specify the integrity constraint.
So, here are a couple of more examples. So,
I will not go through them in detail, I will
request you to take time and carefully understand
them, again these are about different relations
that exist here, about the student and about
the courses that the students take, and in
every case we have specified the set of fields,
that you have in the table in the design of
the schema are listed, in the create table
the ID information about the primary key is
provided and also the information about the
foreign key.
Here department name is the foreign key which
is mapping to this point, similar things can
be observed about the takes relationship which
show the how students are actually taking
courses. So, it relates different it has a
set of fields but it has 2 kinds of primary
foreign keys, one that relate to the student
through the ID and this combination of attributes
which refer to the section.
So, this is how different tables can be created
using the data definition language, here is
a note that you should observe that if you
consider this section ID, the section ID is
a part of the primary key which means that
2 records cannot be same, if they are different
in the section ID, then such records are allowed.
So which means that it is possible that, a
student can attend or take a course in the
same semester, in the same year with 2 different
section IDs because they are primary keys.
So, they can be different. So, if we drop
this from the primary key then we will enforce
the condition that, no student will be able
to take a course, in 2 sections in the same
semester and the same year. So, this is these
are the different design choices that we have
and we will move on, here is one more example
trying to show you the create table command
for the course relation, that we have in the
university database.
Moving on, let us look at how to update or
actually put in different records, in a table
which has already been created, the basic
command is insert, and the keywords for that
is insert into and values, in between you
write the name of the relation, where the
record will have to be inserted and then the
values, will have to be put as a tuple in
the same order in which you would have defined
the attributes of that relation, and certainly
each of the values like this is ID value,
next is the name value the department the
salary, each one of them should be from the
same domain type, as has been specified during
the create table come on.
So, these things will have to remember. And
so, every record will get inserted through
one insert command, similarly a deletion can
be done by delete from students, if you do
delete from students without specifying which
record you want to delete, basically all records
will get deleted. We will see how selective
deletion will happen, that will come on later.
Drop table is a command to remove a table,
a table that has been created can be removed
from the database altogether, by doing drop
table and the relation name you can also change
the schema of a table by using alter table.
So, the form is altar table is a the key words,
you can add a new attribute to relation are
by writing the name of the attribute and the
domain of the attribute one after the other.
Similarly, it is possible also to drop an
attribute that already exists and the syntax
for that will be, alter table the relation
name drop is a keyword and the name of the
attribute, mind you all database systems may
not allow you to drop an attribute to alter
table to remove attributes. And so, it works
in some and it does not work in the rest.
Now, let us. So, that was about the definition
of the table and the basic definition of the
data. So, now we will get into the basics
query structure which is with tables with
existing data, how do I query and find out
different information.
So, the structure of an SQL query and this
you should observe very carefully is normally
said to be, select from where colloquially
will often say, let us have a select from
where. So, it has 3 keywords select which
is followed by a set of this is a set of attributes.
So, this specifies that, when a select query
runs it will finally give us a new relation
and in that relation, the attributes that
will be available are the attributes that
feature in the select list. The next clause
or the next keyword in this is from, which
specifies a set of existing relations.
So, r 1 r 2 r m represent different relations
and these are the relations, which will be
used to actually find the information extract
the information. Finally, the where clause
has a predicate as a condition, which specify
that what condition has to be satisfied. So,
that certain peoples from the relations r
1 to r m, will be chosen and put in this new
selected result, table in terms of the attributes
a 1 to a n.
So, this is the basic understanding of the
or structure of the SQL query and naturally
as I mentioned that will result in a relation.
Now, we will go over each and every clause
carefully, the select clause as I said will
list all the attributes. So, it is like a
projection in terms of the relational algebra
that we have done. So, if we write select
name from instructor then this will result
in finding the names of all instructors from
the instructor table, because this is this
you know is a relation, because it is happening
it is a featuring in the from clause and in
select, we are saying that the attribute that
we want to select is the attribute name.
So, it will the instructor table has 4 attributes
ID, name, depth name and salary from that
it will simply take the name of the instructor
and list that in the output table. So, the
basic form of selection that happens and this
point you may also note, that in SQL everything
is case insensitive, it does not matter whether
you write in upper case or lower case. So,
you can choose the style that you prefer to
use.
This is a very important factor, that you
should keep in mind that we said a while introducing
relational algebra, that in the relational
algebra every relation is a set and which
means that according to set theory. We cannot
have 2 tuples in the same relation, which
are identical in all it is values, because
set theory does not allow that, but please
keep in mind that SQL actually allows duplicates
in relations. So, it is possible that in the
same relation in the same table, I may have
more than one record which are identical in
all the fields, in all the attributes of that
table and this will have lot of consequences
and we will see how often, this property will
have to be used.
So, if you want a typical set theoretic kind
of output, that is if you want the result
to be distinct, all records to be distinct,
then you have to explicitly say that you want
distinct values to be selected. So, all that
you are doing is you are after select and
before the attribute name, you introduce another
keyword distinct.
So, select distinct depth name from instructor
will actually, select the departments of all
instructors and quite why if it just selects
department name of all instructor, then it
is quite possible that the same department
name will appear number of times, because
every department has multiple instructors.
But when we use distinct, then the every name
will feature only once in that selection,
then you can also specify another keyword
all which ensures that the duplicates are
not removed. So, if you do select all depth
name, then all the names will feature with
duplicates, if some department had 3 instructors
the name of that department will feature thrice.
You can use an asterisk after select, to specify
that you are interested in all the attributes
that the relation or the collection of relations
in the from clause has. You can also specify
a select with a literal and without a from
clause, if you do that then it will simply
return you a table with a single row having
that literal value and you can also rename
that table, using what is known as clause
as command. So, this will give you a table
Foo, where there is only one row and that
row has an entry 437. You can use that, for
other purposes also you can do a select of
a literal, from a table with using a from
clause where in a, you will get a single column
table, where as many is as there are records
in the instructor will be produced.
Select clause can also use basic arithmetic
operations for example, here we are showing
a select where the third attribute as you
can see, the third attribute is salary by
12, assuming that the instructor table has
a salary number which is annual salary by
12 naturally you give you the monthly salary.
So, those such arithmetic choices can also
be made, you can also rename that field that
particular salary by 12 field by a new name,
as I said as can be used to rename. So, if
we if you use that then, when you get the
output you will get the column names are ID,
name and monthly salary and in monthly salary
you will actually have a computation, which
is salary by 12 and in the same way, you can
use multiple different kinds of arithmetic
operators.
Now, we come to the where clause, where clause
specifies the condition is a predicate which
corresponds to the selection predicate of
relational algebra. So, it will specify some
condition, here is an example if we want to
find all instructors from the instructor table,
who are associated with computer science department,
then you can say select name from instructor
and to specify that they are from the computer
science department, you will specify department
name is equal to computer science.
So, this will ensure that you select the records
only when this condition is satisfied. So,
all records for which department name is different
from computer science will not be included
here. You can also write predicates using
the different logical connectives and or not
and so on. So, here is an example, where you
are finding all instructors in computer science
with salary greater than 80000. So, here we
have used and clause. So, only records where
the department name is computer science and
salary is greater than 8000 will be chosen
in the result. So, and then the projection
will be done on the name of those instructors,
you can apply comparisons of arithmetic expression.
So, where clause can really write different
kind of things.
Finally, the from clause is sets all the different
relations from where you are actually looking
for the records. So, it kind of corresponds
to the Cartesian product of the relational
algebra. So, if we want to say compute instructor
Cartesian product teachers, then you can say
select star instructor one table comma teachers.
So, this will choose records from instructed
relation, as well as from teacher's relation
and in all possible combined way, it will
put them in the output we have used a star.
So, all fields of in tractor and all fields
of teaches will be there in the output, and
since some fields may have identical name
like ID in instructor and there is ID in teachers,
they will be qualified by the name of the
relation, from can have 1 relation 2 relation
any number of relations as you require. So,
this will cause the Cartesian product to be
computed which may not be very useful as a
an independent feature, but we will see in
the next module how it can give very important
computations, in terms of computing joints
and so on.
So, here is an example of the Cartesian product
that we talked of. So, here is a instructor
relation, the teacher's relation and as you
can see when we have done this cartesian product,
that is select star from instructor comma
teachers, then all fields this is a ID of
the instructor it has there is an ID in teachers.
So, that is also specified here qualified
by the name of the relation whereas, name
comes in directly because there is no attribute
called name in teachers, the department name
comes in directly, salary comes in, directly
course ID comes in, section ID comes in, semester
comes in, year comes in and so on. And the
combination of all tuples in their instructor
relation, against all tuples of the teacher's
relation all possible combinations have come
in this result, which eventually is a cartesian
product of the relational algebra.
So, this is the what we have to summarize,
we have introduced the relational query language
and particularly familiarize ourselves with
the data definition, that is creation of the
table creation, of the schema with the attribute
names, domain types and constraints. And the
updates to the table in terms of insertion
and deletion of values or addition or deletion
of attributes or removing a table altogether
and then, we have given the basic structure
of the select from where query of SQL, which
will be the key language feature of a query
language, that we will continue to discuss
all through this course. .