welcome to module four of database management
systems in the last two modules ah we have
introduced the basic notions of d b m s s
in this module and the next we make an introduction
to the relational model which we said is a
major data model that we are going to use
so this is a what we did in the last module
and in the current one our objective will
be to understand key concepts of relational
model that is attributes and their types the
basic mathematical structure of instance schema
and what is known as keys and to familiarize
with different types of relational query languages
this is a module outline that we will follow
so we again repeat this example from past
this is an example of instructors in a university
a table of instructors given by attributes
or columns i d name department name and salary
these are the four columns the four i ds and
multiple rows which are specific rows or we
often refer to them as tuples so you can say
that since there are four attributes that
is every row has four columns so this is a
four tuple that we have and such a table is
called a relation is as simple as that so
this is it whenever we talk about a relation
we have a number of fields number of attributes
number of columns whatever way we said of
a table and that table according to those
columns it has multiple zero one or any number
of rows of values filled in and that is what
is a relation
now so let us look at attributes more specifically
so attributes each column is an attribute
as you said this every attribute has a domain
the domain is a set of possible values that
attribute can take so if you just look into
the example here so i am trying to define
a table having different students so there
is a roll number for a student there is a
first name last name the date of birth d o
b the passport number the adhaar card number
the department to which the student belongs
and so on so let us say these one two three
four five six seven are the different attributes
now if we look into every attribute then every
attribute has a set of possible values of
which some value is entered in a particular
row for example the roll number is an alphanumeric
string as you can see it has numeric as well
as it has letters whereas the first name or
the last name are simple alpha strings in
fact we can also say that the roll number
actually is not only alphanumeric it has a
fixed length it has a length of here is its
length of nine so you can say alphanumeric
strings of length nine are eligible for being
values of this domain there could be more
restrictions but that the domain will be certain
collection of values which are possible as
values of that attribute when you talk about
d o b that certainly has to be a date so it
is written in the form of d d m m m y y y
y that is two digit date three letter month
code and four digit year the passport number
is a string a letter followed by seven digits
the other number is a twelve digit number
the department is alpha string and so on so
the domain is a set corresponding to an attribute
which define that all possible values that
attribute can take ok
now ah these attribute values if you look
at they are atomic in nature that is you cannot
divide them into smaller parts so what i mean
is say when we are talking about date of birth
the whole date of birth type the date type
is one atomic value for example if you were
to code this in c what you could do you could
ah possibly create a structure with three
fields one is date one is a month one is a
year and we will say that this composite record
composite structure is actually my date they
can do a l s type def you could do if you
are working in c plus plus you will define
a class called date which has these components
and as well as operations with them but that
kind of types are not allowed in a relational
database it has to be an atomic type so in
a relational database will give you atomic
type called date but all of these are pre
specified and has to be taken as one unit
other atomic types are integer ah like we
do not have an integer field here there are
strings there are numerical values which are
kind of floating point values and so on
now some attribute may have a special value
called the null value which is ah the member
of it is domain actually every attribute ah
of any domain can have this special value
the null value is not actually a value it
is actually an absence of a value so it says
that this value is not known so if you look
into the example above then you will see that
for passport we have said that the passport
is a string ah letter followed by seven digits
and it is nullable which means that in the
passport field i may have a value may have
this null value which means that it is not
that the the passport is null what it is saying
is the this passport number for this particular
student the row number two is not known is
unknown now all fields may or may not be nullable
for example will not allow d o b to be nullable
date of birth has to be there will not allow
roll number to be nullable will not allow
first name to be nullable but we may allow
last name to be nullable it is been a been
a style of let not to use your last name many
many people just use one name so you could
allow that it is not known it is not there
whereas ah ah department may not be nullable
it must be there so null is a very critical
concept and what it actually does it actually
ah creates a lot of issues ah and complications
in terms of defining many operations so understanding
null as a value in terms of an attribute is
a critical requirement for the design
now coming to the schema and instance we have
ah discussed about the basic understanding
of schema and instance so understanding them
formally now we say that if we have a schema
so it is like a table having multiple columns
say there are n columns having names a one
to a n then this a one to a n are the attributes
so these are the different attributes that
it will have so ah i am so ah these are the
different attributes so if i have this then
it it basically means that i have a table
where the these are the columns a one a two
a n like this ok so then a relational schema
is a collection of these attributes so it
is a collection of all these ah attributes
so we said r is a relational schema which
has attributes a one to a n
now every attribute a i has a domain d i so
for every attribute i have a set of values
that are possible so if you ah if you recall
then here ah we had different these are the
different attributes and these are their different
domain so d o b is an attribute and the domain
is date so any possible date other is an attribute
and this is the domain which is a so all attributes
each attribute will need to have certain domain
and those are marked by the d sets so we will
say that a particular relation a particular
relation r so r is a schema schema so a particular
relation r is a subset of d one plus d two
cross dot dot dot d l so recall the mathematical
notion of relation which say that a relation
is basically a subset of a set so these are
the possible values so the first attribute
can take values from d one second attribute
can take values from d two and so on and the
nth attribute can take values from d n so
any specific row any specific record is a
set of values for a one a two a n and therefore
is a member of this cartesian product and
the relation is a subset of that so this is
a d value is an n tuple which is a subset
of this a one a two a n this particular record
is an element of this cartesian product set
and r necessarily is a set of such tuples
that is a mathematical view of the schema
and the instance so this is the schema and
this is the instance corresponding to that
schema based on the different domains of the
different attributes and this is the notion
that we will continue using so ah please try
to follow this carefully
now whenever we have an instance we mark that
as a table and every such table so here you
have now understood it very well so these
are my attributes so this is a one this is
a two this is a three this is a four and any
one i name is at the different values a two
a three a one a two a three a four nine eight
three four five is a one kim is a two and
so on now naturally this it is not visible
from the instance because we are taking an
instance view we are not being able to see
what that domain is that will be visible if
we look at the corresponding d d l the definition
language description of the schema which must
have specified i d as a numeric value the
name as a string value the department name
as another string value whereas salary as
a numeric value and so on ok
now what is important to note here is a relation
necessarily is a set as as we said is is a
set which is the ah as the relation r is a
is a set this is a set which is a subset of
this set so a set we know the elements in
a set are do not have any ordering they are
unordered so a relation is necessarily unordered
so it does not really matter that in terms
of this collection of rows which row is at
what position if i reorder them the relation
does not change it is just that they are a
collection of this set of rows so that lack
of ordering is a critical information that
we will have to remember in mind next concept
is key so r as we have seen is a relational
schema which is a collection of which is a
collection of attributes a one a two a n now
k let k be a subset of r so it is one or more
attributes it has to be a non empty subset
now we will say that k is a super key of r
if if we consider the values of different
tuples in the attributes of k and we find
that there cannot be two tuples which are
different but match on these attributes which
mean that the values of the attributes of
k uniquely identify each row of the relation
then we will say that k is a k is a super
key of r so the instructor table that we have
seen i d is a super key similarly so k can
be taken as a singleton set of attribute i
d or k can be thought of as the set comprising
i d and name both of them are super keys of
instructor
now we say a super key k is a candidate key
if k is minimal so the idea is like this that
this is a key super key this is also a super
key but certainly this is a subset of this
this is smaller than this so we will say this
is a candidate key but this is not a candidate
key because it does not satisfy the minimality
condition
there could be multiple candidate key in a
relation if there are multiple candidates
key then we select one to be the primary key
now obviously there is a question of which
one we select but anyone can be selected as
a primary key which is the key of the relation
and we will see that in some cases ah there
is concept of surrogate keys so if i have
a relation where there is no attribute which
can whose value can uniquely identify each
and every row of the table then i might synthetically
generate a value for example like a serial
number i can generate a serial number and
say that this is my value so that serial number
or that computer generated field value has
no business implication the real world did
not have this value it is not like a adhaar
card number or like a passport number but
it is a value which is purely generated to
identify every row uniquely so such keys are
known as surrogate keys or synthetic keys
now let us look at some examples this is again
the same student database i just shown a while
ago the same set of columns but i have added
few more rows now if we look at what could
be a super key there are several candidates
but i have just written a few ah roll number
is certainly a key because i am assuming that
the university assigns roll numbers to uniquely
identify every student so there cannot be
two rows in this table which match in the
value of the roll number and does not match
in the values of the other fields so roll
number can uniquely identify if it can then
any super set of attributes which continual
number will also be a super key so roll number
and date of birth together is a super key
that can also unique to identify every row
trivial what are the candidate keys now there
are of course that could be several other
super keys that has to be kept in mind the
candidate keys are roll number is a candidate
key the first name last name together we can
say is a candidate key
so we are saying that not only the first name
but if we take this pair you remember the
key the set of attributes forming a super
key is a is a set it is not an individual
field so i say the first name last name together
from say key well this does make some assumption
because if i say the first name last name
together from say key that means that there
cannot be two records in this student table
where the first name and last name match but
the records are different so which mean that
no two students having the same first name
and last name can be enrolled in the university
this is a restrictive assumption right but
i am just making that assumption to illustrate
the different possibilities then what is the
other possibility passport number everybody
has a unique passport number so passport number
could also be a key could be a candidate key
adhaar number everybody has a unique adhaar
number so that can be a key and so on
so these are called the candidate keys now
of course we can observe that given the data
it it is clear and it was also mentioned when
the schema was designed this passport number
cannot be a key why can it not be a key can
two students have different same ah passport
number of course not every student has a unique
passport number but it is possible that some
student does not have a passport so if a some
student does not have a passport then the
passport number field of that student is a
null the passport number is a nullable field
if the passport number is null then it is
possible that multiple students may not have
passports so as we can see here that this
student jatin chopra does not have a passport
so similarly dipti dutta does not have a passport
either so certainly if this were to be the
key then for all records for which passport
number is nil this value would not be able
to distinguish them in terms of the rows of
the table so we have to say that passport
number cannot be a key or in other words we
can say that no key can be a nullable field
no key attribute or a participant to a key
attribute could be a nullable field right
so this is one observation here and so that
clearly also implies that if we say that adhaar
number is a valid candidate key that will
mean that for admission to that university
having adhaar number would be mandatory if
somebody does not have a adhaar number that
will have to be null which is not allowed
ok
so let us ah move on so one of these candidate
keys have to be made the primary keys let
us say we make roll number the primary key
and since we make roll number the primary
key in the schema we underlined the roll number
attribute this would be a common way to show
that roll number is a primary key so the others
that are not taken as a primary key are called
the secondary or alternate key so first name
last name pair could be an alternate key adhaar
number could be an alternate key and so on
a key is said to be simple if it consists
of a single attribute so roll number is a
simple key adhaar numbered is a simple key
if it were taken to be primary but first name
last name pair if we take that to be a primary
that will not be considered assemble simple
key because it has more than one attribute
naturally the other if you have a simple key
they have other side is a composite key a
composite key is one which has more than one
field such that none of those fields individually
can act as a key but together they can act
as a key so first name itself cannot be a
key last name itself cannot be a key but together
they can be a key of course under the assumption
that no two students with the same first name
last name are given admission so these are
the different types of keys that can happen
let us have some more views with the keys
we extend the schema and besides a student
i introduce two more schema one is called
the courses which is given by course number
course name credits l t p l t p is number
of hours of lectures tutorials and practicals
and the department so these are the different
fields and from the convention already stated
you can figure out that course number is the
key primary key of this relation i use another
schema which is enrolment which describes
which student is attending which course so
it has a roll number and the course number
so roll number of the student attending the
particular course number and it also has an
instructor i d as to who is teaching that
course given this you can see that in a in
the enrolment relationship i have this pair
roll number and course number which will certainly
be the key for enrolment because if i have
two rows in enrolment how they will be distinguished
they cannot be distinguished by roll number
because a particular student may take multiple
courses so there will be multiple records
having the same roll number but different
course number the course number by itself
cannot be the key because every course will
have multiple students so there will be multiple
rows having the same course number but all
different roll numbers but if we take this
together roll number and course number together
then that forms a key
now such a key such a key having roll number
the roll number itself is a key of another
relation the course number itself is a key
of another relation so when we take the keys
of other relations to form the key of a relation
then we say that these are foreign keys so
roll number and course number are foreign
keys in student and course and since from
enrolment the student and courses are being
referenced are being referred so we say enrolment
is a referencing relation and students and
courses other reference relation and we will
often like to also mention as to what is a
foreign key of a relational schema because
that will help us understand how the different
schemas are interrelated and we will see that
this will come out directly from the notion
of entities and relationships of a year model
of a year diagram a key key is called to be
said to be compound if it consists of more
than one attribute to uniquely identify an
entity occurrence so each attribute which
makes up the key is a simple key in its own
right mind you there is a subtle it sounds
very similar we talked about composite key
earlier we talked up we are talking about
compound key here the subtlety of the difference
is in a composite key every component attribute
is not a simple key by itself but and the
components come from the same table in a compound
key the components are simple key by their
in their own right in some other table and
are put together as a compound key in the
given table so the rule number course number
in the enrolment table is a compound key
so with this i would request you to spend
some time with this relatively elaborated
schema compared to what we have done already
of the university database so every every
rectangular box shows a relational schema
on top of each in blue is written the name
of that relation relational schema so it has
a relational schema like courses the students
the instructors the departments the prerequisites
the time slots the classrooms and so on the
sections and the relationships between them
for example the relationship is takes is a
relationship which relates students with different
sections sections with courses teachers is
another relationship which relates to instructors
with sections so it is showing you directly
as to how the keys of this what are the attributes
what are the key attributes primary key attributes
and also what are the foreign keys that we
have in this for example intakes this is a
foreign key which is featured here course
i d section i d semester here are the foreign
key part of the takes that exists here so
please study ah this schema we will keep on
regularly referring to this schema in future
as well ah so this is what we have here
now we move on to the relational query language
we briefly talk about the relational query
language now we will have to ah in this the
key thing that we need to understand is ah
the relational query language is somewhat
different from the programming languages that
you have studied so far which are procedural
in nature in contrast the relational query
language is non procedural or declarative
in nature a procedural programming language
requires that the programmer tell the computer
how to get the output given the input a pro
program is about finding output for a given
input and you write a procedure the sequence
of steps that need to be done so that given
the input you can compute the output so you
say how the that computation has to happen
and the programmer must know that algorithm
in contrast in declarative programming you
say what you want you will do not say how
that needs to be computed how that will be
computed you may not even know that you may
not even know a single algorithm to compute
the output but you specify what output you
need so this distinction between how and what
of programming differentiates procedural and
declarative programming
so all that you have studied so far in terms
of c c plus plus java python and all that
are procedural programming where you necessarily
have to specify how you will have necessarily
have to specify what the algorithm is but
in declarative you just say what you need
so just a a simple you know ah pathological
example to understand this difference suppose
we were interested in computing the square
root of a number n assuming n is a positive
number the procedural step would be something
like this is an algorithm that you guess a
an x naught which is a square root which is
close to the root of n i mean some guess you
make and then you repeatedly refine this estimate
by taking the arithmetic mean of the estimate
and the quotient of the division of n by this
estimate so you take an arithmetic mean and
find the new estimate and repeat the steps
till you i mean as long as the difference
between the two conservative estimates is
more than a certain value delta this is a
procedural algorithm you are giving an algorithm
so given and following this algorithm we will
find the square root declaratively you can
just say that what is the result i want i
want to result m such that m square equals
n
so you are again asking for the same feel
you are expecting the same output but the
way you are saying is not an algorithm you
are rather specifying a predicate which must
be true in your output you are saying that
the predicate is m square must be n so whatever
m is that square of it must equal n so this
style is known as declarative whereas the
earlier style is known as procedure all query
languages relational query languages are declarative
in nature um we have talked about the pure
languages ah are they are all equivalent we
mentioned that earlier also and also again
to remember that none of them are actually
turing equivalent that means that not all
algorithms can be expressed in them or specifically
relational algebra which we are will look
at in more depth and the relational algebra
will consist of six basic operations which
we will discuss in the next module so to sum
up we have introduced the notion of attributes
and their types we have taken an overview
of the mathematical structure of the relational
model schema and instance we would say mathematically
they are relations mathematically they made
a mapping and we have introduced the very
important concept of keys and in that very
specifically what is a primary key as well
as what is a foreign key in the next module
we will discuss about the different operations
of relational model relational logic