Welcome, to module - 36 of Database Management
Systems. In this module and the next, we will
talk about recovery in databases.
In the last week, ah we have talked at length
in terms of ah the transactions and the concurrency
control and we will see how the acid properties
of the transaction can be fulfilled ah using
the different recovery schemes.
To specifically we will try to understand
the different sources of failure and ah how
the recovery can be facilitated by different
storage structures particularly ah those ah
different models of volatile and nonvolatile
ah storages and ah we will take a look into
recovery schemes that are based on logging
mechanism and ah for this module we will focus
only on single transactions. So, these are
the ah topics ah that will cover.
So, we ah, what we have looked at is ah all
database writes and reads are within a transaction
and transactions ah must satisfy the ACID
properties and ah in terms of the concurrency
control we have already seen that concurrency
in a controlled guarantees ah isolation of
transactions and in ah in a certain way it
contributes to achieving ah maintaining consistency.
Application programs are heavily responsible
for guaranteeing consistency, but ah to really
guaranty the atomicity and durability of the
data that the transactions reads and write
the recovery sub system is required and it
also contributes to the consistency property.
So, let us look at ah if we are talking about
recovery and the phase of failure. So, let
us look at what are the ah generic types of
failures that can happen one is the type transactions
can fail. A transaction can fail due to logical
error due to some internal error or it might
fail due to some ah system error. So, that
ah the system must terminate the transaction,
we have talked about ah several situations
where deadlock might happen and the transaction
needs to be rolled back ah that is a kind
of ah transaction failure error.
The second possible error can happen if there
is a crash in the system. A system can crash
due to hardware failure power failure software
failure. So, um ah we try to make fail stop
assumptions that ah nonvolatile contents are
assumed to be eh corrupted and ah database
systems consequently have to involve a number
of integrity checks to prevent the corruption
of data.
And, ah the third broad category of failures
happen with disk failure a disk might itself
fail it is ah it is hardware may fail the
head may crash ah and when that ah happens
then the destruction is assumed to be detectable
we must be able to detect ah such failures.
Ah there are checksums and other mechanisms
for detecting failures, but broadly these
are the three types of ah failures that a
ba database system can go through.
So, in view of that ah ifs one or more of
this failures happen then we need ah mechanisms
to recover from that let us consider a very
simple ah situation of a transaction which
ah we saw ah earlier to that a transaction
T i transfers ah dollar 50 from account A
to account B and therefore, two updates have
to happen; A has to get debited and B has
to get credited. So, the transaction T i requires
updates to A and B that are happening that
must be written that must be output to the
database in a permanent manner.
So, if failure may occur ah after one of this
modifications have happened and before both
of them are made, so that is one possibility.
One possibility is we can get we have modified
the database without ah ensuring that the
transaction will necessarily commit, but the
database has been checked transaction may
not have committed. So, that will leave the
database inconsistent because the transaction
will have to be rolled back or it may so happen
that ah database has not been modified and
ah the, but ah the transaction has committed.
So, ah if the failure occurs at that ah point
then there will be some lost updates. So,
the recovery algorithms ah strategy has to
primarily take care of two things; one is
during the normal transactions it has to ah
collect enough informations so that the recovery
from failures can be done. So, one is what
we need to do while in normal transaction
is going on because during that time we need
to have enough data so that we can recovery
in the phase of failure and the second ah
set of actions are actions that can once a
failure has happened to recover the database
so that we can ah go back to a consistent
state and ensure the atomicity consistency
and durability of the transaction.
So, before we get into ah these ah discussions
of ah the different ah recovery algorithms
let us quickly look into this storage model
that we are assuming.
We know there is volatile storage which we
have discussed about that we know this ah
nonvolatile storage which ah disk, tape, flash
and all that volatile storage ah disappears
ah whenever system crashes and ah non-volatile
storage is supposed to survive the system
crash, but it may still fail it may still
cause loss of data.
So, we also consider a third kind of storage
which is ah notionally known as stable storage.
It is called a mythical form of storage ah
where we assume that it will survive all kinds
of failures. Now, naturally this ah in in
ideality this can never happen, but we can
approximate this by maintaining multiple copies
ah of the same data on distinct non-volatile
media and ah the stables storage would be
assumed to be one available component ah in
the database system for making the recovery
systems work.
So, as you can see in this ah ah ah diagram
below. So, we are trying to ah explain more
of what is the stable storage. So, this is
a on the secondary storage so, you have a
stable database. So, kind of approximates
that it will never fail ah whereas, ah on
a on a routine basis things happen in terms
of database buffers which are basically volatile
ah databases, the volatile memory.
So, now the fig so, what we do is ah we maintain
ah multiple copies of each block of data and
keep them on separate disk. So, even if one
disk fail that is possible to ah recover from
other disk. There are different kinds of ah
the multiplicity that can be done even it
can be ah located at a remote location so
that ah even if there is a fire or flooding
the database can be recovered, but ah in in
principle will assume that ah the multiple
copies are not all copies can fail at the
same time.
So, it can ah now this will ensure the data
has already been written then it is guarantee
that it will stay we have talked about rate
systems, but what happens if the failure ah
ba happens during the data transfer where
the result is still in ah transient ah state
in it will live with transient copies. So,
block transfer ah in general can ah result
in either in successful completion or in partial
failure, where the destination block actually
has in current information or total failure
where destination block could not be updated
at all. So, to protect ah against the media
again such ah failures ah during the data
transfer ah the one possible solution could
be ah and and we assume that there are only
two copies ah of each block it could you could
have multiple copies to give you more ah resiliency
against failure.
So, if we have two copies and the strategy
could go like this that ah write the information
ah onto the first ah physical block then ah
once that is successfully completed then you
write the same information on the second ah
or physical block and ah the output is completed
only after the second ah write ah the physical
block is successfully completed. So, that
is what we need to guarantee.
Now, to protect against that ah ba that ah
happens if during this transfer with during
this write if some ah ah output operation
is some failure happens. So, to recover from
that you need to find out ah what are the
blocks which are inconsistent, because we
have kept two or more copies so ah ba you
have to compare two copies of ah every disk
block have kept them at separate disks and
see which one ah whether ah there has been
some inconsistence. Now, this is ah this is
theoretically ok, but this is very expensive
because there are so many different blocks.
So, what is typically done a better solution
is ah while you are actually doing the disk
write where you are actually doing the output
on a ah in the process of doing the output
then you record the these writes on a nonvolatile
storage say non-volatile ram or special area
of the disk and use this information during
the recovery to find the blocks that are inconsistent
and only compare those copies. So, that will
be naturally much faster because ah memory
as you know is is much ah faster to access
than the disk and ah these are strategy which
is typically used in the rate system we have
discussed earlier.
So, if either of ah either copy of a inconsistent
block is detected to have some kind of an
error, to checksums to the error then over
write by the other copy, but if both ah have
no error, but are different then overwrite
the second one by the first one. So, this
will ah make sure that ah you always have
even if there is a transient failures you
can take care of the that you know what is
wrong and you can take care of and correct
that.
Now, to make this ah kind of a mechanism work
we ah you resort we have very simple module
of ah data access. We assume that there are
physical blocks ah on the disk that ah that
are on the non-volatile permanent storage
and that is where finally, you want your data
to decide, but you also assume that ah there
are system buffer blocks; the blocks that
we decide temporarily in the main memory,
so, they can be used in the in transit.
So, when you move the block between the disk
and the main memory that is ah initiated by
an input operation. So, you are doing an input
so, all the physical block a that is disk
a block physical block B is brought into the
main memory or you have a output operation
which transfers first a buffer block B to
the disk and replaces the appropriate ah physical
block there. So, these operations when you
move ah physical blocks with the disk you
call them as input and output. So, and we
are making some assumption that ah the data
that we want to write is small enough so that
it fits into a block otherwise there are several
schemes of or you you know spread you data
over multiple blocks .
Now, the other part is each transaction on
the other side is assumed to have a private
work area. So, in the private work area that
transaction actually gives local copies and
ah these ah local copies say you have a data
item X, so, you say that ah for transaction
T i the copy of that data item X is xi and
say, B x is the block that contains ah X.
So, B x is the ah physical block and ah then
you can transfer data between the transactions
private area and this ah buffer block in terms
of read and write operations.
So, we have two kinds of operation; one is
input output which is between the memory and
the physical block that is the disk and the
other is read write operation which is between
the transactions private area and the system
buffered blocks. So, the transaction must
perform read before accessing X for the first
time and once it is done that it has a local
copy now and therefore, subsequent reads can
happen from the local copy and the write ah
can be executed at any time before the transaction
actually commits.
So, let us ah look at ah ah also it is a fact
is that ah the when I want to actually output
the block that contains X, I mean your item
X to be finally, written to disk the output
B x ah need not immediately happen after you
write. So, you are doing it in two stages,
from the transactions ah private area to the
system buffer, to the system buffer to the
disk. So, first is write the next is output,
but this may not ah actually ah follow immediately
once the data exists in the system buffer
it may be actually output on a at a later
time whenever it is then fit to do that.
So, let us ah ah take a very quick looks schematically
here to make ah things some simple ah ah understandable.
So, they are ah data items A and B on the
disk that we are talking of. So, if I do an
input operation then I am actually trans and
this is the buffer this is the system buffer.
So, this is kind of a common buffer where
you can keep data, we will see how to manage
this ah system buffer and this is the private
work area of a transaction say T 1. So, to
process of read I mean if T 1 wants to if
T 1 wants to read A then the that read initiation
will bring A onto the buffer area as X and
then it will read X as x 1 in its private
area, it will this is where it will do the
work. This is a private area where ah T 1
will do the work and possibly it has generated
a write item y with which needs to go back
to the disk. So, again we will do a write
to the buffer area and then at a later point
there will be an output which will take this
Y back to the disk.
So, this will ensure that ah the ah transaction
can after reading the transaction can independently
ah do the write to the buffers and outputs
can happen independently of that either before
that transaction commits or even after the
transaction commits there are difference in
situation there are different protocols that
are followed and we will see through, but
this is the basic simple model that will regularly
be ah used.
So, please keep in mind we will talk about
ah often will talk about three areas ah work
area the private work area of a transaction
this is an memory and the system buffer blocks
where the data is the ah temporarily deciding
on the way of being read or on the way of
being ah written and ah the system disk where
the physical block exists. And, this is the
path way through this ah system buffer that
the read writes will output will happen and
please remember that we will use the term
read write when it is between the private
work area of a transaction and the system
buffer block and will talk about input output
when it is between in terms of the physical
block with the disk
So, the data access ah you can I have already
explained. So, in terms of the data access
these are the steps that the transaction will
do to read or write as I have already explained.
Now, in terms of now, let us see that ah how
will in the background of ah such a storage
access how will the recovery happen and how
will the atomicity be guaranteed.
So, to ensure a atomicity in the phase of
failure we need to output information describing
the modifications to stable storage with input
modifying database itself. So, what we are
saying that to be able to recover that ah
we should write ah the changes to the stable
storage you recall that ah stable storage
something that is assumed to be not ah failing
without actually modifying database.
Now, we do a very ah ah simple mechanism which
is ah called a log based ah recovery mechanism.
So, we will first talk about this log based
recovery mechanism what are the key concepts
of ah logging and ah redo undo redo kind of
ah operations and present the actual recovery
algorithm. There are other alternatives also
like shadow paging we will not discuss about
ah that and I would like to again remind you
that in this ah module we are talking about
single ah transactions at a time, serial execution.
In the next module we will talk about concurrency
of the I mean the behavior of recovery algorithms
and in the case of concurrent transactions
.
So, now let us ah talk about the log based
recovery mechanism. So, ma in the log based
ah recovery mechanism you can you can see
this is the basic this is your stable database
which you want to make use of, these are your
buffers you talked off and we will have certain
logs the information of what have been doing
in terms of the log buffers and the also is
stable log which is a log that is written
in the stable database. So, once we understand
what is ah logging you will understand this,
but I just wanted to show you that like the
data there are buffer copies as well as stable
database copies in terms of log also ah there
will be buffer copies as well as stable ah,
log copies .
So, a log is kept ah in the stable storage,
it is a sequence of records. So, log is basically
a record of what and. So, it is like a if
am doing some task we have always every task
I do I keep a record of what am actually be
doing and that is called the logging. So,
when a transaction starts I write a log record
which ah puts the transaction ID say T i and
then puts a keyword start to the log. So,
that indicates that the transaction T i has
started and ah when it is about to execute
a write, so, ma before it has actually executed
the write, then I write a log record which
ah looks like this ah which is .
So, here if we look carefully this is ah the
idea of the transaction X is the data item
that you want in to write V 1 is the current
value of the data item which kind of we can
say is the old value and V 2 is the value
that we want to actually write. So, here you
can see that we are clearly keeping a track
of what ah we are writing and in that process
what is the original value that would get
changed. So, that is the main important factor
of this logging that every with every write
you remember as to what value was originally
there and what value we have actually changed
it to in that transaction.
Now, in this process finally, when that the
transaction finishes the last statement of
the log record is T i commit. So, that actually
is a meaning of committing a transaction when
this log record is written out. So, that is.
So, a log will have start then different ah
write log records and then finally, a commit
log record.
So, there are basically two approaches of
using log one is called ah immediate database
modification this is what ah we would follow
here and there is a differed database modification.
In the immediate ah modification scheme the
ma it allows updates of a uncommitted transaction
to be made to the buffer or the disk itself
before the transaction commit. So, before
the transaction has committed that is before
the T i commit log record has been written
at that point itself you allow the updates
ah of the transaction to be made to the buffer
or the disk and ah the update log record must
be written before the database is actually
written. So, you must first write the log
and then actual ah database item. So, and
we assume that the log record is output directly
to the stable storage. So, that it is not
there is no possibility of is getting lost.
Now, output of the updated blocks to disk
storage can take place, that is the final
actual output this is where we have written
the log that ok that am doing this change,
but the actual change we can take place any
time before the transaction commits or even
after the transaction commits. If you follow
this ah ma protocol then you say you are in
the immediate modification scheme and in fact,
the order in which the blocks are output that
finally, written to the disk may be different
from the order in which they were originally
written, but the log records the will have
to be written before these each one of this
output are done .
In the deferred modification scheme ah the
change updates are performed to buffer and
disk only at the time of transaction commit
not any time before that. So, that simplify
some aspects of recovery, but it has other
issues. So, we will not talk about this scheme,
just know that there is an alternate scheme
for doing things.
So, now formally speaking what is transaction
commit? A transaction commit is said transaction
is said to have committed if it commit log
record is output to the stable storage. That
is T i commit has gone to the stables stable
storage is the meaning of the transaction
has been committed. Obviously, all previous
log records of the transactions must have
been outputted already because that ah those
commit ah those outputs will have happen in
the same order in which the actions are taken.
Now, the writes performed by the transaction
may still in the buffer. So, you have transaction
is committed everything is done, but your
actual writes that are performed may not have
been outputted. They are they may still be
in the buffer when the transaction commits
and those may be output at a later point of
time.
So, let us take an example here. Let us look
at an example. So, here ah you see the log
records and here is the sequence of write
and output ah A 1 is happening. So, in the
log record the transaction starts here. So,
you have a log record of start, what is the
meaning of this? The meaning of this is transaction
T 0 is ah trying to write A and ah the current
value is 1000 and it wants to change it to
950. So, this log record is written and you
can see that the actual write actual write
has not happened here, actual write is not
done, but it is it already has ah must like
in the immediate database modification scheme
it must write the log record before actually
ah writing the output, actually doing the
output or doing the write. So, ah this has
happened here.
Similarly, the next one ah is another ah update
transaction for B and ah and actual writes
have happened. So, which means the data has
been written from the transactions ah private
work area to the system buffer and then the
transaction has transaction T 0 has done commits.
So, at this point if you go up to this then
the commit of the transaction is already completed
and ah another transaction T 1 starts you
please remember that we have said that we
will ah we are using serial ah ma schedules
only. So, only now another transaction can
commit that has started and ah that has ah
written log record for updating C from 700
to 600. So, there is a write for 600 then
T 1 has commit.
In the meanwhile and at this stage, in the
meanwhile these blocks have been output. So,
they have actually been written the disk and
ah you can understand that ah this block B
B is a block that contains the data of data
item the updated value of data item B and
ah ma this B C has the updated value of data
item C. So, you can have see that ah actually
these output of ah B is happening after the
transactions is 0 has committed whereas, for
ah update of data you can see the ah output
is happening af before the ah T 1 has committed.
So, here it is happening after the commit,
but here it is happening before the commit.
So, both of these are ah permitted both of
these are allowed in terms of the protocol
that ah we are following. And, you can also
see that ah in in terms of ah the order in
which they were written A was written earlier,
but A is output at a later point of time because
that is a different sequence in which the
system might decide for writing the buffer
onto the disk .
So, this is ah the immediate ah database modification
scheme through which we can write the logs.
Now, the question is ok we have written the
logs. So, what is the use of the those logs?
Naturally, the use of those logs are in terms
of two operations to which we say are undo
operation and redo operation and undo operation
is one which ah basically undoes the operation
ah the effect of an update. So, while ah ma
you have done ah you have if this is a log
record then undoing, so, this meant that X
was changed it had a value V 1 and it was
changed to V 2. If you undo that then the
old value comes back to this old value comes
back to X. So, that is if I undo this ah particular
action the which was put in the log record
then X will get back it is original value
and redo is ah doing the same thing over again
if I redo for this log record then the value
of V 2 will again reset on X. So, these are
the two simple undo and redo operations which
will help us achieve the ah recovery systems
ah input.
So, what is meant by undo redo of transactions
let us understand. So, when I undo a transaction
T i that restores the values of all data items
updated by T i to their old values. So, the
values have been updated in in this ah forward
order. So, when you go to undo you will actually
will have to do that in the reverse order,
because it is quite possible that ah X ah
got 1 here then at a some at a some later
point it was updated to 17 then at some later
point it was updated to 13. So, this this
update possibly had happened from 0, this
update had happened from 1, this update had
happened from 3. So, all those transactions
records are there then you going backwards.
So, you will first restore X back to 17 because
this is then this back restoring back to 1
then going back to 0, in this order it will
go on.
And, ah every time ah you restore you write
that you write that out as a record which
is known as ah redo redo only record. So,
you can see that here you are not ah trying
to remember the original value you are just
ah writing the value that you have ah written
out in terms of the undo operation that is
the old value and ah the going in this ah
manner undo operation will terminate when
you have come across ah the beginning of this
ah this one process, when it is complete then
a log record T i abort is written out which
says that the undo is actually over. So, this
is the undo operation .
For redo you said that the redo is doing the
transactions ah doing the same ah instructions
of the transactions in the same manner, it
was done earlier. So, that unlike undo which
goes backwards ah redo goes forward and it
starts from the first ah log record of this
transaction and goes on till the end and ah
for this there is no separate logging for
this operation .
Now, how will the undo redo operations be
used. There are two major situations in which
they are used one is undo is used transactions
roll back have to roll back during normal
operation. That is nothing has I mean there
is no ah system failure or there is no data
disk failure anything, but ah if the transaction
has a normal failure that it cannot complete
it is execution due to some logical error
or because it has to roll back because of
deadlock or something, then you what you do
you just undo the whole effect of the transaction
go backwards and keep on undoing. But, when
the there is a failure ah there is a failure
and you have to recover from that then undo
and redo operations both will be required
as we will soon see.
So, we also need to ah deal with the case
where the recovery from failure while you
are recovering from failure another failure
happens. So, what do you do in that case that
is more complicated will talk about that later.
So, first let us discuss what happens when
you roll back at transactions during normal
operation. So, let T i be the transaction.
So, you have to naturally do the undo because
you have to undo the effect that it has already
created. So, you will scan the log records
ah from the end and for each ah log record
which is kind of an update like this you will
ah perform in update to restore the original
value the old value and write out a redo only
log record or which is called ah compensation
log record which ah says that this has been
undone to the value V 1 which is the original
value of the transaction original value of
the data item sorry .
Now, in going in this process backwards at
some point of time you will reach come across
ah T i start ah log record when you face come
across that you write log record T i abort
indicating that the undo of that transaction
is over. So, this is the basic ah process
of undoing the transactions during rollback.
In the other case if you are recovering from
a failure if there has been a failure then
you do something ah which ah needs to be understood
carefully. So, the transaction T i needs to
be undone if the log contains the record start
T i start, but it does not contain either
T i commit or T i abort. So, perform T i start
you will know that it has started, but because
of failure it could not complete, because
if it could complete or if before that if
it had to roll back because of the normal
execution then it would have written T i commit
or T i abort, but because of system failure
you could not write any one of them. So, the
transaction has to be rolled back .
The other case is the case where the transaction
needs to be redone is when then it contains
the record ah T i start, but in addition it
also contains the record T i commit or T i
abort. So, this is the transaction which had
completed successfully, did the start, it
did the commit or it rolled back the whole
thing happened successfully, but because of
system failure changes have not been able
to take place and therefore, you will you
have to again execute that transactions. So,
that is why you do a re dones. In the earlier
case it is undone you want to undo the effect,
here the effects were given, but they somehow
could not be ah made ah durable the database
have become inconsistent. So, you need to
redo that whole thing.
So, ma it may sound ah little bit awkwardness
that if the it contains the T i abort why
should you actually redo the transaction this
is a just to keep ah things ah simple so that
ah you can ah just trace back the original
history. So, you do not try to really optimize,
but you just trace back ah the original history
and ah do whatever had happened in the way
and then ah that simplifies your algorithm
significantly. And, then if there is a certain
things which ah ah have been done by the undo
operation you also want to go through those
and maintain that status .
So, here are ah some examples here ah they
transaction we are showing it is ah failure
recovery action at ah every case. So, if in
case a the transaction has started and we
made changes to A and B and at that time the
failure happens. So, naturally the start is
there and at ah commit is not there or abort
is no there. So, these has to be undone. So,
this will be undone A will get back the value
thousand and B we will get back the value
2000 and to such ah record T 0, B, 2000 and
T 0, A 2000 that two ah compensation log records
will be and then it T 0 abort will be written
.
Now, if you look at ah second transaction
transaction just a second states ah of ah
as in b then you will see that T 0 has actually
started and committed and T 1 has started
after that which could not complete after
updating C. So, in the case of b since T 0
has start and commit both you have to redo
that because you have lost all these changes
we have to redo again and for that you do
not log anything and then T 1 could not complete
because it has start and does not have the
ah abort or commit. So, you would log record
for undoing it, undoing T 1 and you write
T 1, C, 100 and T 1, abort.
In the third case ah ma both transaction T
0 and transaction T 1 has ah commit start
and commit and both have completed. So, you
have to redo both of them. So, these are the
basic ah different ah cases strategies that
you have in in place.
Now, the question is if you have to do this
for all transactions ah when a failure happens
and a failure may have happened say after
ah 1 year or ah after 8, 9, 10 months and
so on. So, there will be a huge ah you know
ah set of ah redo, undo operations that you
will have do it will run for a very long time.
So, what we do is ah we create something like
a ah check pointing where we said, ok. Ah,
we will ah periodically choose a point of
time where we will make sure that all updates
have actually been consistently put in the
disk and ah the database is surely on a consistent
state and that is called check pointing.
So, whatever is done is a at a chosen point
of check pointing, time of check pointing
all updates are stopped in database. So, there
is no changing changes happening in all transaction
are no new transactions are allowed what is
happening as. So, you make sure that all records
that are currently residing in your buffer
is ah flushed on to the ah stable storage
all modified buffer blocks which were not
output we have also outputted and then you
write that this is a write a log record saying
the check point ah L on to the stable storage,
where L is basically the transactions that
were active at the time of checkpoint in the
transactions that have already completed you
do not need to remember because they have
they are changes by the process of outputting
all log records and all ah modified buffer
on to disk, you make sure that all completed
transactions are fully secured.
Now, they are consistent, they are you would
have to, but ah those which are ah which were
still ah continuing you keep the list and
write that out in terms of the checkpoint
ah log record and take it into the stable
storage.
So, during recovery what we need to consider
is ah we have to now we not have to go back
to the last time the data fail we just need
to go back to the last time we did ah check
pointing and when you go back to the check
pointing ah you already know that ah ma what
are ah the ah transactions that are live at
the time of check pointing. So, you can scan
backwards and ah ah check out ah what ah were
ah they had ah started. So, you need to and
undo redo those are transactions and ah then
you see what are the transactions that have
committed aborted ah have already there in
the output in the stable storage .
So, some of the earlier part of the log may
need ah may be needed for undo operations.
So, you continue scanning backwards till you
find in T i start and then you take care of
that.
Let me just explain through an example. So,
let us ah say that ah this is the checkpoint
where you froze everything and did not allow
any further updates to happen and rolled back
all the data. So, what has happened is in
this transaction T 1 which is committed before
the last checkpoint naturally there was no
obtained pending for that. So, you have made
sure that all the updates in terms of the
log as well as ah the the system buffer has
been written on to have been ah output on
to the disk at the time of check pointing.
So, you do not remembering need to remember
this transaction at all, so this can simply
be ignored.
Now, at the checkpoint you can see that ah
transaction T 1 was in execution. So, certain
things had happened. So, at the checkpoint
the part that has already happened the log
records ah for that as well as the ah output
for that this has already been firmly put
into that because these are checkpoints because
you are writing everything, but this transaction
is still in execution. So, you will put this
transaction in the checkpoint log list. So,
we will say this is ah this is the T 2 and
this will need to be looked at. If you so
so, let let let us see what is you will do
with this.
So, if we look at then naturally T 2 if ah
you have a failure at this point ah if you
have a failure at this point ah as you have
here then naturally this is the last stable
point you know where everything was written
to the disk in a consistent manner. So, what
you will need to do you will have to execute
transaction T 2 once more to make sure that
it is you know up to this point this being
done, so, you need to redo this part. Similarly,
T 3 if you look at it started after the checkpoint
and it ah committed before the system failure.
So, you need to redo that as well.
And, ah if you look into the T 4 if you look
into T 4 you can see that it started before
the system failure of course, after the checkpoint
and it was still running when the failure
happens. So, you do not know what are the
final results of that, so, what you will need
to do? You will need to undo this transaction.
So, this has no impact you can just ignore
these cases you have to redo the transaction
and in this case, in case of T 4 you have
to undo the transaction.
So, by check pointing and you obviously, the
the point you the time you choose for check
pointing has to be judiciously done it may
not be very frequent and then then it will
there be a lot of over it at the same time
if you do it in a in a very after a very long
period of time then naturally you will not
get the benefits, but check pointing is a
very critical feature of doing the recovery
in the databases.
So, to summarize we have ah seen that ah there
are may be different types of failures and
different strategies are required ah for handling
them and a we have also seen that ah we use
different kinds of ah storage structures and
they judicious mix and then arrangement of
these the structure can guarantee, ah recovery
from failures and we have taken their brief
look into the log base recovery mechanism
which is efficient as well as effective and
I will remind you that all this discussion
was done for serial transactions only.