Top of Form
Bottom of Form
Welcome to module 37 of Database Management
Systems. We have been discussing about Database
Recovery. This is the second and concluding
part of the Database Recovery.
We have ah earlier discussed about failure
classification, storage structures and ah
significantly the log based ah recovery mechanism.
In this, we will focus on concurrent transactions
and understand the recovery algorithm for
them and the we will understand the operation
of logging for recovery with early lock release.
We will learn about another kind of logging
mechanism; so, the recovery algorithm.
So, what we have seen so far are we have learned
the basic concept of recovery and logging
and we have assumed the serial execution of
transactions and now we discussed the Concurrency
Control issues. So, now, we will assume that
there are multiple transactions operating
at the same time and ah the components that
are required for the recovery of those.
So, with Concurrent Transaction, all transactions
share we we already know that every transaction
is a private work area that assumption stays,
but we talked about a system buffer area.
So, that system ah buffer area the that area
would be common for all different transactions,
also the log area would be common for all
transactions. So, now, the ah in the buffer
area the, ah data rights are or reads or writes
are done for different transactions and in
the log the different logs of different transactions
are fixed up.
So, we make one assumption that ah if a transaction
has modified an item, then no other transaction
can modify that same item unless that transaction
is committed or aborted. So, which means that
kind of when the transaction modifies the
item it holds a lock and that lock is held
till the end of the transaction and this is
a I mean if we if we ah think back in terms
of our locking protocol, this is a strict
locking protocol that we are talking of. This
is important ah for recovery because if we
did not have this, then it is possible that
multiple updates to the same rate item are
done by multiple transactions. So, if we have
to undo that ah then we will not know we were
which one it to be undone with. So, that is
the basic problem. So, we will assume an exclusive
lock in this case and ah log records will
be written interspersed as we have already
saw.
So, in terms of our storage access ah mechanism,
the same eh earlier ah diagram, this is here
is a disk, here is a buffer, the buffer is
common and the private work area. So, now,
in addition to T 1, we have another transaction
T 2 with it is own buffer area, but so, the
ah x has been written in T 1, has been read
in T 1 as x 1, x has also been read in T 2
as x 2 and ah each are concurrently making
changes in that ah private work area, but
they are using the same system buffer area
for the for writing the output back to the
disk or reading directly from the disk. So,
this is a model that we will go with.
So, what is the recovery algorithm, first
is logging and ah the logging structure remains
same; the start ah transaction log, the update
transaction log and the commit transaction
log as before ah.
When you have to do a transaction rollback
during normal operation; so, for that transaction
T i to be rolled back, what we will need to
do it is a rollback. So, undo has to happen.
So, scan will scan the log ah backwards from
the end and for each log record update log
record, we will ah restore the original value
for which was ah written over and we will
write a ah compensation log record as before
and going backwards in this way when we come
across ah the start ah log record, then we
will stop that scan and write a abort log
record in that place.
So, it is exactly same to what we did.
So, now let us ah look into the actual Recovery
Algorithm. So, the transaction rollback has
has no difference. So, in the Recovery Algorithm,
what we do we have a recovery phase and where
we replay updates of all transactions. So,
we make sure that all transactions whatever
they did they those are done again. So, after
the failure we recover from the failure.
So, we up do all that again whether they are
committed, whether they are aborted, whether
they are incomplete in every case and then
we ah keep track of what are the transactions
which did not complete and for them we do
an undo phase. So, here I am showing another
example here. So, this is ah the last checkpoint
where eh all updates I mean freezing the updates,
everything was ah output to the disk the log
as well as the ah data item updates were put
to the disk and the set of transactions that
are live during that time well execution in
that time were recorded. So, if we look at
that set L in this case, then it will be T
2, T 3 these two transactions.
So, we can ah we have already seen that our
strategy would be that we will ignore T 1
because it had completed before the last checkpoint.
T 2 and ah T 3 were ongoing and then T 4 has
ah started after checkpoint and committed
before that, T 5 started after checkpoint,
but was also active was also in execution
when system failed. So, our strategy would
be, that we will assume as if ah the this,
this ah whole thing as is redone.
So, T 2, T 3, T 4, T 5 all these log records
exist. So, we will follow through them and
redo all of them. If we redo all of them then
naturally we come across ah T 3 and T 5 which
cannot ah proceed further because the system
had could not proceed further because. So,
we do not know in terms of the log what would
have happened to them because the system had
failed. So, after having done this then, we
do an undo phase where we undo this, but naturally
the effect of these will remain. Now you can
question that this could have been done in
a more smart way, do we really need to redo
everything and then undo some parts of that,
that is a ah override in terms of that which
is true, but this just makes the whole algorithm
simple and over it actually is not very hard.
So, we are doing the redo phase, even the
redo phase you will find the ah check point
and you will scan forward ah from the checkpoint
record and as you scan forward from the checkpoint
record; if you have an update, you will simply
redo which means V 2, will again be written
to X j and when you find a start transaction,
then you do not know. Just look at this point
carefully; if you find a start transaction
for example, when you are working on this,
suppose you come across a a start transaction
here, you will come across the start transaction
transactions start here.
So, whenever you get that, then you put this
into the undo list . Initially your undo list
is L because they were going on. So, you do
not know that they could finish all that still
need to be undone and when you come across
a new start, you add that to the undo list
and then the rest of it is simple. So, you
keep on going this way, if you find that the
commit has happened or abort has happened,
you remove that from the undo list, but if
you do not find that then that stays in the
undo list. So, you know if you, if you proceed
from in this direction in the redo phase,
you know and that way when you have scanned
the whole log, you know what are the transactions
which still need to be undone. So, that is
a simple strategy that is followed.
So, ma whenever you have a log record start,
then you put it to the undo list and whenever
you get a log record which is committed abort
which says that before the system failure
the transaction actually had either committed
that it finished everything or you had to
roll back, then you remove that from the undo
list. So, what will be left out, at the end
will be the undo list of transactions that
need to be undone subsequently.
In the undo phase, in the undo phase, you
go backwards because it is undo. So, what
you will do is is a very similar. So, if you
have an update record, then you undo ah in
the ma transaction which is in undo list then
you do exactly in terms of transaction rollback
that you write the old value and write a ah
redo only log record. Now when you find going
backwards, when you find ah ti start. So,
you know that this is a starting point of
the transaction and the transaction is in
undo list. So, it ah it ah came across ah
because it could not be it it it was on the
undo list. So, which means that it could not
be completed and therefore, you have found
the start. So, this is where your undo operation
is over. So, you write a abort ah log record
and once you have written that, then you are
done with the transaction. So, you remove
that from the undo list and ah ah in the in
this way, you will continue till your undo
list is ah becomes empty.
Once it becomes empty, so, then you have found
that T i start for all transactions in the
undo list and there is nothing more to do
. So, after undo phase completes normal transaction
processing can comment. So, your failure recovery
from the failure is already ah taken care
of.
So, here are certain examples which you could
ah check out, here is a start. So, this is
the how that this is the order in which the
transactions are going and ah this is the
crash point, this is where it failed and ah
mind you. So, this is where and this is where
our checkpoint is. So, at checkpoint you can
see that ah T 0 and T 1 are ah what are your
candidates. So, when you start in the redo
phase, you start from this point because before
that everything has been done. You naturally,
you you come across this. So, you redo this
which means you again actually change C from
it is old value 700 to 600 and then T 1 commits.
As T 1 commits, you know that this transaction
is done with. So, you remove that. So, your
ah undo list ah undo list at the beginning
is ah T 0, T 1, but going in the forward direction
when you come across T 1 commit, you naturally
that ah from your undo list, then you come
across T 2 start.
So, you know that another transaction is ah
starting now. So, it may be you do not know
whether it come could complete or you could
not. So, you add that to the undo list ah
then give effect to this update, then if for
T 0 we have ah you have ah a rollback record
that is because ah T 0 actually you can see
that T 0 has aborted. So, the change that
T 0 had done earlier this had to be rolled
back, this rollback is a normal transaction
rollback, this is not because of the failure.
So, this ah mm ah rollback ah had happened
and this is where the rollback is ah complete.
So, T 2 e, T 0 is also completed. So, T 0
after this ah ah is taken care of, then in
the redo phase T 0 is also complete and this
in where you reach the crash point. So, your
undo list is left with only T 2. So, now,
when you have done this, so when you have
taken ah done the redo here that is ah ah
this T 2 which is ongoing is there, then you
write this ah log record. So, this these log
records are written during recovery not ah
during the original transaction and ah T 2
had to ah abort because of the system failure.
So, ah T 0 support was due to the transaction
rollback, but T 2 s abort is because of the
system failure. So, T 2 is rolled back in
the can be rolled back in the undo phase.
So, once this has been done, then you do the
undo phase starting with T 2 and ah then you
go backwards as you go backwards here.
So, you will undo this, this is what you write
you come across T 2 and naturally you have
rollback. So, you write T 2 abort. This is
how the actual rollback can happen and you
can see that ah now the with this ah redo
undo phase you can always bring back the database
to a consistent state and these transactions
are executing concurrently and therefore,
your ah log record is a intermix of the log
record of different transactions. Now the
last ah that ah ma we would like to talk about
is Recovery with Early Lock Release.
What this means is well, so far we have talked
about recovery which is only in terms of data
update, single data updates. So, I mean if
I want to recover I can just ah you know write
back the old data, but ah this is not ah true
in case of ah many other situations for example,
if you are inserting a record in a B-tree,
then ah it is not enough only to undo that
because ah you cannot undo and get back the
same. As you can understand that if you make
inserts or deletes in the B-tree, if you are
made an insert then the structure of the B-tree
itself has changed and after that several
other inserts, deletes may have happened.
So, if you now want to just go back and undo
this particular insert in terms of values,
it is not possible to do that. So, ah when
you ah want to do that, so you cannot do really
kind of ah repeating the history kind of strategy.
So, what you have to do is do some kind of
an undo which is logical. So, so far the undo
was physical that, you wrote this, you change
this value by this value. So, your undo is
a physical. So, you restore the original value
and your undo is done here. It is logical
that is for the operation that you have performed,
you try to ah find out a matching operation
which creates the similar effect as of undo.
So, if you have inserted, then you your undo
is a corresponding delete of that record.
If you have incremented by 10 then ah you
can say that your corresponding undo is a
decrement by 10. So, that is what is known
as the logical undo and it is ah logical undo
is is a very good option in case of ah delete
of, insert delete of people.
So, if you have deleted a people undo to insert,
if you have subtracted then ah undo to ah
undo deposit to go forward and so on.
So, a redo information is logged physically,
so new values for each right even for operations
which are ah logically, which has logical
undo. So, you do not ah do a logical redo
I mean, I will not go into the details of
why this is not done, but it simply makes
things very complicated. So, physical redo
is always physical and ah you can ah show
that physical redo does not ah prohibit this
ah kind of operations that we are trying to
do, but ah the logical ah redo is not used.
We will only use ah ah logical undo operation
.
So, how do you log for such a logical undo
operation, what you do is instead of now.
So, now, it is an operation it may not be
an a a single value update. So, it is not
captured in terms of one you know log record,
but it could be a number of log records which
have actually done 3, 4 different changes
to make that operation happen and you want
to actually define an undo for that operation.
So, when you start this. So, you start ah
with a log which says that ah what is the
transaction and ah what is the operation.
So, you put an identifier to the operation
and then you write operation begin.
So, you know this is where operation has started,
then ah all the things that are ah happening
ah for this operation while the operation
is executing then you write normal log records
with physical redo physical information. All
these logs are written and when this operation
ends mind you, this is a particular operation
you are talking of. So, not not the whole
transaction whole transaction will continue
when that particular operation ends, then
you write an operation in record and along
with that you write, what is a logical, what
is a logical undo information you put that
in. So, let us ah have a look at the example.
So, suppose your operation is insert of a
key record pair, so, let us say this is the
key record pair and ah into index ah I 9.
So, this the operation starts here and then
there are several steps to be done; for example,
you will have to say if X ah is on the key
value which had 10 and is becoming K 5, you
will have a physical ah update undo record
of this. If ah Y is the record id which is
RID 7, then it ah y changes from 45 to. So,
these are all physical redo steps in insert.
So, these are the different instructions in
terms of this broad operation and when you
are done with all that ah then your operation
ends and you write this undo information.
So, insert of, so you had insert of this record
with index 9.
So, now you do write your what will be the
undo, to delete that from index I 9, to delete
this ah key record ID pair. So, this is a
whole locking that we do. So, you can make
use of this ah undo ah operation in terms
of your recovery process.
So, if the crash or rollback occurs before
the operation completes, then operation and
log record is not found you will not find
it. So, you do not know what is the undo operation.
So, in that case the physical undo information
is will be used to undo, but ah if we have
a crash on rollback that happens after an
operation completes, then the operation end
log ah will be available and in this case
we will use the undo operation that is given
in the operation end log record and do a logical
undo and we will ignore all the physical undo
information that the operation ah that that
we will find in the log records. Redo of course
will still use the physical redo information
which is there .
So, if we look into the actual ah if we if
we look into the um transaction rollback with
logical undo. So, if I have an update record
which is naturally physical, ah and then we
can perform the undo which is as we did last
time the creating a redo only record. If I
find an operation end record, then to rollback
we will pick up the logical undo information
from you and ah we will perform that operation.
At the end of that we will ah certainly write
the operation abort record to show to mark
that this operation has been aborted.
So, if we have a redo only record, then we
will ignore it and if we find an operation
abort, then we will skip all the records that
were found till the beginning. Naturally,
you can you can you can understand that 3
and 4 will not happen in a normal course of
ah transaction, it will happen only when the
failures have happened during recovery and
at the end we will add T i ah abort record
to the log. So, the critical thing to to ah
remember in this that whenever we are doing
operation ah hmm unlogging ah, we we are doing
undoing based on the operation logging then
since once we get the operation ends since
we know what the undo information is, we have
to make sure that through the undo process
we actually ignore the physical ah undo ah
records that exist in the log and just go
with the operation case. So, this ah these
are the notes yeah I just mentioned it ok.
So, this is ah an example which you will have
to spend some time and ah understand with
ah care. So, you can see that a transaction
T 0 has started, this is where it has done
a physical update, is a physical ah undo record
and then it does an operation. Of course,
it is a simple operation which changes ah
the value of c from 700 to 600. So, naturally,
so it has decremented by 100. So, your undo
operation here is incrementing by 100.
So, if ah T 0 aborts here, if T 0 aborts somewhere
here you know before your operation end has
happened then naturally the undo will have
to be based on this physical undo structure.
So, you will have to replace 600 by 700, but
if if it happens after this, then this is
the case if it is completed the operation
and then the failure happens, then you will
do the logical undo that is whatever the value
of C is you will just logically add 100 to
that. But that means, that when you go backwards
from here to find the begin, you will actually
have to ignore this physical undo record because
you have already given effect to that in terms
of the operation undo that you are doing.
So, this is the basic ah difference. Here
are different ah subsequent examples on that
and ah you can you can see that ah well here
after the operation end has happened, then
possibly it has released the T 0 has released
a lock on C 1.
So, T 1 has again taken the log. T 1 has again
done the updates. So, then it releases that
and T 0 at this point might ah decide to abort;
if T 0 aborts, then this ah logical undo of
O 1 this operation will add, it had to add
100. So, it adds now this C had become 400,
now it is adding 100 back. So, C becomes 500
and ah then the operation is finished. So,
you write operation abort and O 1 undo of
O 1 gets completed, but you still have after
going going backwards in this, you still have
this record which was directly updated.
So, these are the undo transactions, undo
lock record for that where B is being restored
from 2050 to 2000 and you record the transaction
abort for T 0, T 1 eventually has committed
here. So, this is how the transaction rollback
will happen when logical undo is also used
and this is a very powerful way to ah take
care of that.
This is similarly ah another illustration
for doing the failure recovery for with logical
undo. So, here is the undo is a re redo phase
that you are seeing here, this is where the
end of log at the crash these are redo phase
because these are check point where T 1 was
there. So, at the end of redo T 1 ah if you
if you. So, you are starting to redo from
here. So, you have done operation end. T 1
has not finished T 2 has started. So, you
have added T 2 to the undo list and when the
crash has happened both of them are on the
undo list. So, they have to go through that
undo pass. So, we undo T 2, C, 400. So, this
is what this is this is how you will go.
So, this is the first thing you undo and then
naturally you have come to the beginning of
T 2 start. So, you abort and ah you are going
going back again and you are trying to do
this. Why are you doing this because when
you go back to undo from this point you come
across this operation end which tells you
that the undo operation has to happen by incrementing
C by 300. So, C which had become 400 is now
incremented by 300. You come to the check
point which is the end here in terms of the
operation begin and naturally you declare
operation abort and ah going back ah further
this is ah what you had when transaction T
1 had started.
So, you undo that. That is again a physical
undo and finally, t one aborts. So, this is
how ah in both cases of transaction rollback
as well as in terms of the failure the ah
recovery can be done with the logical undo
process.
Here I have given another example. I will
not ah go through it step by step. So, at
a arts that you go through that following
the same logic and convince yourself that
you understand that how this ah transaction
rollbacks with physical undo as well as logical
undo is taking place.
So, ma with this Recovery Algorithm with logical
undo will look very similar ah to what ah
we have already done with the physical undo
redo and ah though that is what we have stated
here, there is no nothing ah significantly
new. So, I expect that you should be able
to go through these steps.
And ah those will be clear to you again we
have a 2 phase ah recovery of redo phase and
the undo phase and we make use of the operation
undo, logical undo as and when it is possible
and when that is and when we do that, we ignore
all physical ah undo records and when it is
not possible, then we lose the physical undo
records and that is how the recovery can be
achieved.
So, in this module we have ah expose ourselves
with the Recovery Algorithms ah now for concurrent
transactions as well and we have shown that
ah how recovery can be done using operational
logging, operations logging and making sure
that ah really the database may not need to
ah hold on to a lock for a long time on the
data item and delay other transactions, but
if it can define the undo operation on the
on the data on the data item, then it can
release that log early and use that ah logging
mechanism operation logging mechanism to recover
the data.