Welcome to module 18 of Database Management
Systems.
We have been discussing about ah relational
database design.
This is a part 3 of that.
In the last module, we discussed about the
Notion of functional dependency and decomposition
based on that in an elementary level and certain
bit of its ah theory.
In this ah current module, we learnt different
algorithms that use the functional dependencies
and can make conclusions about the design
or make changes to the design.
We will also try to understand the characterization
for lossless, ah join decomposition and the
notion of deter dependency preservation.
Therefore, this module will have these three
ah topics ah algorithms for functional dependencies,
lossless join decomposition and dependency
preservation.
So, first we start with the algorithms and
I quickly reproduce what we had ended in the
last module in terms of computing the closure
of a set of attributes.
So, if we have ah a relation having these
attributes and a set of functional dependencies,
then for a given subset of attributes, in
this case AG we can iteratively compute the
closure set when no further changes can be
done, and ah with using that we can make different
conclusions.
For example, if our question is whether AG
can be a candidate key, we would first like
to check whether it is a super key that is
whether its closure has all the attributes
of art and we would like to check if we have
taken a subset of AG.
If we take just as a attribute A or attribute
G whether the closure of that will actually
work as a key or not.
So, this algorithm of ah attribute closure
turns out to be a very powerful one, where
as we have just seen it can be used for checking
ah super keys, the candidate keys, primary,
non-primary attributes and so on.
It can be used for checking functional dependencies.
For example, let us ah suppose that if we
have to check that whether if a particular
functional dependency alpha determines beta
holds ah , then rather in other words whether
alpha determines beta is in the closure of
the set of functional dependencies F, then
all that we need to do is to compute alpha
plus that is a closure of the set of attributes
on the left hand side of the dependency and
check if beta is a subset of that.
If beta is a subset of that, then I know that
alpha determines beta actually holds .
So, in this manner it can also be used to
compute the closure of ah the whole set of
functional dependencies F. So, if I mean at
least at A, rudimentary level we can think
of that.
If we take any subset of ah the set of ah
attributes and find the closure and then,
all attributes that belong to that closure
set are actually functionally dependent and
therefore, those functional dependencies will
exist.
Now, we move forward from there and talk about
what is known as a canonical cover.
A set of functional dependencies may have
a number of redundant dependencies also.
So, we need to understand that because there
are lot of dependencies which can be inferred
from a certain set of dependencies, for example
if you look into this set, you will easily
understand that in this whole set if I actually
have just this, we will be able to by transitivity,
we will be able to conclude about A determining
C. So, in that way ACA determining C is a
redundant dependency.
So, here I am just showing you some examples.
For example, say I have a set of functional
dependencies as this set and I want to know
whether I can replace it by a simpler set
here where this particular attribute on the
right hand side of this dependency may be
extraneous.
So, if I have to do that, then what we need
to perform is, we need to show that given
the ah set of functional dependencies, the
original set whether this can imply this set
that is from this set of functional dependencies,
whether I can logically conclude the simplified
set.
So, using the rules we will need to do that
I have worked that out here under ah the forward
scheme and we would also need to establish
that if I have the simplified set, then can
I go to the original set that was given.
So, if the simplified set also logically implies
the original set, then we can say that these
are in a way ah equivalent and therefore,
I would like to use a simpler set.
So, there is another ah example following
here where I have another set given, where
if we look into this, I would like to check
whether I can get rid of this C on the left
hand side and as as it stands, we can actually
do that and here in this whole process, I
have shown it in terms of using the Armstrongs
Axioms how you can prove this, but what we
can do to systematize this whole process,
we can again make use of the notion of closure
of attributes and compute whether these two
sets are equivalent, whether simplification
can be done.
So, we will say a cover is canonical.
If it is in a sense minimal and still equivalent
to the original set of dependencies and we
will formally introduce what is minimal.
Before that let us ah just look at the same
examples again.
So, we are trying to show the forward direction
in the first case and the reverse direction
in the first case, but the only difference
that I wanted to highlight is in terms of
showing that you do not need to really explore
on the Armstrongs Axioms, but what you can
do is, you can simply take the left hand side
attribute and compute it closure and see whether
the right hand side is included.
That is basically testing for whether the
given functional dependency is actually implied.
Similar things can be done to simplify the
left hand side also.
So, this is the other example that a short
and I am just showing you that how you conclude
this based on the ah closure of attributes
algorithm.
So, now I can formally define ah these possible
removals.
So, if I can remove an attribute as I have
shown I can remove it from the right hand
side or I can remove it from the left hand
side.
So, if an attribute can be removed, then it
is called extraneous.
So, if I have a functional dependency, let
us say alpha functionally determines beta
and I have an attribute A which belongs to
alpha, then ah we can check whether it is
possible to remove A from alpha.
So, to test that what we do is, we form a
new set by removing the original functional
dependency and adding the new functional dependency
where the left hand side does not have that
A and if F logically implies this, then certainly
we can conclude that ah A on the left hand
side of the functional dependency was extraneous.
Similar thing can be done for checking if
there is an extraneous attribute on the right
hand side of a dependency and in this case,
naturally what we will need to do is, we will
need to work out the simpler set and then
check whether F is implied by that because
as you can understand that if you are making
the left hand, if you are removing an attribute
from the left hand side, then you are making
your precondition softer.
So, you need to see whether that is implied
by the original set and on the other hand,
if you are removing something on the right
hand side, then ah you are making your consequence
ah simpler.
So, you need to understand whether that set
implies the original set.
So, if you look into that and obviously, the
other directions of this implication is not
necessary to be proven because that will automatically
follow because in the first case when I am
removing an attribute, extraneous attribute
from the left hand side of a functional dependency,
naturally the set that I get that will always
imply the original set because it is always
possible to add additional attributes on the
left hand side and so on.
So, here are some examples worked out.
So, here where I show that given a set AC
and AB determining CB is actually extraneous
because as you can see if I remove B, then
I get A determining C which is originally
already there in the set.
You can establish that by computing the closure
of the attribute set.
Another example where you are trying to see
an extraneous attribute on the right hand
side.
So, in this example, C on the right hand side
of the set AB determining CD is extraneous
because it can be inferred even after ah because
AB determining C can be inferred even after
deleting this C from the right hand side.
So, these are using this ah notion.
We can formalize a test for ah whether an
attribute is extraneous.
So, this is the formal steps of the step are
given here, but I am sure you have already
understood through the example.
So, given this A canonical cover of a set
of functional dependencies F, it is denoted
by FC will mean that it is a set which is
equivalent to F which means F will logically
imply all dependencies in FC and FC will logically
imply all dependencies in F.
No functional dependency in FC will contain
any extraneous attribute.
So, all of them will be required attributes
and each left hand side of the functional
dependency in FC must be unique.
So, it is a minimal set of functional dependencies.
Please note on these two core points.
A cover is canonical if it is a minimal set
and it is an irreducible set.
So, neither you can remove any dependancy
nor you can remove any extraneous attribute
from this dependency set . So, here is the
algorithm.
So, I am not going through the steps of the
You can go through that and convince yourself
that it indeed computes the canonical cover
and practice more on that.
So, here I have shown an example where ah
we want to compute the canonical cover here.
So, first since all left hand sides have to
be unique, so first we ah combine ah two,
these two into in terms of A determining BC.
So, it becomes a simpler set.
So, A determining B is removed, then I would
check for A being extraneous in AB determining
C and we find that it indeed is extraneous.
So, ah because B determining C is already
there, you can do the formal test in terms
of the closure.
So, the set gets even simpler.
I will check if C is extraneous in A determining
BC.
I find that it indeed is and again you can
use transitivity to get here or ah can use
ah attribute closure and finally, I get that
the set of the original set F is covered by
a canonical set where just you have A determining
B and B determining C.
So, this set is logically implied by the original
set and this set can logically imply the original
set and we will often use the canonical cover
for simplicity and for ease of application.
Naturally this is strongly using the underlying
concept of equivalence of two sets of functional
dependencies F and G.
They are equivalent if there closures are
equal or in other words, if F covers G and
G covers F, that is F logically implies G
and G logically implies F. So, this table
shows you at different conditions where you
can conclude whether F and G are equivalent
sets of functional dependencies.
So, they will have to, both covers have to
be true for the sets to be equivalent.
Next what I have done is, we have put a number
of practice problems for ah various kind of
things that you can do with functional dependencies.
The first set of problems.
Find in first set of problems you have to
find if a given functional dependency is implied
from a set of functional dependencies.
So, there are three problems where three sets
of functional dependencies are given and you
are given to check one or more functional
dependencies if it is implied from that set.
So, use the attribute closure and the algorithm
that we have discussed to practice these problems
and become master of that.
You can also check if ah you can find candidate
key using the functional dependencies.
The sets are given.
Your task would be to find the candidate keys.
You can also use the algorithms to find super
keys for a given set of functional dependencies.
So, do practice these problems.
You can find prime and non-prime attributes
using functional dependencies.
Prime attributes ah are attributes that belong
to any candidate key, not necessarily the
same candidate key.
All attributes that belong to some candidate
key, you take a set together and you call
them as a prime attribute and non prime attributes
are those that do not belong to any candidate
key at all.
So, here your task is to find the prime and
non-prime attributes using the sets of functional
dependencies given .
You can check for equivalents for a pair of
sets of functional dependencies.
There are couple of problems given on that.
So, please ah try them out.
For here for the different sets, you have
to compute the minimal cover or the irreducible
set or canonical cover of the set of functional
dependencies.
So, please practice on this ah problem, so
that you become comfortable with ah using
this algorithms for dealing easily with the
functional dependency sets of functional dependencies,
individual functional dependencies and so
on.
So, after this week is closed and your assignments
are also done, then we will publish the solutions
for these practice problems as well next let
me ah take up a little characterization of
the concept that we had introduced earlier
in terms of the lossless join decomposition.
So, in the lossless join decomposition, the
problem is ah say that you have a relational
scheme R and you are trying to divide that
into two relational schemes R1 and R2.
So, both R1 and R2 are ah having a set of
ah attributes and R naturally has a set of
attributes which is a union of the attributes
of R1 and R2, then is it possible that ah
if I take a relation, project it on the attributes
of R1 and on the attributes of R2, the two
relations that we get.
If I take a natural join of that, do I get
back R?
If I do, then I say that I have a lossless
join.
If I do not, then I have lost some information
due to this projection and recomputation of
the original ah relation based using the natural
join.
This ah requirement of lossless join decomposition
ah is determined if at least one of the following
dependencies exist in the closure set of F
which this is saying that if I do R1 intersection
R2, that is A attributes which are common.
You will recall that when we do natural join,
it is this set of attributes which take part
because these set of attributes will help
you compute the join between ah projection
on R1 and the projection of R2.
So, if this intersection set of attributes
uniquely determines R1 or it uniquely determines
R2, that is if the intersection set of attributes
is a super key either in R1 or in R2 or both
then, we say that the lost layer, the join
will be a lossless join.
Note that this is a sufficient condition which
means that there could be some instances where
this property is not satisfied yet the join
is lossless, but we need guarantees for our
design.
So, we ah make use of the fact that if one
of these conditions are satisfied, then it
is a sufficient condition to say that the
join will must, join will necessarily be lossless
.
So, here I give you a quick example ah to
show the idea.
So, we have a supplier relationship here which
has five attributes.
Here is an instance of that and we know that
these are the dependencies that hold the supplier
number determines ah the supplier name and
the supplier city and supplier number and
product number together determines the quantity
and we decompose them in this manner, we put
a supplier relationship where we have the
number, name, city and quantity of supplier
and then, we have parts relation where we
just have a product name and the quantity.
So, this is ah the projected supplier relation
instance.
This is a projected parts relation instance
and then, we take a natural join to reconstruct.
So, we are taking a natural join to reconstruct
and we get this relationship.
Now, our desire was that we must get back
the original relation, but if you compare,
you will find that ah this is not the case
here.
We have one tuple here and we have another
tuple here.
I have specifically highlighted them in red
which were not there in the original relation.
They have come in because ah when I did the
join naturally, the join had to be performed
on this common attribute quantity and based
on that value.
So, Nick 5 Nick NY , then we have 10 5 Nick
NY 10, this entry and we have two entries
of 10 and 10 here . So, the combination of
this with this where the product number is
20 is actually not present in the original
ah instance of the relation and that is what
shows up here a similar one exists here.
So, we get extra tuples and mind you though
we are actually getting extra tuple, we will
say that this join is lossy because if you
get extra tuple, then you are losing information,
you are losing correctness.
So, being lossy is actually losing correctness.
So, ah even though we have more tuples, we
say that this is a lossy join and ah you can
now go back and analyze it.
The common attribute QTY is not a super key
either in this or in this.
So, R1 intersection R2 implying R1 or implying
R2 does not hold.
So, it does not and in addition it also does
not preserve this functional dependency because
these are not, no more determined.
Now, let us see it.
So, we saw a case where the join decomposition
that we did and then, the subsequent join
that we performed did not prove to be a lossless
join.
We lost information.
So, let us take a look as to can we ah actually
do a decomposition which will be lossless
where we will not lose information .
So, I take the same example the supplier,
but the decomposition, the same set of dependencies
also, but the decomposition is different.
Now, we have name number, name and city in
one ah supplier relation and supplier name,
number, product number and quantity in the
other parts relation and then, we again go
back and perform the join .
Now, we find that from the original relation,
this was the original relation, this is the
projected supplier relation, these are projected
parts relation and this is the natural join
of these two relations.
So, this is the natural join of these two
relations and we find that they exactly match
with the original relation.
So, we have not lost any information we get
it back.
So, we say that the join is lossless and the
reason we could guarantee that is because
if you look into the set of functional dependencies,
you will find that S number, the supplier
number is a key in the supplier relationship
because it functionally determines S name
as well as S city.
So, R1 intersection R2 functionally determining
R1 is true here and therefore, it actually
gives you a lossless join.
It also preserves all the dependencies because
if you look into these dependencies, you can
check for this dependency.
In this relation, you can check for this dependency
also in this relation and you can check for
this dependency in also in the parts relation
which is something which we were not able
to do in the last decomposition that we have.
So, naturally this is a type of decomposition
that we will prefer . So, here ah we have
ah I have given some more examples which you
can practice and I show that given a very
simple ah schema having three attributes and
two dependencies, one decomposition into AB
and BC is lossless join decomposition whereas,
the other one AB and AC is a lossy decomposotion.
I have given a number of practice problems
on lossless join, so that you can practice
and become master of these kind of algorithm.
Finally, let me ah quickly go over the dependency
preservation ah concept.
Dependency preservation is if you have a relation
which you have decomposed ah into n different
relations, so if you decompose a relation
into a number of ah relations, then naturally
ah all functional dependencies you cannot
check on all the relations because a dependency
may involve attributes all of which may not
be present in a particular ah decomposed relation
that you have.
It may be distributed amongst ah different.
So, when you do this decomposition, for every
relation you get a new set of subset of functional
dependencies.
So, the decomposed relation R i the ith relation
will have a set of dependencies F i which
is a subset of the original set F and involves
only the attributes which exist in R i.
So, ah the decomposition will be said to be
dependency preserving if I can take the union
of all these functional dependencies, what
is projected on R 1, on R 2 and R n, F 1,
F 2, F n.
If we can take union of and if we take F,
they must be equivalent sets which we know
the requirement.
So, equivalence mean that their covers will
have to be equal.
If it is not, then some there will be at least
one dependency which you will not be able
to check in any one of the projected relations
and to be able to check that, you will have
to compute the natural join and that is as
we know is a very expensive process and we
would not be able to do that on a regular
basis .
So, here I have ah written down the algorithm
to test if a decomposition ah actually preserves
the dependency or not.
So, I will not go through the steps.
I will leave that for you to understand, but
what I will do, I will just show you a simple
set of worked out example and reason on that.
So, I show you two different methods of doing
this.
So, here we have a set of attributes given
the dependencies that work in that and a particular
decomposition.
So, given the set of attributes and the decomposition
if we project, now if we project the set of
functional dependencies and these are the
sets that we get.
So, on R1, we have two dependencies on R2,
we have three dependence, one dependency and
r 3 we have one dependency again.
So, if we now think about ah the union of
these and the closure for that, then we can
see that these four dependencies which occur
here and therefore, I have struck them off
in this set.
These four dependencies can be checked directly
on the projected relations.
So, that leaves us with three dependencies
in the original set which cannot be checked
on any one of R1 R2 or R3.
For example, if you consider BC determining
E, then B exist on R1 and C also exist on
R1, but E is not there.
So, you cannot check that dependency on R1,
you cannot check that on R2 because C and
E do not exist and you cannot check them on
R3, check it on R3,because none of them actually
exist.
So, what we will need for the dependency preservation
to hold is the dependencies which are already
existing four dependencies that are struck
off if they collectively can logically imply
these dependencies, so that they can be checked.
Then, we will be able to say that this is
dependency preserving.
So, what you do is something very simple.
You want to say, you want to check whether
this is preserved.
So, we start with the left hand side and compute
the closure.
The only difference you compute the closure
first with the set of functional dependencies
projected on R1, that is F1, the set closure
set that you get, you take that and compute
its closure with respect to the second set
of functional dependencies F2.
The closure that you get, you take that and
you compute the closure with respect to the
third set of functional dependencies which
is on R3 and that is your final closure set.
So, this closure set includes the right hand
side attribute E. So, we can conclude that
BC indeed ah functionally will determine E
and that relationship will be preserved because
we have starting from BC.
We have seen that in every projected relation
what all implied functional dependencies that
can be checked which is what the meaning of
the closure set of attributes R and since
that set eventually has E, we will know that
this can be, this will be preserved.
This set also has F. So, the other one will
also be preserved.
So, this is preserved, this is preserved to
check whether this dependency is preserved.
We need to again repeat the process and find
whether EF ah belongs to the final closure
set which it does and therefore, we conclude
that this decomposition is dependency preserving
.
With the same example I will just ah show
you a little different way of ah ah doing
the same exercise.
I have not written down the algorithm for
this in longhand, but the example should ah
be quite illustrative.
So, we are what you do when you project, you
check if some dependency has multiple attributes
on the left hand, on the right hand side,
then you write them in a separately decomposed
manner.
So, A implies determines BCD is written in
terms of three dependencies.
A implies B, B implies C and C implies D.
So, you make sure that all dependencies are
written in a form where the right hand side
has a single attribute, then you compute what
is known as the reverse functional dependencies
that is you take the right hand side and compute
whether the right hand side can imply the
left hand side.
So, I will just ah show you one.
So, in case the right hand side here is B,
you have AB on the right hand side.
So, you compute the closure with respect to
F. The original set, not the projected set
of D and you get BF.
So, you know that ah this ah inverse, this
reverse functional dependency which is AB
functionally determines A which is the reverse
dependency cannot be inferred and you do this
ah for each of the right hand side single
attribute and check if ah some, if the reverse
dependencies can be inferred or not.
The interesting case occurs here where if
you try to do the closure of A, you actually
find that A determines BC which is a reverse
of this functional dependency can be inferred,
but you do not consider that as a violation
because it is you already have A determining
B and A determining C. So, that logically
implies that A determines BC.
So, it is not a new ah violation that is getting
imposed.
So, with this your test for reverse functional
dependencies is passed and then, you finally
check for whether the three dependencies which
are not part of the projected set of dependencies,
you take the closure of the left hand side
with respect to in this case.
Again the original set of functional dependencies,
not the projected one and check if the right
hand side belongs there.
If they do, then combined with these two strategies
you say that the set of functional dependencies
are preserved under this decomposition.
So, this is the process to follow.
You can follow any one of the two approaches
to solve.
So, given some practice problems on dependency
preservation which you should practice on
to.
Summarize we have studied the algorithms for
properties of functional dependencies and
we have understood the characterization and
determination algorithm for lossless join
decomposition and for dependency preservation
in a decomposition.
In the coming module, we will make use of
these and discuss about how to improve these
designs of relational schemas through the
use of different normal forms.