.
Welcome to module 25 of Database Management
Systems. ah We have been discussing about
storage and file structure.
Ah In the last module we have ah talked about
different storage options.
And in this one we will talk about the; ah
organization of database files, what should
be the typical structure to store the records
in the files. And how the overall database
which manage itself we will talk about those
issues.
So, the file organization; so if you look
at a database; what is the database? It is
a collection of relations.
So, it is a collection of files every relation
is a file. Now, what is a file? A file is
a sequence of records, and what is a record?
It is a sequence of fields. So, this is the
hierarchy that exists and this will have to
be kept in mind, when we ah design the organization
of how we keep this data.
Now, one starting approach could be we can
assume that all records are of fixed size
which makes a life easier and ah each file
has records of only one type again a simplifying
assumption and different files are used for
different relations. So, this is a easiest
case to implement.
So, we will start with that; so this is what
we have we store these are fixed size records.
So, we store them one after the other and
based on the ah fixed size, we can easily
know what is the starting address of any record
and we can access it accordingly. Now, if
a if a record is deleted, then there are several
things that I can do see that this is a different
alternatives, that is if I record delete ah
record I then. So, if we delete any record
then ah we can actually move the records.
So, that ah we consume that space or we can
take the last record and move it there or
we can simply do not do any move, but use
an some additional pointers to ah denote that
these records have become free rather give
it to a free list.
So, these are the three main strategies. So,
here we showing the the first one the record
three has been removed. So, all records have
moved up in this it is we have move the last
record record 11 in the place of record 3.
So, record 3 is gone, but still the whole
thing reminds ah compact ah only ah the point
that must be noted that in the earlier one,
where well we moved everything then the ordering
that ah existed here of this key of this key
field ah is maintained, but if we move the
last record the naturally that ordering has
got ah destroyed. So, it will have implications
in terms of ah indexed organization that will
cover in the next ah modules.
ah The third option could be use a free list,
which is a nice one because ah you would you
do not neither ah here neither you destroy
the the order that existed and no one have
to really move records which is expensive,
but you just start ah with a pointer and keep
on pointing to the empty records.
And ah once you delete it you use that space
itself to point to the next ah deleted record.
So, whenever you have to ah you know delete
a record all that you need to do is adjust
this point. So, which is pretty fast and quite
efficient way of ah getting this ah linked
together in terms of ah; so there is ah as
such no space over it and it is a fastest
possible that you can do now in contest to
fix length record.
If the record becomes variable length, ah
then ah ah certainly every record may of very
different size and and it is very common for
example, ah we have types like varchar a lot
of strings are are varchar. So, we just we
do not know ah how much ah it will take. So,
the typical way you represent that ah is a
you represent ah as to; what is a starting
pointer of a particular ah of the actual value
and the size of the value the number of bytes
it will take. So, when we say twenty one five
which we mean that ah this field will actually
start from location 21 and we will have 5
locations 5 bytes, then the next 1 is ah 26,
10.
So, this will start to 26 and go for 10 such;
so what happens is; if you look into this
part ah of the data, then ah that part is
actually for all practical purposes the fix
length 1, because here you are just keeping
ah double x for the variable length data or
you have some field which is a ah which is
a fixed ah length data anyway or you have
a null which is ah stored in one byte, and
then you have all the variable stuff at at
one end. So, you can actually make part of
this fixed length by using this kind of encoding.
So, this is ah what is explained here.
So, for variable length records a ah one ah
main issue is if you if you keep it like this,
then since you are using actually you are
using pointers here we saying that this data
actually is on 21. So, what will happen is
if you change ah the position of the record
ah if you relocate the record, then all these
references will have to be updated. So, that
becomes a slotted thing. So, what the slotted
page ah ah structure does is it does a a [li/little]
little bit of adjustment it ah ports ah a
a puts a records here at the at the end.
And it has a header it has a. So, it has a
block header as in here and the block header
has actually pointers to the records and ah
then you have a an entry which ah points to
the end of the free space where more records
can still be stored. So, when ah ah you refer
to a particular record you do not actually
refer here. So, you do not refer here, but
you refer here. So, what you maintain is the
header is actually not changed, but if there
are relocations required adjustments required,
then that will be done ah with respect to
this and ah so, this value will change, but
any references made to this location will
remain invariant . So, that is the ah that
is the basic idea of the ah slotted page ah
structure, which can allow you to have ah
the variable length record with easy re locatability
in the design.
Now, let us see the ah given this ah what
is the organization of the records in the
file.
So, there are ah different ah ah organizations
that have been tried out ah the simplest is
the heap is a record can be placed anywhere
in the file where there is space. And you
can link to that ah that is that is one way
certainly there is nothing ah very smart in
terms of doing that ah, but you can you would
possibly like to do better than that. So,
one is you can store the; ah records in a
sequential manner let us store records in
in a sequential order in terms of certain
ah search key.
So, based on the value of the search key you
put them in the sequential orders. So, what
ah it will mean that it will become easier
to search ah the records in that way, but
it has consequences or you can hash you can
use a hash function on a some of the attributes
of the record and the results specified on
which block ah which disk block the record
will be placed. So, these are the different
option and a records of which relation may
be stored in a separate file that is a basic
convention, but in some cases there could
be multi table clustering as well.
So, let us quickly take a look at ah these
options.
So, these a sequential ah file organizations.
So, these things are kept ah sequentially
here as you can see there all consequentially
here and ah this is the link key of those
.
So, this is ah the issues of ah deletion and
if you delete you use ah pointer chains. As
you have ah we have discussed earlier, and
if you have to insert then you look for a
free space, if you find a free space you can
put it ah ah there you insert it there if
there is no free space then you have to use
a overflow block, where you can go and place
that separately as the dilemma shows here;
in a multi table ah clustering what you would
ah do is ah more than one relation could be
kept in the same file.
For example, here we are showing two relations
ah department name building and budget these
attributes doing department and instructor,
id name, department name, and salary is a
other instructor in a way keeping them together
here naturally, where we keep them together.
For example here ah in we have ah one ah which
is ah here in we have ah one, which is ah
ok and entry of record from the department
relation. Similarly here is another which
is from the department relation whereas, these
are entries from the instructor relation;
please note that ah since we are ah doing
it multi table with a department we do not
need to ah keep these information in as a
part of the record, but what you mean is ah
if there is a computer science entry here,
then all those records which follow this computer
science entry are actually instructors in
the computer science till I actually come
across another departments entry where which
will be followed by instructors for that department.
So, that is a basic ah multi table ah convention
that is ah to be followed here.
Now, it it is actually good ah for queries
that involved joining department with instructor,
because ah based on the value of the department
you have the instructors club together and
they could be very easily quickly ah taken
together and ah it is also good for ah single
ah ah queries with ah departments and it is
instructors, because as you can see you can
ah if you want to know for example, ah who
are the faculty for at computer science department;
then it be very easy to answer that, because
ah you need to search for computer science
and then you know all the list of the faculty
will be in consecutive block.
So, you can easily lift that, but certainly
this is not true, ah if you want to ah involve
queries which have department only; because
that department information are all now partially
ah distributed. So, if your query has the
department ah based ah information to be to
be accumulated, then this may not be a good
ah option. So, that will result in ah then
you can have ah supporting pointer chains
to actually link the department information.
So, this is a one kind of a design that you
have ok.
Now ah think about ah; so the whole so, we
have ah; so, far ah talked about the relations
and ah relations going to either single files
or multi table relations; ah multi table file
where ah multiple relations are on the same
file. Now, if you look at the database as
a whole. So, what is a data base?
The database as a whole has a whole lot of
ah tables; and so far we have just been focus
on the fact that tables ah we know the tables
we know their attributes and the data resides
in inside, but if you think in terms of the
database, then somebody; somewhere we will
need to remember that what are my tables?
What are my relations? For a given relation
I need to know what are the attributes that
the relation has, what is the; you know length
type of this attributes I did remember what
are the views that ah I have created on the
database the constraints that exist.
So, all of these information which you can
say is ah databases own metadata information
needs to be also maintained; and ah what is
done is that; also is maintained as a database
within the database system. And such a metadata
system is ah usually known as the name of
data dictionary or system catalogues.
So, it has informations like this. So, you
put them again, you create ah the schema design
based on the all this metadata information
that you need, also you can have ah you will
need to maintain information for users, ah
accounts, passwords and so, on. ah Then you
may have statistical information, where ah
you would like to; we will see the use of
statistical information when we talk about
indexing ah in in the following week ah you
will see that you need to know, what is the
you know how frequently the different queries
are fired, what are the number of peoples
in each relation and so, on; you may also
need to ah have information in terms of what
has been your choices in terms of the physical
locations of file the storage options and
so on the index ah files.
So, here is ah a sample one. So, what ah if
you look into; so you can again ah see a number
of ah schema. So, this is ah saying that the;
this is the relational metadata schema which
is talking about, what is the different relations?
So, every record here is not keeping the data
of your application, but its keeping the information
that here you have these ah different relations.
For example, ah ah couple of modules back
we are talking about the library information
system.
So, in the library information system we had
different we designed different relations
ah the the book issue, the book catalogue,
ah the book copies and so, on. So, those relation
names and the how many attributes they have?
How will you organize the storage, where is
that storage will go to this particular ah
table. Then depending on on the kind of ah
index that you are creating we have still
not discussed about index we will do ah subsequently;
but those index information can be preserved
the view information we can have attribute
ah metadata.
So, it is is ah for the relation name ah what
is attribute name and what is the type of
that attributes. So, if the relation name
is ah say ah book catalogue, then the attribute
name is title, then what is the domain type.
So, we will say this is a varchar; then the
position of that attribute, the length if
it is ah given the user metadata all of this
are typical things that will go into this
ah system catalogue or the data dictionary
that we will require.
So, finally, the access to the storage the
database file ah as ah I have been ah repeatedly
saying is ah partition into fix length units
called blocks, because blocks are defined
ah; so that ah they can be easily allocated
and transfer and they are the fastest ah unit
of ah data that can be transferred between
the disk and the memory.
So, unlike many of our ah typical algorithmic
considerations; so when we talk about ah different
algorithms, what we try to minimize? We try
to minimize certain expensive operations in
the CPU; say the comparison operation or the
assignment or may be the memory read operation.
But in terms of database systems block is
a basic unit of ah data transfer and the data
transfer two and from the disk is the most
time taking factor much ah takes much larger
time compare to any in memory operation that
we do. So, this ah kind of ah becomes ah the
primary unit of cost that we want to minimize.
So, normally we will see that ah as we talk
about index saying and other ah different
kinds of mechanisms, our primary target is
to minimize the number of block transfers.
So, ah certainly we can ah do that by; um
ah can reduce the number of ah disk ah access
by keeping as many blocks as possible in the
main memory. So, we can how can you minimize
that transfer, if we can keep more of the
blocks in our main memory and naturally ah
of course, there is a limitation because main
memory is much smaller. So, often we make
use of different buffers.
So, a portion of the main memory will be kept
to store copies of the disk block. So, every
time you need a block you may not want to
ah need to bring it from the; ah disk storage.
So, you keep it in the buffer in main memory,
and then you have a management strategy to
manage this buffer. So, whenever you want
to actually access a ah record which ah should
be in a particular block; you check whether
that block is already available in the buffer;
if it is available in the buffer it use that
if it is not available in the buffer, then
you take it from the disk you will need ah
quite a bit of cycles for that and as you
get that from the disk then you keep a copy
in the buffer so that it can be used in future.
Now as you keep on doing that, naturally soon
you will run out of ah the buffer memory.
So, you you will come to a situation, where
ah we need to ah ah bring a block from the
disk to the memory, but the buffer does not
have enough ah space. So, then we will have
to create replace some of the blocks and ah
create space for that. So, here is a basic
buffer management ah strategy.
So, ah ah as I said if we if we start if the
block is already there in the buffer, then
ah that is given out if the block is not there
in the buffer the buffer manager will need
to allocate some space how do you allocate
space by throwing out some other block which
is not required or replace ah the; then replace
the block return back to disk and ah if it
was modified and make space free and then
read from the disk and keep a copy in the
buffer. So, that is a simple strategy as you
can see .
Now, certainly when you have to replace the
block in the buffer, then ah the question
is which block would you replace. Now ah if
you recall from your from similar situations
in the ah in the operating system in terms
of memory management, you have read about
different strategies for doing replacement
and one of the ah very common strategy ah
more often used is the LRU strategy of the
least recently used strategy. So, the idea
of behind LRU is use the pass pattern of block
references as to predict the future. So, least
recently used is if this is not been ah used
in the ah recent past ah. So, it has less
likely hood of being used in the future.
Now, ah to queries; ah now here we are trying
to do the similar thing in terms of ah queries.
So, they have a well defined ah access pattern
and ah database system can ah can make use
of that and as it turns out ah LRU can be
a bad ah strategy for example, often you are
ah doing computations ah in in terms of such
what you say such nested loops.
So, you have ah for each tuple you do this;
so you have basically trying to do a join.
So, you have two relations and you are trying
to do a join. So, when you do this when you
are going through the inner loop, there will
be lot of ah transfers that will happen; and
ah the original block where you have been
holding this ah is here and you are not accessing
that for quite some time.
So, while you are doing this ah if you if
this ah block, which was which was holding
r at that time if that turns out to be a LRU;
then you will throw it away, but with that
when you complete this loop and come back
here, you will again have to read it from
the disk. So, this is not LRU for such ah
nested computations may not be a good strategy,
so may be some kind of mixed strategy would
ah work ah better.
So, there are several ah that ah are used
in terms of ah buffer replacement one is called
ah pin block, where you mark a certain memory
block which ah is not allow to be return back
to the disk it has to stay in the buffer or
a toss immediate strategy is is quite often
used. So, it ah frees the space occupied by
a block; as soon as ah the final tuple has
been return.
So, its a toss immediate. So, as soon as you
are done you just ah throw it out you are
you are done with it so you write it back.
ah Another ah which is ah commonly uses most
recently use the; ah ah if ah whenever the
block is ah currently being processed, then
ah the system will kind of keep a marker a
pin. So, that it is not ah removed, but ah
after the final tuple has been processed,
the block will be unpinned and then it becomes
a most ah recently used block and ah you can
go with ah defining the most recently used
block and having the strategy.
You can certainly use different kinds of ah
statistical information and ah in summary;
so on this ah we have ah talked about ah the
basic organization of ah database files starting
from the fixed record to ah variable record
ah handling of ah the different file organization
and ah ah try to take a look in terms of how
records and relations are organized in terms
of the in terms of the files and what are
the options that we have and ah we took a
look at the data dictionary storage the basic
ah system catalogue, where database keeps
its own information.
And ah then ah noted that ah block happens
to be the major unit of data transfer between
the disk and the main memory and ah therefore,
that is the unit of defining unit of cost
that we have to incur, and ah to minimize
that we have a buffering strategy in the main
memory, where the disk blocks will be kept
a a few disk blocks will be kept for quick
use whenever required. And there needs to
be various different smart ah replacements
strategies for good management of this buffer.