.
Welcome to module 31 of database management
system.
This module and the few following it will
be on transactions.
So, we have so far, ah through the modules
that you have done we have so far looked at
the first the schema of a database system,
which is the plan the layout of how the data
will be organized.
Then we have looked at if the data is populated,
then how we can query how we can manipulate
the data.
We have looked at how the data is actually
physically stored, and how it can be efficiently
accessed through different mechanisms in the
storage.
Now we will focus on the actual execution
time.
We will focus on what goes on when the data
in a database system is accessed, it is read,
locally modified and then written back.
In a very simple terms this is the operation
that keeps on happening in the database systems,
which we will identify which we say are transactions.
So, this is what we had done in the last week
talking about index.
And we now start with the understanding of
this concept of transaction, and we explore
various issues related to concurrent execution
of transactions.
So, we will explain in more detail what this
mean.
And these are the 3 topics that we will focus
on in this module.
So, let us first take a look at what does
a transaction mean.
We say transaction is a unit of program execution
that accesses and possibly updates we data
items.
So, it greets possibly makes some local changes
and then it writes it back.
So, here is an example of a transaction.
So, without that detail unnecessary details
what it looks at there are 2 accounts account
A and B, and we want to transfer 50 dollars
from account A to account B. So, we want to
we need to debit account A by 50 dollars,
and then credit account B by 50 dollars that
will achieve the transfer.
So, to start this process we first need to
know what is the current balance of the account
A.
So, that is done by read a the first ah instruction.
Then so, A after reading a has come into a
local buffer into a temporary which exists
in memory, if the current balance was 200
dollar, then that has not changed that remains
to be 200 dollar a has become is a local variable
which is taken the value 200 dollar now.
So, we locally change it we debit 50 dollars
from that.
So, a becomes 100 and 50 dollar, and then
we write it back.
So, in the account balance where it was 200
dollar, it will now become 100 and 50 dollar
with this 50 dollars debited.
Then we have to do the credit process to the
account B. So, in the 4th instruction we read
B. So, let us say the current balance of account
B was 300 dollar, then read B will make the
temporary variable B as 300 we credit 300;
that is, we add 50 dollars to that it becomes
300 and 50, and then we write B onto the account
based balance.
So, account-based balance will now change
to 300 and 50 dollar.
So, this whole sequence of 6 instructions
is called a transaction.
And as you can understand that to achieve
our target of transferring 50 dollars from
account A to account B, all these 6 instructions
have to execute in this order so that we can
get the desired results.
Now the question is; so, this this is pretty
simple, this is like a very simple low-level
program.
But there are 2 main issues that we have to
deal with.
First, what is the guarantee that once the
instruction one starts?
What is the guarantee that it will continue
up to instruction 6?
There may be some failures in between the
disk may fail the hardware may fail the system
may crash.
So, what will happen to the state of the database?
What will happen to the values that exist
in the database?
What will happen to the target operation that
we wanted to do achieved through this transaction
if such failures happen.
A second issue is, we need multiple transactions
to execute concurrently.
What it means that, suppose I am working on
a net banking updating my account I am making
transfers to another party whom I need to
pay.
At the same time, several other people are
also doing operations on their accounts, respective
accounts.
Lot of other operations might happen from
the database itself.
For example, while I am making a transfer
at that same time the database may be crediting
some quarterly interest to my account.
All these transactions, actually execute concurrently.
Which means that, they all are independently
executing.
They use the same CPU, but they achieve the
result at the same time.
So, it is not that the transactions are actually
happening on separate machines, the transactions
have to take effect on the same database.
So, they have to occur in a concurrent manner,
that is what we see is a concurrent manner
because they occur together.
And while this is going on, how do we ensure,
but there is one CPU.
So, the CPU is executing these instructions
in some order.
So, how do we ensure that this in the face
of such concurrency the transactions will
still give me correct result?
So, these are the 2 major issues for which
we are going to study about transactions,
and what we in general say the transaction
management systems .
So, we first set the targets we put some required
properties of a transaction.
The first requirement is atomicity.
Suppose again just look at the same transaction,
suppose the system crashes there is a system
failure after the first 3 instructions has
happened and 4th instruction was about to
happen.
So, what will happen?
The already the account A has been debited
by 50 dollars and account B has not yet been
credited with that 50 dollars.
So, simply at this point if the transaction
if the system failure happens, then simply
50 dollars will disappear from the system
it will not exist.
So, the basic requirement is that once a transaction
start it should either completely happen it
should either do all the 6 instruction as
in this case or it should do nothing.
So, there is an all or none kind of requirement
is that that is what we say it is like.
So, transactions in a way are indivisible
or atomic and this is the atomicity requirement.
The second requirement is called consistency
requirement.
That is as the transactions are making changes
to the database at , through these changes
the integrity of the database the consistency
of the values should not get affected.
So, if we there are certain specific integrity
constraints we have talked of primary keys
foreign keys and so on.
And there could be implicit domain integrity
constraints.
For example, in this accounting case if we
are making transfers, then while making a
transfer from account A to account B the sum
of the balances in account and account B before
the transfer and after the transfer must the
same.
So, money should not disappear, neither should
get should it get generated.
So, what we assume that a transaction when
it starts to execute.
It must start in a consistent database which
is correct in every respect.
During the transaction there may be temporary
inconsistency.
For example, if you look at ah at instruction
4 or instruction 5 at this time, the account
A has already been debited by 50 dollars the
account B has not been credited by that 50
dollar.
So, if you add instruction 4 if you try to
see, what is the sum of the balance in account
A and account B you will see that sum is 50
dollars less.
But when the transaction completes, it completes
the instruction 6, then again, the sum will
be same as thus as it were at the beginning.
So, at the beginning of an execution, and
at the end of a successful execution the database
must be consistent in between there may be
transient inconsistency.
So, this is called the consistency requirement.
The third is again first look at the example
the same on the left is a transaction T 1
which is the transaction we have been talking
of.
And suppose there is another transaction T
2 which happens concurrently.
If it happens concurrently the transaction
T 2 has let us say 3 instructions read A read
B and print A plus B. So, it tries to read
the balance of account A and B and prints
their sum.
Obviously, if the transaction T 2 is allowed
these 3 instructions of transaction T 2 if
they are allowed to be executed.
Between instruction 3 and instruction 4 of
transaction T 1, then T 2 will print a sum
of A plus B which is 50 dollars less, than
the sum of A plus B at the beginning.
So, it will become it will appear as if there
is some inconsistency that has happened.
So, the isolation requirement says that when
transactions ah occur concurrently, the net
effect of the transactions should be as if
they happen either first T 1 happened and
then T 2 happen.
Over first u or T 2 executed and then T 1
executed.
The though even though they can may execute
in a concurrent or mixed manner, the result
of such inconsistent state of the database
should not be available to the other transactions.
So, this is called the isolation requirement.
So, that transactions need to be isolated
appropriately.
So, that they can; obviously, if they execute
serially then the isolation is trivially satisfied,
but that will mean that your throughput, your
performance will be very low.
So, we need transactions to happen concurrently,
but the isolation must be satisfied .
The 4th ah is called the durability requirement,
which says that if a transaction has finally,
completed successfully.
Then the update the changes that the database
that has been made by the transaction, that
must persist even if there is some software
or hardware failures in future so once.
This transaction of transferring 50 dollar
from A to B has successfully completed with
the 6 instructions having been executed and
the money have been transferred, that will
should persist even if subsequently some error
some failures in the database will occur.
So, it must be the changes must be durable
.
So, these 4 properties are together called
the acid properties of a transaction system.
So, acid means a for atomicity that either
all operation of the transaction are properly
reflected in the database or none of them
are reflected consistency c for consistency
execution of a transaction in isolation preserves
the consistency in the database.
The isolation requirement, that if multiple
transactions are occurring concurrently, transaction
Tir Tjr occurring concurrently that is some
instruction of Ti happen then some instructions
of Tj happen then some instruction of Ti again
happen and in this manner.
Even then, the final result should look like
as if Ti has happened followed by Tj or Tj
has first executed followed by Ti the isolation
i for isolation and finally, durability once
the successfully transactions have completed
the changes in the database should persist.
So, a cid the acid properties are the critical
properties of the transaction system and must
always be satisfied.
Next what we look at is as transactions go
through each and every instruction.
The transaction happened to be in one of the
different states.
So, while the transaction as soon as the transaction
starts and starts executing starting from
the initial state it is in an active state.
So, consider this same transaction is done
read it it is in active state it has decremented
A by 50 it is in active state and so on.
So, as long as it is executing, it is in active
state, unless it has ok first let us talk
about success.
So, once it has executed the last treatment,
last instruction that is instruction 6 here,
it is in a state that is called partially
committed.
So, it has been able to successfully complete
all the instructions.
Or it might happen that during being in the
active state, or being in the partially committed
state some errors has happened so that the
normal execution cannot proceed any further.
Then, the transaction comes in to the failed
state.
A transaction which is in the failed state
will eventually get aborted.
Because it is not known when the failure has
happened.
So, naturally at the time of failure there
could be an inconsistency failure could have
happened in the 4th instruction in this transaction.
And as you have already noted.
That a has already been debited by 50 dollars
and B has not been credited that 50 dollars
so, it is in an inconsistent state.
Say failure if the transaction is in a failed
state like this then we need to rollback,
we need to undo the changes that we have done.
We need to credit back the 50 dollars that
was debited from A.
So, that we can reach a consistent state.
And once we have done that once we have done
this rollback successfully, the transaction
goes to an aborted state that is it it could
not take place, and after that you have 2
choices either you can restart the transaction,
or you can totally kill the transaction do
not do it at all depending on different situation
that choice is made.
In the other case if it is it were partially
committed, then all instructions had completed,
now the bookkeeping and other actions were
required.
If there is some failure during that time
from partially committed it comes to fail
state, and then goes to abroad state as I
have already explained.
Or it actually commits all the changes correctly
and it has completed successfully and it goes
to a committed state where the transaction
has successfully finished.
So, every transaction will go through this
state at any point of time a transaction will
be in one of the states, and depending on
the status of execution it will continue to
remain in that state or will change state.
So, this state transition diagram for transactions
are very important, and you must thoroughly
understand what is happening and remember
this particular state transition ok.
Now let us look into the actual concrete execution
situations.
So, in the concurrent execution situation,
what we have we have multiple transactions
that run at the same time on the system.
So, that will advantages it will increase
throughput, it will increase processor and
discrete realization for example, when one
transaction is doing some operations with
on the CPU, some internal computations are
going on the disk can still be accessed by
another transaction to read or write some
values.
So, the throughput will increase and also
the average response time will reduce because
there may be a short transaction.
Which if it were serially done then it will
have to wait for a very long transaction,
which may already been executed executing
ah, but if we allow concurrent execution then
in between that long transaction few cycles
may be taken to execute the short transaction
and the average response time will improve.
So, that is our basic requirement.
Naturally we need to do this in a controlled
manner so that we ensure that the acid property
is the consistency of the database and the
acid properties are maintained.
So, for doing this we create what is called
a schedule.
A schedule is a sequence of instructions that
specify, the chronological, or the time wise
order in which instructions of concurrent
transactions are executed.
So, what is what will the schedule will have?
Scheduler will have for a set of it is defined
for the set of transactions.
And it must consist of all instructions of
those transactions.
And in a certain order, and what is the basic
requirement that in this schedule in this
ordering, the original order of instructions
in any of this given transaction, you have
an individual transaction must be preserved.
But the instructions from different transaction
can be interleaved, intermixed in between
to prepare the schedule . So, a transaction
that successfully completes it is execution
will perform what is called a commit instruction
we will more specifically say what is commit
a commit instruction, which means successful
completion as the last statement that should
be the last statement if the committee is
not given by default also transactions which
have executed successfully are assumed to
have executed commit, or if the transaction
fails to successfully complete the execution;
that means, we will do abort as a last statement
ok.
So, let us take an example so, again we are
going back to the same ah example.
So, we have 2 transactions T 1 and T 2.
T 1 transfers 50 dollars from a to B as we
have seen.
And T 2 transfers 10 percent of the balance
from A to B. So, one transaction debits 50
dollars one transaction debits 10 percent
of the account balance of A to B. So, if they
they are serially executed as you can see
here we are serially executing them as in.
So, first you first your whole of T 1 is executing,
and once this has committed, that is successfully
ended then T 2 is executing.
So, at the beginning if we assume this is
just an assumption.
If we assume at the beginning that a had 100
dollar and we had 200 dollar, then the sum
was 300 dollar.
So, if the a is red 100 dollar is red then
it becomes 50 then you write this A. So, when
you are here at this point, you can see, this
is what you will have because a has changed
from 100 to 50 because you have debited B
nothing has happened on B so, some is 250.
So, you can see that is why I have shown different
colors you can see at 250.
This state of the database is temporarily
inconsistent because the sum has become different
from 300.
Then it reads B it reads 200 adds that 250
it writes B . You come to this point where
ah after this right, when the commit is happening
after the writing this B. Then T 1 has actually
completed, and 50 dollars has got transferred
to account B, and the sum is again back to
300 so, consistency is preserved.
Then transaction 2 starts so, a is red 50
dollars is red in temporary you compute 5
10 percent of that 5 dollar you decrement
a by 5 dollar and write it back.
So, when you have written it back, you write
back 45 dollar.
Again, naturally the sum becomes 5 dollar
less, the 5 dollar that you have kept in this
temp, and this becomes again transitively
inconsistent in in the process.
Then you do the read B, ad that temporary
5 dollar back to B and then you finally, when
you write B here you write back from 200 and
50 you have added 5 dollar to 255, and again
the sum becomes 300 you are again back to
the ah consistent state.
So, you can see, through this process that
when transactions actually happen in a serial
manner, this is how things will move on so,
which is quite understandable.
So, let us move on let us . So, this is a
different schedule you can see, but this is
also a serial schedule here what we have assumed
that all instructions of T 2 are done first
then all instructions of T 1.
I am not going through the going through each
step you can see what are the consistent,
and the temporarily inconsistently states
of the database, but at the end the database
is in a consistent state.
And you can can note that now the end value
of a is 40 dollar, and n value of B is 2 60
dollar.
In the previous schedule, the value was 45
dollar, and 255 dollar these 2 are different.
But both of them are actually correct both
of them are consistent, because when things
happen in this distributed manner, we have
no control in terms of whether that whether
first 50 dollars should be debited and then
10 should be debited transferred.
Or whether first 10 should be transferred
or 50 dollars where will be transferred after
that, either of that is a correct consistent
state.
So, the different schedules might give you
different results that is not of any concern
because both of them are possible valid results.
But the question is it must finally, have
a consistent state of the database so, both
of these are consistent.
Now, take an interesting example, where schedule
3 where where in here if you, if you look
at carefully there are few instructions of
T 1 which are executed.
And then in the temporal order few other instructs,
few instructions of T 2 are executed.
Then again T 1 then again T 2.
So, the instructions from 2 different transactions
are getting interleaved.
And this is what the execution status would
be.
So, you can see that when you are when T 1
writes a this is where you are 50 dollars
has been debited.
Then when T 2 writes a subsequently , another
5 dollar is debited so, it becomes 45.
So, then ah you have T 1 again executing and
adding B on to that.
And by that it is not only that it has gone
into an inconsistent, it is it was already
in an inconsistent state, but that was transient
that was temporary.
But now the transaction T 1 has totally completed.
It is completed his execution it is at it
is commit, but your database is still in an
inconsistent state.
So, this is something which is possible, because
you are doing an interleaving of the instructions
of the 2 transactions in the schedule.
But once you allow the rest of the transaction
B this part to ah complete that is B gets
updated and you reach here.
And that also has committed.
So, your schedule comprised of transaction
one and transaction 2, when both of them have
completed you have again reached state which
is consistent.
And if you look at the results of what you
have achieved you will immediately identify
that this doing it doing the transactions
according to schedule 3, which is interleaving
in in this manner is equivalent to this in
this manner of interleaving is equivalent
to doing them according to in this manner
which is schedule one.
So, you have got a schedule which is equivalent
to schedule one . And it is therefore, so,
this is just an example to show that it is
actually possible to interleave the instructions
of 2 transactions, and create a schedule which
will still which might in the in in the process
have transient or even ah inconsistent commit
states of the database.
But finally, when the schedule ends it will
it is possible that it will bring you to a
consistent state .
Now, look at again for those transactions
look at a different interleaving, a different
schedule, again T 1 T 2 are involved.
But you have now tried to interleave them
in a in a different order . So, earlier the
interleaving was done after T 1 has done right,
here it is done after he has been the locally
debited by 50.
And then this part is done and then the right
is happening.
And now if you go through the steps I will
leave it as an exercise for you in schedule
4.
Now, if you go through the state you will
find that when transaction T 1 commits ah
ends here, you have an inconsistent state.
And finally, even when the schedule ends that
T 2 has committed.
There is A, you are in an inconsistent state
somehow that sum of A and B which was 350
has become 300 has become 350 so, 50 dollars
as what generated.
So, this is so you can see that if you interleave
the transactions, then it is quite possible
that the transactions will may or may not
actually give you a consistent data base.
So, here in this module, we have ah understood
the basic tasks that a data bit base performs
database executes; which is in form of a transaction.
And we have seen that they must satisfy a
set of properties typically called the acid
properties, and atomicity, consistency, isolation
and durability must be satisfied.
And when the transactions are executed in
concurrent fashion, we improve the throughput,
but the concurrent execution of transaction
raise issues of serializability; that is,
the concurrent execution that the interleaved
schedule of instruction of 2 or more transactions
can give rise to certain effect which violate
the acid properties.
And those need to be addressed that certainly
inconsistent database is certainly never acceptable.
And ah so that is the the basic problem that
we have identified which we will have to address
in the coming modules .