the third component of a data model is constraints
a constraint is a logical statement
that means one can compute and test whether the statement is true or false
constraints are part of the data model because they can specify something about
the semantics that is the meaning of the data
for example the constraint that a week has seven and
only seven days is something that a data system would not know unless this
knowledge is passed on to it in the form of a constraint
another constraint shown here
tells the system that the number of titles for a movie is restricted to one
different data models
as we will see in the next module will have different kinds of constraints
there may be many different kinds of constraints
a value constraint is a logical statement about data values
on a previous slide we have said that the age that is
the value of data elements representing the age of an entity can not be negative
we also saw an example of uniqueness constraint when we said
every movie can have only one title
in the words of logic
there should exist no data object that a movie and has more than one title
it easy to see that enforcing these constraints requires us
to count the number of titles and then verify that it one
now one can generalize this to count the number of values associated with
each object and check whether it lies between an upper and lower bound
this is often called a cardinality constraint of data property
in a medical example here the constraint has a lower limit of 0 and
an upper limit of 3
a different kind of value constraint can be enforced by restricting the type of
the data allowed in a field
if we do not have such a constraint we can put any type of data in the field
for example you can have - 99 as the value of the last name of a person
of course that would be wrong
to ensure that this does not happen we can enforce the type of the last name
to be a non - numeric alphabetic string
this example shows a logical expression for this constraint
a type constraint is a special kind of domain constraint
the domain of a data property or
attribute is the possible set of values that are allowed for that attribute
for example the possible values for
the day part of the date field can be between 1 and 31
while a month may have the value between 1 and 12
or alternately a value from the set january february ect till december
now one can devise a more complex constraint where the value of the date
for april june and september and november are restricted between 1 and 30
and if you think about it all three constraints that we have
described in the last slide are value constraints
so they only state how to restrict the values of some data property
in sharp contrast structural properties restrict the structure of the data
we will choose a more complex example for this
suppose we are a matrix as shown in the example and
we have restricted to be a square matrix
so the number of columns is exactly equal to the number of rows
we have not put any restriction on the number of rows or columns
but just that they have to be the same
now this constrains the structure of the matrix and
implies that the number of entries in the structure will be a squared number
if we convert this matrix to a three column table as shown and impose
the same squareness constraint it will translate to a more complex condition
that the number of data rows will be the square of
the number of unique values in column one of the table
we will encounter some more structural constraints in the next module
the second component of a data model is a set of operations that can be performed
on the data
and in this module
we will discuss the operations without considering the bigness aspect
in course three
we will come back to the issue of performing these operations when the data is large
now operations specified the methods to manipulate the data
since different data models are typically associated with different structures
the operations on them will be different
but some types of operations are usually performed across all data models
we will describe a few of them here
one common operation extract a part of a collection based on the condition
in the example here we have a set of records and
we are looking for a sub set that satisfies the condition that
the fifth field has a value greater than 100 000
the only one record satisfies this requirement
note that we called this operation subsetting rather loosely
depending on the context it also called selection or filtering
the next common operation is retrieving a part of a structure that is specified
in this case we specify that we are interested
in just the first two fields of a collection off records
but this produces a new collection of records which has only these fields
this operation like before has many names
the most dominant name is projection
in the next module we will see several versions of this operation for
different data models
the next two operations are about combining two collections
into a larger one
the term combine may be interpreted in various ways
the most straightforward of them is said union
the assumption behind the union operation
is that the two collections involved have the same structure
in other words if one collection has four fields and another has 14 fields or
if one has four fields on people and the dates of birth and the other has four
things about countries and their capitols they cannot be combined through union
in the example here their two collections have three and
two records respectively with one record that common between them
the green one
the result collection has four record
because duplicates are disallowed because it a set operation
there is indeed another version of union where duplicates are allowed and
will produce five records instead of four
the second kind of combining called a join can be done when
the two collections have different data content but have some common elements
in the example shown
the first field is the common element between the two collections on the left
in this kind of data combination there are two stages
first for each data item think of a record of collection one
one finds a set of matching data items in collection two
thus the first records of the two collections match
based on the first field
in the second phase of the operation
all fields of the matching record pairs are put together
in the first record of the result collection shown on the right
one gets the first four fields on the first collection and
the remaining two fields from the second collection
now in this one example we found one pair of matching records from the collections
in general one would find more than one matching record pairs
as you can see this operation is more complex and
can be very expensive when the size of the true collections are large
in the big data world we often hear the term structured data that is data having
a structure which is quite different from the so - called unstructured data
but what is a structure
let consider file 1
it a typical csv file that has three lines with different content
but the file content is uniform in the sense that each line
call it a record has exactly three fields
which we sometimes call data properties or attributes
further the first two of these fields are strings and the third one is a date
we can add more records that lines with the same pattern of data
to the file in the same fashion
the content will grow but the pattern of data organization will remain identical
this repeatable pattern of data organization makes the file structured
now let look at file 2 which is four records of five fields each
except that the third record seems to be missing the last entry
is this file structured
we argue that it is because the missing value makes the third record incomplete
but it does not break the structure or the pattern of the data organization
let looks at these two files side by side
clearly file 2 has more fields and hence is sort of wider than the first file
would you say that they have the same structure
well on the face of it they do not
but if you think more broadly
you would notice that they are both collection of k fields
the size of the collection respectively three and four differs
and k is 3 in the first case and 5 in the second
but we can think of 3 and 5 as parameters
in that case we will say that these files have been generated by a similar
organizational structure and hence they have the same data model
now in contrast consider this file
just looking at it it impossible to figure out how the data is organized and
how to identify subparts of the data
we would call this data unstructured
often compressed data like jpeg images mp3 audio files
mpeg3 video files encrypted data are usually unstructured
in module two we will elaborate on data models that are not fully structured or
are structured differently
this is the first of two hands - on exercises involving
sensor data from a weather station
in this one we will look at static data in a text file
the next one we will look at live data streaming from the weather station
in real time
in this exercise we will begin by opening a terminal window and
changing into the directory containing the station measurements
we will look at these measurements in a text file and then look at the key for
these measurements so we can understand what the values mean
finally we will plot the measurements
let begin
first we will open a terminal window by clicking on the terminal icon on the top
of the toolbar
next we will cd into the directory
containing the sensor data
we will run cd downloads big - data - two sensor
we can write ls to see the contents of this directory
the data from the weather station is in a text file called wx - data txt
we can run more wx - data txt to see the contents of this file
each line of this file is a separate set of measurements
there are two columns in this file the first column is a time stamp and
it separated by a second column by a tab
the second column itself has separate columns and these are separated by commas
the time stamp is the number of seconds since 1970
you will notice that it increases for each time stamp
you will notice that it increases for each measurement
but sometimes measurements come in at the same time
for example this one at 006
the measurements we see that the prefix is 0r1 for
most of them but some have 0r2
if we look at the other measurements
we see that all the 0r1 measurements start with dn dm dx and so on
whereas r2 begins with ta ua and pa
if we scroll down in the text file by hitting the space bar
we will see there are other measurements besides r1 and r2
for example there r5 that has th vh vs and so on
and there r0 which has all the measurements
so dn dm dx ta ua pa
and the remaining ones
next we will open another internal window and look at the key to this
measurements click on the tool bar to open the terminal window
cd into downloads big data two sensor
and the key to these measurements is in a file called wxt520format txt
we can run more wxt520format txt to see this file
this file says where each of the prefix is mean for
example sn is the wind speed minimum
sm is the wind speed average
and ta is the air temperature
so if we go back to our sensor file we see here ta equals 13 9c
that means the air temperature at this
time was 13 9 degrees celsius
we can also create a plot of the data in this text file
by running plot - data py wx - data txt ta
this says to plot the data in the wx - data file and the measure that we
want to apply is ta which according to our key is the air temperature
when we run it it displays a plot of the air temperature found in the text file
in this hands - on exercise
we will be looking at an image file which uses an array data model
first we will open a terminal window and display an image file on the screen
next we will examine the structure of the image and finally
extract pixel values from various locations in the image
let begin
first we will open a terminal window by clicking on the terminal icon at the top
of the toolbar
next we will cdn2 the directory containing the image
cdn2downloads bigdata2 image
we can run ls to see the image in different scripts
the file australia jpg is an image that we want to view
we can use eog to view it
run eog australia jpg eog is a common image viewer on linux
australia jpg is a satellite image of the australian continent
now let look at the structure of this image file
if we go back to our terminal window we can run the image
viewer in the background by hitting ctrl + z and then bg
we can view the dimensions or structure of the array data model of this
image by running dimensions py australia jpg
this says that the image has 5250 columns and 4320 rows
so it is a two - dimensional image
additionally each cell or
pixel within this image is composed of three 8 - bit pixels
these pixels are composed of three elements red green and blue
we can extract or view the individual pixel elements
at a specific location in the image by using the pixel py script
we can run pixel py australia jpg 0 0 to see the value at one location
the 0 0 location is the corner of the image
if we go back to the image the corners are all the ocean so they are dark blue
if we look at the value that was extracted we see that blue has a high
value of 50 whereas red and green are low with 11 and 10
if we view it at another corner by looking at 5000 0
we will see the same value
if we go back to the image the middle of the image which is the land
is orange or yellow
it definitely not blue so let take a look at a pixel value there
okay run pixel py australia jpg 2000 2000
this says that the red has a value of 118 green is 89 and the blue is 57
so the red and green are higher than blue so it not ocean