this is the second hands on exercises for csv data
in the first we saw how to import a csv file into a spreadsheet and
make a simple plot
in this one we will learn how to filter data and
perform some aggregate operations
we will begin by opening a terminal window and starting a spreadsheet
next we will load the csv data into the spreadsheet and
perform a filter over several columns
finally we will calculate an average and sum from the data
let begin
first we open a terminal window by clicking on the terminal icon in
the top toolbar
we can start the spreadsheet by writing oocalc
next let load our csv data into the spreadsheet
we click on file open census csv
and click ok on this dialog to load the data
column f in the spreadsheet is the state and
column h is the census population for 2010
let create a filter that just shows the data for
california for counties larger than one million people
we can create this filter by first selecting both the state name column and
the census 2000 population column
next we go to data filter standard filter
here we change the field name to be the state name
the condition we leave at equals and the value we use california
this filters all the rows unless the state is california
we then want to filter for
all the counties whose population is greater than one million people
to do that in this second line here we change the operator to and
the field name should be census 2010 population and
the condition should be greater than
then set the value to be one million
and click ok
we can see that all the data from the spreadsheet has disappeared except where
the state name is california and
the population is greater than one million people
we can reset or remove this filter to see all the data again
by going to data filter
reset filter
you can perform aggregate operations on the data in a spreadsheet
next let perform some aggregate operations over the data
we can compute the average and the sum of the data
to do this let run these calculations in a separate sheet
create a new sheet by clicking on the green plus button
to compute the average we select a cell and enter = average and
then we select the data that we want to compute the average from
if we go back to sheet one
we can select some of the data from the h column
so let just choose several counties in alabama
when we hit enter it takes us back to sheet one and
we can see that the average is computing
similarly we can compute the sum by entering = sum open parentheses
going back to sheet one and selecting the columns we want to sum
when we are done hit enter and the sum is computed
in this hands on exercise we will be looking at json data
first we will open a terminal window and
then look at the contents of a json file containing tweets from twitter
next we will examine the schema of this json file
finally we will extract different fields from the json data
let begin
first we will open a terminal window
by clicking on the terminal icon at the top of the toolbar
next we will see cd into the directory containing the json data
by running cddownload big data 2 json
we can run ls to see the json file
the json file is called twitter json
we can run more twitter json to view the contents of this file
the json data contains semi - structured data which is nested several levels
there are many tweets in this file and it hard to read using the more command
you can use space to scroll down and when we are done hit q
we can run the jsonschema pi command to view the schema of this data
we run jsonschema pitwitter json
and we will add a pipe more at the end
this shows the nested fields within this data
at the top level there are fields like contributors text and id and so
on but there are also fields nested within these top level fields for
example entities also contains called symbols media hashtags and
so on if we scroll down by hitting space
we will see that there several levels of nesting
for example user also has follow request sent id and so on
we can run the print json script to view the contents of a particular tweet and
a particular field within that tweet
let run print json py
it asks for the file name so
we will enter twitter json
and we will look at tweet 99
so let look at the top level field called text
so here we see the text for note the 99th tweet in this file
we could also look at a nested field within the file by running print json
again the file name is twitter json
we will look at tweet 99 again
and we will look at the field entities hashtags
the hashtags that are embedded or nested within the entities field
this is the first of two hands on exercises involving csv data
in this exercise we will import a csv file into a spreadsheet and
make a simple plot
we will begin by opening a terminal window and looking at a csv file in the terminal
next we will start the spreadsheet application and
import the csv data into the spreadsheet
we can then look at the rows and columns of the csv file and make a simple plot
let begin first open a terminal shell by
clicking on the black terminal icon at the top of the toolbar
next let cd into the directory containing the csv data
we will run cd space download big - data - 2 csv
we can run ls to
see the csv files
the file census csv contains census data for the united states
we can run the command more census csv to see the contents of this file
the first line of this file is the header with the columns separated by commas
you can go down in the file by hitting space
hit q to quit more
next let start a spreadsheet application
we run oocalc to start this
we can import the census data csv file into
the spreadsheet by going to file open
clicking on downloads
big data 2 csv census csv
in this dialog click ok
you can see into this spreadsheet
import of the csv data to a bunch of rows and columns
each column that was separated by a comma in the csv file
is a column in the spreadsheet
we can see that our csv file was successfully imported into
the spreadsheet
if we scroll down to the bottom of the spreadsheet
we can see how many rows there were in the csv file
there are 3194 rows in the csv file
if this file instead had millions or 10 millions of rows
then we would have to use a big data system such as hadoop or hdfs
let scroll back to the top
next let make a simple plot of some of the data in the csv file
let plot the population estimates for several years for the state of alabama
the state of alabama is given in the second row and
the population estimates are given in these columns
let select j through o so you get the population
estimate for 2010 through 2015
we can create a plot of these values by clicking on the chart button
and clicking finish
in the second hands on for csv data we will perform some filtering and
some aggregate operations over the data
welcome
in this module we will talk about data models
if you completed the introductory course of this specialization
you might recall our video on data variety
one way to characterize data variety
is to identify the different models of data that are used in any application
so what is a data model
and why do we care about data models in the context of big data
in this lesson we will introduce you to three components of a data model and
what they tell us about the data
so after this lesson you will be able to distinguish between structured and
unstructured data
describe four basic data operations namely selection projection union and join
and enumerate different types of data constraints like type value and
structural constraints
you will also be able to explain why constraints are useful to specify
the semantics of data
now regardless of whether the data is big or small one needs to know or determine
the characteristics of data before one can manipulate or analyze them meaningfully
let use a simple example suppose you have data is
a file of records with fields called first name last name and date of birth of
the employees in the company that this file consists of records with fields
and not for instance plain text gives us more insight
into the organization of the data in the file and hence is part of the data model
this aspect is called structure
similarly the consideration that we can perform
data arithmetic with the date of birth field and
not with the first name field is also part of our understanding of data model
these are called operations
finally we may know that in this company no one age
that is today date minus the date of birth cannot be less than 18
so it gives us a way to detect records with blatantly erroneous dates of birth
in the following three videos
we will look at these three aspects of data models more carefully
we mentioned before that a data model is characterized by the structure of
the data that it admits the operations on that structure and
a way to specify constraints
in this lesson
we will present a more detailed description of a number of common data models
we will start with relational data
it is one of the simplest and most frequently used data models today and
forms the basis of many other traditional database management systems
like mysql oracle teradata and so forth
so after this video you will be able to
describe the structural components of a relational data model
demonstrate which components become a data model schema
explain the purpose of primary and foreign keys
and describe join and other operations
the primary data structure for
a relational model is a table like the one shown here for a toy application
but we need to be careful about relational tables which are also called relations
this table actually represents a set of tuples
this is a relational tuple represented as a row in the table
we were informally calling this a record before
but a relational tuple implies that unless otherwise stated the elements of it
like 203 or 204 mary and so forth are atomic
that is they represent one unit of information and
cannot be decomposed further
we will return to this issue in the next few slides
thus this is a relation of six tuples
remember the definition of sets
it a collection of distinct elements of the same type
that means i cannot add this tuple to the solution
because if i do it will be introducing a duplicate
now in practice many systems will allow duplicate tuples in a relation but
mechanisms are provided to prevent duplicate entries if the user so chooses
so i cannot add it
here is another tuple i cannot add
it has all the right pieces of information but
it all in the wrong order
so it is a tuple dissimilar with the other six tuples in the relation
okay so how does the system know that this tuple is different
this brings our attention to the very first row that is the header of this table
painted in black
this row is part of the scheme of the table
lets look at it
it tells us the name of the table in this case employee
this also tells us the names of the six columns called attributes of the relation
and for each column
it tells us the allowed data type that is the type constraint for each column
given this schema
it should now be clear why the last red row does not belong to this table
the schema in a relational table can also specify constraints
shown in yellow in the third line of the schema row
it says that the minimum salary of a person has to be greater than 25000
further it states that every employee must have a first and last name
they cannot be left null that means without a value
why does not department or title column have this constraint
one answer can be that a newly hired employee may not be assigned
a department or a title yet but can still be an entry in the table
however the department column has another constraint
it restricts the possible values that is the domain of the attribute
to only four possibilities
hr it research and business
finally the first says that id is a primary key
this means it is unique for each employee
and for every employee knowing the primary key for
the employee will also uniquely know the other five attributes of that employee
you should now see that a table with a primary key
logically implies that the table cannot have a duplicate record because if we do
it will violate the uniqueness constraint associated with the primary key
let us introduce a new table containing the salary history of employees
the employees are identified with the column empid but
these are not new values that this table happens to have
they are the same ids that are present in the id column of the employee table
presented earlier
this is reflected in the statement made on the right
the term references means the values in this column can exist
only if the same values if you are in employees the table being referenced
also called the parent table
so in the terminology of the relational model the empid column of empsalaries
table is called a foreign key that refers to the primary key of the employees table
note that empid is not a primary key in this empsalaries table
because it is multiple to post with the same empid
reflecting the salary of the employee at different times
you will remember join is a common operation that we discussed before
so here is an example of a relational join performed
on the first three columns of employee and empsalaries table
where employees id and empsalaries empid columns are matched for equality
the output table shows all the columns involved
the common column is represented once
this form of join is called a natural join
it is important to understand that join is one of the most expensive
that means time consuming and space consuming operations
as data becomes larger and tables contain hundreds of millions of tuples the join
operation can easily become a bottleneck in a larger analytic application
so for analytical big data application that needs joins it very important to
choose a suitable data management platform that makes this operation efficient
we will return to this issue in module four
we end this video on a practical note
in many scientific and
business applications people start with csv files
manipulate them with the spreadsheet then migrate their relational system only
as an afterthought where the data becomes too large to handle the spreadsheet
while the spreadsheet offers many useful features
it does not conform and enforce many principles of relational data models
consequently a large amount of time may be spent in cleaning up and
correcting data errors after the migration actually happens
let me show a few examples from a spreadsheet that has 125 000 rows and
over 100 columns
the spreadsheet here lists terrorism attacks gathered from news media
so each row represents one attack
this is a valuable piece of data for people who study terrorism
but we are going to look at it from a relational data modelling viewpoint
first notice the column marked in green
it lists two weapons used in the attack separated by a semicolon
why is this really common
it makes this column non - atomic
it means that this column actually has two different values
in a relational design this information will be moved to another table
just like the multiple salaries of employees were placed in a separate table
next notice the column outlined in red
it describes the amount of property damaged by a possible terrorist attack
in this column the intended legitimate values are unknown
minor major and catastrophic
however the value in the highlighted part of the spreadsheet is minor and
then within bracket likely less than 1 million
which means a query like find all attacks for
which the property damage is equal to minor cannot be answered directly
instead we need to perform a substring search for
minor in the beginning of the description
which is doable but it a more expensive operation
this shows the columns of the spreadsheet
so this is part of the schema of the data
if you observe carefully you will see a recurring pattern
the designer of the data table determined that there can be at most three types of
attacks within a single encounter and represented with three separate columns
now in proper relational modeling one would say that there is a one to many
relationship between the attack and the number of attack types
in such a case it would be more prudent
to place these attack type columns in a separate table and
connect with the parent using a primary key foreign key relationship
here another block with a similar pattern
this time this is about the types and subtypes of weapons used
now can you determine how you might be able to reorganize this block
we will leave this as an exercise