in this video we will talk about a new that is usually not covered much
it called valence
simply put valence refers to connectedness
the more connected data is the higher it valences
the term valence comes from chemistry
in chemistry we talk about core electrons and valence electrons of an atom
valence electrons are in the outer most shell have the highest energy level and
are responsible for bonding with other atoms
that higher valence results in greater boding that is greater connectedness
this idea is carried over into our definition of the term valence
in the context of big data
data items are often directly connected to one another
a city is connected to the country it belongs to
two facebook users are connected because they are friends
an employee is connected to his work place
data could also be indirectly connected
two scientists are connected because they are both physicists
for a data collection valence measures the ratio of actually connected data items
to the possible number of connections that could occur within the collection
the most important aspect of valence
is that the data connectivity increases over time
the series of network graphs comes from a social experiment where scientists
attending a conference were asked to meet other scientists they did not know before
after several rounds of meetings
they found new connections shown by their red edges
increase in valence can lead to emergent group behavior in people networks
like creation of new groups and coalitions that have shared values and goals
a high valence data set is denser
this makes many regular analytic critiques very inefficient
more complex analytical methods must be adopted to account for
the increasing density
more interesting challenges arise due to the dynamic behavior of the data
now there is a need to model and
predict how valence of a connected data set may change with time and volume
the dynamic behavior also leads to the problem of event detection
such as bursts in the local cohesion in parts of the data
and emergent behavior in the whole data set
such as increased polarization in a community
now we will talk about a form of scalability called variety
in this case scale does not refer to the largeness of data
it refers to increased diversity
here is an important mantra you need to think about
when we as data scientists think of data variety we think of the additional
complexity that results from more kinds of data that we need to store process
and combine
now many years ago when i started studying data management
we always thought of data as tables
these tables could be in spreadsheets or databases or just files but somehow
they will be modeled and manipulated as rows and columns of of tables
now tables are still really important and dominant however today a much wider
variety of data are collected stored and analyzed to solve real world problems
image data text data network data geographic maps computer
generated simulations are only a few of the types of data we encounter everyday
the heterogeneity of data can be characterized along several dimensions
we mentioned four such axes here
structural variety refers to the difference in
the representation of the data
for example an ekg signal is very different from a newspaper article
a satellite image of wildfires from nasa is very different from tweets
sent out by people who are seeing the fire spread
media variety refers to the medium in which the data gets delivered
the audio of a speech versus the transcript of the speech
may represent the same information in two different media
data objects like news video may have multiple media
an image sequence an audio and closed captioned text
all time synchronized to each other
semantic variety is best described two examples
we often use different units for quantities we measure
sometimes we also use qualitative versus quantitative measures
for example age can be a number or
we represent it by terms like infant juvenile or adult
another kind of semantic variety comes from different
assumptions of conditions on the data
for example if we conduct two income surveys on two different groups of people
we may not be able to compare or
combine them without knowing more about the populations themselves
the variation and availability takes many forms
for one data can be available real time
like sensor data or it can be stored like patient records
similarly data can be accessible continuously for
example from a traffic cam
versus intermittently for
example only when the satellite is over the region of interest
this makes a difference between what operations one can do with data
especially if the volume of the data is large
we will cover this in more detail in course two
when we explore the different genres of data and how we model them
we should not think that a single data object or
a collection of similar data objects will be all uniform in themselves
emails for example is a hybrid entity
some of this information can be a table like shown here
now the body of the email usually has text in it
however some of the text may have ornaments around them
for example
the part highlighted in yellow represents something called a markup on text
we will get to markups later in the course
emails contain attachments
these are files or embedded images
or other multimedia objects that the mailer allows
this screenshot from my outlook shows the image of a scanned image
of a handwritten note
when you take a collection of all emails from your mailbox or
that from an organization you will see that senders and
receivers form a communication network
in 2001 there was a famous scandal around a company called enron that engaged in
fraudulent financial reporting practices
their email network partly shown here has been studied by data scientist to find
usual and unusual patterns of connections among the people in the organization
an email collection can also have it own semantics
for example an email cannot refer to that means cannot copy or
forward a previous email
finally an email server is a real - time data source
but an email repository is not
does email and email collections demonstrate significant
internal variation in structure media semantics and availability
characteristics of big data - velocity
velocity refers to the increasing speed at which big data is created and
the increasing speed at which the data needs to be stored and analyzed
processing of data in real - time to match its production rate as it gets generated
is a particular goal of big data analytics
for example this type of capability allows for
personalization of advertisement on the web pages you visit
based on your recent search viewing and purchase history
if a business cannot take advantage of the data as it gets generated or
at the speed analysis of it is needed they often miss opportunities
in order to build a case for the importance of this dimension of big data
let imagine we are taking a road trip
you are looking for some better information to start packing
in this case the newer the information
the higher its relevance in deciding what to pack
would you use last month weather information or
data from last year at this time
or would you use the weather information from this week yesterday or
better today
it makes sense to obtain the latest information about weather and
process it in a way that makes your decisions easier
if the information is old it does not matter how accurate it is
being able to catch up with the velocity of big data and
analyzing it as it gets generated can even impact the quality of human life
sensors and smart devices monitoring the human body can detect abnormalities
in real time and trigger immediate action potentially saving lives
this type of processing is what we call real time processing
real - time processing is quite different from its remote relative
batch processing
batch processing was the norm until a couple of years ago
large amounts of data would be fed into large machines and
processed for days at a time
while this type of processing is still very common today decisions based on
information that is even few days old can be catastrophic to some businesses
organizations which make decisions on latest data
are more likely to hit the target
for this reason it important to match the speed of processing
with the speed of information generation and get real time decision making power
in addition today sensor - powered
socioeconomic climate requires faster decisions
hence we can not wait for all the data to be first produced
then fed into a machine
there are many applications where new information is streaming and
needs to be integrated with existing data to
produce decisions such as emergency response planning in a tornado or
deciding trading strategies in real time or getting estimates in advertising
we have to digest chunks of data as they are produced and give meaningful results
as more data comes in
your results will need to adapt to reflect this change in the input
decisions based on processing of already acquired data such as batch processing
may give an incomplete picture
and hence the applications need real time status of the context at hand
that is streaming analysis
fortunately with the event of cheap sensors technology
mobile phones and social media we can obtain the latest information
at a much rapid rate and in real time in comparison with the past
so how do you make sure we match the velocity of the expectations
to gain insights from big data
with the velocity of the big data
rate of generation retrieval
or processing of data is application specific
the need for real time data - driven actions within a business case is
what in the end dictates the velocity of analytics over big data
sometimes precision of a minute is needed
sometimes half a day
let look at these four paths and discuss when to pick the right one for
your analysis
the dollar signs next to the numbers in this example indicate how costly
the operation is
the more dollars the higher the cost
when the timeliness of processed information plays no role in decision
making the speed at which data is generated becomes irrelevant
in other words you can wait for as long as it takes to process data
days months weeks
and once processing is over you will look at the results and
probably share them with someone
when timeliness is not an issue you can choose any of the four paths
you will likely pick the cheapest one
when timeliness of end result is an issue
deciding which of the four paths to choose is not so simple
you will have to make a decision based on cost of hardware
time sensitivity of information future scenarios
in other words this becomes a business driven question
for example if speed is really important at all costs you will pick path four
as a summary we need to pay attention to the velocity of big data
streaming data gives information on what is going on right now
streaming data has velocity meaning it gets generated at various rates
and analysis of such data in real time gives agility and
adaptability to maximize benefits you want to extract
characteristics of big data veracity
veracity of big data refers to the quality of the data
it sometimes gets referred to as validity or
volatility referring to the lifetime of the data
veracity is very important for making big data operational
because big data can be noisy and uncertain
it can be full of biases abnormalities and it can be imprecise
data is of no value if it not accurate
the results of big data analysis are only as good as the data being analyzed
this is often described in analytics as junk in equals junk out
so we can say although big data provides many opportunities to make
data enabled decisions the evidence provided by data
is only valuable if the data is of a satisfactory quality
there are many different ways to define data quality
in the context of big data
quality can be defined as a function of a couple of different variables
accuracy of the data the trustworthiness or reliability of the data source
and how the data was generated are all important factors
that affect the quality of data
additionally how meaningful the data is with respect to the program that
analyzes it is an important factor and makes context a part of the quality
in this chart from 2015 we see the volumes of data increasing
starting with small amounts of enterprise data to larger
people generated voice over ip and social media data and
even larger machine generated sensor data
we also see that the uncertainty of the data increases as we go from
enterprise data to sensor data
this is as we would expect it to be
traditional enterprise data in warehouses have
standardized quality solutions like master processes for extract
transform and load of the data which we referred to as before as etl
as enterprises started incorporating less structured and unstructured people and
machine data into their big data solutions
the data become messier and more uncertain
there are many reasons for this
first unstructured data on the internet is imprecise and uncertain
in addition high velocity big data leaves very little or no time for
etl and in turn hindering the quality assurance processes of the data
let look at these product reviews for a banana slicer on amazon com
one of the five star reviews say that
it saved her marriage and compared it to the greatest inventions in history
another five star reviewer said that his parole officer recommended
the slicer as he is not allowed to be around knives
these are obviously fake reviewers
now think of an automated product assessment going through such
splendid reviews and estimating lots of sales for the banana slicer and
in turn suggesting stocking more of the slicer in the inventory
amazon will have problems
for a more serious case let look at the google flu trends case from 2013
for january 2013 the google friends actually
estimated almost twice as many flu cases as was reported by cdc
the centers for disease control and prevention
the primary reason behind this was that google flu trends used a big data on
the internet and did not account properly for uncertainties about the data
maybe the news and social media attention paid to the particularly
serious level of flu that year effected the estimate
and resulted in what we call an over estimation
this is a perfect example for
how inaccurate the results can be if only big data is used in the analysis
imagine the economical impact of making health care preparations for
twice the amount of flu cases
that would be huge
the google flu trends example also brings up the need for
being able to identify where exactly the big data they used comes from
what transformation did big data go through up
until the moment it was used for a estimate
this is what we refer to as data providence
just like we refer to an artifacts provenance
as a summary the growing torrents of big data pushes for
fast solutions to utilize it in analytical solutions
this creates challenges on keeping track of data quality
what has been collected where it came from and
how it was analyzed prior to its use
this is akin to an art artifact
having providence of everything it has gone through
but even more complicated to achieve with large volumes of data coming
in varieties and velocities
characteristics of big data - volume
volume is the big data dimension that relates to the sheer size of big data
this volume can come from large datasets being shared or
many small data pieces and events being collected over time
every minute 204 million emails are sent
200 000 photos are uploaded and 1 8 million likes are generated on facebook
on youtube 1 3 million videos are viewed and 72 hours of video are uploaded
but how much data are we talking about
the size and the scale of storage for big data can be massive
you heard me say words that start with peta exa and
yotta to define size but what does all that really mean
for comparison 100 megabytes will hold a couple of encyclopedias
a dvd is around 5 gbs and
1 tb would hold around 300 hours of good quality video
a data - oriented business currently collects data in the order of terabytes
but petabytes are becoming more common to our daily lives
cern large hadron collider generates 15 petabytes a year
according to predictions by an idc report sponsored by a big data company called
emc digital data will grow by a factor of 44 until the year 2020
this is a growth from 0 8 zetabytes
in 2009 to 35 2 zettabytes in 2020
a zettabyte is 1 trillion gigabytes that 10 to the power of 21
the effects of it will be huge !
think of all the time cost energy that will be used to store and
make sense of such an amount of data
the next era will be yottabytes
ten to the power of 24 and brontobytes ten to the power of 27
which is really hard to imagine for most of us at this time
this is also what we call data at an astronomical scale
the choice of putting the milky way galaxy
in the middle of the circle is not just for aesthetics
this is what we would see if we were to scale up 10 to
the 21 times into the universe
cool is not it
please refer to the reading in this module called
what does astronomical scale mean for a nice video on the powers of ten
all of these point to an exponential growth in data volume and storage
what is the relevance of this much data in our world
remember the planes collecting big data
our hope as passengers is data means better flight safety
the idea is to understand that businesses and organizations are collecting and
leveraging large volumes of data to improve their end products
whether it is safety reliability healthcare or governance
in general in business the goal
is to turn this much data into some form of business advantage
the question is how do we utilize larger volumes of data
to improve our end product quality
despite a number of challenges related to it
there are a number of challenges related to the massive volumes of big data
the most obvious one is of course storage
as the size of the data increases so
does the amount of storage space required to store that data efficiently
however we also need to be able to retrieve that large amount of
data fast enough and
move it to processing units in a timely fashion to get results when we need them
this brings additional challenges such as networking bandwidth
cost of storing data
in - house versus cloud storage and things like that
additional challenges arise during processing of such large data
most existing analytical methods wo not scale to such sums of
data in terms of memory processing or io needs
this means their performance will drop
you might be able to get good performance for data from hundreds of customers
but how about scaling your solution to 1 000 or 10 000 customers
as the volume increases performance and cost start becoming a challenge
businesses need a holistic strategy to handle processing of
large scale data to their benefit in the most cost effective manner
evaluating the options across the dimensions mentioned here
is the first step when it comes to continuously increasing data size
we will revisit this topic later on in this course
as a summary volume is the dimension of big data related to its size and
its exponential growth
the challenges with working with volumes of big data include cost scalability
and performance related to their storage access and processing