let look at a 2nd example where big data can have a big impact on saving lives
i mean literally saving lives one life at a time
i collaborated with a number of world - class researchers in san diego and
an industrial group who are dedicated to improving human health through research
and practice of precision medicine
what is precision medicine
it is an emerging area of medicine targeted toward an individual person
analysing her genetics her environment her daily activities so
that one can detect or predict a health problem early
help prevent disease and in case of illness provide the right drug
at the right dose that is suitable just for her
very recently the white house and the national institute of health here
in the american have declared it to be a top priority area for research and
development for the next decade
the expected learning outcome of this video is for
you to give example of sensor organizational and
people - generated data used in precision medicine
and explain why the integration of different kinds of data is critical
in advancing healthcare
for any technology to succeed in real life we need
not only a certain level of maturity of the technology itself but a number of
enabling factors including social economic environment market demands
consumer readiness cost effectiveness all of which must work together
why is big data for precision medicine important now
let see
an important aspect of precision medicine is to utilize
an individual genetic profile for his or her own diagnoses and treatment
analyzing the human genome
which holds the key to human health is rapidly becoming more affordable
today cost to sequence a genome is less
than 10 of what it cost just back in 2008
but human genomic data is big
how big
in a perfect world just the three billion letters of your genome
would require about 700 megabytes to store
in the real world meaning the kind of data generated from genome sequencing
machines we need 200gb to store a genome
and it takes now about a day to sequence a genome
we are finally beginning to create more electronic records that can be stored and
manipulated in digital media
most doctors offices and hospitals now use electronic health record systems
which contain all details of a patient visit and lab test
how big is this data
as a quick example the samaritan medical center watertown new york at 294 that
community hospital reported 120 terabytes as of 2013
the data value more than double in just the last two years
so clearly just in a past two years dramatic changes have prepared the health
care industry to produce and analyze larger mounts of complex patient data
to summarize what we have seen so far the key components of these changes are :
reduced cost of data generation and analysis increased availability of cheap
large data storage and they increased digitization of previously paper records
but we need one more capability to advance toward the promised land of individualized
health care practices
we need to combine various types of data produce by different groups in
a meaningful way
let look at this issue from the same point of view as ilka did
with her discussion of how big data can help with wildfire analytics
the key is the integration of multiple types of data sources
data from sensors organizations and people
in the next few slides we look at each of these and
then i will share a story about some of the new and really exciting ways people data
especially has the potential to change healthcare big data landscape
let start with sensor data
sure digital hospital equipment have been producing sensor data for
years but it was unlikely that the data was ever stored or
shared let alone analyzed retrospectively
these were intended for
real - time use to inform healthcare professionals and then got discarded
now we have many more sensors and deployment
and many more places that are capturing and
explicitly gathering information to be stored and analyzed
let just take a new kind of data
that increasingly becoming common in our daily lives
fitness devices are everywhere now
their sales have skyrocketed in the last few years
they are in wristbands watches shoes and vests directly communicating with your
personal mobile device tracking several activity variables like blood pressure
different types of activities blood glucose levels etc at every moment
their goal is to improve wellness
by having you monitor your daily status and
hopefully improve your lifestyle to stay healthy
but the data they generate can be very useful medical information
because this data is about what happens in your normal life and
not just when you go to the doctor
how much data do they generate
the device called fitbit can produce several gigabytes a day
could this data be used to save healthcare costs effect a healthier lifestyle
that a question mark
it safe to guess that this data alone would not drive the dream of
precision medicine
but what if we consider integrating it with other sources of data
like electronic health records or a genomic profile
this remains an open question
this is an open arena for research that my colleagues at scripts are doing
it also a potentially significant area for product and business development
let look at some examples of health related data being generated by
organizations
many public databases including those curated and
managed by ncbi the national center for biotechnology information
had been created to capture the basic scientific data and knowledge for
humans and other model organisms at the different building blocks of life
these databases carry both experimental and computed data that are necessary to
observations for unconquered diseases like cancer
in addition many have created knoweledge - bases
like the geneontology and the unified medical language system
to assemble human knowledge in a machine processable form
these are just a few examples of organizational data sources and
governmental data gathered by health care systems around the world
could also be used as a massive source of information
but really some of the most interesting and
novel opportunities seem likely to come from the area of people generated data
mobile healths apps is an area that is growing significantly
there are apps now to monitor heart rates blood pressure and
test oxygen saturation levels
apps we might say record data from sensors but
are also obviously generated from people
but there is more people generated data that interesting beyond censure
measurements
in 2015 the webby people voice award
went to an app which supports meditation and mindfulness
rather than an electronic sensing device
a human would indicate how many minutes per day they spent meditating
if they interact with the app which reminds them to be mindful
then we have human generated behavior that we could not get from a sensor
there are well over 100 000 health apps today in either itunes or google play
and by some estimates the mobile health app market
may be worth 27 billion dollars by 2017
so really we are just seen the beginning of what data might be generated here
from what is being called human sensors but to really understand where the power
of people generated data might take us in the era of big data for healthcare
let imagine how things stand now
in general a patient goes to see their doctor and
maybe their doctor asks if they have had any side effects from their medications
the accuracy and
hence the quality of data patients provide in this kind of setting is very low
not that it really the patients fault
it might have been days or weeks ago that they experienced something
they may be unsure whether something they experienced was actually a reaction
to then report it
and there might be details about exactly when they took a medication that
are meaningful but they have forgotten it after the fact
today people are self reporting reactions and experiences they are having
we are on twitter on blog sites online support groups
online data sharing services : these are sources of data that we have
never had before that can be used to understand in a far more detailed and
personal rate the impact of drug integrations are responses to certain
if applications were designed to integrate doctor and
hospital records with information on when drugs were taken and
then to further mine social media or collect self reports from patients
who knows what kinds of questions we will be able to answer
or new questions we may be able to ask
where does big data come from
the first thing i would like to say before talking about big data
is that it is not new
most of the big data sources existed before but the scale we use and
apply them today has changed
just look at this image of open link data on the internet
i thought this image was so cool
it shows not only there are so many sources of data but
they are also connected
if you want to check it out yourself
we will give you the link at the end of this video
big data is often boiled down to a few varieties of data generated by machines
people and organizations
with machine generated data we refer to data generated from real time sensors in
industrial machinery or vehicles that logs that track user behavior online
environmental sensors or
personal health trackers and many other sense data resources
the large hadron collider generates 40 terabytes of data
every second during experiments
but human generated data we refer to the vast amount of social media data
status updates tweets photos and medias
with organizational generated data we refer to more traditional types of data
including transaction information in databases and
structured data open stored in data warehouses
note that big data can be either structured semi - structured or
unstructured which is a topic we will talk about more later in this course
in most business use cases any single source of data on its own is not useful
real value often comes from combining these streams of big data sources
with each other and analyzing them to generate new insights
which then goes back into being big data themselves
once you have such insights
it then enables what we call data enabled decisions and actions
let now look into these different types of big data in more detail
why is big data generated by machines useful
let go back for a second to our first example for
machine generated big data planes
what is producing all that data on the plane
if you look at some of the sensors that contribute
to the half terabyte of data generated on a plane
we will find that some of it comes from accelerometers that measure turbulence
there are also sensors built into the engines for temperature pressure
many other measurable factors to detect engine malfunctions
constant real - time analysis of all the data collected provides help
monitoring and problem detection at 40 000 feet
that approximately 12 000 meters above ground
we call this type of analytical processing in - situ
previously in traditional relational database management systems
data was often moved to computational space for processing
in big data space in - situ means bringing the computation
to where data is located or in this case generated
a key feature of these types of real - time notifications is
that they enable real - time actions
however using such a capability would require you to approach your
application and your work differently
if you are using an activity tracker you should probably come up with a strategy
for how you will incorporate the usage of these useful gadgets into your lifestyle
just like that if you are planning to incorporate big data driven insights into
your organization you need to define a new strategy and a new way of working
most big data centric businesses have updated their culture to be more real - time
action oriented refining real - time processes to handle anything from customer
relations and fraud detection to system monitoring and control
in addition such volumes of real - time data and analytical operations that need
to take place requires an increased use of scalable computing systems
which need to be a part of the planning for an organizational big data strategy
they see affects of such changes also in scada system
scada stands for supervisory control and data acquisition
scada is a type of industrial control system for remote monitoring and
control of industrial processes that exists in the physical world
potentially including multiple sites many types of sensors
in addition to monitoring and control scada system can be used to define
actions for reduced waste and improved efficiency in industrial processes
including those of manufacturing and power generation public or
private infrastructure processes including water treatment oil and
gas pipelines and electrical power transmission and
facility processes including buildings airports ships and space stations
they can even be used in smart building applications to monitor and
control heating ventilation air conditioning systems like hvac
access and energy consumption
again the management of these processes once the trends patterns and
anomalies are identified in real - time needs to be decided in the big data case
as a summary as the largest and fastest type of big data machine generated
data can uniquely enable real - time actions in many systems and processes
however a culture shift is needed for its computing and real - time action
big data generated by machines
it everywhere and there a lot
do big planes require big data
absolutely !
did you know that a boeing 787 produces
half a terabyte of data every time it flies
really almost every part of the plane updates both the flight and
the ground team about its status constantly
where all this data coming from
this is an example of machine - generated data coming from sensors
if you look at all sources of big data
machine data is the largest source of big data
additionally it is very complex
in general we call machines that provide some type of sensing capability smart
have you ever wondered why you call your cell phone a smartphone
because it gives you a way to track many things
including your geolocation and connect you to other things
so what makes a smart device smart smart
generally speaking there are three main properties of smart devices
based on what they do with sensors and things they encapsulate
they can connect to other devices or
networks they can execute services and collect data autonomously
that means on their own they have some knowledge of the environment
the widespread availability of the smart devices and their interconnectivity
led to a new term being coined the internet of things
think of a world of smart devices at home in your car in the office
city remote rural areas the sky even the ocean
all connected and all generating data
let look at an example of a device that has some of these things in it
an activity tracker is a device or application for monitoring and
tracking fitness - related metrics such as distance walked or run
calorie consumption and in some cases heartbeat and quality of sleep
what if everyone in new york city wore an activity tracker
what if everyone wore several
i personally have three activity trackers that i use on a daily basis
one to track my sleep another one to track my physical activity and
a third my smartphone that goes everywhere with me
so it is not that unusual to imagine that this will be the case for many people
as you have already heard from in a previous lecture on personalized data
such activity trackers have enabled a new way
of doing patient intervention via personalized medicine
similarly the sensors in planes have generated a new way of looking at
fleet management and flight safety
as a summary machines collect data 24 7 via
their built - in sensors both at personal and industrial scales
and thus they are the largest of all the big data sources
organization - generated data
benefits come from combining with other data types
how are some organizations benefiting from big data
let look at real world examples to see the advantages these organizations
are getting out of big data
one of these companies is ups
ups delivers 16 million shipments per day
they get around 40 million tracking requests
that huge
an estimate of how much data ups has on its operations is 16 petabytes
can you guess how much money ups can save by reducing each driver route
by just one mile
if they can reduce distance traveled by each truck by even one mile
ups can save a whopping 50 million american per year
this is where big data steps in
utilizing complex optimization over large datasets
can lead to route optimizations that were previously not visible to the company
big data together with smart processing
enables ups to manage thousands of route optimizations
let travel from package delivery to the retail domain
an organization from the retail shopping domain
that heavily utilizes big data is walmart
walmart is a big organization that gets 250 million customers in 10 000 stores
did you know they collect 2 5 petabytes of data per hour
they collect data on twitter tweets local events local weather
in - store purchases online clicks and
many other sales customer and product related data
they use this data to find patterns such as which products are frequently
purchased together and what is the best new product to introduce in their stores
to predict demand at the particular location
and to customize customer recommendations
overall by leveraging big data and
analytics walmart has maintained its position as a top retailer
ups and walmart examples were just two out of a number of companies using big data
big data is producing results for companies in all sectors
studies forecast spending on big data technologies to go up
drastically in the next five years
a study by bane and company suggests that early adopters of big
data analytics have gained a significant lead over the rest of the corporate world
for graphics referenced here
we see that companies that use analytics are twice as likely
to be in the top quartile of financial performance within their industries
five times as likely to make decisions much faster than market peers
three times as likely to execute decisions as intended
and twice as likely to use data very frequently when making decisions
this points to the growth and demand of people and
technology centered around or specializing in big data applications
as a summary organizations are gaining significant benefit from integrating
big data practices into their culture and breaking their silos
some major benefits to organizations are operational efficiency improved marketing
outcomes higher profits and improved customer satisfaction