step 2 - b : pre - processing data
the raw data that you get directly from your sources are never in the format that
you need to perform analysis on
there are two main goals in the data pre - processing step
the first is to clean the data to address data quality issues and
the second is to transform the raw data to make it suitable for analysis
a very important part of data preparation
is to address quality of issues in your data
real - world data is messy
there are many examples of quality issues with data from real applications including
inconsistent data like a customer with two different addresses duplicate customer
records for example customers address recorded at two different sales locations
and the two recordings do not agree
missing customer agent demographics or studies
missing values like missing a customer age in the demographic studies
invalid data like an invalid zip code for example a six digit code
and outliers like a sense of failure causing values to be much higher or
lower than expected for a period of time
since we get the data downstream
we usually have little control over how the data is collected
preventing data quality problems as the data is being collected is not
often an option
so we have the data that we get and
we have to address quality issues by detecting and correcting them
here are some approaches we can take to address this quality issues
we can remove data records with missing values
we can merge duplicate records
this will require a way to determine how to resolve conflicting values
perhaps it makes sense to retain the newer value whenever there a conflict
for invalid values the best estimate for
a reasonable value can be used as a replacement
for example for a missing age value for an employee
a reasonable value can be estimated based on the employee length of employment
outliers can also be removed if they are not important to the task
in order to address data quality issues effectively
knowledge about the application such as how the data was collected
the user population and the intended uses of the application is important
this domain knowledge is essential to making informed
decisions on how to handle incomplete or incorrect data
the second part of preparing data
is to manipulate the clean data into the format needed for analysis
the step is known by many names
data manipulation data preprocessing data wrangling
and even data munging some operations for
this type of operation i mean data munging wrangling preprocessing
include scaling transformation feature selection
dimensionality reduction and data manipulation
scaling involves changing the range of values to be between a specified range
such as from zero to one
this is done to avoid having certain features that large values from
dominating the results
for example in analyzing data with height and weight
to magnitude of weight values is much greater than of the height values
so scaling all values to be between zero and
one will equalize contributions from both height and weight features
various transformations can be performed on the data to reduce noise and
variability
one such transformation is aggregation
aggregate data generally results in data with less variability
which may help with your analysis
for example daily sales figures may have many serious changes
aggregating values to weekly or monthly sales figures will result in similar data
other filtering techniques can also be used to remove variability in the data
of course this comes at the cost of less detailed data
so these factors must be weighed for the specific application
future selection can involve removing redundant or irrelevant features
combining features and creating new features
during the exploring data step
you might have discovered that two features are correlated
in that case one of these features can be removed
without negatively affecting the analysis results
for example the purchase price of a product and
the amount of sales tax paid are likely to be correlated
eliminating the sales tax amount then will be beneficial
removing redundant or
irrelevant features will make the subsequent analysis much simpler
in other cases you may want to combine features or create new ones
for example adding the applicant education level
as a feature to a loan approval application would make sense
there are also algorithms to automatically determine the most relevant features
based on various mathematical properties
dimensionality reduction is useful when the data set has a large number of
dimensions
it involves finding a smaller subset of dimensions that
captures most of the variation in the data
this reduces the dimensions of the data
while eliminating irrelevant features and makes analysis simpler
a technique commonly used for
dimensional reduction is called principle component analysis or pca
raw data often has to be manipulated to be in the correct format for analysis
for example from samples recording daily changes in stock prices
we may want the capture price changes for
a particular market segments like real estate or health care
this would require determining which stocks belong to which market segment
grouping them together and perhaps computing the mean range
standard deviation for each group
in summary
data preparation is a very important part of the data science process
in fact this is where you will spend most of your time on any data science effort
it can be a tedious process but it is a crucial step
always remember garbage in garbage out
if you do not spend the time and
effort to create good data for the analysis you will not get good results
no matter how sophisticated the analysis technique you are using is
step 3 : analyzing data
now that you have your data nicely prepared
the next step is to analyze the data
data analysis involves building a model from your data
which is called input data
the input data is used by the analysis technique to build a model
what your model generates is the output data
there are different types of problems and
so there are different types of analysis techniques
the main categories of analysis techniques are classification regression
clustering association analysis and graph analysis
we will describe each one
in classification the goal is to predict the category of the input data
an example of this is predicting the weather as being sunny
rainy windy or cloudy in this case
another example is to classify a tumor as either benign or malignant
in this case the classification is referred to as binary classification
since there are only two categories
but you can have many categories as well
as the weather prediction problem shown here having four categories
another example is to identify handwritten digits as
being in one of the ten categories from zero to nine
when your model has to predict a numeric value instead of a category
then the task becomes a regression problem
an example of regression is to predict the price of a stock
the stock price is a numeric value not a category
so this is a regression task instead of a classification task
other examples of regression are estimating the weekly sales of a new
product and predicting the score on a test
in clustering the goal is to organize similar items into groups
an example is grouping a company customer base into distinct segments for
more effective targeted marketing like seniors adults and
teenagers as we see here
another such example is identifying areas of similar topography
like mountains deserts plains for land use application
yet another example is determining different groups of weather patterns
like rainy cold or snowy
the goal in association analysis is to come up with a set
of rules to capture associations within items or events
the rules are used to determine when items or events occur together
a common application of association analysis is known as market
basket analysis which is used to understand customer purchasing behavior
for example association analysis can reveal that banking customers
who have certificate of deposit accounts surety cds also
tend to be interested in other investment vehicles such as money market accounts
this information can be used for cross - selling
if you advertise money market accounts to your customers with cds
they are likely to open such an account
according to data mining folklore a supermarket chain used association
analysis to discover a connection between two seemingly unrelated products
they discovered that many customers who go to the supermarket late on sunday night
to buy diapers also tend to buy beer who are likely to be fathers
this information was then used to place beer and
diapers close together and they saw a jump in sales of both items
this is the famous diaper beer connection
when your data can be transformed into a graph representation with nodes and
links then you want to use graph analytics to analyze your data
this kind of data comes about when you have a lot of entities and
connections between those entities like social networks
some examples where graph analytics can be useful are exploring the spread of
a disease or epidemic by analyzing hospitals and doctors records
identification of security threats by monitoring social media
email and text data
and optimization of mobile communications network traffic
and optimization of mobile telecommunications network traffic
to ensure call quality and reduce dropped calls
modeling starts with selecting one of the techniques we listed
as the appropriate analysis technique depending on the type of problem you have
then you construct the model using the data you have prepared
to validate the model you apply it to new data samples
this is to evaluate how well the model
does on data that was used to construct it
the common practice is to divide the prepared data into a set of data for
constructing the model and reserving some of the data for
evaluating the model after it has been constructed
you can also use new data prepared the same way as with the data that was used to
construct model
evaluating the model depends on the type of analysis techniques you used
let briefly look at how to evaluate each technique
for classification and regression you will have the correct output for
each sample in your input data
comparing the correct output and
the output predicted by the model provides a way to evaluate the model
for clustering the groups resulting from clustering
should be examined to see if they make sense for your application
for example do the customer segments reflect your customer base
are they helpful for use in your targeted marketing campaigns
for association analysis and
graph analysis some investigation will be needed to see if the results are correct
for example network traffic delays
need to be investigated to see what your model predicts is actually happening
and whether the sources of the delays are where they are predicted
to be in the real system
after you have evaluated your model to get a sense of its performance on your data
you will be able to determine the next steps
some questions to consider are should the analysis be
performed with more data in order to get a better model performance
would using different data types help
for example in your clustering results
is it difficult to distinguish customers from distinct regions
would adding zip code to your input data help
to generate finer grained customer segments
do the analysis results suggest a more detailed look at
some aspect of the problem
for example predicting sunny weather gives very good results
but rainy weather predictions are just so - so
this means that you should take a closer look at your examples for rainy weather
perhaps you just need more samples of rainy weather or
perhaps there are some anomalies in those samples
or maybe there are some missing data that needs to be included in order
to completely capture rainy weather
the ideal situation would be that your model platforms very well with respect to
the success criteria that were determined
when you defined the problem at the beginning of the project
in that case you are ready to move on to communicating and
acting on the results that you obtained from your analysis
as a summary data analysis involves selecting the appropriate technique for
your problem building the model then evaluating the results
as there are different types of problems
there are also different types of analysis techniques
step four reporting insights
the fourth step in our data science process is reporting the insights gained
from our analysis
this is a very important step to communicate your insights and
make a case for what actions should follow
it can change shape based on your audience and should not be taken lightly
so how do you get started
the first thing to do is to look at your analysis results and
decide what to present or report as the biggest value or biggest set of values
in deciding what to present you should ask yourself these questions
what is the punchline
in other words what are the main results
what added value do these results provide or
how can the model add to the application
how do the results compare to the success criteria determined at
the beginning of the project
answers to these questions are the items you need to include in your report or
presentation
so make them the main topics and gather facts to back them up
keep in mind that not all of your results may be rosy
your analysis may show results that are counter to what you were hoping to find
or results that are inconclusive or puzzling
you need to show these results as well
domain experts may find some of these results to be puzzling and
inconclusive findings may lead to additional analysis
remember the point of reporting your findings
is to determine what the next step should be
all findings must be presented so that informed decisions can be made
visualization is an important tool in presenting your results
the techniques that we discuss and explore in data can be used here as well
what were they
scatter plots line graphs heat maps and other types of graphs
are effective ways to present your results visually
this time you are not plotting the input data but
you are plotting the output data with similar tools
you should also have tables with details from your analysis as backups
if someone wants to take a deeper dive into the results
there are many visualization tools that are available
some of the most popular open source ones are listed here
r is a software package for general data analysis
it has powerful visualization capabilities as well
python is a general purpose programming language
that also has a number of packages to support data analysis and graphics
d3 is a javascript library for
producing interactive web based visualizations and data driven documents
leaflet is a lightweight mobile friendly javascript library
to create interactive maps
tableau public allows you to create visualizations
in your public profile and share them or put them on a site or blog
google charts provides cross - browser compatibility
and closed platform portability to iphones and android
timeline is a javascript library that allows you to create timelines
in summary you want to report your findings by presenting your results and
value add with graphs using visualization tools
step 5 act turning insights into action
now that you have evaluated the results from your analysis and
generated reports on the potential value of the results the next step is to
determine what action or actions should be taken based on the insights gained
remember why we started bringing together the data and
analyzing it in the first place
to find actionable insights within all these data sets
to answer questions or for improving business processes
for example
is there something in your process that should change to remove bottle necks
is there data that should be added to your application to make it more accurate
should you segment your population into more well defined groups for
more effective targeted marketing
this is the first step in turning insights into action
now that you have determined what action to take
the next step is figuring out how to implement the action
what is necessary to add this action into your process or application
how should it be automated
the stakeholders need to be identified and become involved in this change
just as with any process improvement changes we need to monitor and
measure the impact of the action on the process or application
assessing the impact leads to an evaluation
evaluating results from the implemented action will determine your next steps
is there additional analysis that need to be performed in order to yield
even better results
what data should be revisited
are there additional opportunities that should be explored
for example let not forget what big data enables us to do
real - time actions based on high velocity streaming information
we need to define what part of our business needs real - time action to be
able to influence the operations or the interaction with the customer
once we define these real time actions we need to make sure that
there are automated systems or processes to perform such actions and
provide failure recovery in case of problems
as a summary big data and
data science are only useful if the insights can be turned into action
and if the actions are carefully defined and evaluated
steps in the data science process
we have already seen a simple linear form of data science process
including five distinct activities that depend on each other
let summarize each activity further before we go into the details of each
acquire includes anything that makes us retrieve data including; finding
accessing acquiring and moving data
it includes identification of and authenticated access to all related data
and transportation of data from sources to distributed files systems
it includes way to subset and match the data to regions or times of interest
as we sometimes refer to it as geo - spacial query
the next activity is prepare data we divide the pre - data activity
into two steps based on the nature of the activity
namely explore data and pre - process data
the first step in data preparation involves literally looking
at the data to understand its nature what it means its quality and format
it often takes a preliminary analysis of data or
samples of data to understand it
this is why this step is called explore
once we know more about the data through exploratory analysis
the next step is pre - processing of data for analysis
pre - processing includes cleaning data sub - setting or
filtering data creating data which programs can read and
understand such as modeling raw data into a more defined data model
or packaging it using a specific data format
if there are multiple data sets involved
this step also includes integration of multiple data sources or streams
the prepared data then would be passed onto the analysis step
which involves selection of analytical techniques to use
building a model of the data and analyzing results
this step can take a couple of iterations on its own or
might require data scientists to go back to steps one and
two to get more data or package data in a different way
step four for communicating results includes evaluation of analytical results
presenting them in a visual way creating reports that include
an assessment of results with respect to success criteria
activities in this step can often be referred to with terms like interpret
summarize visualize or post process
the last step brings us back to the very first reason we do data science
the purpose
reporting insights from analysis and determining actions from insights based
on the purpose you initially defined is what we refer to as the act step
we have now seen all the steps in a typical data science process
please note that this is an iterative process and findings from one step
may require the previous step to be repeated with new information