there are many ways of looking at scalability
and we will consider them as we go forward in the course
one way is to consider scaling up and scaling out
simply put it is a decision between making a machine
that makes a server more powerful versus adding more machines
the first choice will involve adding more memory
replacing processes with process of more course and
adding more processes within a system with a very fast internet connection speed
the second choice will involve adding more machines to a relatively slower network
now there are no absolutes here
in many cases we will choose the former to get more performance for
large leader systems
the general trend in the big data world
however is to target the scale out option
most big data management systems today
are designed to operate over a cluster up machines and
have the ability to adjust as more machines are added and when machines fail
cluster management and management of data operations over a cluster
is an important component in today big data management systems
now we will briefly touch upon the complex issue of data security
it is obvious that having more sensitive data implies the need for more security
if the data is within the walls of an organization
we will still need a security plan
however if a big data system is deployed in the cloud
over multiple machines security of data becomes an even bigger challenge
so now we need to ensure the security for not only the machines
but also the network which will be heavily used during data transfer
across different phases of data operations
for example if the data store and the data analysis are performed over
different sets of servers that every analysis operation gets to
an additional overhead of encrypting the data as the data gets to the network and
decrypting when it gets to the processing server
this effectively increases operational cost
as of today while there are many security products the methods for
ensuring security and achieving data processing efficiency at the same time
remains a research issue in big data management
now the goal of a storage infrastructure obviously is to store data
there are two storage related issues we consider here
the first is the issue of capacity
how much storage should we allocate
that means what should be the size of the memory how large and
how many disk units should we have and so forth
there is also the issue of scalability
should the storage devices be attached directly to the computers
to make the direct io fast but less scalable
or should the storage be attached to the network
that connect the computers in the cluster
this will make disk access a bit slower but
allows one to add more storage to the system easily
now these questions do not have a simple answer
if you are interested you may look up a website given on your reading list
a different class of questions deals with the speed of the iu operation
this question is often addressed with this kind of diagram here called a memory
hierarchy or storage hierarchy or sometimes memory storage hierarchy
the top of the pyramid structure shows a part of memory called cache memory
that lives inside the cpu and is very fast
there are different levels of cache called l1 l2 l3
where l3 is the slowest but still faster than what we call memory
shown here in orange near the middle
the figure shows their speed in terms of response times
notice the memory streamed here is 65 nanoseconds per access
in contrast
the speed of the traditional hard disk is of the order of 10 milliseconds
this gap has prompted the design of many data structures and
algorithms that use a hard disk but tries to minimize the cost of
the io operations between the fast memory and the slower disk
but more recently a newer kind of storage
very similar to the flash drives or
usbs that we regularly use have made an entry as a new storage medium
these devices are called ssds or solid state devices
they are much faster than spinning hard disks
an even newer addition is the method called nvme
nvm stands for non - volatile memory
that makes data transfer between ssds and memory much faster
what all this means in a big data system is that now we have the choice of
architecting a storage infrastructure by choosing how much of each type of
storage we need to have
in my own research with large amounts of data i have found that using ssds
speed up all look up operations in data by at least a factor of ten over hard drives
of course the flip side of this is the cost factor
the components become increasingly more expensive as we go from the lower layers
of the pyramid to the upper layers
so ultimately it becomes an issue of cost - benefit tradeoff
sound let us consider a real life application to
demonstrate the utility and the challenges of big data
many industries naturally deal with large amounts of data
for our discussion we consider an energy company that provides gas and
electricity to its consumers in an urban area
in this news report you can see that commonwealth edison or con ed
the gas and electric provider of new york
decided to place smart meters all through its jurisdictions
that comes to 4 7 million smart meters
now smart meters are smart because aside from measuring energy consumption
they have a two way communication capability between the meter and
the central system at the gas and electric company
in other words they generate real time data from the meters to be stored and
processed at the central facility
how much data
according to this report
the number of data received at the center is 1 5 billion per day
so the system will not only consume this data but process it and
produce output at 15 - minute intervals and sometimes 5 minute intervals
let do the math
that comes to ingesting and processing
about 10 5 million data points per 15 minutes
so what kind of computation must take place within these 15 minutes
well one obvious computation is billing where one needs to compute who especially
in the commercial sector who actually owns the meter and should be billed
this requires combining the meter data
with the data in the customer database maintained by the company
but let just consider computation related to analytics
we can list at least four different kinds of computations
the first is computing the consumption pattern per user not per meter
per user where the output is a histogram of hourly usage
so the x axis of the histogram is hourly intervals and
the y - axis is a number of units consumed
this leads to the computed both daily and over larger time periods
to determine the hourly requirements for this consumer
the second computation relates to estimating the effects of
outdoor temperature on the electricity consumption of each consumer
for those you who are statistically inclined
this often involves fitting a piece - wise linear progression model to the data
the third task is to extract the daily consumption trends that occur
regardless of the outdoor temperature
this is again a statistical computation and may require something like
a periodic alter regression algorithm for time series theta
the algorithm is not that important there
what is more important is the ability to make make good prediction has a direct
economic impact because the company needs to buy energy from others
for example an under - prediction implies they will end up paying more for
buying energy at the last moment to meet the consumer requirements
the fourth task is to find groups of similar consumers based on their usage
pattern so that the company can determine how many distinct groups of customers
there are and design targeted energy saving campaigns for each group
this requires finding similarities over large number of time series data
which is a complex computation
regardless of the number and complexity of computation required
the company constrained by the fact that it has only 15 minutes to process the data
before the next and computation has to be performed
that issue is not just the bigness of the data but
the strip and strings of the arrival to output time
the analytics has value only if it can be completed within the life - cycle deadline
so if we were to design a big data system for such a company you would need to
understand how much are the computation can be executed in parallel and
how many machines with what kind of capability are required to handle the data
rate and the number and complexity of the analytical computations needed
hi my name is chad berkley
i am the cto of flightstats and i am here today to talk to you a little bit about
our platform and how we acquire and process data
but first of all i would like to start by just kind of introducing the company and
telling you a little bit about what we are all about
so flightstats is a data company and
we basically are the leading provider of global real - time flight status data
we pull in data from over 500 sources and we aggregate that data back together and
we sell it out to our customers which our other businesses as well as consumers
so just to give you a little bit of information about the scope and
scale of what we do
like i said we have over 500 sources of data
and on a daily basis we process about 15 million flight events
those that includes landings arrivals departures
any time the status of the flight changes we got some sort of message on that
we process about 260 million aircraft positions per day so we have an extensive
network that monitors graph positions for realtime flight tracking applications
and we also handle about one million pnrs or passenger name records
which are the actual data type of an itenerary any time you
book travel a pnr is created for you for your travel
and it includes all of the segments like air travel ferries
hotels taxis anyhting that can be scheduled on your trip
and we basically take in all that data and
we aggregate it together and we sell it back out
and how most people kind of know us for flightstats com that our
consumer site for business where we handle about 2 million daily requests
and we handle about 1 million mobile app requests
that our b to b side we cert out a lot of data by apis and real time data feeds
people make about 15 million api requests to us everyday
and we also send out about one and half million flight and trip notifications
so if you get a push notification to your phone
telling you that your flight is delayed or on time
that possibly has come from us
so a little bit about how the data flows through our company
we bring in all these different types of data and
our sources and it flows through our data acquisition team
we have a team whose primary purpose is to pull in all sorts of raw data
a very heterogeneous datasets
and process that into a normalized form
so if you kind of follow the blue arrow in this diagram you can see that it goes
through this raw data channel through the data hub
which the data hub is a central component of our system that i will talk
a little bit more about in a second
so the blue data the blue line is raw data coming in from the source
it goes through our data acquisition system
it turns into that purple line which is a normalized form
it then goes back through our data hub again and into our processing engine
our processing engine is really where most of the business logic happens
the first thing we have to do is we have to match any piece of
flight information against a flight that we know about and
primarily the way we know about flights is through schedules
so we import schedules on a daily basis from one of our partner
schedule providers
that data once it matched is then processed and
the processing basically looks at each message and tries to determine if
we think that that message needs to be passed on to consumers
so you know it looks at things like have we seen that message before
or is it a duplicate
is it from a data source that we trust
are there other things going on that we need to know about that
may impact whether that message is true or not
and once we decide that a message should be passed through
if you follow the green line
it goes into our process data channel on our hub and
it then pushed out to a couple different places
so first of all
it goes into our production database which is where all of our real time data lives
that database serves data to our websites
to our mobile apps and a variety of other places
it also goes into our data warehouse which
is where our analytics products use it
i will talk a bit more about that in a minute
and then the stream of data actually goes up to so many of our customers
we do not need a database on our side
they would rather build a database on their side so
we actually just stream all of the processed data directly to them
they then host it within their own systems
so a little bit more about the hub the hub is central to how we move data around
it a technology that we developed in - house
and it an object storage based scalable highly available
multi - channel data queuing and eventing system
the object storage part is we use amazon s3 to store this data
so it an object storage system
it scalable we can scale it horizontally or
vertically depending on but the what type of data is flowing through it
it highly available meaning
that we have multiple instances of it in different data centers
so if one that goes down we can easily pull another one up or
it we are going to cross multiple instances
and then it multi channel
so it got a rest interface and any surface can create
a new channel within the system and start posting data to it
that data is then queued based on the time that it comes in and
other services can be listening for events on those channels
so as soon as a new piece of data comes into one of those channels
any service that listening on that channel gets an event notification
they that service can then act upon that piece of data
and do whatever processing it may need to do
this project is open source and anybody can download it and use it
so a little bit about some of the data that we collect and aggregate
and flifo is kind of the industry term for flight information
and primarily we look at kind of the five different parts of flight
so we pull in information on gate departure and then that becomes a runway
departure basically when the wheels go up that is a runway departure
we do in - flight positional tracking so when your flight is moving along
about once every ten seconds we get notified of its latitude and longitude
and its heading and its speed and
its vertical center descent rate and several other variables
then once it lands
as soon as the wheels touch the ground we are notified of a runway arrival and
when the door is opened at the gate we have gate arrival information
all five of these data fields come in three different forms
so we have a scheduled scheduled departure and arrival
we have estimated departure and arrival which can come from a variety of sources
either airlines airports positional data et cetera
and then we have actuals so if we have an airport or
an airline that sending us data about exactly when the wheels touch down or
exactly when that door opens on that aircraft we push that data as well
we also generate some data at flight stops
so special incidents if an aircraft has an issue it in the news
we do flag our content with a message from our support staff
we do some prediction
right now we are just starting to get into that market or we are actually trying to
predict 24 hours out whether a flight will be delayed disrupted or on time
we do some synthetic positions so over oceans primarily
we do not get tracking data on aircraft over the oceans
there is currently no satellite - based tracking system for aircraft
so we basically take the last known position a heading a speed
and if we have a flight plan we will use a flight plan to synthesize the positions
when we are not getting actual positions over large bodies of water
we also generate notifications so the push alerts
the preflight emails delay notifications those types of things
we create those based on what we see in the data that coming in to us
we store all of our historical data in a data warehouse
so right now we have six years of historical flight data
and that powers our analytics products
so we allow airlines to do competitive analysis and route analysis
routes are very important to airlines
that how they compete with each other and
that primarily how they are judged by the faa and
other governmental organizations on whether they are on - time or not
we also do airport operations analysis things like taxi in and taxi out times
very important for lots of airports runway utilization
hourly passenger flows through airports that type of information
and we do on - time performance metrics so
airlines can look at how they are doing
how many flights did they complete
how many flights were on time within 14 minutes
and they can compare themselves to their competitors
so we host all of this in a hybrid cloud architecture
hybrid cloud basically means that we have our own private datacenter resources and
we also host resources in the amazon web services cloud
most of our core data processing and service layer is in our private data
center and we are getting ready to spin up a second private data center as well
right now our main data center is in portland oregon and we are going to spin
another one up on the east coast of the united states probably in q2 or q3
for our api we try to keep those close to our customers so
api end points and web end points live in amazon
and they are automatically routed to whichever end point is closest to you
you will automatically be routed to them
all of our private infrastructure is virtualized with vmware
we pretty much have a fully virtualized environment
and we are an agile shop so we have six small fast teams
those are product centric teams we allow them to be as customer interactive
as they need to be and we try to make our teams semi autonomous
so teams get to choose their own tools they get to choose their
own development methodologies they choose a variety of things
and we physically allow them
to do what they need to do to get their job done as quickly as possible
we try to automate everything
you do something once manually and then the next time you write a script or
program to do it
and we also measure everything
right now we are taking in about 2 5 billion metrics per month off
of our systems
and we use those metrics to monitor our application performance
to monitor revenue to monitor pretty much everything we do in the company
we really try to enable total system awareness
everything from the hardware layer up to the website is monitored
and we use industry best practices and tools and of course we try to recruit and
hire the best talent possible a little bit about our software stock
we are primarily a java shop
our core processing services are all written in java
we do use node js in our microservice edge layer
and node js is actually starting to move more down into the processing service
layer as well
we use many different types of data bases
our primary realtime database is post press
and we use mongo for the backend of our api services
on the website we are all html5 and we are moving to react and redux and
we are making use of elasticsearch for quick searching and indexing on our data
and of course we have ios and android mobile applications
so you can find out more about flightstats on our website
if you need data for your applications
please go to the developer center at developer flightstats com
you can sign up for a free test account and
be able to pull data directly off of our apis
if you are interested in the hub like i said that open source
please check out the git hub page and if you have any additional questions
feel free to contact myself john berkeley and
i would be happy to answer any of your questions via email
thanks for listening today and hope you have a great day
bye
different data sources in the game industry include using your finger
what type of device is coming from
the amount of headsets
it pretty much infinite
as far as the number of ways we can bring data in from the game
and it could be joystick or mouse keyboards there lots of ways
as well as what happens inside the game itself as far cars or
the driving tires flying machines anything
the volume of data it really depends on the type of game and
how often they want to send the data in
how many types of events they have tagged and how many users are playing the game
so if you have a user you have 5 million users that are playing your game and
you are tapping and you are tracking each tap of the screen
of where they went or each click of the mouse as they were using it
you are going to get a lot of volume of data
and so you need to be prepared to bring in a lot
of different data very very quickly
as far as the variety of data it depends
you have round pizzas and you have round tires
i mean they are completely different
they are both round but there different ways that you are going to want to know how
many pepperoni are on one pizza and how many lug nuts go on a tire
so the variety is really unlimited as well
it really just depends on each game
so you have to be prepared to bring in all kinds of data
touch data wheel data track speeds anything
and if you put taxonomy together that you can define as an example of verb
object location value and any number of other sources then you can basically
track anything you want as long as they all fall into the same kind of buckets
and the buckets can be different sizes based on the type of events
they do not all need to be 4 some can be 2 some can be 20
it does not really matter
the modeling challenge has really come down to who designs the structure at which
you store your data and how you want to retrieve that data
those kind of of storage and retrieval models are very very important
because what it really comes down to is speed
you can record a lot of data and it can take you five years to query it
it does not really do you any good
so you need to make sure you plan for reporting speed because that ultimately
what within the organisation needs is the ability to report on it very quickly
the management challenges really come down to trying to figure out what data to
store
a lot of times we go into various companies and you have got producers sitting
across the hall from designers and they do not even know each other
they do not realize what they want and the programmer says
i am going to put these events in and the product manager who wants to figure out
how many times somebody crashed says well i need these events in
so unless they are communicating you are going to get the wrong type of data
so the management challenge is trying to make sure everybody communicates
they decide on the taxonomy and the structure and
then we can go forward with tagging and getting in the entire game working
we process stayed in two main ways
one is streaming data
one is batched or scheduled data
streaming data has scripts that run instantly the minute the data arrives
and so as the data come in it gets processed and
then stored in a reporting format
so they can easily generate reports up to the second very very quickly
batch processing data really depends on the type of data where it coming from
most of the time when we download data from itunes or youtube or
something like that it comes in a csv or a very similar format
there not really a lot of processing we need to do
it more of ingesting that data
there are processes we need to run with some type of batch data but
most of the batch data we receive comes in as a csv or
other similar already processed formats
so typically while you can do processing in both modes most processing typically
happens with the streaming real - time data than it does with offline batch data
we actually did not use any technology in the a big data space
we created our own from scratch
what we did was we decided what kind of model we wanted
how we were going to store data
how we were going to retrieve data
and ultimately how we were going to reduce the data
because the more and more and more data you have the slower it is to actually do
a query because you have to look through all the different pieces of data
a lot of databases solve this problem for you but they were really doing it in more
generic way were we needed something very specific
so we started from scratch building our own data storage and retrieval and
reporting from the ground up
when it came to scalability it was really about designing the parts of
the system that could be independently scaled
so if data coming in in real - time we send that into what we call a gateway
and the gateway could be three gateways let say
but if the data starts getting over loaded
i just have to add another gateway
and a gateway is just this little light layer that just receives data
passes it on and goes back to it job does not do anything else
so it can receive a lot of data very quickly but
also i can just add another one
and it just automatically logs in and adds itself to a list and
now the data is being distributed amongst four gateways instead
query engine is the same way
when you are doing queries to try to get data out of the system so
you can build reports
if i need more query engines because people are doing more reporting
we can add more query engines
so the idea behind scalability is trying to break the services up into
the type of services that they most make sense
so that if you need to
you can add just the service without rebuilding the entire platform
my advice for people designing systems for big data is to first
try to understand what you want to accomplish
what is the goal
i mean we are going to ingest everything and we are going to report on everything
it not really something that you can achieve without some special thought
if you are going to focus on your area going to be say gardening
then look at what kind of things you are going to do in the gardening area and
try to focus on what that type of data is going to be
this is not going to restrict you to only being a gardener but
it is going to give you focus on how to design your system so
that they are actually going to work for you
you are going to continually evolve your systems add more things to them and
grow them
i would not suggest starting with an unlimited variety of options and
hoping you are going to solve all the problems
start with the goal of what your current solution is and expand from there
data can be fun but it can also be overwhelming
so try to keep the data in mind without keeping the world in mind and
i think you will be just fine