getting started
why hadoop
we have all heard that hadoop and
related projects in this ecosystem are great for big data
this module will answer the four ws and an h about why this statement is true
before we dive further into the details of hadoop
let take a moment to analyze the characteristics of the hadoop ecosystem
what is in the ecosystem
why is it beneficial
where is it used
who uses it
and how do these tools work
the hadoop ecosystem frameworks and applications that we will describe in this
module have several overarching themes and goals
first they provide scalability to store large volumes of data
on commodity hardware
as the number of systems increases so does the chance for crashes and
hardware failures
a second goal supported by most frameworks in the hadoop ecosystem
is the ability to gracefully recover from these problems
in addition as we have mentioned before big data comes in
a variety of flavors such as text files graph of social networks
streaming sensor data and raster images
a third goal for the hadoop ecosystem then
is the ability to handle these different data types for any given type of data
you can find several projects in the ecosystem that support it
a fourth goal of the hadoop ecosystem
is the ability to facilitate a shared environment
since even modest - sized clusters can have many cores
it is important to allow multiple jobs to execute simultaneously
why buy servers only to let them sit idle
another goal of the hadoop ecosystem is providing value for your enterprise
the ecosystem includes a wide range of open source projects
backed by a large active community
these projects are free to use and easy to find support for
in the following lectures in this module
we will take a more detailed look at the hadoop ecosystem
first we will explore the kinds of projects available and
the types of capabilities they provide
next we will take a deeper look at the three main parts of hadoop
the hadoop distributed file system or hdfs
yarn the scheduler and resource manager
and mapreduce a programming model for processing big data
we will then discuss cloud computing and the types of service models it provides
we will also describe situations in which hadoop is not the best solution
this module then concludes with two readings involving hands - on
experience with hdfs and mapreduce
so let get started
mapreduce simple programming for big results
mapreduce is a programming model for the hadoop ecosystem
it relies on yarn to schedule and
execute parallel processing over the distributed file blocks in hdfs
there are several tools that use the mapreduce model to provide a higher level
interface to other programming models
hive has a sql - like interface that adds capabilities that help with
relational data modeling
and pig is a high level data flow language
that adds capabilities that help with process map modeling
traditional parallel programming requires expertise on a number of computing and
systems concepts
for example synchronization mechanisms like locks semaphores
and monitors are essential
and incorrectly using them can either crash your program or
severely impact performance
this high learning curve makes it difficult
it is also error prone since your code can run on hundreds or
thousands of nodes each having many cores
and any problem related to these parallel processes
needs to be handled by your parallel program
the mapreduce programming model greatly simplifies running code in parallel
since you do not have to deal with any of these issues
instead you only need to create and map and reduce tasks and you do not
have to worry about multiple threads synchronization or concurrency issues
so what is a map and reduce
map and reduce are two concepts based on functional programming
where the output the function is based solely on the input
just like in a mathematical function f x = y y depends on x
you provide a function or operation for a map and reduce
and the runtime executes it over the data
for map the operation is applied on each data element
and in reduce the operation summarizes elements in some manner
an example using map and reduce will make this concepts more clear
hello word is a traditional first program you code
when you start to learning programming languages
the first program to learn or hello word of map reduce is often wordcount
wordcount reads one or more text files and
counts the number of occurrences of each word in these files
the output will be a text file with a list of words and
their occurrence frequencies in the input data
let examine each step of wordcount
for simplification we are assuming we have one big file as an input
before wordcount runs the input file is stored in hdfs
as you know now
hdfs partitions the blocks across multiple nodes in the cluster
in this case four partitions labeled a b c and d
the first step in mapreduce is to run a map operation on each node
as the input partitions are read from htfs map is called for
each line in the input
let look at the first lines of the input partitions a and
b and start counting the words
the first line in the partition on node a
says my apple is red and my rose is blue
similarly the first line on partition b says you are the apple of my eye
let now see what happens in the first map node for partition a
map creates a key value for
each word on the line containing the word as the key and 1 as the value
in this example the word apple is read from the line in partition a
map produces a key value of apple 1
similarly the word my is seen on the first line of a twice
so the key values of my 1 are created
note that map goes to each node containing a data block for
the file instead of the data moving to map
this is moving computation to data
let now see what the same map operation generates for partition b
since each word only happens to occur once
a list of all the words with one key - value pairing each gets generated
please take a moment to observe the outputs of map and
each key - value pair associated to a word
next all the key - values that were output from map are sorted based on their key
and the key values with the same word are moved or shuffled to the same node
to simplify this figure each node only has a single word in orange boxes
but in general a node will have many different words
just like our example from the two lines in a and b partitions
here we see that you and apple are assigned to the first node
the word is to the second node
and the words rose and red to the third
although for simplicity we drew four map nodes and three shuffle nodes
the number of nodes can be extended as much as the application demands
next the reduce operation executes on these nodes to
add values for key - value pairs with the same keys
for example apple 1 and
another apple 1 becomes apple 2
the result of reduce is a single key pair for
each word that was read in the input file
the key is the word and the value is the number of occurrences
if we look back at our wordcount example
we see that there were three distinct steps
namely the map step the shuffle and sort step and the reduce step
although the wordcount example is pretty simple
it represents a large number of applications to which these three steps
can be applied in order to achieve data parallel scalability
for example now that you have seen the wordcount application
consider changing the wordcount algorithm to index all
the urls by words after a web crawl
this means instead of pointing to a number the keys would refer to urls
after the map with this new function which by the way is called a user
defined function the output of shuffle and sort would look like this
now when we reduce the urls all the urls that mention apple would look like this
this is in fact one of the ways a search engine like google works
so now if somebody came to the interface built for this application
to search for the word apple and entered apple
it would be easy to get all the urls as the word itself
no wonder the first mapreduce paper was produced by google
we will give you a link to the original google paper on mapreduce from
2004 at the end of this lecture
it is pretty technical but
it gives you a simple overview without the current system implementations
we just saw how mapreduce can be used in search engines
in addition to counting the words and documents
although it possible to add many more applications let stop here for
a general discussion on how the points of
data parallelism can be used in search in this three step pattern
there is definitely parallelization during the map step
this parallelization is over the input
as each partition gets processed one line at a time
to achieve this type of data parallelism we must decide on
the data granularity of each parallel competition
in this case it will be a line
we also see parallel grouping of data in the shuffle and sort phase
this time the parallelization is over the intermediate products
that is the individual key - value pairs
and after the grouping of the intermediate products
the reduce step gets parallelized to construct one output file
you have probably noticed that the data gets reduced
to a smaller set at each step
this overview gave us an idea of what kinds of tasks that mapreduce is good for
while mapreduce excels at independent batch tasks similar to our applications
there are certain kinds of tasks that you would not want to use mapreduce for
for example if your data is frequently changing
mapreduce is slow since it reads the entire input data set each time
the mapreduce model requires that maps and
reduces execute independently of each other
this greatly simplifies your job as a designer
since you do not have to deal with synchronization issues
however it means that computations that do have dependencies
cannot be expressed with mapreduce
finally mapreduce does not return any results
until the entire process is finished
it must read the entire input data set
this makes it unsuitable for interactive applications where the results must be
presented to the user very quickly expecting a return from the user
as a summary mapreduce hides complexities of parallel programming and
greatly simplifies building parallel applications
many types of tasks suitable for
mapreduce include search engine page ranking and topic mapping
please see the reading after this lecture on making pasta sauce
with mapreduce for another fun application using the mapreduce programming model
programming models for big data
we have seen that scalable computing over the internet to achieve
data - parallel scalability for big data applications is now a possibility
thanks to commodity clusters
cost - effective commodity clusters together with advances in distributed
file systems to move computation to data
provide a potential to conduct scalable big data analytics
the next thing we will talk about is how to take
advantage of these infrastructure advances
what are the right programming models
a programming model is an abstraction or existing machinery or infrastructure
it is a set of abstract runtime libraries and
programming languages that form a model of computation
this abstraction level can be low - level as in machine language in computers
or very high as in high - level programming languages for example java
so we can say if the enabling infrastructure for
big data analysis is distributed file systems as we mentioned
then the programming model for big data should enable the programmability
of the operations within distributed file systems
what we mean by this being able to write computer programs that work
efficiently on top of distributed file systems using big data and
making it easy to cope with all the potential issues
based on everything we discussed so
far let describe the requirements for big data programming models
first of all such a programming model for big data should support
common big data operations like splitting large volumes of data
this means for partitioning and placement of data in and
out of computer memory along with a model to synchronize the datasets later on
the access to data should be achieved in a fast way
it should allow fast distribution to nodes within a rack and these are potentially
the data nodes we moved the computation to
this means scheduling of many parallel tasks at once
it should also enable reliability of the computing and
full tolerance from failures
this means it should enable programmable replications and
recovery of files when needed
it should be easily scalable to the distributed notes where the data gets
produced
it should also enable adding new resources to take advantage of distributive
computers and scale to more or faster data without losing performance
this is called scaling out if needed
since there are a variety of different types of data
such as documents graphs tables key values etc
a programming model should enable operations over a particular set
of these types
not every type of data may be supported by a particular model but
the models should be optimized for at least one type
is it getting a little complicated
it does not have to have to be
in fact we apply similar models in our daily lives for everyday tasks
let look at the scenario where you might unknowingly apply this model
imagine a peaceful saturday afternoon
you receive a phone call from a friend and she says
she they will be at your house in an hour for dinner
it seems like you completely forgot that you had invited your friends for dinner
so you say you are looking forward to it and head to the kitchen
as a quick solution you decide to cook pasta with some tomato sauce
you need to take advantage of parallelization so
that the dinner is ready by the time your guest arrive that within an hour
you call your spouse and your teenage kids to action in the kitchen
now you need to give them directions to start dicing the ingredients for you
but in the heat of the moment you end up mixing the onions tomatoes and peppers
instead of sorting them first
you give everyone a randomly mixed batch of different types of vegetables
they are required to use their computer powers to chop the vegetables
they need to ensure not mix different types of veggies
when everyone is done chopping you want to group the veggies by their types
you ask each helper to collect items of the same type put them in a large
bowl and label this large bowl with the sum of individual bowl weights
like tomatoes in one bowl peppers in another and the onions in the third bowl
in the end
you have nice large bowls with the total weight of each vegetable labeled on it
your helpers are soon done with their work while you are focused on coordinating their
actions and other dinner tasks in the kitchen you can start cooking your pasta
what you have just seen is an excellent example of big data modeling in action
only it is really the data processed by human processors
this scenario can be modeled by a common programming model for big data
namely mapreduce
mapreduce is a big data programming model that supports all
the requirements of big data modeling we mentioned
it can model processing large data
split complications into different parallel tasks and
make efficient use of large commodity clusters and distributed file systems
in addition it abstracts out the details of parallelzation
full tolerance data distribution monitoring and load balancing
as a programming model
it has been implemented in a few different big data frameworks
next week we will see more details on mapreduce and
how its hadoop implementation works
to summarize programming models for
big data are abstractions over distributed file systems
the desired programming models for big data should handle large volumes and
varieties of data
support full tolerance and provide scale out functionality
mapreduce is one of these models
implemented in a variety of frameworks including hadoop
we will summarize the inner workings of the hadoop implementation next week
in this lecture we will use hadoop to run wordcount
first we will open a terminal shell and
explore the hadoop - provided mapreduce programs
next we will verify the input file exists in hdfs
we will then run wordcount and explore the wordcount output directory
after that we will copy the wordcount results
from hdfs to the local file system and view them
let begin
first we will open a terminal shell by
clicking on the icon at top of the window here
next we will look at the map produced programs that come with hadoop
we can do this by running hadoop jars user jars hadoop examples jar
this command says we are going to use the jar command to run a program
in hadoop from a jar file
and the jar file that we are running from is in usr jars hadoop - examples jar
many programs written in java are distributed via jar files
if we run this command we will see a list of different programs that come with hadoop
so for example wordcount
count the words in a text file
wordmean count the average length of words
and other programs such as sorting and calculating the length of pi
in the previous lecture we downloaded the works of shakespeare and
saved it into hdfs
let make sure that file is still there by running hadoop fs - ls
we can see that the file is still there and it called words txt
we can run wordcount by running hadoop jar
usr jars hadoop - examples jar wordcount
this command says that we are going to run a jar
and this is the name of the jar containing the program
and the program we are going to run is wordcount
when we run it we see that it prints the command line usage for
how to run wordcount
this says that wordcount takes one or more input files and an output name
now both the input and the output are located in hdfs
so we have the input file that we just listed words txt in hdfs
we can run wordcount
so we will run hadoop jar usr jars hadoop - examples jar
wordcount words txt out
this is saying we are going to run the wordcount program using words txt
as the input and put the output in a directory called out
so we will run it
as wordcount is running your prints progress to the screen
it will print the percentage of map and reduce completed
and when both of these reach 100 then the job is done
now that the job is complete let look at the results
we can run hadoop fs - ls to see the output
this shows that out was created and this is where our results are stored
notice that it a directory with a d here
so hadoop word count created the directory to contain the output
let look inside that directory by running hadoop fs - ls out
blank audio we can see that there are two files in this directory
the first is success this means that the wordcount job completed successfully
the other file part - r - 00000 is a text file
containing the output from the wordcount command
now let copy this text file to the local file system from hdfs and then view it
we could copy it by running hadoop fs - copytolocal
out part - r - 00000 local
and we will say local txt is the name
you can view the results of this
we are running more local txt
this will view the contents of the file
we can hit spacebar to scroll down
we see the results of wordcount in this file
each line is a particular word and the second column is the count
of how many words of this particular word was found in the input file
you can hit q to quit
scalable computing over the internet
most computing is done on a single compute node
if the computation needs more than a node or parallel processing
like many scientific computing problems we use parallel computers
simply put a parallel computer is a very large number of
single computing nodes with specialized capabilities connected to other network
for example the gordon supercomputer here at the san diego supercomputer center
has 1 024 compute nodes with 16 cores each equalling 16 384 compute cores in total
this type of specialized computer is pretty costly
compared to its most recent cousin the commodity cluster
the term commodity cluster is often heard in big data conversations
have you ever wondered what it exactly means
commodity clusters are affordable parallel computers
with an average number of computing nodes
they are not as powerful as traditional parallel computers and
are often built out of less specialized nodes
in fact the nodes in the commodity cluster
are more generic in their computing capabilities
the service - oriented computing community over the internet have pushed for
computing to be done on commodity clusters as distributed computations
and in turn reducing the cost of computing over the internet
in commodity clusters the computing nodes are clustered in racks
connected to each other via a fast network
there might be many of such racks in extensible amounts
computing in one or more of these clusters across
a local area network or the internet is called distributed computing
such architectures enable what we call data - parallelism
in data - parallelism many jobs that share nothing can work on
different data sets or parts of a data set
this type of parallelism sometimes gets called as job level parallelism
but in this specialization we will refer to it as data - parallelism
in the context of big - data computing
large volumes and varieties of big data can be analyzed using this mode
of parallelism achieving scalability performance and cost reduction
as you can imagine there are many points of failure inside systems
a node or an entire rack can fail at any given time
the connectivity of a rack to the network can stop or
the connections between individual nodes can break
it is not practical to restart everything every time if failure happens
the ability to recover from such failures is called fault - tolerance
for fault - tolerance of such systems two neat solutions emerged
namely redundant data storage and
restart of failed individual parallel jobs
we will explain these two solutions next
as a summary the commodity clusters are a cost effective way
of achieving data parallel scalability for big data applications
these type of systems have a higher potential for partial failures
it is this type of distributed computing that pushed for
a change towards cost effective reliable and
fault - tolerant systems for management and analysis of big data