it can be said without a doubt and the internet and
the worldwide web changed everything in our lives
the worldwide web is indeed the largest information source there is today
but what is the data model behind the web
we will say that it is the semi - structure data model
so after going through this video you will be able to distinguish between
the structured data model that we talked about the last time and
semi - structured data model
further you will recognize that the most
times the semi - structured data refers to tree structured data
and you can explain why tree navigation operations are important for
formats like xml and json
let a take a very simple web page
now this page does not have a lot of content or stylization
it does not even have links to other pages but
let look at the corresponding html code
this code is used by the browser so that it can render the html and
notice a few things in this data
the entire data comes within the html and slash html blocks
and we similarly have a body begin and end a header begin and
end a list begin and end and a paragraph begin and end
everywhere here a block is nested within a larger block
the second item to notice is that unlike a relational structure
there are multiple list items and multiple paragraphs
and any single document would have a different number of them
this means while the date object has some structure it is more flexible
so this is the hallmark office semi structure date model
now xml or
the extensible markup language is another well known standard to represent data
you can think of xml as a generalization of html where the elements that
the beginning and end markers within the angular brackets can be any string
and not like the ones allowed by standard html
let see an example from a biological case
as you can see there are two elements called sample attribute
they do structurally different because they
have different numbers of sub elements called the value
another interesting issue about xml data processing
is that you can actually credit for the structure elements
for example it is perfectly fine to ask what is the name of the element
which contains a sub - element whose textual content is cell type
as you can see you will get two results sample attribute
an experimental factor because sample attribute has a sub - element called
category and experimental factor has a subelement called link and
each of these subelements have the value celltape
now we cannot perform an operation like this in a relational data model
for example we cannot say which relation has a column with a value john
the same idea can also be seen in json or the java script object notation which
is a very popular format used for many different data like twitter and facebook
consider the example here all of the format looks different
we have a similar nested structure varies that is lists
containing other lists which will contain topples which consists of p value ps
so the key value pairs at atomic property names and their values
but one way to generalize about all these different forms of semi structured data
is to model them as trees
let go back to xml
the left side shows an xml document and
the right side shows the corresponding tree
since the top object of the root element is document
it is also the root of the tree
now under document we have a report element with author and
date under it and also a paper element with title author and source under it
the actual values like is the textual content of an element
since a text data item cannot have any further components
these text values are always the leaves of the tree
now modeling a document as a tree has significant advantages
a tree is a well - known data structure
that allows what is called a navigational access to data
imagine you are standing on the note paper
now you can perform a getparent operation and navigate the document
or you can perform a getchildren operation to get to the title author and source
you can even perform a getsiblings operation and get to the report
you can also ask a textual query like which strings have the substring data and
seek their root - to - node path to get to the path from document to the text nodes
you can possibly see how queries can be evaluated on the tree
now let us take the query
who is the author of xml query data model
in one evaluation scheme we can navigate up from the text note to title
to paper and then navigate down to author and then to don robie
well how do we know that we have to get up to paper before reversing the direction
well paper is the least that the lowest in the tree
common ancestor of the author note and the xm query data model note
we will come back to semi structure data in a later module
in this hands - on activity we will be looking at graph data in gephi
first we will import data into gephi and then examine the properties of the graph
next we will perform some statistical operations on the graph data
and then run some different layout algorithms
let begin
we are not running gephi in the cloudera virtual machine on the coursera website
there will be a reading with instructions on how to download install and
run gephi on your native hardware instead of in the virtual machine
once you have gephi started let import the data into gephi
we will go to file import spreadsheet and in the csv dialog
we will click the button with dot dot dot
we will choose diseasegraph csv and click open
make sure that as table says edges table click next
and make sure create missing nodes is checked
we will click finish to import the csv file as a graph
gephi now shows the graph in the center pane
the little black circles are the nodes of the graph and
the lines between them are the edges
in the top right we can see that there are 777 nodes and 998 edges
next let perform some statistical operations on this graph
in the statistics pane we can see average degree
let compute the average degree of the graph by clicking on run
this says that the average degree is 2 569
let close this let compute the connected
components we will click on run
we will leave this as a directed since the graph is directed
click ok it says that there
are 5 weakly connected components and 761 strongly connected components
let close this
next let run some different layout algorithms over the graph
the bottom left we will go to choose layout
we will choose force atlas and click run
click stop to stop the layout
we can see that gephi has grouped strongly connected components together
in different clusters
we can also see that they are parts of the graph that are not connected
let run a different layout algorithm
the combo box choose fruchterman reingold click run
after it runs for a few seconds click stop then click the magnifying glass
center on graph to see the whole graph
in this layout all the nodes appear to be equally spaced
but we can also see the nodes with many edges
in this hands on activity we will be working with lucene
a search engine that uses a vector space model to index data
first we will open a terminal window and
change into the directory containing the data and scripts
next we will index some text documents and query terms in lucene
after that we will query using weighted terms or
boosting to see how this changes the rankings
finally we will show the term frequency - inverse document frequency or
tf - idf in terms
let begin
first let open a terminal window by clicking on the terminal icon at the top
of the tool bar
next let cd into the directory containing the scripts and data
we will run cd
downloads big - data - 2 vector
we will run ls to see the scripts
the data directory contains three text files
each of these text files contains news data about elections
let index these files by running runlucenequery sh data
next let query lucene for some terms in these text documents and see the rankings
let query for the term voters
you can see the rankings and scores that news1 csv ranked first
news2 csv was the second ranking and the third was news3 csv
let query for delegates
for this term we see that news2 csv
was first and news1 was second and
news3 did not contain the term at all
now let query for both terms voters and delegates
in this result we see that news2 was ranked first
news1 was ranked second and
news3 was ranked third
now lets use query term waiting or
boosting to increase the relevance of voters
i can do this by ensuring voters carat 5 delegates
the carat 5 notation is a syntax for
lucene for boosting
when we run this we see that now news1 is ranked first
news2 is ranked second and news3 is ranked third
notice this is different from the original query with voters and delegates
where news2 is ranked first and news1 was ranked second
now let look at the term frequency inverse document frequency or tf - idf
we will enter q to quit this and
we will run lucene tf - idf sh data
let look at the tf - idf for voters
you can see that it ranked number 1 for news1
second news 2 and news 3 is last
lets try delegates
here we see that news 2 had a higher score than news 1
and news 3 is not listed because news 3 does not contain this term
hit q to quit
so the next category of data we discuss has the form of graphs or networks
the most obvious example being social networks
now speaking of social networks
tim libzek created a social network from the lord of the rings trilogy
this graph represents the characters allegiances
that is who is faithful to whom in the books
so the nodes are characters and other entities like cities and
the edges connecting pairs of nodes represent allegiances
so after this video you will be able to identify graph data in practical problems
and describe path neighborhood and connectivity operations in graphs
but this specialization includes a separate course in graph analytics
that provides a much more detailed treatment on the subject
now what distinguishes a graph from other data models
is that it bears two kinds of information
one properties and attributes of entities and relationships and
two the connectivity structure that constitutes the network itself
one way to look at this data is shown in the figure
borrowed from the apache spark system
in this representation
the graph on the left is represented by two tables on the right
the vertex or node table gives ids to nodes and lists their properties
the edge table has two parts
the colored part represents the properties of the edge
whereas the white part contains just the direction of the arrows in the network
thus since there is a directed edge going from node 3 to node 7
there is a tupple 3 7 in that part of the edge table
now this form of the graph model is called the property graph model
which we will see many times in this course and in the specialization
now representing connectivity information gives graph data a new kind of
computing ability that different from other data models we have seen so far
even without looking at the properties of the nodes and edges one can get very
interesting information just by analyzing or querying this connectivity structure
consider a social network with three types of nodes user city and
restaurant and three types of edges friend likes and lives in
the leftmost node ag represents me
and i am interested in finding a good italian restaurant in new york
that my friends or their friends who also live in new york like
i shall possibly choose it3 because it has the highest number of
like edges coming into it from people who have a lives in edge to new york
and at the same time
can be reached by following the friend edges going out from me
now this shows a very important class of operations and ground data namely
traversal that involves edge following based on some sort of conditions
a number of path operations required some sort of optimization
the simplest among these is the well known shortest path query which is applied to
node networks to find the best route from a source location to a target location
the second class of optimization operations is required to find
an optimal path that must include some user specified nodes for
the operation has to determine the order in which the nodes once we visited
the classical application is a trip planner
where the user specifies the cities she wishes to visit and
the operation will optimize the criterion like the total distance covered
the third category is a case where the system must find the best possible
path in the network given two or
more optimization criteria which cannot be satisfied simultaneously
for example if i want to travel from my house to the airport
using the shortest distance but also minimizing the amount of highway travel
the algorithm must find a best compromise
this is called a pareto - optimality problem on graphs
the neighborhood of a node n in a graph is a set of edges directly connected to it
a k neighborhood of n is a collection of edges between nodes that are
at most k steps away from n
so going back to our mini social network graph bob jill
and sarah are the first neighbors of ag while max tim and
pam belong to the second neighborhood and not the first neighborhood of ag
finally jen is a third level neighbor
an important class of analysis to perform with neighborhoods is community finding
a community and a social network can be a very close group of friends
so the graph shown in this figure has four communities
one can see in the figure that each community has a higher density of edges
within the community and a lower density across two different communities
finding densely connected parts of a graph
helps identify neighborhoods that can be recognized as communities
a more complex class of operations include finding the best possible clusters
which is another name for communities in a graph so
that any other grouping of nodes into communities will be less effective
now as graphs become bigger and denser these methods become harder to compute
thus neighborhood - based optimization operation present
significant scalability challenges
if we inspect the neighborhood of every node in a graph sometimes
we will find neighborhoods that are different from all others
these neighborhoods are called anomalous
consider the following four graphs and on the central red node
the first graph is odd because it almost perfectly star shaped
that is the nodes that the red node is connected to are almost unconnected
amongst themselves
that really odd because it does not happen in reality much
so it an anomalous node
the second figure shows a neighborhood to which
a significantly large number of neighbors has connected amongst themselves
this makes the graph very cliquish where a clique refers to a neighborhood
where each node is connected to all other neighborhood nodes in the neighborhood
the third figure shows a neighborhood
where some edges have an unusually heavy weight compared to the others
the fourth figure shows a special case of the third
where one edge is predominantly high rate compared to all the other edges
connectedness is a fundamental property of a graph
in a connected graph
each node is reachable from every other node through some path
if a graph is not connected but there are subgraphs of it which are connected
then these subgraphs are called connected components of the original graph
in the figure on the right there are four connected components
a search gradient like finding optimal paths
should be performed only within each component and not across them
for large graphs there are several new parallelized techniques for
the detection of connected components
we will discuss a map reduce based technique for
connected components in a later course
we have discussed quite a few data models but
there are many other data models that have been developed for
various purposes and we really cannot cover all of them in a single course
we will end these lectures on data models with an example that may give you
an insight into a class of objects that define in many different applications
so after this video you will be able to describe how arrays can serve
as a data model explain why images can be modeled as vector arrays
specify a set of operations on scalar and vector arrays
now we have all seen the arrays
in the simplest case an array is a matrix like this
let call this array a
the top row in yellow gives the column numbers and
the left column also in yellow gives the row numbers
when we need to refer to a value of the array as a 3 2
we mean the value of the cell in row 3 and column 2
this is called indexed structure where 3 and
2 are the row and column indices that are necessary to get the value of a data item
the area has two dimensions
so hence there are two indexes
if these were a three dimensional array we would have three indexes
now earlier
we have seen that we can represent the two dimensional array as a three column table
one column for the row index one column for the column index and
the last column for the value
thus a k dimensional array can be represented as a relation with k
plus one columns
the number of tuples in this representation will be the product of
the size of the first dimension times the size of the second dimension and so forth
then in this case the size is five in each dimension
so there are 25 c column tuples in a relation representing the array
a more useful situation occurs when the cells of an array have
a vectors as values
as you can see in the 2d vector array here each cell has a three vector
that is a vector with three elements
therefore if we want to receive a cell value and
treat it like before we will get back the whole vector
now this type of data should look familiar to you
because images often have a red green and blue channels per pixel
in other words
images of vector valued arrays where each array cell has a three color vector
we can also think of the array model in the context of satellite images
where there are many more channels depending on the range of wavelengths
each channel catches
let us consider the operations on arrays of vectors
because it is a combination of two models one can create different combinations of
array operations vector operations and composite operations
here are some
the dimension of the array here the first operation is two
if we pick up any dimension say one
the size of it is also two because they are two elements
zero and one in each dimension
as we saw before the value of the cell 1 1 is a vector 16 301 74
while the value of a11 component 2 is 74
the length of the vector is a square root of the sum of the elements of the vector
so length of a11 would come to 310 375
the distance function can be so
simple like the euclidean distance function between two vectors or
the cosine of an angle between them as we saw in the previous lecture
but it can also be something more complex based on the needs of the application
obviously one can also perform operations like selection over indices so
we can ask which cells had the zero value greater than 25
giving as the result zero one and one zero
you will experience some of these operations in your hands on session