big data generated by organizations structured but often siloed
the last type of big data we will discuss is big data generated by organizations
this type of data is the closest to what most businesses currently have
but it considered a bit out of fashion or
traditional compared to other types of big data
however it is at least as important as other types of big data
so how do organizations produce data
the answer to how an organization generates data
is very unique to the organization and context
each organization has distinct operation practices and
business models which result in a variety of data generation platforms
for example the type and source of data that a bank gets is very different from
what a hardware equipment manufacturer gets
some common types of organizational big data come from commercial transactions
credit cards government institutions e - commerce banking or
stock records medical records sensors transactions clicks and so on
almost every event can be potentially stored
organizations store this data for current and
future use as well as for analysis of the past
let say you are an organization that collects sales transactions
you can use this data for pattern recognition to detect correlated products
to estimate demand for products likely to go up in sales and
capture fraudulent activity
moreover when you know your sales record and can correlate it
with your marketing records you can find which campaigns really made an impact
you are already becoming a data savvy organization
now think of bringing your sales data together with other
external open public data such as major world events in the news
you can ask was it savvy marketing or
a consequence of external events that triggered your sales
using proper analytics
you can now build inventories to match your predicted growth and demand
in addition organizations build and apply processes to record and
monitor business events of interest such as registering a customer
manufacturing a product or taking an order
these processes collect highly structured data
that include transactions reference tables and
relationships as well as the metadata that sets its context
usually structured data is stored in relational database management systems
however we call any data that is in the form of
a record located in a fixed field or file structured data
this definition also includes spreadsheets
as i have mentioned before traditionally this type of
highly structured data is the vast majority of what it managed and
processed in both operational and business intelligence systems
let look at the sales transaction data in our previous example
if you look at the data in the relational table on the right
as the name structured suggests
the table is organized to store data using
a structure defined by a model
each column is tagged to tell us what data that column intends to store
this is what we call a data model
a data model defines each of these columns and
fields in the table and defines relationships between them
if you look at the product id column you will see that it includes only
identifiers that can potentially be linked to another table defining these products
the ability to define such relationships easily make structured data
or in this case relational databases highly adopted by many organizations
there are commonly used languages like sql
the structured query language to extract data of interest from such tables
this is referred to as querying the data
however it could even be a challenge to integrate such structured data
this image shows us a continuum of technologies to model
collect and query unstructured data coming from software and
hardware components within an organization
in the past such challenges led to information being stored
in what we call silos even within an organization
many organizations have traditionally captured data at the department level
without proper infrastructure and policy to share and integrate this data
this has hindered the growth of scalable pattern recognition
to the benefits of the entire organization
because no one system has access to all data that the organization owns
each data set is compartmentalized
if such silos are left untouched organizations risk having outdated
unsynchronized and even invisible data sets
organizations are realizing the detrimental outcomes of this rigid
structure
and changing policies and infrastructure to enable integrated processing of
all data to the entire organization benefit
cloud - based solutions are seen as agile and
low capital intensive solutions in this area
as a summary while highly structured organizational data is very useful and
trustworthy and thus a valuable source of information
organizations must pay special attention to breaking up
the silos of information to make full use of its potential
the key integrating diverse data
whatever your big data application is and
the types of big data you are using the real value will come from integrating
different types of data sources and analyzing them at scale
so how do we start getting this value
sometimes all it takes
is looking at the data you already collect in a different way
and it can mean a big difference in your return on investment
this new story from june 2015 mentions that carnival cruises
is using structured and unstructured data from a variety of sources
carnival turns it into profit
using price optimization techniques on the integrated data
for you to achieve such a success story
you will need to include data integration into your big data practice
however there are some unique challenges when attempting to integrate these
diverse data sources and scaling the solutions
course two on on the specialization we will teach you more about these issues
but let take a moment to define why effect of data integration is useful
data integration means bringing together data from diverse sources and
turning them into coherent and more useful information
we also call this knowledge
the main objective here is taming or more technically managing data and
turning it into something you can make use of programmatically
a data integration process involves many parts
it starts with discovering accessing and monitoring data and
continues with modeling and transforming data from a variety of sources
but why do we need data integration in the first place
let start by focusing on differences between big data sets
coming from different sources
you might have flat file formatted data relational database data
data encoded in xml or json both common for internet generated data
these different formats and models are useful
because they are designed to express different data in unique ways
in a way different data formats and
models make big data more useful and more challenging all at the same time
when you integrate data in different formats you make the final
product richer in the number of features you describe the data with
for example by integrating environmental sensor and
camera data with geographical information system data such as in
my wildfire prediction application i can use the spacial data capabilities
with non - spacial data to more accurately run fire simulations
in the past although we were able to see the images of the fire
from mountain top cameras just like this image we were still
not able to tell what the exact location of the fire is automatically
now when a fire is detected from a mountain top camera
viewsheds are used to estimate the location of the fire
this location information can be fed into the fire simulator
as early as it detected to predict the size and
location of the fire in the next hour more accurately and faster
similarly i can use real time data with eye curve data sets and
use them all together
additionally by bringing the data together and
providing programmable access to it i am now making each data set more accessible
moreover integration of diverse datasets significantly
reduces the overall data complexity in my data - driven product
the data becomes more available for use and unified as a system of its own
one advantage of such an integration is not often mentioned
such a streamlined and integrated data system
can increase the collaboration between different parts of your data systems
each part can now clearly see
how their data is integrated into the overall system
including the user scenarios and the security and privacy processes around it
overall by integrating diverse data streams you add value to your big data and
improve your business even before you start analyzing it
next we will focus on the dimensions of the scalability and
discuss how we can start tackling some of these challenges
what launched the big data era
in this video you will learn about two new opportunities that have
contributed to the launch of the big data era
opportunities are often a signal of changing times
in 2013 an influential report by a company called mckinsey claimed that
the area of data science will be the number one catalyst for economic growth
mckinsey identified one of our new
opportunities that contributed to the launch of the big data era
a growing torrent of data
this refers to the idea that data seems to be coming continuously and at a fast rate
think about this today you can buy a hard drive to store
all the music in the world for only 600
that an amazing storage capability over any previous forms of music storage
in 2010 there were 5 billion mobile phones in use
you can be sure that there are more today and
as i am sure you will understand these phones and
the apps we install on them are a big source of big data
which all the time every day contributes to our core
and facebook which recently just set
a record of having one billion people login in a single day
has more that 30 billion pieces of content shared every month
well that number from 2013
so i am sure that it much higher than that now
does it make you think how many facebook share you made last month
all this leads to projections of serious growth
40 in global data per year and 5 in global it spending
this much data has sure pushed the data science field
to start remaining itself and the business world of today
but there something else contributing to the catalyzing power of data science
it is called cloud computing
we call this on demand computing
cloud computing is one of the ways in which computing
has now become something that we ca do anytime and anywhere
you may be surprised to know that some of your favorite
apps are from businesses being run from coffee shops
this new ability combined with our torrent of data
gives us the opportunity to perform novel dynamic and scalable data analysis
to tell us new things about our world and ourself
to summarize a new torrent of big data combined with computing capability
anytime anywhere has been at the core of the launch of the big data era
asking the right questions
the first step in any process is to define what it is you are trying to tackle
what is the problem that needs to be addressed or
the opportunity that needs to be ascertained
without this you wo not have a clear goal in mind or
know when you have solved your problem
an example question is how can sales figures and
call center logs be combined to evaluate a new product
or in a manufacturing process how can data from multiple
sensors in an instrument be used to detect instrument failure
how can we understand our customers and
market better to achieve effective target marketing
next you need to assess the situation with respect to the problem or
the opportunity you have defined
this is a step where you need to exercise caution analyzing risks
costs benefits contingencies
regulations resources and requirements of the situation
what are the requirements of the problem
what are the assumptions and constraints
what resources are available
this is in terms of both personnel and capital
such as computer systems instruments etc
what are the main costs associated with this project
what are the potential benefits
what risks are there in pursuing the project
what are the contingencies to potential risks and so on
answers to these questions will help you get a better overview of the situation
and better understanding of what the project involves
then you need to define your goals and objectives
based on the answers to these questions
defining success criteria is also very important
what do you hope to achieve by the end of this project
having clear goals and and
success criteria will help you to assess the project throughout its life cycle
once you know the problem you want to address and understand the constraints and
goals then you can formulate the plan to come up with the answer
that is the solution to your business problem
as a summary defining the questions you are looking to find answers for
is a huge factor contributing to the success of a data science project
by following the explained set of steps you can formulate better questions
to solve using analytical skills and link them to business value
building a big data strategy
before we focus on big data strategy let look at what strategy means
although it is associated with a military term
a dictionary search on strategy shows the meaning as a plan of action or
policy designed to achieve a major or overall aim
this definition calls out the four major parts that need to be in any strategy
namely aim policy plan and action
now we are talking about a big data strategy
so what do these four terms mean for us
when building our big data strategy we look at what we have
what high level goals we want to achieve what we need to do to get there
and what are the policies around data from the beginning to the end
a big data strategy starts with big objectives
notice that i did not say it starts with collecting data
because in this activity we are really trying to identify what
data is useful and why by focusing on what data to collect
every organization or team is unique
different projects have different objectives
hence it important to first define what your team goals are
have you ever had the scenario where you see the temperature on the weather report
and someone else highlights the humidity instead
to find problems relevant to solve and
data related to it it might be useful to start with your objectives
once you define these objectives or
more generally speaking questions to turn big data into advantage for your business
you can look at what you have and analyze the gaps and actions to get there
it is important to focus on both short term and
long term objectives in this activity
these objectives should also be linked to big data analytics with business
objectives
to make the best use of big data each company needs to evaluate how
data science or big data analytics would add value to their business objectives
once you have established that analytics can help your business
you need to create a culture to embrace it
the first and foremost ingredient for
a successful data science program is organizational buy - in
a big data strategy must have commitment and
sponsorship from the company leadership
goals for using big data analytics should be developed with all stakeholders and
clearly communicated to everyone in the organization
so that its value is understood and appreciated by all
the next step is to build your data science team
a diverse team with data scientists information technologists
application developers and business owners is necessary to be effective
as well as the mentality that everyone works together as partners with
common goals
remember one for all
no one is a customer or service provider of another
rather everyone works together and delivers as a team
since big data is a team game and multi - disciplinary
a big part of a big data strategy is constant training
of team members on new big data tools and analytics
as well as business practices and objectives
this becomes even more critical if your business depends on deep expertise
on one or more subject areas with subject matter experts working on problems
utilizing big data
such businesses might have subject matter experts who can be trained to add big
data skills and provide more value added support than a newcomer would have
similarly any project member would be trained to understand what
the business objectives and products are and how he or
she can utilize big data to improve those objectives using his or her skills
many organizations might benefit by having a small data science team whose main job
is do data experiments and test new ideas before they get deployed at full scale
they might come up with a new idea themselves
based on the analysis they perform
they take more research level role
however their findings can drastically shape your business strategy
almost on a daily basis
the impact of such teams becomes evident over time
as other parts of your organization starts to see the results of their finding and
analysis affecting their strategies
they become strategic partners of all verticals in your business
once you see that something works
you can start collecting more data to see similar results at organizational scale
since data is key to any big data initiative it is essential
that data across the organization is easily accessed and integrated
data silos as you know are like a death knell on effective analytics
so barriers to data access must be removed
opening up the silos must be encouraged and supported from the organization
leaders in order to promote a data sharing mindset for the company
another aspect of defining your big data strategy
is defining the policies around big data
although it has an amazing amount of potential for your business
using big data should also raise some concerns in long term planning for data
although this is a very complex issue
here are some questions you should think of addressing around policy
what are the privacy concerns
who should have access to or control data
what is the lifetime of data which is sometimes defined as volatility
anatomy of big data
how does data get curated and cleaned up
what ensures data quality in the long term
how do different parts of your organization communicate or
interoperate using this data
are there any legal and regulatory standards in place
cultivating an analytics driven culture is crucial
to the success of a big data strategy
the mindset that you want to establish is that analytics
is an integral part of doing business not a separate afterthought
analytics activities must be tied to your business objectives and
you must be willing to use analytics in driving business decisions
analytics and business together bring about exciting opportunities and
growth to your big data strategy
finally one size does not fit all
hence big data technologies and
analytics is growing rapidly as your business is an evolving entity
you have to iterate your strategy to take advantage of new advances and
also make your business more dynamic in the face of change
as a summary when building a big data strategy
it is important to integrate big data analytics with business objectives
communicate goals and provide organizational buy - in for
analytics projects
build teams with diverse talents and establish a teamwork mindset
remove barriers to data access and integration
finally these activities need to be iterated to respond to new business
goals and technological advances