Welcome to module eleven of database management
system. ah This will be on advanced SQL.
Before we ah start ah let me quickly recap
what we did last ah week in the five modules.
ah Last week we totally spent on discussing
first the introductory features of SQL how
to create data and how to write basic queries,
and we studied about all different kinds of
SQL operations at theoretic operation, handling
of null values aggregation, ah nested queries
and so on. And then we did an intermediate
level of ah SQL query formation in terms of
joint expression, views and ah integrities
ah different kinds of SQL data types and importantly
authorization.
In the context, in this context, we now take
up some more of the SQL features which are
somewhat advanced. And ah we will try to understand
how SQL can be used from a programming language,
and familiarize with functions and procedures
in SQL. This will violate some of the basic
premises that we started with in saying that
SQL is a declarative language only because
as you understand functions procedure as procedural
language features we will see how to handle
those, and we will take a look into another
important feature of Krieger's.
First with accessing ah SQL. So, this is the
module outline accessing SQL from a programming
language . So, this is just kind of an abstract
view that you can think of that what we have
been doing so far naturally there is a database
which has primarily two things schema and
tables. Of course, there are many other things
there are index, there is authorization that
triggers and and all that, but there is a
database which stores everything.
And so far we have been dealing with only
this part of ah the information that I can
write certain SQL query to define table, using
table names, attributes and certain logic
and that goes through certain query processor
works on the database to get me either create
the desired effect. Either that is creating
table instances or creating index or extracting
certain ah relation values, defining some
views and so on. So, all these have to happen
through an SQL interface. So, this has to
happen through an SQL interface.
So, whatever system we are using whether you
are using mySQL, Postgres, Oracle, Cybers
SQL server whatever you using that has some
interface through which these SQL queries
can be executed, so that is kind of a standalone
complete system. But, in general, we will
have lot of more requirements in terms of
the application. For example, the application
might require some graphics, SQL does not
have support for graphics; application might
require certain numerical ah algorithms to
be executed might require some geometric computations
to be done ah poly intersection of polygons
to be computed and so on and so forth.
It might require some network programming
and so on. So, there is a need to do all these
and certainly these are best done in terms
of certain native language that could be C,
c plus plus, java, c sharp, visual basic,
python any of the native languages which has
support for a variety of different tasks.
So, what is critical is can we make a bridge
between these two that is can we take the
advantages of the SQL domain and the advantages
of the normal imperative procedural programming
domain together. That is I can ah do some
graphic representation and then certainly
go to the database extract some information
and then present it in the graphics and vice
versa. For example, whenever we access ah
say gmail, we get to see them in terms of
an html presentation which is some kind of
a graphics rendering, but the all the mail
entry certainly come from some database.
So, somewhere there is a connection ah by
which when I say get my inbox ah mails and
somewhere the information ah goes over from
this to the SQL query up to the database and
the result is brought back to me. I see that
in the html page ah here, but here there must
be certain mail database, where all these
information exists . So, ah what I am trying
to come at is it is critical that the application
programs ah or or you know high level programming
normal programming languages native languages
should be able to interface with SQL. And
ah what we discuss here is two different mechanisms
for this interfacing. The first one is using
a connection library and this is what ah I
I will specifically show you .
So, for if you are using a connection library
then you have a set of ah APIs application
programming interfaces these are basically
functions in that library. So, that with that
application can connect to the database because
certainly the database is somewhere else is
a different server. And send an SQL command
to the database server so that you can say
that this is what I want. And then a result
is computed the result of that computation
the table the can be brought back those tuples
can be brought back to the ah application
program. Mind you ah when we are are here
when you are sending the information in terms
of the database server, we are talking SQL
command, we are talking about attributes tables
of the SQL space.
Whereas, when I want it in the program I want
it in terms of program variables. So, there
has to be certain correspondence made between
them. There are a variety of tools available
which allow you to do this ah JDBC is common
very commonly known which is specific for
java. We have an open database connectivity
APIs which has ah different versions for different
languages these are the common languages that
it is used with. And as we will see later
on that there is another ah mechanism for
doing the same thing called the embedded SQL,
we will come to that later .
So, JDBC is a java API, I will not go into
details here if you know java you should be
able to quickly look up. So, it is a it communicates
with the database by opening a connection
creating what java calls a statement object
and executes the query using the statement
objects and ah that is used to send the query
as well as to get back the result. So, java
is ah object oriented as you know so statement
object is used as a as an encapsulation which
travels between the java program and the SQL
ah query processor. And since the query gets
back the result since the query gets back
there is that kind of there is exception mechanism
to handle errors which is common for java
.
What you the see in contrast ah does a similar
thing, but since it is to cater for different
languages it has got a softer model it has
got less powerful model. It is a standard
application program to communicate with database
server. So, again it has to open a connection
to the database, send queries and updates
and get back results. So, these are these
are the three basic things, these three other
three basic things that certainly needs to
be done if I want to ah easily work across
the application programming domain and the
database programming domain . So, applications
such as GUI, spreadsheet, etcetera can use
ODBC.
So, yeah I am just quickly showing you an
example ah we will talk about application
programming mode in a in a later module. So,
this is ah a python example. So, python ah
for this the ODBC for python is known as py
by ODBC library. So, you need to import that.
And then ah using that you can connect. So,
if you have to connect you have to say which
database who is the user, what is the password,
because authentication needs to happen. So,
SQLS is a database here and with this ah this
user with this password is connecting you
that ah is successful you get a conn object
and on the conn object you have something
what is known as a cursor. Cursor is nothing
but if you think about ah it is it is kind
of a pointer. So, it can be used to point
to either a row or a whole query or a table
.
So, you get back a cursor object. So, then
this is if you look into this part, this part
is nothing but a pure SQL query. So, you take
that as a string and pass it on to the execute
method of cursor. So, what it does is, so
this is this has done the first ah task which
is connecting to the database. Now, you are
basically ah putting the query to the database
in terms of doing saying that this execute
. Similarly, so if that will get executed,
so the table is created naturally there is
no result to get if you have created a table.
Now, you do an ah insert. So, again this particular
record, you can see that within this double
quote, this whole insert ah syntax you take
take that as a string and just give it to
ah execute as a parameter.
In the third, that you do is do a select.
So, you have done this we have inserted a
record, created a table inserted a record
in that and then now you are doing a select.
So, certainly we expect one record to come
back. So, these are the SQL executions and
then your get back result. So, cursor has
another method which is known as fetch one.
So, what it will do that if your result table
has ah multiple entries, then the cursor ah
will if will be will start with the first
row and fetch one will bring the whole of
this first row as a row vector.
So, it will bring in as all the components
as one as a python string. And ah then you
check whether it is empty or not, if it is
empty then the I mean there is nothing to
bring back, so you are done. So, you break
otherwise you simply print the row, so you
are printing there. And then you go back again
this is while true. So, what happens is the
cursor will advance to the next row and get
you the next row. Again you do the same thing
go back it will come back to the same, but
once ah you get an empty ah result, you know
that there is nothing more to proceed and
you break.
So, this is what is illustrated then there
are some more ah this particular record is
deleted, then again another record is inserted.
And another select is done. So, this is how
a native program here in this case python
can interact with the database and do any
of the SQL tasks that we were ah doing earlier
with SQL interface, now we can be done from
the python, so that is a basic ODBC mechanism
. I particularly chose python to just give
you a different flavour, you can ah we will
have ah assignments on on doing it for C and
using jdbc on java as well .
Now, I am come I will come back to the same
interaction ah ah issue, but this time you
can see that I am using a different diagram.
The database is the same; this part is the
same; the query processing is same, but instead
of having a connection library, now I have
put the SQL query itself as a part of the
native program, the C program. So, this is
what is called embedding . So, you say I embed
I put the SQL as a part of C, but naturally
SQL is not C. So, we need to put certain ah
additional syntax in C, so that I can directly
write SQL as a part of the C program. I am
talking about C, again just as an example
if this is true for other several other languages
which can be used as used for embedding SQL
within them.
So, this is called the embedded SQL, it works
for C, C plus plus, java fortran etcetera.
And the language native language in which
your embedding is called the is known as a
host language. And basic form of these languages
allow that the are come from the System R.
So, what is ah important is this particular
statement EXEC-SQL. This EXEC-SQL written
inside the body of a C program will tell the
C compiler that this part is not C; this part
is actually embedded SQL. And it will be treated
differently, it will be compiled by the SQL
compiler within the C compiler, so that is
the basic structure, so EXEC-SQL. And then
you put the pure SQL statement the embedded
SQL statement . So, let us ah go forward and
see some of this, ah there are different syntax
for different native language embedding .
So, to be able to connect you say EXEC-SQL
and connect to server username using password.
So, we saw similar things in terms of ah ODBC
based ah connection these three information
needs to be specified which database server,
who is the user, what is the password. So,
here you say that in this form. And this particular
statement you can write as a part of the C
program. Now, naturally the question ah here
is ah in the in the earlier case when we are
using the connection library, your results
came back through the cursor which you then
ah could deal because the cursors are necessarily
objects in your native language. So, in python
the cursor was a particular ah object in the
pyodbc library.
But now you have embedded the SQL in terms
of your c program. So, naturally the results
or whatever you are doing in C which needs
to have a communication with the SQL statement
ah need to be differentiated from the SQL
ah names themselves. So, any native language
ah variable that needs to be treated ah in
SQL will be marked with a colon preceding
it. So, credit amount of this a colon credit
amount, so it becomes a SQL variable provided
credit amount itself is a C variable, so that
is the basic ah you know connection mechanics.
There are far more details in that , but I
am just giving you the glimpse .
Now, any region where you write the SQL, you
can write it as exact SQL begin declare section,
and END declare section this is where you
specify what are the different ah what are
the different C variables C declarations that
need to be used for this SQL definition. I
will just show you an example soon so that
ah.
Similar to the ODBC style, you have a you
will declare a cursor. So, this is ah to write
the embedded SQL, you use declared c cursor
for such and such SQL queries, so then that
C, variable C will become your handle in the
in the C language to be able to answer handle
the query results . So, here is an ah example.
So, you can see that ah credit amount is a
variable in the host language . So, you are
using it in SQL with colon credit ah amount
which says that it is this host language variable.
So, that you can set a particular credit amount
and ah go with that . And ah this is the query,
and you have set a cursor on that which you
can make use of in the exact SQL. So, let
us this is the example continued.
Let us look at other features. You can once
you have set a query you can actually execute
that by the open statement. So, you say EXEC-SQL
open c, the cursor. So, that will execute
the query that you have associated with that
cursor. And then once that has been done,
then you can fetch the results ah into that
cursor one by one; one tuple at a time . Once
you are done with all that then you simply
close.
So, let us ah look at a example. This is a
program which will ah which prompts the user
for an order number, and ah retrieves the
customer number I mean given an order number
it will retrieve the customer number, salesperson,
status of the order and it will display that
as the retrieved information on the screen
. So, here is a C program. It starts on here
with the main. So, you can see that this says
that ah EXEC-SQL include, SQLCA, SQLCA is
the communication area. So, there is a there
is a exchanges going on between the c program
and SQL program. So, the area that is used
by both for this transaction is known as SQLCA
.
Then you have the declare section. So, you
are saying these are SQL exec declaration.
So, these are, but within that what you have
are pure c declaration, but all the declarations
of c that are put within this can be used
in SQL query with a colon at the beginning.
So, that the value can be exchanged to the
SQLCA then in the next you are specifying
what will happen if you have an error. So,
you say SQL look at this EXEC-SQL whenever
SQL error go to query error. So, it will go
to this level. If it is not found that is
no result is there it will go to this. So,
you by making sure that if there is some error
that happens in the SQL part, what will happen
in your C program. And then subsequently you
have sample C program which reads the order
number, and after having read that you are
doing this.
So, what does it do, EXEC-SQL is to say that
this is embedded, this is the select query
starts, the fields, the relation, the condition.
And then there are three attributes. So, you
are setting an association with three variables
in the C program. So, if I want to the result
of this select will be a table of three attributes
three columns, so we are giving a name to
each one of these three attributes in terms
of our C program. So, there is a cust id.
So, I say the cust id attribute in SQL is
colon cust id here which is basically cust
id variable in the C program. Let me clean
up again. So, this is cust id; this is in
SQL; this is my C program, and this is my
C program variable in SQL which corresponds
to this its similarly order based. Similarly,
this is in SQL attribute this is a array of
character here. And this is a correspondence;
this is a correspondence.
So, now, you can easily see that once this
has been done I will be able to get all these
values here, normally the program would be
longer the you will have to iterate over the
cursor as you did in case in the ODBC case.
But ah in this case since we are using one
order number we know that there will be only
one record. So, we have not shown the iteration
on the cursor. So, once you have got this
you are you are using those values to print
out the result. And in case this query has
got into some problem because of SQL, then
it will automatically jump to SQL query this
particular level. If it has got ah a bad number
which means that no such record was found,
it was a null table then it will immediately
take you to this. So, this is how the embedded
SQL worked.
So, there are these are two different styles
the ODBC style and the embedding style are
two different styles. If you have if you ah
depending on ah the preference you use that
earlier days people used to use more of embedding,
ah I believe that now the preference is more
for the ODBC kind of connection oriented system
ODBC jdbc kind of because they are ah certainly
more programmer friendly this .
You can do updates ah through embedded SQL
as well. So, I will not go through the details
you can just go through this and understand
that. Let me move onto the next ah advanced
part of SQL which is function and procedural
construct. Now mind you again this is these
are the two models that we have I have already
shown you. The two models in which ah the
application program the native language program
and the query language ah can interact the
ODBC mechanism and the embedded mechanism.
But what we are now empowering is so far our
our basic premise was that this site is a
procedural I I discussed this at the very
beginning .
And this side is declarative . So, in SQL
you do not say that ah how you find out a
result, you say what you want as a result,
these are more like predicates. And in C program,
you cannot specify ah what you want as a result
you would rather say that do step one, step
two, step three and you will get this result.
So, C program is all full of functions again
I am talking about C as a placeholder it is
true for most of the programming languages
we use otherwise ah. So, there are procedural
languages. So, procedures in C are functions.
Whereas, in SQL you had select from where
kind of conditional clause.
Now, what we are saying that ah SQL also ah
in later version have allowed certain functions
and procedures, which can be part of SQL.
It also has allowed certain imperative constructs
like ah case like ah loop like ah while, repeat
those kind of to make certain kind of procedural
programming easier in SQL . And naturally
these again can be used in in conjunction
with the connection oriented ah applications
with the native or embedded oriented mechanisms.
So, we will just take a quick look into some
of these function and procedural features.
So, this started coming in ah from SQL 1999.
And ah you can have functions and procedure
written in SQL itself. And function and procedures
written external language or the host language
also. So, both of them are are available.
What is interesting is ah some database systems
support functions which are table valued.
Functions, we always know functions ah written
ah objects only , but ah in SQL you can have
functions which have table valued which written
new functions . So, and certain imperative
ah imperative constructs have come in.
So, there are several databases have their
proprietary constructs and all that also.
So, at at this level of the course since we
are not focusing particularly on any specific
database systems, we will not talk about those.
We can do enough in terms of the standard
SQL itself. So, this is how you define a function
which looks ah very similar to the ah SQL
definition, create function, give it a name
certainly here are the parameters. And here
is a return type. So, if you are familiar
with C, C plus plus, Java you I mean it is
just that the syntax is different, but the
elements are same .
There is a begin end in the scope. And ah
this is the pure SQL that you are writing
here. So, this is a function which is not
a function in C, this is a function in SQL.
So, this you can write this function in SQL.
And ah once you have written that function
then you can actually use that. So, if you
look at the function is department name, then
separately I am writing a query, I am using
this department name as function. So, whenever
I I whenever this query will get executed,
this function will be called, and the corresponding
values will get returned. So, this is the
basic ah mechanism ok.
So, so there are SQL functions have several
details which you can go through it has returned
naturally. And you can have table functions
where it can return table. So, the syntax
is given again its clear to see what will
happen if you return a table which is computed
from the select from where query that you
have within the function.
I can have SQL procedures which ah just performs
some action, but ah ah does not have a have
a return value so to say. And ah you can use
them they can declare and call those ah procedures
explicitly. Procedures can be functions and
procedures ah can be overloaded as well if
you are on SQL 99 .
Now, there are several language constructs
as I mentioned SQL does allow while repeat.
So, I am I am just covering them ah in in
terms of completeness it is not that ah these
are ah frequently used features or I recommend
that you do lot of them ah right here. If
you need to do procedural thing its always
better to do them outside, but ah in some
cases it may be easier to code a query if
you can write a while, repeat ah kind of loop.
You can write a for loop which iterates over
the records of a table which is certainly
very convenient. So, if you want to do something
over the records of a table compute something
that the for loop will become easier.
You have a conditional ah statement case actually
we have seen the case already. So, which is
very easy in terms of coding many of the features.
So, here are some of them ah then you have
exceptions. So, I am not going through these,
these in in depth, but this is just to making
you aware that while SQL ah continues to be
predominantly a declarative language, it does
have quite a bit of procedural support which
ah in an appropriate time can be used if required.
So, you can look up the manual for that. And
there are a whole lot of things you can do
with the external language routines.
That is can write a function in C and actually
call it from SQL, this is just doing the other
way round. Earlier in terms of ah embedding
or in terms of ODBC, a C function was executing
a query. Now, you are doing the reverse you
are saying that I can write a SQL query which
uses a C function that already exist. So,
there are external ways of binding, I will
not go through these ah slides in depth, ah
because again the you will have to come a
certain way before you can actually start
using such features. But ah get to know that
there could be as from SQL you can use any
external language library; and if some library
is good for certain computation which is needed
for your query which is a non database kind
of computation then you can make use of this
external language routines.
So, I have put together all the basic features
ah that external language routines will need.
But again I would tell you that there are
benefits, but there are lot of drawbacks in
using them. And I would not recommend that
you frequently use these features. You should
primarily restrict to SQL programming, and
then anything that you need to do in the native,
you should go to choose your language and
do that.
There are security issues also that you will
need to understand here . Finally, before
we close I will just mention a another feature
called triggers, triggers are very important.
A trigger is a statement that is executed
automatically when ah something happens in
the database. So, you want that well things
are happening. And ah well ah I I want to
know if a particular ah value has exceeded
a certain level or if something has become
null or some violatory things are happening
and so on. So, how do you know that because
a database is being accessed by hundreds and
thousands of people and with hundreds of tables
and millions of records.
So, triggers are a mechanism by which you
can ah set that under this condition, I want
a trigger, I want something ah specifically
to happen. So, again they were introduced
in 99, but ah earlier also triggers were there,
but in 99 standard they became formal earlier
they were ah somewhat you know differently
structured. So, you might find that the system
that you are using for practice ah the trigger
in that may have a different format and semantics
then the what we are discussing here.
So, the most common ah triggering events are
insert, delete, update. So, if something ah
ah some update is happening, so I can say
that ah after this update, I want such and
such things to happen . Or I can during the
update I can one that well I am doing an update.
So, there is an old value which is typically
referred to as ah old row, the row that is
getting updated. And there is a new row the
new set of values that are getting created.
So, I might want between the old row and the
new row that ah certain things happen .
So, I can say that ah well just ah look into
this. So, again the syntax is all similar.
Create trigger, trigger there is a name of
the trigger and ah this is the condition . Before
update of takes, takes is a relation ah referencing
new row as row n row. So, this is the new
value that we set. Now, what are you saying,
saying that for each row what you do when
n grid is blank n row dot grade is blank that
is if this is if you are updating and you
have got a got you are going to update, a
grade value which is blank then you simply
set it to null.
So, it is possible that ah the grade that
has come in and grades are characters and
what has come in from the input and is going
to get updated is a show a certain grade to
be now because it may not have been decided.
Now, you do not want those blank values to
be present. You want because blank cannot
be checked, we have we have checkers for null
and so on. So, you want to set that to null.
So, trigger can make this thing happened because
otherwise how will you know what value is
actually getting changed . So, there could
be several ways trigger can be used.
For example, this is showing one that as you
change the grades then certainly based on
the grades credit earned value is computed.
So, as a greatest change if it is now once
grades have been entered say for ah 200 students.
Now, after reviews grades for three of them
are getting changed. So, how do you know that
for for those students, the change of the
grade may impact the computation of the on
credits. So, you would like to update that
on credits or it may or may not be required.
So, the trigger will tell you that ah after
update. So, whenever the update happens you
take the old and the new value n row and o
row, and then you are putting some conditions
that if that new row is grade is f, and is
not null; old row is grade or it is not null,
then you try to do this.
So, if it was failure, and if it continues
to be failure, new grade is not f; if it is
f then you do not have to do anything; if
it is null it do not have to do anything.
But if it is if it was f or it was null, and
now it has become a different grade then certainly
the computation to update the credits earned
is required. So, and the trigger gives you
the right point when you can do this because
otherwise you will not know in terms of millions
of updates happening when this particular
thing is going on.
Triggers can be on on statements as well you
can ah decide leave for your reading. But
you have to be careful that ah triggers sounds
very interesting and and what happens particularly
with the ah early stage of programming ah
people get overboard with triggers and start
using them ah severely, but triggers do have
a lot of overhead. So, you should not um many
of the things that triggers can do, can be
done through other means for example, by materialized,
views and so on. So, as we go along we will
mention that these are the problems that need
to solve get solved by triggers; otherwise
ah normally you should think twice before
you actually use a triggers. So, there could
be different other ways of solving the same
problem.
And because ah you have to keep in mind that
triggers are expensive because once you have
triggers and actually internally database
for every update. If you have an update trigger
on a field or a relation, then with every
transaction with every change the database
has to check if your trigger is true or not
and so therefore, there is a cost to that.
The other thing is there are triggers are
for the live execution. So, if you have offline
for example, you are loading the data from
a backup copy or you are replicating your
database at a remote site and so on, then
you have to put off the trigger; otherwise
you know falsely the triggers will start happening
and that may have a catastrophic effect that
might trigger of different alarms and all
that. So, you have to be careful with triggers
in that manner. So, cascading executions and
all those.
So, to summarize ah we have and this kind
of closes our ah direct discussion on SQL.
So, we have introduced the use of the very
important aspect the use of SQL from a programming
language, the interface between the native
language and query language boundary. And
that is something which will be extremely
useful for application programming. And we
are familiarized with you know the imperative
extensions of SQL, the procedural extensions
of SQL in terms of functions and ah procedures
that you can directly write in SQL. And we
have just ah introduced ah concept of triggers,
so that you can ah sniff what is going on
in your database.
So, there is the quite a few other features
of SQL as well ah majority of them are advanced
features dealing with ah olap and several
others, which I chose to skip at this level
of the course. So, this will close our discussion
on ah SQL. And next we will move onto ah the
design of the database looking into the algebra
and the modelling.