Welcome to module 22 of database management
systems, we have been discussing application,
design and development this is the second
part of that discussion.
In the last module, we have taken a quick
look at the application programs and the ah
user interfaces, looked at the fundamental
notions of web and specifically the servlets
and JSP.
In the current module, we would like to understand
the 3 tier architecture in little bit more
detail, and ah explore quickly take a look
into the rapid application development processes
what kind of help is available, for quickly
develop ah applications and then, we briefly
we will look into the issues in terms of an
applications performance and it is required
security, and ah at the end we will discuss
how a mobile app is similar to such web based
ah database applications? And how they are
different?
So, this is the outline the 5 ah parts. So,
in terms of the application architecture again
the presentation layer, or the user interface,
business logic layer, and the data access
layer, the frontend, the middle layer and
the backend. Now, in the presentation ah layer
or the user interface ah it is typical that
ah ah applications follow, what is now known
as MVC architecture, model view control ah
architecture where, ah the model is the the
is kind of the business logic that, ah ah
that is implemented in terms of ah the frontend
information. View is the actual presentation
of the ah data, that HTML and controller is
one who, receives ah different events execute
actions and so on and then, we will go into
the other layers.
So, here let us ah ah try to understand this
ah flow. So, ah there is a request ah in the
web browser say, to ah to the service. So,
this is the the sequential now, let us say
we are trying to log in to Gmail. So, in one
we send a form HTML form which, has the username
and the password and possibly encrypted, that
comes to the controller ah. So, which basically
controls ah the different events.
So, the controller knows that, ah it has to
now decide ah whether, ah this ah what actions
are required in terms of this input data.
So, it is sends it to the model which, is
ah the ah business logic here. So, the business
logic ah model knows now well. So, at this
there is an application which, ah deciphers
the business logic which says that, ah business
logic required here is we have a password
and we have a user names now, we have to decide
whether this user is a valid user and ah whether,
he or she can be allowed to login. So, the
model has to check on the user data, the user
id and password data and therefore, it has
to come from a database. So, it passes on
this ah request to the data access layer,
the data access layer in turn access the database.
So, you can think of data access layer is
something like a SQL query layer where, you
have formed a query select ah etc., from etc.,
where, user id is equal to PPD, password is
equal to XXX, the database ah depending on
what is found in the database is back to the
model, and the model then sends it to the
control it is says ok, this is what ah I have
found. So, this is the result of the data,
that ah result of the ah request that has
been ah prepared. So, it is says that well
this is ah have been found and therefore,
we have extracted the mails in the inbox that
existed, or it is says that the authentication
is not possible. So, it plugs in a error message
and sends it to the controller, controller
now knows that ah a response has to be framed.
So, the controller sends it to the view ah
of the MVC, the view we prepare the HTML that
needs to go back. So, view prepares the HTML
and sends it back to the controller. So, controller
now has the response which it is sends back
to the web browser through the internet, and
we get to see that well now, my inbox and
mails are all here.
So, this is a complete flow of starting from
here, going ah through this, coming back,
going here, going back here, is the is the
whole rout of the ah request, response that
goes over the HTTP in a typical web ah or
application scenario, that is the there is
a way this application architecture is expected
to work.
So, here I have ah created a small table,
showing you the the different activity is
that happens at the presentation logic and
data layer of different common applications
like, web mail like, Google. So, at the presentation
ah layer you will do things like, log in,
mail list, view inbox, sent item, outbox so
on, mail composer. So, we can write mails
filters of checking at different mails. So,
all the all these happens.
So, for example, if you talk about ah filters
they they might often happen in the java script
itself, ah that trans within ah the browser,
the logic the business logic will do user
authentication, connection to mail server
because, a mails have to come from a different
server, they are not they may not be setting
typed in terms of the of the ah database itself.
And ah then user encryption, decryption and
the data side you will have different tables
to ah ah represent the mail users, the users
like ah you and me all who are users of the
Gmail, the address book of ah each for each
one of us the mail items and so on, and that
will give us the functionality of send, receive
mails, managing address book and so on. So,
similarly I have listed ah an application
for net banking which can where, we can check
balance and do transactions ah transfer funds,
or a timetable where ah you can manage time
table for multiple courses taken by multiple
teachers and so on. So, you can if you ah
think about an application then, you should
be able to ah moderately map it is a functionality
across the presentation logic and data layer.
So, that you know what you want to do at the
clients, and ah which is which is at the presentation
layer, or what you want at the absolute packet
which is on the data, what tables and ah ah
all all the databases that you want to maintain,
and the business logic of how actually this
application will give you the result, how
actually it will?
So, that that is something where, you will
have a whole lot of complex logic that might
come in.
So, coming to the business ah logic layer
specifically, that provides ah abstraction
of that will provide abstraction of various
entities, students, instructors, courses,
ah mails, ah ah your accounts, ah balance
and so on, and that will enforce business
tools for carrying out this. So, a student
can enroll in a class only if she has completed
prerequisites, you can transfer funds from
one account to the other, provided the you
have the authority to transfer, provided you
have enough funds in the account, that is
going to get debited and so on. So, those
are the different business tools, which will
be ah employed by the business logic layer,
and it will support a work flow which defines
how a task will be carried out in terms of
the multiple participants, and ah remember
that all participants may not actually be
human beings, they could be some could be
human being some could be other machines or
other applications as well.
So, it gives you the work flow. So, you can
any any of the 3 application that I just mentioned,
everywhere you can find that there is a work
flow, if you are want to check a mail then,
there is a steps that you need to do go to
the inbox, ah chose the particular mail item,
get the body and then if you want to reply
to that, ah select that, the submit that,
you get a get a new form when you write the
reply, and within that form you get the original
[cop/copy] copy of the original mail and so
on. So, all these kind of work flows will
be supported by the business logic layer .
Now, certainly you can understand that ah
at the frontend, ah if we if we talk about
what are different you know languages and
models, that we are working with in the frontend
naturally our language is ah HTML tries for
presentation, embedded with java script, at
the backend in the data it is the ah the database
and the SQL query. So, it is a relational
model, but what happens in between? What happens
in the business layer which connects them?
Now, naturally business layer you could write
complex business tools ah.
For example, in the time table application
we will have a complex algorithm, ah I know
to find out what ah allocation of ah ah class
rooms and slots, are feasible for assignments
of ah teachers to courses availability of
rooms and so on. So, often ah the business
logic layer, the this tier would be convenient
to write in some typical common high-level
language like, ah C plus plus or java, and
ah naturally you would know from your experience
of software engineering that, if you have
a object based language then, that will be
a very convenient to do that. So, which means
that, if you have ah say a a some ah ah entity
as a a student in your relational database
then, most likely in your business logic,
which is a java code you will have a class
called student. So, the relation student is
in the relational model, and your class student
is in the object based model, and you will
need to define ah ah these ah in terms of
certain mapping of the attributes, which we
had shown when we talked about embedding of
a languages, and this is ah what is commonly
known as a object relational ah ah mapping.
So, that objects can map to multiple tuples,
in multiple relations and can be viewed in
a different way. So, so this mapping itself
we could create a virtual view in the business
logic layer, in the business logic language
that you are looking at. Of course, they have
been ah attempts to ah create a models, which
are relational models which are also object
oriented those are called object relational
databases, ah some ah of them have been successful,
but not really commercially successful. So,
we continue to ah work with ah SQL, and the
relational database kind of things in the
database level, and some kind of a high-level
language like, C plus plus, java and the object-based
model in the middle tarred in the in the business
logic, and continue to do the object relational
mapping for solving the problems. So, you
can here here I have given the points of what
happens? How the objects get created? Application
opens a session, which connects to the database
because, we need to get the data from the
database, they can be objects that can be
created safe to the database.
They can be extracted from the database; new
objects can be created and mapping use to
create a appropriate tuples in the database.
So, it is a 2-way traffic that will keep on
happening where, the business logic layer
will continue to see entities as objects whereas,
the database layer will continue to see them,
as tuple in the relational database .
So, ah there are also several web services,
that can be used and a you may be getting
familiar with that, we will not go deep into
this, but I will just mention that, ah web
services a mechanism through which, you can
access a data from remote server using what
is known as a remote procedure call, and ah
today very common ah approach ah for this
is called rest representation state transfer,
which allow standard HTTP request to a URL
to execute a request and return data, and
a several of the web services are based on
that, and are the ah ah are big web services
which you must have heard of, but I just mentioned
it at this point because it is contextual,
but we will not get into those in in this
course really. Now, coming to ah how do you
actually ah develop applications ah.
Now, it is not a easy process that is a lot
of refer require to develop web applications,
ah you need ah to support the functionality
that of current day web. So, you need several
approaches to speed up applications. So, you
this is in parallel to if you think of how?
What has been done to speed up ah development
ah processes, development applications for
different say C applications, or C plus plus,
or java applications.
So, one approach naturally is to ah variety
of ah function library, ah which can help
you easily get user interface elements like
buttons, checkboxes, radio drag and drop features
in the IDE, ah IDE stands for integrated ah
development environment like, ah ah visual
ah studio, ah front page these kind of which
can use use a, which can create user interference
elements easily you can automatically generate
code for user interface, and ah these are
all parts of rapid application development
tools, and ah some frameworks are ah very
popular, this is for primarily the java server
faces or JSF is a framework where, you can
rapidly develop fill in all the requirements
of the different layers, in in a web based
database application in other very popular
is ruby on ah rails, which allows easy creation
of simple crud create, read, update, delete.
So, if you look at database applications and
common applications will all applications
will at least need to do this it lead to create
data, read data, update data, delete data.
So, you can do that quickly with ruby on rails.
So, if you are locating into really the ah
development of database applications, get
yourself familiar with this rapid application
development processes.
There are different other ah frameworks as
well, another very popular and ah widely used
framework is ah Microsoft specific, this is
unfortunately not portable because, it is
proprietary of Microsoft where, you can use
the ah the dot net ah framework of Microsoft,
which helps you with lot of ah an a resources
ah and libraries which are already provided,
and ah like ah we talked about JSP, we can
use ASP dot net here active server page in
the dot net framework, which provides a whole
lot of ah controls and you have a very nice
powerful id in terms of visual studio, high
were being ah proprietary these ah need licenses
ah and you need to pay for that. So, many
a times, ah many developers may not be able
to afford it or like it for that reason. Naturally,
ah as you designed applications and ah ah
create that, you will have to be careful about
it is performance because, ah certainly we
all want very fast results.
So, if I ah log in to my Gmail application,
and ah I would expect that as soon as I press
the submit button with a couple of seconds,
my inbox will be displayed on my browser,
I am not ready to wait for 2 minutes, 3 minutes,
5 minutes for doing that.
So, while developing the application you will
have to make an estimate of how often it will
be used? How many users will use that every
day and so on? Ah how many, what is your ah
expected heat rate? That is, when the maximum
number of users are trying to use this then,
what is the ah you know estimated number of
request per second? That will come to your
server. And to to improve performance their
different kinds of techniques can be used,
the significant of them is ah called caching,
caching is nothing but if you expect to ah
request to be ah similar ah. So, that they
are results should be similar then, after
the first request ah besides sending the response
back, you actually keep a local copy of that.
So, that if a similar request come in future,
you can you may not re compute it, you can
just send that caches copy. So, it can be
done in terms of ah verity of ah JDBC connections
called connection pooling, it can be done
in terms of database queries, caching of generated,
HTML and ah so on.
It can be done at the clients network side
also by caching pages by web ah proxy; obviously,
if you are using caching to improve performance,
you will have to understand lot more of the
web ah dynamics in depth because, ah certainly
if you cache then there is a possibility,
that somebody is asking ah is sending a request
for which, the response would not be the same
as what it was, when the last time the response
was computed and cached. So, if you send the
cached information back then then, you may
be giving a dated information. So, ah possibly
ah say for example, if you are checking at
ah the ah net banking transaction, you have
making a fund transfer and checking your account
ah transactions after that one transfer, you
would not expect a cached page whereas, ah
if you are looking at the ah website of a
say ah IIT Kharagpur then, ah it will be ok
to cache that because, it is not expected
to change very frequently. So, these are different
factors. So, ah we we do not have it in the
scope to going to different issues of, how
to improve performance? And what are the different
challenges?
But I just want that you to be sensitive about
these issues. Other very deep ah you know
concerned, deep requirement about applications
are the security of applications, there are
this is a very involved topic, and there are
several ah issues that are involved.
So, and ah I am ah talking about only a few
of them because, ah the many of them require
knowledge about several other fields particularly,
in the field of security and an encryption
and so on. So, one ah that is very common
in terms of SQL ah query is ah known as a
SQL injection where, based on I mean there
is if you are expecting some ah inputs to
come ah, and fill up certain parts of the
SQL query then, you will have to be careful
that, ah user should not be able to give ah
such input say such strings. So, that the
query actually mean something different, this
query may be which was just a ah query to
read something, may update something, or give
some different result. So, here I have just
briefly highlighted ah some of those issues
, ah there are ah other security issues like,
leakage of password if there are important
things which are based on a single password
then, use the password gets compromised because,
it is shared or it is ah broken in a middle
by some hacker and so on then, you will have
a lot of ah risks involved.
So, ah you should be you will need to make
sure that, you do not store passwords you
just store encrypted forms of that in which
encrypted forms, ah you have must have ah
observed ah for the last couple of years that,
ah in many cases earlier you could just log
in. So, giving just one password was enough,
but now in many transactions for example,
if you are ah logging into a net banking ah
ah application then, often you will be asked
to provide some additional ah key information,
or you will be asked to ah do a authentication
by OTP ah one-time password and and so on.
So, these are ah common because, ah you know
it is risky to work with just a single authentication,
and you will find that some net banking applications
for example, if you are doing a fund transfer,
then they actually require 2 additional ah
password authentication, one is a special
password for fund transfer, and then possibly
we will be asked to go through an OTP. So,
depending on the criticality of your application
and the potential vulnerability of the application,
your authentication mechanism will have to
be appropriately designed.
Ah there are issues in terms of ah security,
in terms of the application level also for
example, if you um ah if you are looking at
a at a student application where, the you
want to say that the student, every student
can see his or her own grade, but they should
not be able to see the grade of others. Now,
how do you implement this? Now, 2 issues are
one is ah the database cannot implement, this
database cannot ah provide this as a part
of access control because, database has no
idea about who the application users are,
and the second ah if you the if you recall
the way, we talked about ah authorization
in SQL, that is in terms of tables or columns
of the tables, but SQL has no mechanism to
create authorization for rows of the table.
So, this will have to be handled, in terms
of what is known as at the application layer.
So, this is ah where you are. So, what this
is saying that you are created a view where,
ah you are ah ah created a view student text
where, to do this you will have to read you
are saying where, text dot id is equal to
this function called ah is sys context dot
user id. So, sys context is an object naturally,
dot user I d this function called. So, what
this function gives you call to the function
gives you is an information about the end
user identity, and that identity has to match,
the identity that exist in the text I d for
the result to be computed. So, this will ensure
that depending on who is actually the current
user, the same view will be evaluated for
different results.
So, this is ah no not a not a very ah sound
this is not a very comfortable ah situation
because, here the authorization is not being
implemented in the database level, but is
being implemented at the application level,
but ah that is way things a ah because, ah
most of the fine grained authorization currently,
is done entirely in the ah application ah
level only a extension to SQL authorization,
ah at for similar ah you know fine graining
and so on has been proposed, but ah they have
not been ah implemented because, there are
several issues of implementing where there
several issues of how do you represent? How
do you module? And most importantly, these
have potentials of slowing down the database,
ah query process and significantly
So, often this is not a a preferred mechanism
either. Another way to ah ensure security
is to keep audit trail, trail must log actions
ah into it and ah.
So, where you write down ah actions in terms
of who carried out and update, or who access
some sensitive data, or who did a delete and
so on. So, audit trails can be used later
on if the need arises to detect, ah if some
security breach that happen, or if some damage
has been caused by the security breach, that
can be corrected and so on create a trace.
So, auditing is is necessarily a very required,
ah in a very required activity for any data-based
application and audit trail had a good mechanism
for that. So, when you develop applications
you have to consider has to whether, you would
like to support audit trail of course, if
you support audit trail then, somewhat your
application will get slowed down, it will
require more ah disk to keep that trail because,
every transaction every details ah you will
get logged in to the audit trail, but it is
very, very important for critical applications
like, ah net banking where currently it is
mandated every transaction that, you do every
action that you do on your account, through
the net banking is trailed in the banks end.
So, that if later there is a there is some
ah dispute, there is some ah breach has found
then, the same can be recovered and trace
back to the actions, that you are actually
taken ah. At the end ah of this module let
me take a quick look into the mobile apps
ah.
These are somewhat different, but ah it is
very important to ah ah today to take a notion
of the ah mobile app. So, it is a a type of
a application ah software, which is designed
to run on a mobile devise. So, it this is
not necessarily mean that, ah it has to be
a smart phone, it could be a tablet or you
know some small device, which typically is
handled and carried around . So, it is typically
ah specifically for use on small wireless
computing devices, and ah it is designed with
considerations for demands and coincident
of the device. So, how are how is a different?
If I want to use the application or want to
have an application which does my task, but
I want to do it as a mobile app, I want to
do it for a small wireless ah handled device.
Certainly, there are ah if we if we since
the small device it has lot of constraints,
ah there are ah lot of demands of the device,
compare to if we were using a aha web browser
in a desktop or a laptop where, you have lot
of resources.
And also on the this is this is on the one
kind of ah the restriction side and on the
ah other side, ah these devices ah have certain
capabilities, which your desktop ah ah or
laptop may not have and therefore, it may
be you may be able to do ah more interesting
application using this mobile devices, and
there could be really interesting mobile apps,
and as you all must be ah using today use
10s of ah if not 100s of mobile apps for different
applications, many of which actually support
a database at the backend. So, these are in
red are some of the negatives, ah which are
restrictive in terms of a mobile application
the first thing is form factor, which is the
the look ah the aspect ratio the size and
the style of the device, which influences
display and influences the way you navigate.
In a, in a desk of application you will typically
use ah a mouse, or a ruler and keyboard to
navigate, but that is not possible or that
is not easy in terms of a mobile device. So,
you are navigation ah may happen in in a different
way.
The presentation itself may happen in a different
way, you have a very limited display area.
So, you might ah want to stack multiple responses
one after the other whereas, the in a in a
web application running on a desktop, you
would probably have shown them on different
tabs side by side, or would have just shown
them side by side on the display. Then, mobile
devices typically have limited memory, they
have limited computing power, very importantly
most of them run on battery and therefore,
they have one limited power available. So,
you are ah applications will lead to be power
optimized, which is not the case with the
normal web based application, you have a wireless
connection, so which ah may be limited in
bandwidth based on your connectivity and that
time, and so on. So, you while developing
a mobile app corresponding to a possible ah
web application, your considerations would
be very different. So, if I say that ah ah
a bank say, HDFC bank ah has a net banking
application, which runs on the browser. And
it is ah also having a mobile app, which ah
runs on say the android phone then, the their
requirements and their style of ah solutions
will have to be very, very different. And
at the same time ah if I talk about a mobile
app then, the mobile devices often have features
which desktop do not have for example, you
have a number of senses available like, ah
accelerometer and so on which you can make
to advantage for example, ah we I mean in
in many smart phones, if we just rotate the
screen, ah rotate that device, then the display
self-rotate automatically, which ah we use
we use some some kind of an accelerometer
ah inputs ah for that, you have a touch screen
which ah can allow a wide range of gesture
based navigation, which is typically not possible
in desktop and most of the laptops.
So, ah having said that, ah naturally there
are ah there are 2 aspects of mobile apps
as well. So, when we talking about mobile
apps, we have talking about ah stand alone
mobile apps, ah there are other ah ways of
[dev/developing] developing applications also
for example, we can do a typical web-based
application, but we can use a website which
is specifically designed catering to the mobile
devices. So, these ah send back ah pages,
which ah are smaller in size are stack differently
and so on. So, in contrast to that a mobile
app are actually, applications that are downloaded
and runs on the system. So, these are all
different possibilities and even though mobile
website is also becoming popular, but certainly
mobile apps are very, very common in terms
of a majority of critical applications of
data bases that we have.
So, this is the ah typical architecture of
a mobile app as you can see again here, that
you have the 3 layers presentation, business
and data the only difference being now, since
ah you have ah a a a um a device, which can
go anywhere and ah you have a connectivity.
So, this is this is what shows the connectivity,
this is the this is the device side and this
is the pure backend or your service provider
side. So, since ah you you ah your connectivity
is not may not be very strong, you try to
create all the layers of a presentation, business,
as well as data on the mobile phone itself,
but naturally all the data you will not have
on your device ah, you are checking mails
on the Gmail naturally, you will not have
all the data on your Gmail.
So, what you do is you use the connection
to connect to the remote database ah provided
by the service, but primarily most of this
layer of this ah presentation, business and
a small part of the data layer are all realized
within the phone itself, or within the mobile
device itself. So, the data layer is split
in this case, which is very different from
how you do the web-based applications? And
ah specifically, it might need ah customizations
based on ah the kind of ah ah platform, you
are using whether you have using android,
iOS and windows, and these are all custom
solutions ah for that and ah you could also
note that, ah there are different types of
mobile apps one large class is known as native
application where, which is completely written
in the native language of the platform. So,
for if you are doing an iOS mobile app then
you will write it in object C, objective C
if you are doing an android one you will write
it in C or C plus plus or java is platform
specific whereas, there is another class of
ah mobile apps, which are known as web apps
which run completely inside the web browser,
so much like the way java scripts ah work.
So, they feature interfaces built with ah
HTML and the style shades, and they have powered
by different web programming languages like,
ruby on rails java script to PHP and so on.
And certainly there is a third kind, when
you combine the attributes of both native
and wave application and ah you try to you
know. So, you can very easily understand,
that if your application is a native one then
it is not portable across ah devices, this
is not an iOS application is not run on android
and so on.
If it is a web app app, then it is portable
because it is portable across different phone
tablet or computer because, you are using
generic technologies. So, you could ah do
a hybrid app also where, you could use ah
redundant or common code, which is usable
across platform and ah ah add some tailor
functionality in terms of the native system.
So, these are the typical kinds of mobile
apps that.
You might be developing and there a several
factors to considered in the design issue,
you have to first decide on the ah device,
you have to take specific note of the typical
resources, that you will ah your device will
support memory, power, speed. You have to
consider what should be the band width should
it be 2 g, 3 g, 4 g or wireless ah you know
lan, what kind of connections you would expect?
Decide on the layers in the architecture,
select the technology based on the ah device
choice and the other factors define the user
interface, navigation and ah maintain the
work flow.
So, these are very variety I will not go into
details of this, but just wanted to give a
glimpse of the fact, that in today's time
while you are talking about database applications
then it is a very reality, that you will ah
create that as a mobile app.
So, in this ah module to summarize your study
aspects of ah database application architecture,
understood the steps of rapid development,
and took a quick look into the issues of application
performance security, and what it takes to?
Ah what are the distinctive features of a
mobile app for database applications?