.
Welcome to module 21 of Database Management
Systems in this module and the next too we
will discuss about application design and
development.
In the last week we have ah for the whole
week in the five modules we have discussed
about relational database design; in depth
we have looked into what are the different
aspects of that.
And now we get into the core issue of if I
have a relational database design existing
and that is populated with the data then based
on that how do we develop, how do we create
an application where the user can interact
and actually ah get answers to the questions
that the user has or the user can actually
update ah the data create new data, remove
old data and so, on. So, we would in that
process like to familiarize with the fundamental
notions of ah notions and technologies of
ah web applications and specifically we would
learned about servlets and Java server pages.
So, these are the free topics to be covered.
So, we first start with application programs
and user interfaces. So, the situation is
the where we do have a relational database
design it is populated ah with ah the required
data, but how about the interaction with the
user incidentally most of the you database
users do not ah interact with the database
or query the database using language like
SQL because as you have seen it is not a very
friendly language and it is not presentable
in a way which I would we would always expect
or we would like.
So, usually an application program acts as
a as we say as an intermediately between the
user and the database. And it is often split
into three layers as we will say frontend
middle layer and backend. So, on the right
ah I have shown these ah three layers we will
talk more about the this is just a representative
diagram. So, the frontend is the user interface
it is also called the presentation layer.
So, it is the the layer where it is the part
of the application where there are forms GUIs
ah and ah different ah ways to input as well
as get output of the data.
Which is directly interacting with the user
then we have a middle layer or its also called
ah the business logic layer or the application
layer where the functionality of the application
the required operations of the or desired
behavior of the application are coded and
it is kind of acts as a link between the frontend
and the backend and what is the backend?
Backend is a actual data access layer or it
is where the persistent data the database
that we have created ah exist it is typically
large in volume need sufficient access and
so, on. So, in this module we will try to
understand as to how such what are the different
requirements and what are the different technologies
involved in creating such a layered application.
Now, if we historically look at; so, here
we are just showing ah three phases ah initially
60s and 70s where the first database applications
started then the interaction used to be takes
based from the terminal.
And the those to directly connect to the main
frame computer where the data existed through
either a direct connection dial up phone or
proprietary network. And as we move to the
80s; then ah we saw the advent of ah local
area networks to application programs or desktop
would interact to with the database through
these ah local area networks. And beyond that
we have the what we call the web era which
is 1990 onwards we in the that is that is
about roughly the last 30 years where typically
the applications are now based on web browsers.
So, the frontend where we actually interact
are web browsers and that ah connect to the
web application server the database everything
through an internet. And I must ah tell you
at this point that when you say this is the
architecture it does not necessarily mean
that the cloud shown as internet will have
to be the web, it could be an internet which
is created ah with a set of ah systems within
your organization which we typically call
as an intranet or couple of ah organizations
across.
Which we say are extranet or it could even
be a set of systems ah which are connected
through the internet protocol within your
ah lap or it could even be a single computer
in which all these layers are integrated together,
but by internet we mean it is a internet protocol
and technologies will be used for doing this
interaction.
So, web interface has become the de-facto
ah standard which ah gives a very distributed
access to the database enables large number
of users to access together. And ah it avoids
the requirement of downloading or installing
specialized code into that all that we need
is just a web browser. And we have seen we
are living through a variety of applications
which are of this kind ah the banking application,
the airline and railway reservations car rental
hotel booking or web mail systems we will
ah check ah mail in Gmail or Yahoo those are
all different web interfaces through which
we actually access a the required set of databases.
And every even even every ah enterprise operations
the ERP are now web based and that is become
a de facto standard. So, in the web ah interface
ah along with a web interface what has been
imagined of let of the last ah about 10 years
are mobile interfaces that we are getting
ah use to using such applications from our
mobile phone or tablet. And ah these are similar
in architecture and workflow as of the web
application, but ah there are significant
differences to and at a later point ah in
the next module, we will discuss about the
specific requirements of mobile apps in this
context as well.
So, before we move forward in terms of the
details of how to build this applications;
we need to familiarize ourselves with the
ah basic notions of the web as such. So, we
call them as web fundamentals.
So, web is a distributed information system
which is based on hyper text a hyper text
is one where you have a part of the text available
to you and then you have links we say our
hyper links which can connect to the different
documents contents.
Which are locate at other places at other
servers and typically most web documents ah
are hyper text documents which are formatted
in terms of what we know as HTML Hyper Text
Markup Language; you will be familiar with
that I am sure. So, they contain text and
along with that they can have a ah other ah
components like images, video, the text as
ah specifications for font colors style all
that. And in addition there are forms which
can be used to enter data and send them back
to the web server.
Now, naturally when we operate on the web
we need to ah ah have the functionality of
pointing to different resources and this is
done by what is known as URL or uniform resource
locator. So, that is a URL is a procedure
to which you can identify and point to a certain
ah specific ah location of content. So, here
I am showing an example of ah such a URL all
of you be familiar with URLs.
But just to look into the different components
the first component http colon this http is
actually a a tells us the way the content
would be accessed and this is typically called
a protocol http its stands for hyper text
transfer protocol which allows you different
text to be accessed. The second component
ah in this URL which is between the two forward
slash and the next slash www dot acm dot org
identifies uniquely identifies a machine on
the internet ah you will understand this is
the symbolic name and the actual machine has
what is known as an IP address.
And ah we will not go into those details,
but for us it is enough to understand that
ah www dot acm dot org here is ah uniquely
ah relatable to a particular machine on the
internet. And the last part ah which is remaining
sigmod and if there are more and more and
more parts, then it identifies the document
inside within that machine. So, URL can be
used in a um multiple other ways also.
For example ah I can use ah URL ah locator
to specify a file in by machine for example,
I have shown an example of an AVI file in
my ah c drive ah in windows and that is done
through a similar URL where the protocol is
not http the protocol is file telling me that
it is actually residing in my local machines.
So, I have shown two ways to ah to look at
that and ah you will see that between the
two forms; if you look at the second form
you can easily ah understand that the machine
to be identify this is called the local host.
And in the first form that part is missing
because it is by default the machine where
I am running this code and rest of it is same
which is basically the identifying the document
to be ah ah to be located in that machine.
Similarly this such URL can also in the last
example you can see that www dot Google dot
com is the ah ah basic machine where I am
putting the ah URL and ah then the rest of
it is search.
So, which actually takes it to a document
where where I tell the search to be performed
and then there are parameter to this ah form
the parameter is ah q is equal to silberschatz
which is equivalent to same that I am asking
Google dot com to search for contents which
have silberschatz in it. So, this is the basic
ah purpose of the uniform resource locator
or URLl incidentally you may have hard the
names like U R I and U R N in addition to
U R L. So, they are related, but they mean
little bit different things as this venn diagram
shows. So, a U R I can be either a URL or
a U R N or it could be both. So, U R N functions
like a persons name; so, you can conceive
it that way universal resource name and URL
resembles that of a ah persons street address.
So, U R N says what is the name of the content
and URL says where that can be found. And
ah U R I in general could be either the name
or the address or both of them ah .
In this ah context of our discussion we will
continue to use the term URL only, but I just
wanted you to ah be aware of the other two
terms in case you come across them in the
text.
So, we know by now that http HTML provides
the formatting the hyper text links images
and so, on and http provides the protocol
through which the contents are exchanged between
ah different machines in the internet. So,
you can ah select from a set of options in
terms of a HTML ah popup menus radio buttons
ah check boxes and so, on; you can enter values
to text box and once a form has been filled
up that form will be sent back to the server
from where it came and ah would be acted upon
by the server http helps in that transfer
mechanism.
So, the here is a ah sample HTML code let
me ah show you the effect of this in the next
slide. So, if you ah look in here then you
can see that these are this is what ah is
known as a tag and ah it kind of ah the tax
are kind of given in the form of ah parenthesize
notation.
So, it has a has a opening and a closing and
ah these have to have to actually match and
you can see that the ah opening is written
within ah corner brackets and the closing
is write the same tag name, but you put a
forward slash for the name. And then ah between
ah the closing ah opening and the closing
you can write more tabs in a nested manner.
So, here it says that I have HTML which has
a body and ah the body expanse this much and
then we are saying that there is a table.
So, this is the table that you can get to
see and ah then it also says that there is
a form and ah this is the form that you get
to see within the table you can see. So, it
is saying that ah this is an ID there is a
name; so, it is describing the first row the
department. So, you can see each one of them
the the ID is here the name is here the department
is here similarly this is a next row where
it is saying it is 0 1; 00128 Zhang Computer
Science.
So, this is how you can you actually in an
HTML in a text form all these ah details will
be given and when it is ah rendered by the
web browser then you will see a table like
this. Similarly here we are ah I I am showing
a an instance of a form which is use to input
data. So, we are ah saying that ah here is
a is a drop down and it is written out here
in terms of options.
So, the first options student is is ah visible
here if you drop down you will actually see
another option instructor here you will not
see that because it is a frozen image. So,
and then ah I I have a qualifier name and
there is a input text box where you can input
any ah strain up to size 20. And ah once this
has been done then you have a input which
is submit, which is the submit button here
which shows that you can now submit and then
this form filled up form will be sent back
to the web browser from where it originally
came.
So, this is the basic ah mechanism of ah HTML
ah you can ah learn little bit more about
that and get familiar with it. So, a document
name in a URL may identify a a program that
is written that generate. So, HTML could be
either ah at the URL in the web server you
can either have a HTML which we say is a static
HTML or you could actually have a program
which ah when you send the request it actually.
For example, when you are doing Google you
said ah www dot Google dot com slash ah search
question mark q is ah has a value silberschatz.
Then actually at that ah location there is
no ah HTML currently existing which ah contains
the search result, but instead there is a
program ah which will be executed based on
the submission of this form and when run that
will generate a HTML document. And once that
is generated then this will be passed back
to the ah to your web browser. So, that is
a basic mechanism.
So, if you want a new service on the web then
you all that you simply need to do is to create
and install a new program that will provide
that service and through this process we will
see how easily this can be done and how web
browser provides a graphical interface to
this information service. There is there has
been another other other mechanisms of doing
similar things also which was particularly
popularly are called the common ah gateway
interface or CGI, but ah now we have various
other ways of doing the same thing.
So, in this context then the basic ah three
layers that we started discussing with are
here. So, this is the most common way an application
is. So, this is where your your frontend is
where ah you have the browser where you see
that this is the network; we are just in general
writing network it could be internet it could
be intranet and a web server. So, when you
send a request this is received by the server;
web server somehow computes a result HTML
and that send back to the browser and that
is how the interaction keeps on happening.
So, the browser and the web server together
often would be refer to as a frontend because
that gives a presentation that presents the
results the interaction to you. The next is
the application layer which is the business
ah logic where you write and then you have
the data access layer or the database server
and these are the actual disk where the data
exist. So, this is a tier 1 this is tier 2
and this is tier 3 which is a very typical
ah way a web ah application will be architected
and these are the three layers or three tiers
that we will usually find.
So, often ah actually three is not a very
magical number in terms of tiers; it is possible
that you could have more some applications
have more tiers. And some applications may
choose to have multiple functionality in the
same layer for example, web server and application
server functionality could be clubbed together
and when this is done we say that we will
then we have only two layers. So, the frontend
and the middle layer are merge together and
the backend or the database server becomes
a second layer.
So, we would often might want to do that the
reason we do that ah I I will just take to
back to the ah three layer view. So, if ah
the question is naturally if we have the web
server and we have this connections this is
clear; now the question is what is this connection
and what is this connection? Is it necessary
that ah they will have to be on the same server
physically or will they be on can be on different
server and servers could be connected through
a LAN or they themselves could be on ah different
servers ah over the internet and may they
may be connected through internet.
So, all of these are possibilities and ah
the way we connect is the way we will write
the application will be will not depend on
the way these servers are connected between
each other we will often assume that as if
they are ah connected over a net and write
it in a way so, that even when they may be
connected over a LAN or even when they may
actually be on the same machine things will
work in the same way.
Now, one point that should be born in mind
in terms of the http protocol is it is connectionless.
So, this is a very very critical concept and
ah it means that ah once I start the process
I ah have an URL; I submit that and that goes
to the server the server runs an application
or it is a static page server picks up and
returns me that HTML; the http loop is closed.
So, that is the all that happens and when
I submit again something based on that. So,
I have gone to Gmail mail dot Google dot com
I submit that and I get back a ah form ah
which tells me to put my user ID and login
I do that I submit and that when that goes
then there is no memory about the earlier
ah interaction that has happen.
So, when my ah login submission goes ah it
is authenticated in the backend I am able
to login and I am given back the first screen
of my mail box which is ah the inbox screen.
And as soon as I get that inbox ah the HTML
containing the inbox on my browser that transaction
has also been over. So, if I now want to look
at a specific mail it has to be a new query
and it is not remember anything from the previous
query.
So, this connectionless property naturally
makes it makes certain things more difficult;
you will you will ah realize that many of
the other ah connections that we do for example,
if we login to UNIX ah ah system or to a window
system if we use some database connections
they are connected till the we disconnect
them, but in http it is not. So, it is connectionless
every time you do you you have a separate
ah session. So, naturally the question ah
this was I mean the there are there are reasons
of why this is done this way this is to reduce
ah load from the server and ao, on.
But naturally the consequences therefore,
we cannot remember information from one request
response ah loop to the next. So, if I have
logged in to my mail Gmail account and I have
seen the I have got the inbox then when I
want to check my first mail the system does
not ah know any more that I am logged in because
ah that ah session request response has is
over and now I am making a new request that
show me the first mail and I expect to see
the whole body.
So, there is no information that is carried
from one request to the other which ah makes
ah http difficult to work with. So, the solution
for that is ah something which is known as
a cookie.
So, a cookie is a small piece of text which
contain information ah which is identifying
and ah which can go back and forth between
the browser and the server. So, first it is
sent by the sever to the browser and the what
the browser does.
So, this happens the first time. So, when
we logged in my browser has got a got some
cookie from the ah mail ah ah Gmail server.
Then the browser can send it back to the server
when it is doing the next ah request so, that
I can be identified as a logged in person
and. So, the browser can keep it ah as a I
mean locally in in its memory or locally here
and that is a part of the http protocol.
So, this keeps on this cookie keeps on going
back and forth back and forth. So, every time
I send a request the cookie actually has to
go to tell the server that yes this is the
ah Partha Pratim Das who is already logged
in an authenticated himself for checking his
mails. So, cookies are are a big convenience
and they are very important factor of the
web applications. So, they can be stored ah
permanently or for a limited period of time
ah.
Next ah um ah let us ah look into some of
the core technologies that are involved the
first technology is ah is called a servlet.
Servlet is nothing but as you can understand
from the name itself is ah as you have book
booklet booklet is a small very small book
servlet is a very small server. So, it is
a Java application which can do certain tasks;
so, it is an kind of an application program
and ah every time we request then the server
actually spawns a new thread and ah in that
thread this ah servlet would be running and
once the request is serviced the thread will
be closed.
So, this is the typical ah ah server servlet
ah view. So, which shows that ah in the servlet
you are creating actually creating the requested
I mean possible HTML response that you would
like to have.
So, there are ah; so, there are different
details you can read through that. So, this
is the typical ah servlet code. So, it actually
is a is a Java code which ah through print
line will ah generate different ah lines of
the HTML. Now naturally servlets ah maintain
session the way we ah talked about.
So, that through an interaction I can continued
to be identified and the servlet can check
whether the session is on or the session is
already over. So, these are these are the
different ways of ah doing that in terms of
shaking the user ID and ah several ah web
servers ah application servers have support
for servlet apache tomcat is one of the very
popular one. So, which you must have heard
the name of and there are, but there are several
other servers as well.
Now, along with the servlet there is another
concept which is called server side scripting.
Server side scripting is a is a mechanism
where you define an HTML document and to within
that ah HTML document ah can be used. So,
you may have some inputs to that and they
can be used to ah directly fire embedded SQL
queries.
So, we talked about a madding of ah SQL query
in while we discuss about the basic mechanism
of host language and query language. So, here
the HTML kind of a language is a host and
you can embed ah the query right in ah as
a part of that. And ah so, that query goes
to the database ah query server and you get
the answer and that answer is placed where
your original query was there. So, that you
continue to get very easily a my complete
HTML as a response.
So, this kind of a mechanism is makes it very
easy because a it is quite easy to ah conceive
of the HTML and fill in. So, if I have asked
for say ah logged in to the my mail ah Gmail
service then I have given the input as my
user name password and when that got gets
authenticated. Then I get a response which
is ah select ah mail from different respective
tables where my authentication is there the
user name is PPD and so, on. So, it becomes
quite easy to ah actually create the HTML
and there several ah such scripting language
is JSP and PHP are the most ah popular ones.
So, this is how a a typical ah JSP will look
like. So, you can see that this actually looks
like HTML, but inside that you have a you
have some part of a Java code. So, what will
happen the body will get replaced when the
ah when ah the the response has come for example,
here the response is ah doing hello world.
So, when this is executed then whatever is
a result will replace the body in the HTML
here and the result in the HTML will get generated
. There is another mechanism of scripting
which is also very popular called PHP. So,
this is how it is done.
Similarly, you could have ah ah script an
client side also for example, if you are entering
data for say a month and ah in numeric and
you happened to enter 14; then in most ah
cases ah the page will ah immediately give
a error saying that 14 cannot be a valid month;
so, there is a validation involved.
So, in the client side in the browser there
are some small script that can run a most
typically it is a Java script which can too
different authentication which is possible
without actually accessing the data in the
database. You cannot for example, validate
a mail data based on the client side scripting
sitting on the browser, but you can ah validate
small things like ah valid data forms, range
of data and so, on.
And it is it is very important because if
you could not do that then all you required
is you would have send that faulty month numbered
14 to the to the backend server and got an
error and you would have come back and then
have to correct it, but you can do this locally
at the browser itself.
So, client side scripting has a lot of value,
but you will have to have to remember that
a if you are doing client side scripting then
there are security issues.
Because ah it is ah quite possible that if
you are doing things on the client side that
is on the browser then we might also inadvertently
or by a malicious intact actually make damages
to the machine on which the browser is running.
So, there are different kinds of care that
is to be taken for example, Java applet which
is another way of doing client side computation
disallows ah file writes and so, on.
And Java script as I have said is widely used
and it can function to check for input validity
which I gave an example of it can modify the
displayed web page, it can communicate with
the web server to fetch data and so, on. And
it is you should familiarize yourself with
Java script more; it is a very powerful mechanism
to ah do compute the sample things at the
client side this is an example that I have
given.
So, you can read through and you will be able
to if you know Java you will be able to understand
Java script very easily, you could get through
that. And ah so, there are multiple options
of doing such things, but ah JSP has a has
a unique position because it is it is very
useful in many context wise a ah JSP has certain
USP like ah ah active server page ah which
is ah used ah in terms of the Microsoft platform
ah is ah also another mechanism of doing server
side scripting, but JSP is better because
it is portable ah in with respect to pure
ah servlets which we showed you in the beginning
JSP performs ah is easier to use.
Because JSP has the structure of the HTML
page whereas, in a pure servlet we will have
to use print line to print every tag of the
HTML which is cumbersome. JSP ah in contrast
with Java script ah is certainly a different
thing because Java script runs on the browser
on the client side, JSP runs on the server
side and certainly JSP is ah compared to static
HTML is more powerful because it can handle
dynamic information.
So, in this that brings us to the end of this
current modules; so, what we have ah done
we have understood the basic requirements
of database application programs and user
interfaces understood the basic terminology
of the web and took a look into the core notion,
core technologies of ah application development
which is in terms of the servlets and Java
server pages .