Welcome to module 13 of database management
systems, in this module and the next 2 we
will discuss about entity relationship model.
So, far we have had a good look into the SQL
language, the query language and it is formal
basis in terms of relational algebra and calculi
.
In this module we will un try to understand
the design process for database systems, because
so far whatever we have done we have assumed
that the schema is known to us, that some
instance is given to us and then we have tried
to extract different query information from
the relation; but now we will look into how
do we model the real world and actually get
into the design process .
So, after an overview of the design process
we would study entity relationship model,
which is used to represent the real world
whatever exists in the real world that will
have to be represented for our use and final
representation in terms of different relations
the design process at an abstract level.
The initial ah phase of database design certainly
has to characterize what data is required
to be maintained for an enterprise.
So, whether I am doing, if I am doing an university
database naturally we will need to identify
that ah what are the data needs the students
need to be described, the instructors need
to be described, the courses sections time
slots grades examinations etc; but if I am
trying to deal with an world which is ah say
railway reservation, then I will need to deal
with stations trains date (Refer Time: 02:26)
the different classes of coach that the train
has and so on.
So, the initial phase is to characterize the
data requirement next ah the designer has
to choose a data model because, unless we
can we cannot deal with a natural language
or English kind of description and ah work
towards getting a particular schema.
So, we will need to use a data model and apply
the concepts of the data model that we choose
and translate the requirements into what is
known as a conceptual schema of the database
which is not a not a very concrete 1, but
a conceptual one this is what grossly what
I want to do and a fully developed conceptual
schema will indicate my functional requirements,
in terms of what usually is called a specification
of functional requirements system requirements;
if it will specify what kind of users will
be involved what kinds of operations transactions
will be performed and so on .
Now, once we have that ah kind of a conceptual
model that abstract that is a conceptual more
abstract data model, we will go to the next
phase of the design which is finding out what
is the more concrete design through a process
of logical design.
In the process of logical design we will first
decide on the database schema, we need to
decide on what is a good schema.
So, there are principles to say that what
is good and what is not so good, we need to
make business decisions to find out which
attributes we record in the database; we need
to make computer science decision as to how
the relational schemas will be interrelated
between themselves, how the attributes will
be distributed and at a last phase we need
to also decide on the physical design which
will tell us what is the physical layout of
the data.
So, conceptual design refined into logical
design finalized with physical design is our
gross process of design.
Now, in this for the conceptual design we
primarily follow a model called entity relationship
model; that tries to identify the collection
of entities and relationships.
An entity is nothing, but it is its is an
object is a thing that is distinguishable
from other objects.
So, if I say that student is an entity, then
the student is distinguishable from another
entity course both of them are distinguishable
from a third entity instructor and so on.
So, every entity for the purpose of distinction
is described by a set of attributes or properties
and these entities will have relations between
them.
For example, you can say that a course will
be attended by students; students will be
advised by instructors.
So, this attended by advised by these are
relationships or association between several
entities and the model which represents initially
diagrammatically and then in textual form
this kind of relationship is known as the
entity relationship model or the entity relationship
diagram .
We will then use it to get a relational set
of relational schema which subsequently we
normalize; the normalization is nothing but
refinement of the design which improves a
design to make it better in terms of correctness,
in terms of ease of manipulation performance
and.
so on.
So, it basically removes bad designs from
the database and converts them into good designs;
we will talk about this normalization theory
later in the course right now we are interested
only in the entity relationship model, which
will be used for conceptual design and then
will give us the basis for the logical design
in terms of the schemas .
So, let us ah take a deeper look into the
entity relationship model and entity relationship
model as I said is developed to facilitate
the database design.
Get the overall logical structure it is useful
in mapping the meaning and interactions of
the real world in terms of certain diagrammatic
schemas and it employs 3 basic concepts entities
or entity sets we talked about entities, all
entities that share the same set of properties
like if student is an entity, then the collection
of student is an entity set a instructor is
an entity collection of instructors is an
entity set.
So, all entities in an entity set will share
the same set of attributes, will have relationship
sets which define relationship between multiple
entity sets and certainly in the process will
use make use of attributes.
These are the 3 key components of an ER model
it also has a ER diagram as we will show soon.
So, as already defined entity is an object
that exist and is distinguishable from other
objects, entity set is a set of entities of
the same type that share the same properties
and an entities is represented by the set
of attributes or properties that describe
it.
So, when we say instructive for example, if
we say here these are my attributes you have
already learned this in terms of studying
SQL.
So, it has there is 5 attributes and these
5 attributes together or the values of these
5 attributes for a particular instructor defines
my entity set instructor, collection of these
attributes define my entity set courses.
So, these are my different entity sets that
exist that can be defined .
So, a subset of attributes in the entity set
forms a key called the primary key, which
can uniquely identify every entity in that
entity set we have already been familiar with
this concept of primary key the same concept
continues.
So, these are examples of ah entity sets instructor
with 2 attributes and student with 2 attributes
as well .
A relationship is an association among two
or more entities, so here we have an entity
here shown as a student this is a student
entity, identified by the student id which
is a primary key in the student entity set.
We have an instance of an instructor entity
identified by the id of the instructor Einstein,
which identifies any instructor uniquely and
then adviser is a relationship set which relates
these 2 .
So, what I we want to mean is if I say adviser
relates 445532 2222, what I want to mean is
peltier the student peltier is advised by
the instructor Einstein.
So, whenever we relate two or more entity
sets like this we get relationships.
So, a relationship is a mathematical relation
Emma more than two or more entities, each
taken from the entity set.
So, you can see that it can have components
e 1 e 2 en, n entity sets and each entity
e 1 should belong to entity set capital E1,
e2 should belong to entity set capital E2
and so on and is called a relationship we
have already seen the advisor relationship
as above.
So, here what we show is a relationship advisor
by these arrows these lines.
So, what we are showing is this connection
between these 2, show that this student is
advised by this instructor where as you can
see.
So, crick advises Tanaka where as Shankar
and Zhang both are advised by Katz.
So, this group of associations between instructor
and student is the gives me the relationship
adviser as to who advises whom .
A relationship also like the entity sets the
relationship also can have some additional
attribute.
For example, when I say that crick advises
Tanaka I may associate an attribute date type
attribute set third May 2018, to mean that
when did this process of crick advising Tanaka
started, we can it can be some other attribute
also.
So, all that I am trying to highlight is attributes
can be assigned to relationships as well .
Now, how will a relationship span out, we
have said that a relationship must involve
2 entity sets.
So, primarily relationships are binary it
involves 2 and most ah relationships in most
databases are binary in nature, but it could
be that there are we will see later that there
are possibilities of having relationships
which are ah more than binary ternary and
higher.
So, here are example students works on research
projects under the guidance of an instructor.
So, here we have as you can see students research
projects and instructors, so there are 3 entity
sets.
So, if I want to maintain a relationship of
say project guidance between them then that
turns out to be a ternary relationship we
will talk about this more later.
There are constraints in terms of the cardinality
of the relationship, the cardinality basically
talks of that when we have when I have a relation
entity set E1 and identity set E2.
So, there are different entities in them and
I have different associations between them,
then the question is how many of the entity
of one entity set is related to how many of
the entities of the other entity set and certain
types of cardinality measures are very important.
To track and we say it is whether it is 1
to 1 to many many to one or many to many.
So, here the examples or the schematics, so
in the first one in the diagram A you see
that every entity from the entity set A relates
to exactly one entity in the entity set B
or you can say at most one entity in then
they decide B similarly every entity in entity
set B relates to exactly one entity in entity
set A or at most 1 entity and entity set a
if this holds then we say this relationship
is one to one whereas, in diagram B you see
that a 1 relates to b 1 as well as b 2 a 2
relates to b 3 as well as b4.
So, 1 entity in A relates to more than 1 entity
may relate to more than 1 entity in B, but
if you look from B side every entity in B
is related to at most 1 entity in A then we
say from A to B it is 1 to many.
Now naturally since I can put the relations
in any order ah as we have one to many if
you look in the other direction it becomes
many to 1.
So, many to one is from A to B many to one
is where more than one entity in set A may
relate to one entity inside B, but all entities
in set B relates to at most one entity inside
A and when there is no restriction at all
that is any number of entities in set A may
relate to any number of entities inside B
and any number of entities in set B may relate
to any number of entities in set A we say
it is a many to many relation.
So, we have one to many one to one, we have
one to many and many to one and we have many
to many and it often helps in the design to
be able to characterize which type of relationship
we do have.
Coming to the attributes ah we can note that
attributes are of different types, one is
they could be simple or composite a simple
attribute is just one single domain value
like a salary number like an id like a name
string and so on; whereas, a composite attribute
may comprise of multiple parts.
So, consider this this is a composite attribute,
so name is an attribute if I think of then
it has different parts, it is a first name
middle name last name if I think of address
it has.
So, many different parts then street itself
has, so many different parts.
So, whenever an attribute is comprised some
more of the components, when it is not a simple
value then it is called a composite attribute
we will see how to handle them; then some
attributes may be single valued, for example
a person has a has 1 name let us say, but
has one address, but may have 2 or more phone
numbers, the attributes which can take more
than 1 value is known to be multi valued attribute.
So, we also need to specify whether certain
specifying in the design whether certain attributes
are single valued or multiple valued multi
valued; of course, single value attributes
are easy to deal with if it is multi valued
we need to do some design changes.
Certain attributes can be derived for example
age, now I cannot keep the age of some a person
in the database because, with every day the
age changes.
So, what we typically keep is a date of birth
and the age is computed on the day when the
particular query is made to find out what
the age is so it is called a derived attribute
and each 1 of them will have corresponding
set of domains.
Some attributes ah in the design may turn
out to be redundant also consider this you
have already seen this this is an instructor,
which has a department name along with the
different attributes and certainly I have
a department ah table, so which department
relation which gives the details of the department.
Now since every instructor belongs to a department,
so naturally we might want to have a relation
in department which could give the instructor
and his or her department name.
So, if we maintain that then this becomes
a redundant attribute this is not required,
because if that information is already there
in this relation.
So, in several cases there is a question of
whether we maintain some information in terms
of a relation or we can make that directly
include that directly in the entity set and
get rid of that relation.
So, if I have the inch depth relation and
then the attribute department name appears
on both these sets, inst dept as well as on
the instructor and there is ah duplication
replication of the data which we want to avoid
. But we will see the different cases when
which style of design, whether we would be
better to maintain the department name as
a part of the instructor relation or it would
be better not to have it there and have a
separate relation which maps instructor id
against the department name.
Finally comes a concept of weak entity sets
you need to understand this a little bit,
consider the university database example.
So, we have courses we have students we have
ah instructors and we have section, a section
is if a course is large then it needs to be
taught in multiple sections.
So, for the same course at the same semester
in the same year I may have different sections,
in which the students are divided and naturally
there could be multiple instructors each teaching
1 section of that course and students will
be distributed on the sections not on the
course.
Now, consider this section entity, if you
look into this then this is how what we we
maintained we did a course id semester year
and section id, but if you look into specifically
and if you want to know know you know that
there is a section and there is a course.
So, you may want to relate these 2 section
with the course and set up an entity between
them.
So, what will it relate it will relate the
course id of the course with all of these,
but the course id is already there as a part
of the section right.
So, you would say that well it is not ah required
to have the course id ah, since it already
has that and ah it it identifies it.
So, we can can we remove this course id from
here, well if we remove the course id now
we have a different problem.
If you remove the course id then you have
section id semester and year.
But this does not uniquely represent the tuples
of this relation because, there could be 2
section as in the same semester in the same
year for 2 different courses how do you distinguish
them.
So, you get into a situation where the course
the section gets identified uniquely provided,
either you know the relationship between the
section and the course in terms of the sec
course relationship or you include the primary
key of course, into the relation section which
we did in the design and this is not a coincidence
this is something which happens regularly
and is ah is the characteristics that specify
the existence of weak entity sets .
So, the weak entity set is one whose existence
depends on another entity set.
So, if I just say section having section id
year and semester then it is not uniquely
specified, until I have a relation section
course which relates the section to the particular
course id.
When such relationships are used to identify
entities of a particular entity set, then
the unique side the course side which is unique
is known as the identifying entity and the
other attributes in this case section id year
semester are known as the discriminators.
So, we have a relationship between a weak
entity set which is section, we have a strong
entity set which is course why is it strong
because course is identified by course id
itself.
Section is not unless you have a set course
kind of relationship set between the course
and the section which specifies that well,
for this course this is the section this is
the year this is the semester.
So, this is the identifying entity through
which the entities of this set gets specified
and whenever that situation happens then we
say that we have a weak entity set.
So, weak entity sets naturally cannot happen
by themselves their existence dependent on
identifying entity set and the identifying
entity set owns the weak entity set.
So, the courses in that way own the section
and the identifying relationship between them
is necessary to uniquely identify every entity
of this weak entity set or section in our
case.
So, this notion is ah very important for the
design as we will see that the relational
schema that we eventually created, in this
case from the entity set section we did include
course id as a part of the primary key not
using the sec course kind of relationship
and we will show how this design style for
dealing with entity weak entity sets influences
the different database designs.
So, weak entity sets are critical notions
that you need to be aware of need to be confident
of.
So, in summary we have introduced the design
process for database systems I will just quickly
recap, the first stage is identifying the
data items which is leading to the conceptual
design, which will primarily do in terms of
the entity relationship model identifying
the entities the entity sets, the attributes
that define the entity set, describe the entity
set, the subset of attributes forming primary
key that uniquely specifies every entity set,
every entity in the entity set and the relationships
typically binary may be non binary also, relationships
that hold between the different entity sets.
So, this is the conceptual design that will
lead to more detail logical design of how
the relationship should be organized, what
is the cardinality of that, what kind of attributes
do I have, whether it is sample whether it
is composite whether ah certain attributes
are ah derived or not.
So, all those are different aspects will have
to be detailed out and we need to identify
what are the weak entity sets and what are
the strong entity sets, what are the identifying
entities and with that we could complete the
logical design and then we will need to make
it in terms of it express it in terms of a
relational schema.
So, in this module we have just taken a look
in the first part the entity relationship
model and the very basic of how the conceptual
design will go forward, in the model we have
seen all the different primitives required
to represent the reality represent what holds
in the real world.