welcome to module twelve of ah database management
systems, in this module we will talk about
the formal relational query languages. In
the last couple of modules we have discussed
about sql at length introducing it dealing
with the intermediate level of sql features,
and then exposing to some of the advanced
features as well. The foundational mathematical
model of sql the query languages are to be
discussed in this present module.
So, this is what we had done in the last module.
In the current 1 we will work to understand
the formal query languages.
Primarily through relational algebra, and
then we will also take a look into some of
the calculus aspects tuple relational calculus,
and domain relational calculus and we will
show by example the equivalence between the
algebra and the 2 calculus.
So, formal relational query languages are
of 3 types 1 is known as relational algebra
this is procedural in nature. So, we specify
what operations need to be done to achieve
the result and the whole formulation is based
on set algebra . The second ah formal query
language is tuple relational calculus which
is non procedural and is based on predicate
calculus. The third one the domain relational
calculus is a minor variant of the people
relational calculus is and is also non procedural
and predicate calculus based.
So, we start with the relational algebra in
the relational algebra.
It was created by Edgar F Codd at IBM in 1970.
So, you can see that it is ah quite an old
formulation it is a procedural language it
has six operators we have taken a quick view
of these earlier in this module we will look
at them at length. The select project union
set difference Cartesian product and rename,
we will also look at few derived operations
like intersection and division which can be
expressed in terms of these basic operators.
And each one of these operators can take 1
or 2 relations as input and they produce 1
relation as a result.
So, we start with the select operation which
you know has a notation sigma subscript p
is a predicate it is called the selection
predicate and within parentheses we have a
relation r on which this predicate applies.
So, it is defined as a set where you collect
all the tuples all the rows designated by
t and you specify that t belongs to the relation.
So, it already exists in that relation and
it satisfies the particular selection predicate.
So, any tuple that satisfies this predicate
is included in the result any that does not
satisfy is excluded from the result, p here
particularly is a propositional calculus formula
or expression. Where we have different terms
that are connected by conjunction or and disjunction
or or or negation or not, and each term by
itself could be something like this it is
an attribute operator and an attribute where
operators are different comparisons operators
1 of the any six or a term could be an attribute
operator a constant.
So, given that we can write any expression,
which is a predicate and applying that we
can select the tuples from the relation r
which satisfy this predicate . So, here we
show an simple example instructor is a relation
department name is an attribute within course
physics is a constant or literal. So, this
selection show will select all the tuples
where the attribute department name is equal
to physics and all the others will be eliminated
for reference I have also quoted here the
example that we had shown at the time of introducing
relational algebra.
So, you can see that here we have a more complex
propositional term propositional formula where
there are 2 terms, the a should equal b and
d should be greater than 5. So, in the selection
result both of these conditions must be satisfied
by all the tuples which feature here. So,
this is the first operation that relational
algebra has the select operation .
Next we move on to the second operation which
is a project operation where a relation can
be projected in terms of a number of attributes.
So, pi is the notation r again is the relation
and the subscript at A 1, A 2, A k, are key
attribute names k has to be at least 1 and
these attributes will be retained in the relation
.
So, the result is defined as the relation
of k columns by erasing all the columns of
r which are not listed amongst this a 2 k.
Naturally, if you erase some columns it is
possible that 2 rows that were distinct in
those columns, but are identical in A 1 to
A k feature in the relation since every relation
is a set no distinct no 2 copies of the same
people are allowed. So, the duplicate rows
will be removed from the result remind you
this is in contrast to what sql does by default
where duplicates or multi sets are allowed
by default here we are talking about the formal
relational algebra where it is purely set
theoretic.
So, duplicate rows on projection will be removed
from the result. So, we have an example from
the instructor relation we had seen earlier
we are projecting id name and salary. So,
we are removing the department name, which
also exists in the same relation and as a
reference you can see the example that we
had seen earlier while introducing the relational
algebra where projection is done from 3 columns
ABC into 2 columns A and C, and this results
in at least results in 2 rows which are identical
and therefore, in the final result 1 of those
the duplicate 1 is removed .
Moving on that the third operation is quite
simple it is set theoretic union. So, our
union s where r and s are 2 relations our
set of peoples which either belong to r or
belongs to s, or belongs to both, the condition
is you can take union if both these relations
have the same additive and the order of the
attributes must satisfy that every corresponding
attribute must have compatible domains. So,
if we I talked about the second column of
r, and if we talk about the second column
of s they must be of the same type and this
must hold for all columns that the union forms
that is all columns of r as well as s , otherwise
this operation is not defined.
So, as an example we show that to find all
courses taught in fall 2009 semester, this
is a this is the query where we do a selection
to find all tuples which are taught, which
represent courses taught in fall 2009 semester,
from the section relation we do a projection
to get the ids of those courses only. And
the second row tells you the courses that
are taught in the spring 2010 semester, and
we do a union to get courses that are taught
either in fall 2009 semester, or in spring
2010 semester, or both . This is how the ah
union is performed and this is the earlier
example repeated here.
set difference is again just simple difference
of sets r minus s where a tuple belongs to
r and it does not belong to s. So, you remove
all the tuples belonging to s that exist in
r to get r minus s again they must have the
compatibility of having the same arity and
attribute corresponding attribute domains
must be compatible , this is an example to
show to find all courses taught in fall 2009,
but not in spring 2010.
So, as opposed to union in the last slide
you do a set difference to get this result.
So, this is how you can use set theoretic
operation to get different relational results
this is also the result from the earlier example
.
Set intersection can be supported is supported,
but it is not a basic operation because as
it is defined by all tuples which belong to
both r and s. It can actually be computed
by applying set difference twice and certainly
for set intersection also the same assumption
about arity and compatibility of types hold
and this is the earlier example.
Next is Cartesian product, where we take 2
relations and for the Cartesian product we
make we juxtapose 1 relation with the other.
So, t is a relation from is a tuple from r
q is a tuple from s and we put them side by
side to get a tq rho in the Cartesian product
r cross s, which basically means that you
compute all possible combinations of pupils
from r and of s. It is assumed that the attributes
of r and s are disjoint that is a schema of
r intersection schema of s is null.
If the attributes are not disjoint then we
must use renaming which we will soon see,
and here is an example that we had shown earlier
of r and s computing r process, Cartesian
product is a very useful operation particularly
for computing join as we have seen in sql
already.
Rename operation basically allows you to rename
some expression attribute into another. So,
the operator is rho and you have an expression
to which you give the name x and that is how
the renaming of you can have multiple attributes
of x as well.
Division is a is another operator in relational
algebra that ah can be applied between 2 relations,
but it is a derived operation. So, it says
that ah if I have, so let me just ah show
you by, by a little bit of sketch that if
I have 2 relations which are which has a set
of attributes z and s which is a set of attribute
x, such that actually the set z is a superset
of x. So, z has more attribute the relation
r has more attributes.
So, if you take the difference of attributes
between z and x and call it y then we are
interested what happens on these remaining
set of attributes y .
So, this is what, we have this is my x set
of attributes this is where x occurs this
difference is y this whole set is z. Now in
this what we want is we want to in the output
we want a relation having only the y attribute
such that for every tuple in that relation
if I consider all the tuples of s then their
cross product must be a part of r.
So, for every tuple here if there are say
4 tuples here, a tuple here must have all
these 4 tuples along with it in the result.
If it does not have any 1 or more of them
then that tuple will not feature in the final
result .
So, the result of a division is a relation
TY that include tuple t if ruples tr that
is the part of the tuple the tuple that appear
in r and on that on the y part the difference
part it matches. So, that you have that tr
x is equal to t s where t s actually exist
in s.
This must happen for all tuples in s , so
division ah is is a very good ah interesting
operator which is often ah required for coding
different queries. So, it is a derived operation.
Let us take an example, let us say this is
this is the relation r and this is a relation
s and I am trying to compute r divided by
s.
So, what I want is over the attributes of
this is therefore, x this is x this attribute
y attribute set y. So, all over x all the
values that I have, I must have those values
in the relation r, if I do then the attribute
the particular tuple matching on the attribute
y goes onto the result. So, alpha goes onto
the result because you have both alpha a alpha
1 as well as alpha 2 in the set r, in the
relation r.
Beta 1 is there and beta 2 is also there,
so beta also goes into the relation alpha
goes in because 1 is there 2 is also there,
but gamma will not go in because I have gamma
1, but I do not have a tuple gamma 2 in r
if I had gamma 2 in r that will go in the
result.
So, if I can say it again the whole of the
relation s must happen over the x attributes
of r, consider these 2 together . If that
happens then the attributes on y the tuples
would be chosen and that is how we get the
result having alpha and beta .
Let us look at 1 more example, so this is
got r has 5 attributes this has x as 2. So,
this is this is 2 attributes x, these are
3 attributes y and what I have to look for
is those tuples in r where the values over
y would be same and I should be able to get
the whole table of x over whole table of the
relation s over the x attributes. So, if we
look at here this is a 1, b 1, a 1, b 1, here
these are identical.
So, this particular tuple will go into the
result if I look in here this tuple will go
into the result, but if I consider this tuple
beta a gamma which has a 1 over d, but beta
a gamma does not have b 1 it has b 3, so it
will not go into the result. So, if you conceptually
look at that is the reason this is called
a division. So, you get this here you get
this here. So, this is like the way we divide
that this is the whole and wherever it goes
in if the tuples that are identical on the
white set of attributes we will collect them
into the final result .
So, this is the diffusion operation which
by which we can compute the students who have
taken both a and b courses instructor 1 will
be found out from this division operation.
so formally speaking a basic expression in
relational algebra consists either of a relation
in the database, which is a instance or a
constant relation which does not change which
is given. And then we have six operations
of union set difference cross product, selection
projection, and renaming that can give us
all sorts of different relational algebra
formula and also the derived operations and
whatever we have seen of sql can be expressed
in terms of this relational algebra formula.
Now, relational algebra is not something totally
unique the same thing can be done in terms
of other formulations also.
A second formulation which is also used is
known as tuple relational calculus, which
is non-procedural relational algebra was procedural
because you are actually doing the ah explaining
what the operations or you are detailing out
what the operations are in tuple relational
calculus you are specify what the condition
is you are specifying what this condition
is.
So, those tuples which satisfy this condition
form the relation, so p is a predicate. So,
whatever t satisfies the predicate are included
and ah if a is an attribute then t A will
denote the value of the tuple on attribute
A, A could be a single attribute it could
be A set of attributes also and t is a relation
that belongs to r, ps as I said it is a its
a predicate calculus formula.
So, it could be a set of attributes or constants
this I am just included for your help if in
case you have become rusted with predicate
calculus you can refer to the a predicate
calculus as a set of attributes and constant.
It has set of comparison operators the six
of them, there are a set of connectives these
are all same as the propositional calculus
ah there is implication which says if x is
true then y is true if x is false then the
whole thing is true vacuously .
And what makes it primarily predicate calculus
is a fact that it has existential quantifier,
which says that the formula there exists t
belongs to r Qt holds if I can find at least
1 tuple t which satisfies Q t.
Similarly, there is a universal quantifier
where I will say that for all t belongs to
r Q t is true if for all tuples of r t satisfies
Q t. So, this in tuple relational calculus
all conditions all predicates are formula
of this kind and with that we can represent
any.
Relational set in full there is a word of
caution because ah it is possible to write
tuple relational calculus expression that
can potentially generate infinite relations.
Now, infinite relations are naturally not
representable for example, if I write simply
this that r is a relation and I write this
predicate that not of t belongs to r, which
is basically complement set of r now a complement
set of r potentially may be infinite if the
domain is infinite.
So, such expressions tuple relational expressions
are not acceptable as a part of the design
. So, whenever we want to do this we would
like to guard this by putting some additional
condition and we have to make sure that any
expression that we have in tuple relational
calculus is a safe expression, in the sense
that it does give me finite number of tuples
in the relation .
A third formalism that exists that is used
is known as domain relational calculus.
Which is also non procedural and equivalent
in power to tuple relational calculus again,
which is very similar to tuple relational
calculus the only difference being if you
just recall tuple relational calculus. We
are writing ah collection of tuples t such
that Pt that is the predicate P is satisfied
by t here, instead of writing a tuple variable
t we write expand it out in terms of all its
components.
So, we write the values of the different components
of t over different n attributes and write
it as a n tuple and so here instead of having
1 variable t we have n variable x 1 to xn
and therefore, the predicate is formed of
this n variables where x 1 to xn are represent
the different domain values, domain variables
and that leads to the reason for the name
domain relational calculus.
Now, of the 3 formalisms that we have seen
we will not go into ah direct mathematical
proofs, but in the next couple of slides,
I just show that they are equivalent in nature.
What means that if I can write an expression
in relational algebra then it is possible
to write an equivalent expression in tuple
relational calculus and in domain relational
calculus and vice versa.
So, if I can write an expression in any 1
of these formalisms then there are equivalent
expressions in the other 2 formalisms as well
which is probably very easy to see between,
tuple relational calculus and domain relational
calculus because 1 is just representing the
whole tuple as a single variable whereas,
the other is representing it in terms of n
domain variables.
So, their equivalence is pretty much very
similar the fact that your predicate calculus
formula has to change, but it is not, so obvious
for ah the equivalence between relational
algebra and the calculi.
So, we just show a few examples of the basic
operations for example, say select operation.
So, I am just not showing the proof, I am
just giving you some example cases to show
through a relation r has 2 attributes A, B
this is what you wanted to write in relational
algebra that you want to collect all tuples
where B is equal to 17.
Naturally in tuple relational calculus you
can easily write the first condition is you
are doing it on r. So, t must belong to r
and your condition is B should be 17. So,
this predicate will represent the same set
or the same relation as in tuple calculus
in domain calculus there are 2 components
a and b. So, you have to say component taken
together must belong to r and the component
b must be equal to 17.
So, you can see that it is pretty straightforward
to see the equivalence between a relational
algebra expression involving select and the
corresponding tuple calculus or domain calculus
expressions this is ah through an example,
but you can certainly easily generalize this
as a proof.
Similarly, for projection if we do a projection
on a then all that we are trying to do is
we are trying to create a new relation where
only the a attribute exists. So, in the tuple
t the a attribute exists and if I have projected
and got this tuple t then in my original relation
r there must be some tuple p such that on
the attribute a they match they are same.
So, it is the same thing in relational algebra
we said that keep a and erase everything else
here we are saying that if we have been able
to get a tuple t which has a value t a then
there must be a tuple p in r, which has the
same value over the same attribute. So, this
condition is equivalent representative of
the projection, and the same thing can be
written in domain calculus you can go through
it carefully and convince yourself .
You can combine this as in the relational
algebra as well as in tuple calculus. So,
here you apply 1 relation 1 operation and
then the other 1 selection then projection
here you are combining this this is part of
projection this is also part of projection,
but this condition has come from the selection
and get a total predicate calculus predicate
which will give you the tuple calculus expression
for this combined expression of relational
algebra , domain calculus will certainly happen
in a similar manner .
Union certainly straightforward, so you can
do it yourself.
Set difference is again ah very straight forward
because that is. In fact, in set theoretically
whatever operations we have their relational
algebraic definition itself is a tuple calculus
formula you can expand them out and write
in the domain calculus as well .
Intersection plays out in the same way tuples
that belong to both r and s.
Cartesian product is a little bit more involved
because all that you are saying here is if
I have a Cartesian product then if that product
has a tuple t. Then there must be a tuple
p in the relation r the left relation there
must be a tuple q in the in s the right relation.
So, that the final tuple t matches p on the
a attributes the b attributes that is attributes
of relation r and the components of t matches
the tuple q in the attributes of s.
If all these conditions happen together then
naturally this tuple t is a valid tuple for
the Cartesian product. So, you could take
examples and work this out and convince yourself
that these are really equivalent.
we can ah define a natural joint in a similar
way, which I will leave it as an exercise
for you to convince yourself that this relational
algebra expression for natural joint indeed
has similar equivalents in tuple and domain
calculi .
Division we just showed as a derived operation,
we have not showed how in relational algebra
you can write division using the other operations.
I will leave that as an exercise as well,
but here what I show is in tuple calculus
how you can write division using the quantifiers.
Here you can see that here for the first time
we do need to use the universal quantifier
to make sure that while I divide that the
whole of the table of s must be available
against the part of the tuple part of the
y attributes as we said that will be collected
in the result .
so, to summarize we have discussed primarily
the relational algebra with some examples,
we have introduced the tuple relational and
domain relational calculus and through a set
of examples. We have shown that we have illustrated
that the algebra and the calculi are equivalent
and ah I would request you to work out more
examples to understand the equivalence, or
if you are really enthused please try out
proving their equivalence formally as well.