Welcome to module 30 of Database Management
Systems.
We have been discussing about ah indexing
and hashing and this is a concluding module
on that.
We have ah in the last module discussed about
different hashing techniques static and dynamic
and compare that in introduce bitmap indices.
Now in this module we would ah specifically
ah look into the use ah cases, we will ah
check as to how indexes can be created in
SQL first.
Because we will have to use it you have already
known the theory of various different indices
and so, on so, how do you actually tell the
system to index.
And the second is the important thing as to
when should you index and on what.
So, we we talked about a few guidelines for
indexing.
So, that is that is what we want to learn.
So, index can be defined in SQL in very similar
syntax as you create a table.
So, you say create index put a name for that
index and then you say on which relation are
you indexing and put the list of attributes
on which you are indexing.
So, if ah branch can relation can be indexed
on branch name and I may call that b index.
Now, there is a way to also express create
unique index if you say create unique index
and it will expect that the search key ah
is a candidate key because I mean in the sense
it all values of that will have to be distinct
unique.
Now ah this used to be very common to do this
kind of indexing earlier, but now it is more
preferred that ah ah you can use unique integrity
constraint in terms of the create table which
we have already discussed.
And that will ensure that you have that kind
of a condition satisfied and you may not create
unique index for that .
If you do not want an indexes actually do
drop index and put the index name.
So, most database system allow specification
of the type of indexing and clustering that
you want to do.
So, you can create an index for a cluster
also and you can create index for composite
index for multiple columns.
So, let us ah run through quickly couple of
examples create an index for a single column
to speed up queries the test that column.
So, we are saying ah employee ah emp tab is
a is a relation which has an attribute e name
the employee name and we want to create an
index on that if we do that then any search
that is based on the employee name will become
really fast.
Now, while you create the index you could
also use optionally various other factors
which relate to ah particularly the storage
setting you can ah set what is you know what
is the storage you want to keep for the index
how you would like to ah increase increment
that and and so, on what is the table space.
And very most interestingly you could say
that compute statistics now this is something
which is optional, but is very useful.
For example, if you are not sure as to how
your ah data is getting distributed in different
ah relations and how really they are queried
ah you would not know whether an index is
good or it is inappropriate.
So, it is good to actually compute that statistics
in terms of ah the index that you want to
know that by doing this index what kind of
accesses have happened?
So, compute statistics will ah will tell the
database system to keep on computing this
which you can subsequently refer to.
You can create index on ah two columns also;
so, here we are showing one where emp tab
is indexed on employee name eme name and employee
number together.
So, you saying that you create an index on
both of these and compute the statistics at
the same time .
Now, other ways there are ah index that can
be created ah on functions.
So, suppose if there is a query which going
to sort ah based on the uppercase writing
of the e name.
So, if I just index the e name then that itself
would not speed up the operation because while
you want to sort then the e name will have
to be changed into the upper case by upper
and that is every time will have to do that
for every record and then actually apply the
sorting comparisons.
So, that will become a slow process, but you
can do a function based indexing where you
can specify as you can as you can see here
the function based indexing where you say
that you index based on upper e name.
So, what will happen your actual values are
are in ah impossibly lower case or mixed case,
but your index emp upper e name will get created
on the in the order of the upper case of ah
e name and will be very useful in terms of
the sorting later on.
Now, you can like the normal index you can
also create the bitmap index.
So, you just say create bitmap index on the
name and rest of the structure is similar.
So, if there is a student relation which has
ah these fields I can we can create an index
on gender; we can create another index on
semester these are very typical candidate
for bitmap index because gender can take 2
values here male and female semester can take
4 values 1, 2, 3, 4.
So, the bitmap ah are shown here and then
if I want to do a select where the gender
is F and semester is 4; then it is basically
ending the bitmap of F which is 0 1 1 and
the bitmap of semester 4 which is 0 0 1.
So, if we if we add these two we will find
that ah we have the result which is 0 0 0
1.
So, which tells me that student id the fourth
record of the student ID 103 is a result.
So, this is how bitmap indexing can be used
in SQL.
And actually this the whole thing can can
be used subsequently in multiple key access
ah for example, if you are doing a query where
it is you have department name is finance
and salary is 8000, then there could be several
strategies for processing this query ah using
the index values for example, if you have
single ah index ah index on single attributes.
So, use you can use the index on department
name to find instructors which have department
and finance.
And then test if the salaries 80000 or you
can use index on salary to find instructors
with salary 80000 and then test if department
name is financed.
Or you can use department name index to find
pointers to all records that part in to finance
department.
Index on salary to find all records that part
in to 80000 salary and then take intersection
of the both sets ah to get the final result.
So, multiple key access could be achieved
in terms of various ah single indexing single
attribute indexing also.
When we are doing composite search keys then
naturally if there are 2 then ah the indexing
means that you will have to define a combined
lexical order.
So, department name salary means that either
department it is it is ordered to ah indexes
are ordered in terms of just the department
name.
Or if the department name is same then they
are ordered in terms of salary this ordering
in in which you write the attributes in the
ah multi composite search key is very important
because you can see that for the two if if
the department name is same then the salary
will be compared, but not the other way around.
So, when you have index on multiple attributes
say again going back to that same example
of department naming finance and salary being
ah 80000.
So, using separate index is less efficient
though we saw how that can be done, but we
can also efficiently handle if we have this
indexing on department name and salary.
Then we can also easily handle queries like
department name is finance and salary is less
than 100; it is not because as as you can
can easily figure out because if I can find
the equality then I also know ah what is less.
But note that we cannot efficiently handle
if I say that where department name is less
than finance and balance I am sorry this should
be salary ah salary is 80000.
The reason is that the ordering of the attributes
in this composite key is department name salary.
So, if there is if department name is less
than is there is no way to check for the equality
of salary, but if the department name equals
then there is a possibility of checking on
the salary.
So, because of this ordering this will ah
may fetch many records that satisfy the first
one, but not the second condition.
Now, ah you should also remember that you
need a special privilege to create an index
because this is partly in the domain of the
administrators job.
So, you need the specific privileges access
rights to be able to do that.
So, to create a new index either you have
to own ah ah or own that that those set of
tables on which you are creating the index
and or have the index objective privilege
for those tables or ah the schema that contains
the index might also have a quota.
So, that you can because creating the index
means you are will be using the temporary
tablespace on a on a regular basis.
And ah, but with this you will not be able
to create index in some other user schema
for that you need a global ah right which
is the create any index kind of system privilege.
So, also check if you are not being able to
create an index check what is your privilege
that exists ah function based indexes require
other privileges; please check on that.
Now, let us.
So, we have seen how to create index how to
use that in terms of the SQL application SQL
query system.
Now we will quickly take a look into why how
should we index and where.
So, ah if you recall ah in in the modules
16 to 20 in the week four we have studied
various issues of a proper design of ah relational
database system, we focused on normalization
of tables that can reduce redundancy and minimize
anomaly how can we easily adhere to ah various
constraints ah how to improve the efficiency
of access and update a better normalized design
often gives better performance.
For example, we optimizing the ah minimizing
the requirement for computing join and all
those.
So, those advantages we have saw, but the
actual performance of a database system is
significantly impacted by the way the physical
data is organized and managed which does not
come across in terms of the logical design
that we have seen.
So, these are what are being achieved in terms
of indexing and hashing.
So, this is where we we need to understand
the actual boundary to the physical organization
and that is what we have been trying to do.
So, if you think back while you are normalizing
at the design level.
So, those are the startup time activities;
so, usually we will design and normalize and
you know make the create table and do all
that at the beginning of a database system.
And it is really it will really be changed
later because it will have severe implications,
but the performance behavior will continue
to evolve will continue to change because
the design does not tell you exactly what
the statistics of that data would be what
the behavior of the data would be.
So, it will evolve as data base is used over
time.
Hence you will need to continuously collect
statistics about the data of various tables
to learn of the patterns as to which table
is getting heavier which where what are the
attributes on which more accesses are happening,
where what kind of queries you are getting
and you have to adjust the indexes on the
tables to optimize the performance.
So, that is the whole whole ah requirement
all about unfortunately ah unlike the functional
dependency or multivalued dependency theories
that we studied in the design space; there
is no sound theory that determines optimal
performance.
So, ah all that have is is more more and expertise
that you develop through experience.
So, ah what I will take you through are a
set of few common guidelines about how to
keep your database ah agile ah while ah you
are you go through the life cycle of different
data coming in and going out.
So, the first rule I say rule 0 is the indexes
lead to access update tradeoff we have already
seen this at every query results in a search
in the underlying physical data structure
as we have understood.
Having specific index on search certainly
can improve performance, but as we have already
noted every update with the be it insert,
delete or update of values will result in
update of the index files.
So, it is an overhead or penalty for quicker
access that we are paying.
So, having unnecessary indexes can cause significant
degradation of performance.
Index files will also occupy significant space
on your disk and it may actually cause ah
to slow down your behavior due to memory limitation
during index ah computation.
So, rule 0 indexes lead to this trade off
always be watchful about that use judgment
to index.
Rule 1 index the correct tables decide which
tables are best candidates for index to creating
an index if you frequently want to retrieve
say less than 15 percent of the rows in a
large table.
Now first 15 percent is a ballpark number
this can ah vary greatly according to the
relative speed of the table scan ah.
Fast of the table scan you can use a lower
percentage of cut off more cluster the row
data you can use a higher percentage for cut
up ah.
Index tables index columns used for joining
multiple tables if you have situations or
multiple tables are used in joins ah on a
on a moderately regular basis then the columns
are used in the join in these tables; these
tables should be indexed based on those.
The primary and unique keys automatically
have indexes, but you might want to you have
an index on the foreign key.
So, consider that ah small tables do not require
index if a query is requiring unnecessarily
long time or or unexpectedly long time; it
is time to check if the table has become really
big compared to small and it might be term
to index that.
So, rule 1 index the correct tables and certainly
related to that is index the correct columns.
The columns with some of the characteristics
I have just noted down ah are good candidates
for indexing values are relatively unique
in the column, then indexing will give you
a good benefit.
There is a wide range of values where you
can your regular indexes will work well.
There is a small range of values where bitmap
indexes will give you good results.
So, use those in column contains many nulls,
but queries often select all rows having a
value.
So, there are column have lot of null values,
but whenever you do a query then you actually
take out rows which have values.
So, in those cases you can ah you can actually
if you involve certain I mean if you write
the SQL query by keeping ah the ah condition
in a way.
So, that the index can be used that is for
example, you could put a condition such that
only non null values will be matched.
Compared to that if you have just taken (Refer
Time: 17:54) at non null check your first
query would run faster; if you have an index
on the COL X because the query would be able
to work on that index.
So, these are ah things that you should do
in terms of the column.
And if a column ah has the kind of characteristic
that there are many nulls in the column and
you typically do not search non null values;
then it is good it it is better not to index
those columns long and long row columns cannot
be indexed anyway.
So, this remember the rule 2 index the correct
columns.
Ah Then ah the rule 3 limit the number of
indexes for each table the more the index
more over it we have already seen this ah
as a part of rule 2 rule 0 as well.
When rows are inserted or deleted indexes
of a table must be updated when columns are
updated all the indexes on the column must
be updated.
So, there is a lot of cost; so, half as limited
number of indices as will start with purposed.
So, you must regularly weigh the benefit of
having the indexed for queries against the
performance overhead of the updates.
For example, if a table is ah primarily read
only you might use more indexes because the
overhead will be less, but if a table is heavily
updated you might use fewer number of indices.
Rule 4 choose the order of columns in the
composite ah index.
So, you have already seen couple of slides
back I talk to you to the impact of what is
the impact of ordering in other columns in
terms of composite index.
So, the order of columns in the create index
statement can affect performance.
So, the column that you expected to be used
most often put that as the first index.
Because it is also possible that you are actually
not doing a query which takes the whole of
the composite search key, but a part of it,
but if you have a composite search key index
you will still benefit if the the query is
using the attributes from the first part of
the index.
So, here I am showing some example say there
is a vendors part table and let us say there
are 5 vendors and let us say.
So, there is vendor id part number and unit
cost forget about unit cost for this consideration.
So, it is primarily ah part number and vendor
id.
So, let us say there are 5 vendors and each
vendor has about 1000 parts.
So, and let us say that it is ah queried like
this that the part number in such and such
and vendor id is such and such you get you
select all all that matches.
Now, if you create a composite index then
it should be on part number vendor id not
the other way around.
Because ah if you if you do that then queries
where only part number is used will also run
faster, but the vendor id here is not a very
good candidate for ah indexing as a as a first
attribute because it has only five possible
values very small number of value.
So, indexing really does not help here it
cannot discriminate after indexing there will
be lot of clusters still found.
Rule number 5 gather statistics to make index
usage more accurate that is a that is a very
very important factor the database can use
indexes more effectively if the statistical
information is available.
So, gather statistics learn from that we have
already discussed how to gather statistics
from the create index statement.
And then there are functions these are function
names in oracle in your system you might want
to check up what these functions are called.
So, by that you can find out statistics about
the tables and the schema that you have and
use that information to subsequently optimize
the index.
The last rule ah rule 6 is drop index that
are no longer required.
So, if an index might be dropped because for
several reasons for example, it is it simply
does not speed up the queries.
So, table might have become too small there
will be many rows in the table, but very few
index increase right we have seen these are
not the ideal.
So, it may not have been the case earlier
and now it may may be the case.
So, in that case that index should be drop
because it is not helping you the queries
in your application do not use the index the
query you have certain indexes and the queries
are done on other attributes or other composite
attributes.
So, it is not the indexes of no value and;
obviously, index must be dropped before being
rebuilt if you are rebuilding if you are creating
ah new index in a new way then.
So, make a judgment and drop indexes which
are no longer required as an when you observe
that in drop indexes and improve the performance.
When you ah drop an index all extents of the
indexes segment are return to the tablespace.
So, this is basically the space management
and SQL command for this you already know
now please keep in mind that if you drop a
table then all associated indexes are automatically
dropped because; obviously, if the data is
not there then how about their index.
So, to drop an index ah you you need the drop
any index system privilege we talked about
privileges earlier too.
So, this summarizes our discussions on on
ah indexing and hashing.
So, here in this particular module you have
learned to create index in SQL and introduce
few rules for good index.
Overall in ah this week in all the 5 modules
we have learnt about how to speed up ah query
processing, how to speed up the execution
of access insert delete queries in your database
through the lifetime.
And we have looked at various different indexing
schemes, we have looked at hashing and ah
made comparisons.
So, one take back that you can certainly have
is the most important indexing scheme or ah
indexing structure is the B plus tree which
can be used for ah data files as well as for
index files and ah several like SQL server
uses the the B plus tree only.
Now, hashing options we have looked at and
we have seen that it has a varied acceptability
it is a powerful technique, but not all systems
use that equally ah strongly.
And we have then ah made understood that indexing
ah a database or tables on different attributes
is a very delicate responsibility which has
to be done with a lot of judgment.
And for that statistics must be rightly collected
and good judgment in terms of the distribution
of the data, access of the data nature of
queries all these need to be considered carefully
so, that you can really get good performance
from the design that you have.
So, ah on top of ah the knowledge of good
design that you acquired through the all the
theory of normalization and you know redundancy
removal; your good judgment in terms of good
appropriate index design will take you a long
way in terms of making a very good database
system engineer.