.
Welcome to module 27 of Database Management
Systems. We are discussing indexing and hashing
mechanisms in a database and this is the second
in that series. In the last module, we have
discussed the basic requirement of ah indexing
and we have learnt about ordered indexes using
primary index.
Which can be dense or parts and the multi
level indexes. Now, in this ah module we would
ah try to look for ah the basis of how ah
indexing the index file structure can be very
efficiently represent it. So, we will do a
quick recap of ah our notions in ah algorithms
goes.
Where we have talked about ah earlier balanced
binary search trees I mean not in this ah
ah particular course delivery, but I expect
that you have gone through ah algorithms course
where you have learnt about balanced binary
search trees as options for optimal in memory
search data structure and from that will try
to understand the issues relating to external
search data structures for persistent data
and very specifically we will study two three
four tree as a precursor to BB plus tree which
is an very efficient external data structure
for databases and index tables. So, these
are the two topics to cover.
So, first let me ah quickly take you around.
Ah with search data structure now I should
warn you that here I am looking at we are
looking at a little different kind of a problem
here we are looking at search as it is performed
in the algorithms course which mean that ah
when you talk about data structures in algorithms
course. You typically talk of data structures
which have two basic properties one they are
ah volatile data structures transient that
is they are created when the program starts
and you operate on the data structure find
queries and then as soon as your program ends
they disappeared. So, they are not persistent
data in contrast when you are dealing with
database we are ah dealing with persistent
data which stays even when ah no queries being
performed.
And the second which is the consequence of
the first is ah the data structure that you
are study in algorithms work in memory. So,
they work in a small limited space and they
could be volatile whereas, the database ah
the data structure required for databases
has to reside in the disk. So, we have seen
the tradeoff between the; ah on the storage
hierarchy between memory and disk and other
layers. So, they will be brought to memory
and then certain operations done and ah then
possibly written back and so, on.
So, there is ah similarity in terms of the
strategies, but there is a very significant
difference in that that because of the persistency
the data ah structures that are used in the
database ah application in the persistent
data application has to work with a very different
kind of cost. So, when we talk about ah ah
cost of an algorithm say a search algorithm
we will say that ah a search algorithm or
a sort algorithm has a certain complexity
vssr you know ah the merge sort has the complexity
order n login n and what it actually means.
Is a number of comparisons you you can estimate
to do it in sorting n numbers is ah approximately
n times log n, but when we talk about external
data structure or disk base data structure
then your cost may often not be the operations
in the CPU like comparison or addition or
assignment your cost will shift to actually
the number of disk access is the page access
is that you have to do, because as you have
already noted that the cost of a disk access
is ah much larger couple of orders larger
compared to the basic cost of ah different
ah processor operations.
So, I will start with ah this in this module
I will start talking about data structures
which we are found to be efficient in memory
and then we will migrate to seeing how they
can be ah used in in a in a with simple extension
in the as external data structures as well.
So, what we have ah if you have given a to
search a key in a list of n data items what
are the different choices I could make use
of a linear search either items could be in
an array ordered or ah unordered in an array
or they could be on a list either ordered
or unordered I can ah search that list sequentially
and find the data item.
So, I have just shown an example here there
is a couple of data items given in that area
and trying to find ah 28, there are 16 comparisons
that I need to do and we all know that we
can do much better if we keep the this item
sorted in terms of ah in an increasing order
or say decreasing order here it is increasing
order and then we can do a binary search divide
and conquer and I can find the same value
28.
Now, in just four comparisons and ah from
that we have come to the also know that this
whole ah binary search order can be easily
represented in terms of a binary tree structure
called the binary search tree.
So, ah if we compare worst case time here
again again here please ah keep in mind that
we are talking about in memory data structure.
So, here the time is primarily that of comparison.
So, if you look at the different data structure
like unordered array ordered array unordered
list and ordered list and binary search tree
and if you check the complexity of the three
basic operations which we will need in that
in a database application the research insert
and delete you can find that ah the search.
Usually, is order n unless you have a un ah
ordered array ah I mean between array and
list the search is order n unless you have
an ordered array and you can do a binary search.
The insert ah the time that I show for insert
or for delete is ah usually order one, because
ah ah when I say insert is order one what
it means its ah that ah after I have been
able to search an item which I need to insert
after I have been able to find its position,
what is the additional time that you need
to actually insert that item? So, that insert
cost is ah often for unorder array and ah
any kind of list is order one because you
can just manipulate a couple of pointers and
insert that, but if you are using an ordered
array to make your search efficient then to
insert you need a order n insertion because
at the right place you need to move the elements
to the right to make the space for the new
element, because you need to maintain the
ordering that the elements have.
So, kind of we find that between the array
and the list there is kind of a trade off
in terms of ah if you want to make search
better you have ordered array and that degrades
the insert delete complexity and vice versa.
So, to take the benefit of both we the binary
search tree is device to a you expect that
the search will take the worst case order
h cost which h is the height of the tree,
because that is the maximum number of comparisons
that we will need to reach that leaf node
and a BST ah binary search tree if it is balanced
then h would be of the order of log n and
this is what we desire.
So, if you look at ah BST is ah is balanced
h is of the order of log n I am not going
into the theory of ah proving why ah balancing
means h is of the order of log n or how this
order of log n comes if you have ah doubts
please refer to your algorithms book you will
find plenty of that now that naturally now
if a in in the data structure if I am regularly
inserting and deleting data.
Then it is not guaranteed that it will remain
balanced it might for example, if I am inserting
the data in a in a say in increasing order
in a in a binary search tree then every time
the insertion will happen on the rightmost
node and ah if . So, that will mean that I
will have along the rightmost node I will
have a long chain and therefore, it become
like a linear list and therefore, any search
in that will not remain optimally it will
take order in time.
So, there as different strategies that you
have studied in terms of ah balancing just
to remind you there are ah strategies which
give you the best possible worst case time
of log n which is the famous AVL tree ah there
are randomized strategies in terms of randomized
BST skip list there are amortized strategies
which say that I do not really care about
what happens with a particular insertion search
or deletion ah, but what I care is if I have
done a large number of ah insert delete search
operations on the array then on the average
ah what it should be balance on the average
it should be of ordered log n.
So, we have seen all of these ah different
strategies and ah . So, in an order in an
attempt to ah generalize them for external
data structure we note that these are typically
good for in memory operations these are good
worked well; when you deal with a small volume
of data I mean you may be that may still be
large, but is small in the sense that the
whole data fits into the memory and you can
manipulate muscles the whole data in memory
and ah it ah of course, all these ah many
many of these ah algorithms.
Particularly, the AVL tree and quite a bit
of the randomized BST have complex rotation
ah operations that need to be performed the
order different random generators need to
be involved in the randomized BST or skip
list. So, there are other complexities in
this whole ah factor comparison cost is not
the only cost that you have and ah in the
the simple thing is they do not skill, what
external data structures they are not ah optimized
in terms of ah minimizing or optimizing the
disc accesses or they do not scale to millions
and millions of entries and so, on.
So, you need to look at a different ah approach
and ah this different approach ah in in ah
the day in terms of database ah ah application
database structures is called B plus tree
and what I am going to discuss is an in memory
version of that which is a 2, 3, 4 trees.
So, that we can understand the basic principle
of ah such search data structure which can
work ah with external ah data with this data,
but first understand them in as an in memory
version .
So, what is a 2, 3, 4 tree a 2, 3, 4 tree
in contrast to other BSTs or in contrast to
the typical BSTs where ah you know every operation
needs the height of the tree to be balanced
because ah some leaves ah could could happen
at a much deeper level some could be at a
much shallow level in a 2, 3, 4 `tree all
leaves always are at the same level the same
depth the bottom level.
So, height h is the height of all the leaf
nodes and that is guaranteed to be of order
of log n, if the tree has n number of nodes
the complexity of search, delete and insert
all are order h that is a consequence of a
constant height h or or a fixed height h that
ah given n that is maintained all data are
kept in a sorted order. So, if you do a in
order ah traversal of the tree you will get
the data in the sorted order, but the (Refer
Time: 12:13) difference is in contrast to
the BST where every node is a binary node
is a is a (Refer Time: 12:19) one key and
has two children here every node either a
leaf node or an internal node every node is
one of the three types it can either be a
2-node or a 3-node or a 4-node.
A 2-node holds one, ah data 3-node once holds
2 data and 4-node holds 3 data and ah there
they give the name get the name 2-node 3-node
and 4-node based on the number of children
that they can have the 2-node can have 2 children,
3-node 3 children and 4-node 4 children. They
can generalized easily to larger nodes which
can have ah a large number of different types
of nodes and it extends very naturally to
external data structure. So, that is with
the basic about the 2, 3, 4 tree.
So, let us ah just ah go through it in little
bit more detail it uses three kinds of node
as I have said and ah now now let me just
show you. So, if you are talking about ah
a 2-node. So, this is a 2-node . So, there
is one data item S and all search keys which
are less than S around this side all search
keys which are on greater than S around this
side.
We are just for the simplicity of discussion
where I am assuming that all keys in this
data structure are unique. So, there is no
repeated keys the repeated keys can be handled
in a very easy manner . So, this is one type
of node a second type of node is a 3-node
which must contain two data items S we are
calling it S and L and three links the first
is less than S the last is greater than L
and the middle is greater than s, but less
than L which means actually what we enforce
in terms of the two keys that exist at the
node S must be less than L.
So, values less then L go on one link values
between S and L go on the middle link and
values greater than n go on the third link.
Similarly, if I have a 4-node here I have
three values where S is less than M is less
than l. So, now, you can understand why the
acronyms S, M and L small, medium and large.
So, on and we have four links the first link
gives you values less than S second is between
S and M third between M and L and forth greater
than L. So, these are the or three different
types of ah nodes that a 2, 3, 4 tree can
support and if if it is a leaf node then it
can be it can contain either 1, 2 or 3 get
items . So, let us go forward.
Now, to search to search is a simple extension
of BST you know how to search in a BST you
ah start with the route see whether the given
key to search is greater than the key at the
route if it is greater you go to right if
it is less you go to left and you do the same
thing here for a 2-node for a 3-node all that
you will need to find out is between S and
L whether it is less than L then less than
S then you take the leftmost whether it is
greater than L then you take the rightmost
if it is between S and L you take the middle
similar strategy you do for 4-node and search
is a simple extension of the BST algorithm.
So, you can suddenly work it out .
Now, what we will need to do in terms of an
insert insert is very interesting. So, for
insert first you search and find the expected
location where you are expecting it. So, that
is not there. So, you will expect. So, now,
what are the possibility? Possibilities where
you have found the expected location that
node could be a 2-node if it is a 2-node all
that you simply need to do is change that
where 3-node inserts the second item if it
is a 2-node it has only one item. So, just
insert this new item there and making it into
a 3-node good.
In the second case if you find the the location
if you find that it is a 3-node. So, it has
two items you just change it to a 4-node and
insert this is as a third item; obviously,
when you insert you will have to decide has
to whether where you should insert that depends
on whether you are given key is greater than
the key that already existed or smaller than
that and so, on. Now, the question is what
happens; when if you locate the place to be
insert itself is already a 4-node. Now, naturally
you do not have anything bigger than a 4-node.
So, if it is a 4-node then all that you need
is to split that node you have to split the
node. So, you have a 4-node.
So, you have a 4-node. So, you have you have
a data one one here you have data 2 here,
you have data 3 here and you are you know
that the your d has to get inserted in this.
So, you cannot insert it by by changing the
node type because this is a maximum allowed.
So, all that you want to do is to change that
into at different structure and that structure
is called a node splitting structure. So,
we will we will see in the next slide as to
how this is done and we will see how different
splitting ah sequence can happen and what
will happen when a 4-node will split when
it was a root or or the different kinds of
parents that it has let us just go there .
So, what we are saying is the suppose ah you
have a 4-node which is a root now splitting
that is actually doing this. So, you have
to convince yourself that ah enough 2, 3,
4 tree what we have already assumed; whether
I represent this or I represent this are algorithmically
their equivalent. So, a single root 4-node
and a such a structure of ah your ah 3, 2-nodes
are equivalent why is it? So, for example,
if you are looking say if you are looking
for a here then it is ah it say it is less
than s. So, you come here now if you are looking
for the same a here what happens a is less
than S. So, it is it must be less than M remember
S is less than M is less than L.
So, a is less than M. So, you take this part
it is less than S to you come here let us
take a case of c lets say c. So, if if it
is c you should come here, now if you check
here c if it is falling on this link; that
means, it is greater than M and it is less
than L. So, is greater than M you come here
it is less than L. So, you come here. So,
you reach the same link. So, you can see that
ah actually a 2, 3, 4 tree is not a unique
representation depending on ah the requirement
I can replace 4-nodes in terms of other 2-nodes
and actually create a new tree configuration.
So, if it is at the root I can get rid of
a 4-node and replace it by this equivalent
tree .
Now, suppose there are the 4-node is not at
the root it is somewhere else. So, what are
the possibilities the; if it is not at the
root it must have a parent now the parent
ah could be a 2-node. So, if it is a 2-node
then these are the two possibilities if it
is a 2-node, then . So, this is a parent node
which is a 2-node. So, then the 4-node could
be a left child of that or it could be a right
child of that if it is a left child, then
we use split take the middle item and insert
it in the parent and by that process a parent
becomes a 3-node from a 2-node and make these
become two different 2-nodes.
Again the way I ah was just explaining ah
in the in the previous slide you can convince
yourself that this structures are equivalent
for example, if I am looking for d let us
say if I am looking for d in this tree.
So, if I am looking for d that is greater
than l. So, how do I arrive here now since
this is a left child? So, it must be placed
than P, otherwise it could not have occurred
on this side. So, it is less than P. So, d
is less than P d is greater than l. So, given
that if I search for d here. So, it is less
than P and since ah it is we I also have from
this the d is greater than M, otherwise it
would not have come to the; this third link
this forth link it would have been ah elsewhere.
So, I know that d is greater than M. So, and
it is less than P. So, if I combined this
2, then d has to go on this middle ink, because
it is greater than M and less than P and then
I have it is greater than L. So, it has to
be on the right. So, it comes to the right
position.
So, in this way you can ah convince yourself
in in in every search case that ah if the
parent is a 2-node, then you can equivalently
split the 4-node and make an insertion in
the parent 2-node converted into 3-node and
get rid of the 4-node altogether that lives
us with ah .
One ah other case which is if the parent is
a 3-node naturally if it is the parent is
a 3-node then there are three possibilities.
Now, because ah your 4-node could be a left
child a middle child or a right child and
in every case you do the same thing you split
the 4-node take the middle item put it to
the parents. So, parent converts from 3-node
to 4-node. Now and your rest of the split
and pointed adjustments had done. So, that
you get rid of this.
So, what happens in this process in and like
the earlier ones here you do not get rid of
the 4-nodes altogether, ah because in in replacing
one 4-node your creating another 4-node, but
in the process what is happening the 4-node
is moving up it is it is going one level up.
So, again what you will do is in in recursively
the new parent 4-node parent will again be
split and I just split if it is ah it is parent
that is parent of the parent if that parent
is also a a 3-node, then that will become
a 4-node this will continue till your root
becomes a 4-node and we know that when root
becomes a 4-node I can always change it to
a configuration of 3, 2-nodes. So, in this
process as we have shown that ah we can actually
get rid of the 4-nodes in the whole of the
2, 3, 4 tree when it is required.
So, the basic ah strategy is very simple that
will keep on ah constructing the 2, 3, 4 tree
and whenever we come across ah a 4-node for
the first time we will split that and rearrange.
So, that I can get rid of it. So, here what
I show you is a basically an insert sequence
over the next couple of slides where which
is trying to insert the data in this ah following
order starting with an empty ah 2, 3, 4 tree.
So, we first insert 10. So, you get this then
we insert 30 that is here. So, 2-node becomes.
So, the here the convention that I am I am
following is blue is a 2-node green is a 3-node
and red is a 4-node. So, then you insert ah
sixty it becomes a 4-node and as soon as it
becomes a 4-node the next element to be entered
is 20.
But, before that this 4-node will have to
be split and this is the case of splitting
at the root, because this is this has no child
yet. So, you split and you get the middle
moves to the top here as 30, then you have
two children 10 and 60 and after the splitting
you move on to actually ah inserting the intended
20 into it.
So, 20 gets ah inserted ah on on this side
20 is inserted on this side, because a smaller
than this and comes here. So, this ah 2-node
becomes a 3-node then you insert ah 50 which
goes on this side which goes on this side
and gets inserted here. So, your insertion
continues your.
Next to insert is 40 which gets the inserted
here it becomes a 4-node and as soon as it
becomes a 4-node and before the next insertion
of 70 can happen you need to do a split. So,
you do a split.
If you do a split then ah your 50 moves to
the to the parent this becomes a 3-node. Now
and your 40 and 60 becomes two 2-node children
as this. So, it is a same ah information is
represented, but ah now in this new ah 2,
3, 4 tree you do not have any 4-node. So,
in you can go ahead and ah insert 70.
So, insert 70, 70 gets ah inserted here the
2-node becomes ah 3-node the this is done.
So, then you insert 80, 80 gets inserted here
is is greater than it comes here and this
becomes a 4-node and . So, naturally the next
would be two
insert ah 15. So, 15 ah goes in on to the
left. So, 15 has ah come in here which becomes
a 4-node. And the next is to ah insert 90.
So, which has to get inserted here it should
have got inserted here. So, this is already
a 4-node. So, you need to split.
So, in split and as you split you get ah 40
ah 40 was already there you get 60 and 80
and the 70, that existed in the middle goes
to the root and your root becomes a 4-node.
So, this is ah the configuration you move
on to your 90 gets inserted. Now, you have
to insert ah 100. So, you before that this
your root has become a 4-node. So, you do
a split. So, as you do the split this is a
new configuration that has happened and this
is what has resulted from the split of this
ah 4-node at the root.
And then naturally you can go ahead and ah
insert 100 and 100 is now inserted. Here,
you could do adjustments of ah changing this
ah this 4-node into into by by splitting it
and moving it onwards I have not ah shown
that, but if you ah now go back if you just
now now go back on on these ah this whole
whole process and you will see that ah ah
specifically that we claim that all leaf nodes
would be in ah the same level. So, you can
see that ah initial three trees all are at
the same level, then leaf and their level
0 and then when you have had this split then
the leaf nodes ah 10 and 60 are both at level
once.
So, we can see that when actually you split
at the root you add one level to all the leaf
nodes and that is the only time your height
changes. So, beyond that ah you look at this
ah the level has not changed I am going to
the next the level has not changed instruments
to be height 1 level does not change height
1 does not change does not change till the
left here and then we have a case again of
splitting a 4-node at the root.
When the one level has been added to all the;
so, all the ah leaf nodes where at level 1
now all of them are at level 2. So, in a 2,
3, 4 tree you achieve this ah invariance of
ah all leaf nodes being at the same level
by maintaining that the only time the height
changes is when you split a 4-node at the
root and add one level uniformly to all of
them.
And then rest of the logic is quite simple
that ah these are here you can do actually
follow the same logic as of the ah binary
search tree analysis that if there are n ah
n items here; then the maximum height could
actually be order log n; because we though
though all nodes are not binary, but ah the
nodes that are not binary actually have more
data.
So, they will be they will ah the height will
always be log n or less than that of course,
there is ah an issue of ah concluding the
complexity, because now you will argue that
there are 3-nodes or 4-nodes where more than
one comparison is required to decide about
the node, but the counter argument to that
is even if that be the case even if you have
along the path of ah the tree from the root
to any leaf node.
Even if all of the nodes are of ah are 4-node
that cannot happen as you have seen because
you you will keep on splitting and distributing
that, but if all of them are ah or 4-node
also then what will add is simply a factor
of three ah two rather additional ah with
the log n and the overall complexity remains
to be log n will go.
Now, if you have to delete you have to do
ah very similar operations I have not shown
the details, but you look at the node and
ah then actually find the in order successor
ah for that and swap it with the item and
ah then you can do the other arrangements
of collapsing the nodes as we have done the
splitting of nodes. Now I have to do the collapsing
of nodes following the same river structure
and leave that ah as an exercise to you just
work it out at home.
So, if you look at ah if the 2, 3, 4 tree
and there is a time to justify why we are
doing this all leaves are the same depth which
is a great advantage the height is ah order
log n always complexity of search insert delete
all are order log n all data kept in sorted
order it generalizes easily to larger nodes
are and extends to external data structure.
So, what you mean by larger nodes, let us
let us look at that a little bit before that
of course, 2, 3, 4 tree has a major disadvantage
compared to binary research trees of the other
kinds because it uses a variety of node types.
So, you I mean when you change from a say
2-node to a 3-node you actually if you think
in programming terms you have lot of additional
cost, because you need to distract the 2-node
and create ah a 3-node.
If you split a 4-node and create 3, 2-nodes
as ah required, then you have to distract
the 4-node and create 3, 2-nodes. So, there
are lot of over rights in terms of that.
So, ah what leaf if we if we just simplify
that process and if you assume that, there
is only one node type which has enough space
for three items and four links ah we do not
have two I mean we functionally there will
be 2-node 3-node 4-node, but physically let
them with a same type of node. So, any internal
ah node ah can have ah what is ah specification?
So, there the same type any internal node
has 2 to 4 children and a leaf node has 1
to 3 items that is what all that we are saying.
So, by doing this we will waste some space,
but we have several advantages particularly
when you look at this for external data structure.
So, what will happen is if I can ah think
about 2, 3, 4 tree in that manner then I can;
obviously, generalize that it is not ah necessary
that I will have to restrict myself at 4 links,
4 children, I can do do more than that.
So, in general I can say that there are a
node has n children and ah it is each node
is not a leaf ah not a root or a leaf will
have between n by 2 and n children. So, put
n as 4 you will find that it becomes 2, 3,
4 tree and a leaf node will have ah n minus
1 by 2 which is 1 and for enough n being 4
and n minus 1 or 3 values which is what did
you have.
So, if you just generalize from 2, 3, 4 to
n by 2 to n and ah have a a container have
a node container which can have have either
n by 2 or n by 2 plus 1 or n by 2 plus 2 or
maximum up to n minus 1 ah data items and
corresponding number of children then we will
be very easily be able to arrange for a similar
data structure which will have all the nodes
ah all the leaf nodes at the same level and.
So, this is the structure which is ah which
extends very easily and this is a fundamental
structure of what he says a B-tree or a b
plus tree will see the differences shortly.
But this is a basic notion and the strategies
of node splitting and ah node merging in case
of ah deletion and ah the algorithm of insertion
ah deletion that we have discussed here will
simply get generalize in case of B-tree when
we go to the next module. So, we have recapitulate
in on the balanced binary search tree and
we introduced ah a the notion of a 2, 3, 4
tree which is a precursor to b plus tree B-tree
which is which are efficient external data
structures and will be covered in the next
module.