Welcome to module 9 of database management
systems. We have discussed about the introductory
level of SQL the structured query language
in this module and the next we will take up
some more intermediate level features of SQL.
So, these modules are called intermediate
SQL.
So, in the last module this is what we have
done which was part of the closing part of
the introductory SQL the nested sub queries
and modifications to the database. Today,
we will, in this module learn about SQL expressions
for join and views and we will take a quick
look into understanding the transaction.
This is the module outline as it will span.
So, we start with the join expressions in
SQL join as we have already introduced. Takes
two relations and returns a result as another
relation. So, it is two different instances
of two schemas and we try to connect them
according to certain properties..
So, a join operation is primarily a Cartesian
product, which relates tuples in two relations
under certain conditions of match. It also
specifies that after the joining has been
done, what are the tuples, which will be present
in the output join? So, join operation typically
uses sub query, is used in a sub query, in
the from clause we will see those uses later.
So, if we look into the different types of
join that SQL support, these are the different
classifications. So, we have cross join, we
have inner join, which specifically could
be equi join and even more specifically natural
join and we will see there are variety of
outer join, that are possible. There could
be a self-join also, where one relation is
joined with itself.
Cross join is just a formal join based, name
for Cartesian product of two rows. So, you
could explicitly do a cross join, which you
can see here or you can implicitly also do
a cross join, but by specifying two or more
relations in from clause, and taking all the
attributes from there, we have seen these
kind of Cartesian products earlier. So, cross
join here is more as placeholder, in the context
of the join semantics that pure Cartesian
product is a cross joins, but what would be
more interesting is, when we take different
kinds of inner and outer joins.
So, let us start with a simple example to
understand the issues. So, there is a relation
course, which has four attributes and in this
particular instance, it has three tuples,
three rows and there is another relation prereq,
which specifies the prerequisite for every
course.
So, it has two attributes; the course id and
the corresponding prerequisite course id.
It also has three rows, three tuples here,
and if you look at the instances carefully,
you will find that the three courses that
are specified in the course relation all are
not specified in the prereq relation. Bio
301 and C S 190 is present in prereq, but
C S 315 is not present in at the same time,
the prereq has one particular tuple, specifying
the prerequisite of C S 347, which in turn
is not present in the course relation. So,
with this observation, let us start trying
to see what different joint mean.
So, in a join is computed, then in terms of
the two relations that we have, there is an
attribute course id, which is common. So,
once we have taken the cross product, we will
from the cross product, only retain those
rows, where the course id in relation course
and the course id in relation prec prerequisite
are same. So, when we do this particular record,
when it gets mapped with this corresponding
record, it will generate the corresponding
output record. Similarly, C S 190, when it
is mapped to the C S 190, in the prereq, it
will generate the second record, we have already
understood this, the third record in the courses
C S 315 has no match here in prereq..
So, that will not feature in the output. Similarly,
in the prereqs C S 347 that exist has no match
in courses. So, that also will not appear
in the output and also in the output you find
that the course id has actually featured twice.
This is the first column course id comes from
course. So, it should more formally be called
course dot course id whereas, the second one
comes from prereq. So, it should that should
formally be called prereq dot course id.
Now, if in addition to saying that, this is
an inner join, if I also specify the word
natural, I can say natural here, if say natural,
then this second duplicate attribute course
id will be dropped from the output that becomes
a natural join, inner join as the name suggests,
finds out the inner part of the two relations..
So, if we look at the two relations as A and
B only those records, which are both have
instance in A as well as B, in terms of equality
of this course id attribute will come in the
output. So, this is the basic type of join,
inner join which is most commonly used.
Now, we can extend this into a different kind
of join, known as outer join in the inner
join. As you have seen that courses that exist
in the course relation, but are not there
in the prereq or the ones that exist in the
prereq and is not there in the course are
not featuring in the final inner join output.
So, there is some loss of information in terms
of this. So, why we are doing this we can
compute and add tuples from one relation that
may not match with the with any tuple in the
other relation and if we want to do that then
naturally for the other attributes of that
tuple in the target relation we will not know
the values. So, we will use null values this
is the basic idea of outer join..
So, let us see what it specifically means?
We first talked about left outer join, left
in the sense that we have, this is how it
is written. Left outer join is a sequence
of commands that you give, you are also saying
it is natural, which means that the common
attribute will not feature twice in the output
and this is the left relation and this is
the right relation. So, left outer join specifies
that in the output all records of the left
relation, in this case the course relation
must feature..
So, naturally when we do the join, we will
get these two records as we have got in terms
of the inner join, in terms of course 315
the C S, C S 315, the third course there is
no instance in the prereq, we will still have
that in the output, but since the prereq value
for that, the prerequisite value is not known,
the prerequisite id will be set to null here.
So, left outer join ensure that, all relations
of the left relation, all tuples of the left
relation will necessarily feature in the output
and that is a reason. If you see in the Venn
diagram, the whole of this set, A is shown
whereas, this part certainly will not feature..
Now, similarly we can have a right outer join,
where the concept is the same except that.
Now, we ensure that all records of the right
relation, in this case the prereq relation
will feature and therefore, C S 2347 for which
there is no entry in the course relation will
also come as a record and since we do not
know the title department name and credits
for these fields, we will put them as null
and this again is a natural one. So, course
id is featuring only once. So, you will understand
that since, we have a left version and we
have a right version.
We can actually have a full version as well.
So, if we look into the join relations in
general, it takes two relations and returns
a result and those additional operations are
used in the sub query in from and there is
a set of join conditions. So, these are the
join conditions that we are specifying, whether
it is natural and we will soon see that we
can actually not depend only on the attributes
that are common, we can actually specify that
which attributes should be used in computing
the joint. So, those are on condition and
the using clause, we will just illustrate
them soon and finally, there are four types
of join that can happen, that is the inner
join. We have seen the left outer join, right
outer join and we will soon see the full outer
join..
So, full outer join as you must have guessed
will ensure that you get certainly the tuples
from the inner join, which is here, you will
get the tuple from the left outer join that
is here, that is a tuple which exists in course
and there is no corresponding matching tuple
in the prereq and you will also get the tuple
from the right outer join, that is for tuple,
which exists in the prereq relation, but there
is no corresponding tuple in the course relation
and corresponding missing values are all set
to null. So, these three kinds of outer join
are possible.
So, you can also specify join by saying that
explicitly saying what attribute we want to
join on and if you specify that, then you
are saying it is a course inner join prereq.
This part was same then you are putting an
on clause, saying in the on clause, you will
have to provide a predicate that is, which
field should equate or match with what field.
So, you are saying course dot course id is
equal to prereq dot course id.
So, this result incidentally happens to be
same as just doing the inner join, but we
are illustrating that, on clause can explicitly
use. For example, between the two relations,
we have more than one common attribute, but
we may want to actually do the inner join
based on only one of them or equality on two
of them and so on..
So, this kind of a join, where inner join,
where you set two fields to be equal or two
or more fields to be equal is also known as
equi join and since we have not specified
natural, you can again observe, then the course
id attribute has occurred twice. If it was
said natural then the second course id attribute
would not have come in the result, this is
a showing. The left outer join in terms of
on clause and we have seen similar results.
And now, this can be seen in terms of the
on clause as well, and you can see in that
second course id field. This entry is null,
because actually you do not have that in the
prerequisite set and; obviously, this set
will be null, this field will be null. So,
this is another example, showing you the natural
right outer join, this is you, showing you
full outer join and we are showing the use
of the using clause. We can say using and
put a set of attributes and the meaning is
the join will be performed, based on those
attributes. So, here in this case again the
join will be based on course id.
So, that was about different kinds of join
that we can do, which we going forward. We
will see that form, a very critical has a
very critical place, in terms of query formulation.
Now, we take you to a different concept known
as views now.
We have seen that. So, far we have been computing
certain query results, based on one or more
relations one or more instances. Now, in some
cases, we may want the results to be restrictive
in terms of based on the user or based on
the context, in which the result should be
used. So, we may not want all fields of a
result to be visible to all the users or to
the application. So, we may not expose the
whole logical model and in those cases, we
introduce a view. So, here we are showing
one, where, from the instructor relation,
we are only picking up three fields and we
are not picking up the salary field..
Now, you would think that, well this is what
we can do in terms of the normal query and
certainly then, what is the point of using
this? Now, what we can do is, we can create
this not adjust as a query, but as a view
one, once we create this as a view, it actually
this query expression is treated as what is
known as a view expression and every time
you want to use that view. The actual tuples
in that view are computed, but this is not
actually a relation that exists in the database.
So, it is a kind of, can be thought of as
a kind of virtual relation, which exists,
which can be seen only when you use that.
So, there is a subtle, but very strong difference
between, actually computing a result, through
a select query and defining a view, based
on a select query and then making use of the
view, as if it were actually a relation that
existed. So, to do this, this is how we go
about. It is the send text, is very similar
to the create table. So, you do a create view
give a name and then you specify as is the
connective and specify the query expression,
which is an SQL query, which will let you
compute the view, every time you actually
need it..
So, this is a view name, once a view is defined,
the view name can be used as a virtual relation,
it can be used exactly as we use any of the
really existing relation, the conceptual relations
that we have created, through create table.
So, it is the difference, this is what needs
to be understood very well, the view definition
is not the same as creating a new relation,
once you create the new relation, the time
you have created it, you get the result and
that result is explicitly available as a set
of tuples as a table rather a view is a definition,
which you stored in the database as an expression.
So, every time you make use of that view,
at that time the set of tuples are computed.
It is not existing in the database as stored
like the real relations and based on that
computation, all the rest of the query will
actually be executed.
So, let us take a quick look, this is a create
view, we have created the view of a, of view
called faculty, from instructor relation.
Instructor relation is the real one, I existing
one and faculty is a view expression being
created and in that, what we have done? Simply,
we have taken a done, a projection, we have
lived left out the salary field. Now, we can
make use of that view, you can see that we
are doing from faculty..
So, this actually is a view, but this behaves
as if this is varying relation. So, from faculty
we are trying to find out the name of all
those faculty; who belong to the biology department.
So, what will happen, when they want to execute
this query? This will refer to this view.
So, to execute this query, it will have to
first execute this query, get the temporary
virtual instance of the virtual relation,
created and based on that, this query will
be computed and the results will be given
accordingly.
So, that is the basic purpose of the view
that the whole thing, the whole view expression
remains as an abstraction in the database
and computed whenever it is used. So, this
is showing you another view, which shows certain
computed information. For example, we are
creating a view for departmental total salary,
which will show as two fields department name
and total salary, which has been created by
aggregation..
So, anytime we make use of this view in a
from clause, we will get, we will feel as
if such a relation really exists where the
department name and the total salary of the
instructors in that department are stored,
but it really does not exist. It is computed
whenever it is needed, whenever it is used,
you can actually use views to create other
views.
For example, this is one view which is the
view of physics fall 2009, which are all courses
that are offered in physics, from the physics
department in the semester fall of year 2009
and using that we can create another view.
See here again, we are in the, from clause
we are using this view. So, creating this
using this view, we are creating yet another
view, which shows the courses that ran in
the Watson building. So, views can be used
as I have already said as any other.
Actual relation, but they do not really exist.
So, if you expand out, if you just put the
physics fall 2009 expression, within the view
definition of physics for 2009 Watson, this
is your earlier view relation. So, this is
known as view expansion. So, this is actually
the query that, you are executing and that
has a lot of value.
So, as we have said views can be defined indirectly
from one relation. So, these are called direct
dependence or they could be defined in terms
of a chain of relations v one in terms of
v 2 v 2 in terms of v 3 and. So, on and a
view relation can be recursive also that a
view could be in terms of itself.
A lot of power view expansion is the process
that SQL uses to evaluate a view. So, I would
request you to study this and understand that
this process works. This is pretty much like
pseudo code C program.
Now, moving to recursive views, the views
where the same relation can be used in the
view to define another view, we need like
every other recursive structure. We need first
a non-recursive statement, which is called
the seed statement. we need a recursive statement,
which can recur, we need a connection operator,
which can connect the non-recursive and the
recursive results together put them together,
the only connective that is valid is union,
all that is multi set union and we also need
some kind of a terminal condition to guarantee
that the recursion really a terminus, it does
not go on forever.
So, let us take an example. So, this is in
context of a relation flights, where the four
fields are as specified and there is an instance
shown, which show that different source destination
of different carriers, carrying people from
one source to the other destination and what
do you want to find is all destinations that
can be reached from Paris. Now, you can see
that from Paris, if I can reach Detroit and
from Detroit I can reach San Jose, then I
can actually reach San Jose from Paris. So,
that is the basic reach ability. So, that
will necessarily, if I want to compute that,
then I will be able to compute this very easily
by doing natural join of flights with flights
provided, I take say source..
Let us compute it like this, flights f 1 join,
flights f 2 and I will have f 1 dot destination
equal to f 2 dot sources. So, the idea is
if something goes from Paris to Detroit that
is in f 1 and if some flight goes from Detroit
to San Jose that is in f 2, then the destination
in f 1 and the source in f 2 have to be equated.
So, if we do this kind of a self equi join,
then we will be able to find out all flights
that go from Paris to San Jose or all places
that you can reach from Paris in one hop.
Naturally, once you reach, once you do that
then you may be able to go to another destination
in two hops and once you do that then, you
may be able to reach another, yet another
destination in three hops and so on. So, we
do not really know how many hops, maximum
would be required to compute this reachability
information. So, that is the reason we need
to make use of the recursion and so, this
is how we express it.
So, if we look into this, we are specifying
that is a recursive view. It will happen with
itself, this is the name and this is what
we want to compute source destination and
we take another dummy attribute kind of which
specify the depth of recursion. So, the present
instance of the relation is at depth 0.
So, which defines your non recursive seat
part so, it says select. So, you have renamed
is at flights as route, you are specified
that it has to start from Paris and you can
find out the source destination pair at depth
0, then you specify the recursive part that
is the second hop has to be defined. So, we
are saying that, if you had the reachability
then call, let us call it in one. This reachability
maybe in one hop that is a depth 0 maybe in
2 hops that is a depth 1 maybe at 3 hops;
that is a depth 2 and you take another instance
of flight as out 1 and what you need is the
destination in the first in one has to be
same as the source in the other..
So, that they get connected and then you output
the source from the first one destination
from the second one and naturally the depth
has got incremented, because you have done
added one more hop and so, this is the and
you add another condition saying that in one
dot depth should be less than equal to 100.
This is as I mentioned is a terminal condition
which makes sure that, you do not get into
infinite recursion. So, this view, recursive
view cannot be used to compute any reachability,
which has more than 101 hops.
So, that is to be noted and finally, we need
to connect these two results, which is the
initial start seed and the recursive one.
So, this is the connection operator.
So, this is basically the idea of the recursive
view, those of you who are more familiar with
discrete structure, would have known among
relations in some more depth, you would know
that, we can define a transitive closure of
a binary relation. So, this recursive view
is necessarily computing the transitive closure
from the flights relation. So, this is the
instance of the flights and on the final computation,
this is what you get. This gives you all the
destinations that can eventually be reached
from the source Paris.
So, the recursive is very powerful in the
sense that without recursion a non-recursive
version can only find flights up to a certain
number of hops and whatever ma query you write
it is always possible to write out a database
instance which will have more hops and your
query will necessarily fail.
So, we make use of the recursion here to make
sure that you can actually extend this to
whatever depth you want and to compute this
we keep on computing till no changes are possible
and in that sense this recursive views are
said to be monotonic in that every time you
compute your result necessarily becomes larger
and that is the reason you for the purpose
of being monotonic you are actually making
use of the union all. So, that makes it all
inclusive
So, now, if we go and this is the instance
and this you can. Here, I have shown that
how the iteration actually happens in the
iteration 0, in the flights itself, you had
three destinations, then you add two more
in iteration 1, in iteration 2, you do not
add anything else. So, your result henceforth
will not change. So, you have reached a fixed
point and you have computations, are over.
You can also update a view you can insert
a record directly into a view, but since view
only is partial information on the relation,
when you insert into a view since, view is
virtual. There will have to be an insertion,
in the real relation and in the real relation
you may not know certain fields. So, if you
are doing this insertion into faculty, which
is a view of instructor, then the salary field
is not known. So, in the actual instructor
a null will have to get inserted in the salary
field. So, the salary field needs to be null
able kind of field so updates on views have
certain restrictions.
So, there are some more instances that I have
given, which you can study and try to understand
that what the difficulties of updating on
the view are. So, it can be done, but it has
to be done in a restrictive sense. So, these
are the different conditions that has to happen
for views to be updated. So, please go through
these slides to understand what are there
in terms of the views? Finally, view is a
virtual relation, but it can be materialized
also, that is materializing is basically computing
a physical relation at the at the instance
of the view, but naturally if you materialized
then there is a certain point of time, where
you have materialized where you have made
it into a physical relation and hence, if
your original source data in the view changes
in future the materialized view also need
to be updated otherwise, your data will get
bad.
Finally, in this module, we mentioned that,
there is something called transactions, which
we will take up at a later stage, in much
depth. This is just to get you familiar with
atom a transaction is a unit of work, which
is usually atomic, which is either fully executed
or if it fails, it will be rolled back as
if it never occurred and this is required
for isolation in concurrent transactions.
So, we will talk about this lot more when
we take up concurrency and related issues..
So, come transactions implicitly begin and
they end by either committing the work that
they have successfully finished or rolling
back that, this cannot be done. So, there
are some features in the SQL for doing transactions
and, but usually you can transactions, commit
by default and the only it is exceptions,
when the rollback is happening and we will
see more of that later.
So, to summarize in this module, we have learnt
about two important SQL features in terms
of join and views and we just introduced the
basic notion of committing transactions .