welcome to module three of database management
systems course we started discussions introducing
the database management systems in module
two this is the second and concluding part
of that discussion so ah this is what these
are the aspects that we are discussed earlier
starting from level of abstraction to the
outline of database design in the current
module we would like to understand the modules
of database management systems little bit
more and we will try to familiarize with the
concept of major components of database engine
will elaborate on those and will familiarize
so with the basic ah architecture of a database
management system some of the internal components
and we will present a brief historical perspective
of the d b m s so this is the ah outline that
we will follow so we have already discussed
about the database design i would like to
raise a few further issues about that so we
have seen that there is a logical design which
is driven by the business decisions and refined
by the computer science decisions there is
a physical design as well and based on that
we had ah at presented this particular table
asking whether this database is this is whether
this is a good design or or not
so let us ah have a little look into this
for example ah we have introduced the department
name and the building in which the department
is housed so if we look at there are multiple
instructors say let us say professor einstein
ah who teaches in the physics department that
is housed in the watson building and if we
look through there is a professor gold who
also teaches in the physics department and
naturally that is housed in the watson building
now the question is so physics department
if it is housed in the watson building then
all the instructors in this in this table
all the instructors who are part of the physics
department would have their department housed
in the watson building so there is a certain
issue of between these two there are certain
issue of redundancy that is the same information
is given more than once which is not a very
desirable thing the consequence of this could
be suppose tomorrow the university decides
to move this ah physics department from watson
to the taylor building this will mean that
once this is moved then this watson will have
to be changed to taylor also this watson will
also have to be changed to taylor all instances
of watson that correspond to the physics department
in this table will have to be changed to taylor
and that is not a good scenario so it is not
only that we have redundancy we have potential
for anomaly that is we might the application
program the application programmer might forget
to update the building say for this entry
then we will be in an inconsistent database
so to put it in simple terms that this is
not a good design and there are several issues
to consider in terms of whether some design
is good or some design needs refinement so
need to come up with a methodology ah to ensure
that each of the relations in the database
is good so we primarily follow two approaches
in doing this one is using the entity relationship
model which models the enterprise is a collection
of entities or concepts or if you are familiar
with the object orientation classes and the
relationships that hold between these entities
so in a university database the entities are
students courses teachers and the relationships
are a teacher teaches a set of courses a student
attends a set of courses and so on the teachers
supervise a set of students for projects and
so on and then represent them diagrammatically
in terms of a er diagram entity relationship
diagram and once that has been done then we
try to follow a certain normalization theory
this normalization theory tries to capture
that what are the properties that must hold
in this database design that must be satisfied
on this database design in terms of what is
known as database dependencies there are varied
forms of dependencies functional dependencies
multi value dependencies joint dependencies
and so on and try to formalize and evaluate
whether a design is good or it is bad test
them for quality and then normalize to make
them better make them the best possible that
can happen
so that is this is something ah that is starting
from the entity relationship model which captures
the real world to the actual database schema
there is a process of representation and then
ah capturing of ground truths that hold in
the database should hold in the database system
and then normalize the database is a basic
requirement of the design approach we have
talked about object relational data models
for a few more points about that that in a
relational model everything is flat every
value is atomic in the sense that everything
if you ah look back and think in terms of
c then every field is a value which can be
a simple you know built in type like integer
like ah fixed length string variable length
string a floating point number like that but
i cannot have a composite you know ah object
kind of fields but in a relational data model
we extend in the object relational data model
we extend the relational model by including
the object orientation and the constituent
constructs ah to deal with added data types
higher data types ah where attributes are
allowed to have complex types non atomic values
that may allow things like nested relation
that is a value could itself be a relation
could itself be a table and but we try to
preserve the relational foundation ah and
we will see what those foundations mean and
provide upward compatibility to to existing
relational databases
so this is what the basic concept of object
relational data model saw and as i said that
we will just glimpse through it but this is
not the primary ah objective that we will
try to cover in contrast the x m l extensible
markup language was , defined by w three c
and it was originally intended for marking
up document languages not as it is not it
was not designed as a database language it
was designed for marking up so it is kind
of saying that this particular element ah
should be put in capital this should be in
blue colour this means a verb this means a
paragraph there should be a page break here
those kind of markups but subsequently it
turned out that the way x m l deals ah with
different components in terms of tags and
the ability to create nested tags makes a
great language for exchange of data as i explained
in the last module also so it is become the
basis for all kinds of new generation data
interchange format so as i explained that
any database should be able to convert the
data instances of the tables in terms of corresponding
x m l format and then you take it to some
other database where you with which you are
intending to interchange the data and that
target database should be able to import from
that x m l structure and it becomes it is
become widely available that you have different
tools for parsing browsing and querying x
m l content document data and so on
so if you are ah familiar with c programming
i hope so you are ah you can look up certain
x m l parsing and try out there are great
tools to learn ah moving on let us briefly
look at what is the core of a database management
system the database engine the database engine
primarily contains three major components
the storage manager the query processing engine
sub engine and the transaction manager the
storage manager is a is a module or a collection
of modules in a database management system
that provide the interface between the low
level data and the application program so
we have looked at the storage manager is the
one which is a bridge between the physical
level of abstraction and the logical level
of abstraction then finally to the view level
of abstraction so the storage manager has
to deal with interactions with the operating
system on which the d b m s is kept the file
manager of the operating system it is responsible
for efficient storage retrieval update of
the data it is responsible to make sure that
if there are certain problems in the file
system then the data is not corrupted and
so on
so the issues certainly that involve are the
access to the storage the organization of
the files and very importantly indexing and
hashing and we will talk about the concept
of indexing later in the course it primarily
says that if i want to ah for example you
can simply understand that if you are if you
have a large chunk of data that you want to
organize for efficient search then now can
use the binary search tree in simple algorithm
terms the binary search tree needs to be organized
in terms of one data component we say that
well there is one value based on which you
can say that comparison is done so that at
every node if that value is smaller you go
to the left sub tree if that value is larger
you go to the right sub tree and so on so
in a if we want to organize the records of
a database system in terms of such a binary
search tree then the question certainly is
which field do i use for the search tree comparison
now whatever field i used for search tree
comparison on that field the searching would
be very efficient but if i want to search
on a value for a different field the searching
would not remain that efficient so indexing
is a mechanism by which you can actually create
auxiliary search trees on multiple fields
so that the search on multiple fields can
be made efficient and we will talk about this
later when that particular module comes up
but the storage manager has to deal with such
issues moving on the query processing ah is
if we have we have already talked about the
language the d d l the d m l the query language
so it is some kind of like the c program it
is some kind of a text based programming code
so naturally that code needs to be parsed
and translated as we typically do in a c compiler
so there needs to be a query compiler so it
parses and analyses the code but translated
unlike the c program which translates the
c program into an intermediate code and then
into ah the binary instructions of the machine
the assembly binary instructions of the machine
the query translator translates the query
into relational algebra expressions i said
that there are two kinds of languages the
commercial query language and the pure language
so it translated in terms of a program in
the pure language it which could be a relational
algebra language and then it tries to optimize
so that is that is a that is a that is a critical
term to be noted that there is an optimizer
so this optimizer is a critical component
which tries to make sure that the query when
it is run on your data will run with the most
you know least amount of time in an effective
manner so and then an execution plan needs
to be decided we will will be able to understand
this when we go to the actual relational algebra
execution plan basically says that if there
are multiple operations in that query to be
performed then how those operations in which
order they should be performed and where should
temporary tables be used where they should
be skipped and so on and then once that has
been done then it passes on to an evaluation
engine which actually runs that query on the
data that you have the instances of the data
that you have and that brings out the resultant
query output which is another table of results
that we get so this query processing is a
is a core part of a database engine which
actually allows us to write text based queries
and relative data efficiently change update
data efficiently insert data efficiently and
so on
so so when we do this that we need to look
at alternative ways of evaluating a query
there could be different ways to write the
same thing these are called equivalence expression
equivalent expressions and what are the good
algorithms for doing each and every operation
there is a cost between good and bad way of
evaluating so this has to be understood that
the same thing you can compute in a you have
seen this similar concepts in in normal programming
language is also i mean we have seen for example
for sorting the several ways to sort and some
are better some are not as efficient so ah
if the similar things in terms of a query
needs to be evaluated and the cost between
good and bad ways need to be figured out so
then we need to estimate the cost of every
operation it depends on the information of
what has happened in the past the statistical
information and need to estimate those statistics
for intermediate results these are a couple
of things that the query processing sub engine
in a database will do
so beyond the storage manager and the query
processor ah we have a transaction management
system which is very very critical and core
of the database system it is a primarily has
to deal with two fundamental issues of a database
one what if a system fails see database systems
are unlike the programs that you have written
so far a program starts execution ends the
program always deals with transient data the
data did not exist before your program started
it ceases to exist after your program ends
so a program however complicated however important
has a limited lifetime a database in contrast
has a much longer lifetime which deals with
persistent data that is very important to
understand that is the each application whether
i am doing a bank fund transfer whether i
am ah making a credit card payment to whether
i am checking the balance or i am booking
a railway ticket whether i am purchasing a
book from amazon each one of the applications
are like the normal program it has a fixed
lifetime i start it i do certain operations
i am done with it but the data that is behind
it the data of my accounts my account balance
my transactions my ah different bank charges
all that need to stay on and on and on and
beyond every particular operation that i have
done on the database so which means that if
this database system feels at some stage for
some reason then we have an enormous impact
of that and that is not something that we
can absorb that something that we can accept
so a database system has to come with the
concept of recovery it must be possible if
the system fails it must be possible to recover
it to a certain earlier point where it is
consistent so transaction management system
is responsible to guarantee this kind of recover
ability of databases then the other question
that we have discussed about earlier also
is a multiple users are you accessing the
same database the same set of data at the
same time so what how to make sure that more
than one user can concurrently use an update
without the data getting inconsistent that
is as as i had mentioned there is only one
seat available one berth available on a particular
train on a particular date and two users at
the same time has initiated a booking it should
not happen that both of them get the booking
so one should get one should not get and that
needs to be the complexity is high for this
kind of you know decisions because in a the
databases as applications are significantly
distributed indian railways have no idea of
who is going to do what booking of which berth
from where at which point of time so transaction
management system is as the name suggests
defines something called a transaction which
always keeps the database consistent and operable
so it is a collection of a transaction is
a collection of operation that performs a
single logical function in a database application
this is this is very very critical it is a
collection of operations and performs a single
logical function so it does not do anything
and everything it just does a single particular
logical operation and ah that is what forms
the transaction so a transaction management
system is a component that ensures that with
all these transactions happening hundreds
and thousands of transactions happening every
second in a database system in a typical database
system the data should still remain consistent
in a consistent state in spite of failures
in spite of concurrences it must make sure
that at no point of time it should happen
that an amount has been debited from an account
and has not been credited to account or an
amount has been credited to an account and
has not been debited to the corresponding
account or the same seat same berth is booked
by two persons at the same time and so on
so forth so this also includes concurrency
control manager which controls the interaction
among different concurrent transactions which
ensures the consistency in the database and
provides the total safety so in total we have
seen the different components of the database
engine comprising the storage manager comprising
the query processor and the transaction manager
now we move on to we will just have a quick
look in terms of who are the typical users
of a database system so if we see the grossly
the users of a database system can be grouped
into i mean you can group it in multiple different
ways but this is a typical way to group that
you have the naive users those like those
the the the ah secretarial staff who sits
at the teller of the bank now that person
just needs ah does not know database management
system but that person just needs to know
the particular application he knows a few
set of screens graphical screens what needs
to be filled up where which button needs to
be clicked and so on and can use this database
through an application interface so this is
a lowest level of user then you have the set
of application programmers about whom i talked
about in my ah course overview ah presentation
that application programming is a big chunk
of you know i t services that databases need
who actually write the application programs
well the naive user is similarly using it
application programmers are responsible for
writing coding this application program so
they need to understand the database designs
they need to understand how to ah write the
query language how to fit with the application
data input output all the systems
the next level are the analysts who are called
the sophisticated users so they design different
kinds of query tools they are responsible
for the design of the database that is a schema
the ins different ah constraints the authorizations
and so on and manages that over a period of
time when the application requirements change
they might need to redesign the schema migrate
the data from an old schema to a new schema
so analysts are higher level of programmers
they have ah far more solid understanding
of the database management system to be able
to design different kind of query tools that
the application programmer will use and at
the end there are database administrators
so database administrators are ah people with
specialized rights who can do a lot of privileged
operation on the database for example ah taking
backups of databases for example creating
different users ah for example if there has
been a failure then how to do the failure
recovery scripts recovering the database and
so on so they do all kinds of administration
tasks but not the usual day to day data maintenance
and you know query processing and so on so
if we if we if you would like to know your
positions and i would say that by through
this course you are going to position yourself
amongst the application programmers and the
analysts and as i mentioned that the first
half of the course ah is focused on application
programming aspect and the second half would
be more focused on the analysis and some of
the administrative will do little bit of administration
but not nearly serious administration tasks
now ah we will take a quick look into the
database internals and architecture so i will
take you to this diagram i am sorry this diagram
is little ah small in terms of the script
size so please refer to the actual presentation
so if you if you look at the top here is the
users so is trying to show what different
users use this is a query processor that we
have known so the query processor gets a query
and so that naturally this query comes from
the application program so the compiler link
these these are the basic processing then
the of compiler organization the evaluation
engine which actually takes care of the processing
of the whole query and then it goes to the
storage manager which is now taking this whatever
the evaluation engine needs to do has to go
through different modules in the storage manager
which we will talk about these modules when
we ah we do have a discussion module on the
storage management later in this course and
we will then talk about what is a file manager
and what is authorization and so on but these
are the sub components these are the sub components
of the storage management needs to do and
then the storage manager is the only one who
deals with the actual data the actual disk
storage the different files and so on
so as you can see that the whole system is
kind of ah layered ah in terms of so this
is this is your your basic physical layer
that you have and this is your final view
layer that you have and in between this is
a logical layer that you that you deal with
so you can you can see that the abstractions
as we had talked about are also mapped in
terms of them way the actual database system
architecture is managed and finally the data
stays in the disk storage which ensures that
whatever data i have is actually persistent
in nature it does not go away any data that
stays within here or within the application
interfaces transient so that data these data
are transient they will disappear as soon
as the application is over but these data
are persistent they exist beyond this and
architectures supports that whole gamut from
of all applications or transiency of the applications
based on the persistence of the data at the
storage so that is a basic architectural view
of a typical database systems the actual architecture
we form more complex but we just want to take
a schematic view so that we can understand
it better
so it the actual architecture may again vary
based on the computer system that you are
using it could be centralized we will talk
about some of these at later modules ah centralized
in the sense that there could be one database
server or you know a group of database servers
at the same physical location connected together
to which all applications all user will connect
to it could be in terms of a client server
model which is a very typical client server
model that the programming systems are so
that typically for for example any of the
net based internet based database applications
we are looking at are necessarily client server
in nature what you are doing in the browser
is a client and there is a server back far
back there the multiple tiers in between them
ah databases could be single processes or
for performance they could be in terms of
multiprocessor ah parallel databases the data
sets themselves could be so large that it
may not be possible to search on them through
a single processor in a reasonable time they
could be distributed the data itself could
be distributed tables could get so large that
i may not be able to keep them at a single
point
so these are different aspects of you know
complex real life database system that exist
and we will deal with some of those some of
those aspects over the course of time but
you have to keep in mind that a final architecture
of a database and its associated application
will have some of these factors that you will
need to know and maybe decide on ah in terms
of history well and i will not go through
each and every point here this is ah more
for completeness and to give you an essence
of how things have been going so database
system started in the fifties and early sixties
then major developments of these relational
models and all that started happening in the
seventies and in eighties really it proliferated
large in terms of prototypes and commercial
systems parallel distributed systems object
based systems started happening in eighties
nineties it really exploded in terms of large
decision support data mining applications
ah you know applications widespread use of
ah internet based data applications and and
and systems emergence of google and all that
from twenties early to i am in early two thousand
it has been x m l and automated database administration
and now what we are facing in at the big data
which are certainly ah aspects of other courses
but at the back of back of back at the last
layer then often is a strong relational system
that exists so to summarize in this module
we have introduced the models of database
management system the major components of
a database engine and discussed about the
internals and architecture and this will conclude
our discussion on the internals of database
management systems and next we will move on
to exposing more on the relational model