Welcome to module 7 of database management
systems, this is a second part out of total
3 of introduction to SQL.
In the last module, we have discussed about
the evolution of SQL the data definition language
part of it and the basic structure of queries.
In the current module we will complete the
understanding of the basics queries structure
and will see how, common set theoretic operations
can be performed in terms of queries. We will
familiarize ourselves with the handling of
null values and aggregation operation, that
will be frequently required for forming queries.
So, this is a module outline these are the
topics, that we will discuss. So, we started
the discussion of some more basic operations
in the query.
We have already discussed this that, if we
do select star from 2 tables then it results
in a Cartesian product we have seen this result
earlier..
Know by itself as we had said that, by itself
the Cartesian product may not really make
a lot of you may not be very useful, but suppose
we want to answer this kind of a query, that
find all names of all instructors who have
taught some course and for those you also
write the course_id. So, what we are interested
in is the name of the instructor and course_id.
So, we put that on the select course these
are the 2 tables that are required because,
the name of the instructor is there in the
instructor table relation and then the relationship
between which instructor teach which course
is in the teachers table. So, in the instructor
table we have the name in the teachers table,
we have the course_id and also this relationship
as to which course is taught by which teacher
and here, we have the relationship between
which id of the instructor has which name.
So, what we do is, when we do this Cartesian
product will get something like this, as we
have already seen, but we want to qualify
it by with a predicate which say that, we
will out of all these combinations will choose
only those where, the instructor.ID equals
the teachers.ID. So, if we look at say in
the first row the instructor.ID is this, teachers.ID
is this, which is id of the teachers table
they are same. So, which says the this instructors
Srinivasan actually teaches the course CS-101
whereas, if you look into this row it says
that instructor.ID is this and teaches.ID
is this and we are really not interested in
this combination, because this combination
does not convey anything meaningful. So, by
the use of this where clause, we will try
to choose only those records where, these
2 ids are same which will tell us that, this
particular instructor actually teaches that
particular course.
So, if we do that, then you will find that
majority of the records that, actually came
about in the Cartesian product are eliminated
from this result. So, I have struck them out.
So, you can currently see in this part you
can see only 4 records the 3 courses taught
by Srinivasan. So, and the one course taught
by you. So, in the output you will have
this name, this name part and this course_id
part because, you are projecting on these
2. So, this will be the output table which
will get generated and just to remind you,
this is the notion of natural join that, we
had discussed in relational algebra in this
case we will actually call it equi join because,
we are using a equality condition after the
Cartesian product to join these 2 relationship.
So, this is a very critical operation in many
of cases in our database query system.
There is and this is another extension of
this similar example. So, here we have added
another predicate in the where clause, specifying
that instructed or department name is art..
So, which means this will now, give the names
of all instructors in the art department only
who have taught some course and specify their
course_id. So, in different such ways, you
can manipulate and create queries.
It is possible to read them, we have already
seen examples you can rename a relation you
can rename an attribute and the style is to
use as. So, here you can see that, in the
select query we have said from instructor
as T. So, the name of this relation can be
treated as T and we again see that as instructor
as S. So, actually what we are doing a join
between the same relation instructor and instructor.
So, and we are trying to find out all instructor.
So, you have higher salary than some instructor
in computer science. So, the some instructor
in computer science is specified by this condition,
because department has to be computer science
and the fact that salary is higher. So, as
if you treat that, though it is actually a
join between a product between instructor
and instructor the same relation, but by renaming
you treat them as if they are 2 different
tables having name T and S, and then it becomes
easier to write this kind of query. So, otherwise
it is it is quite difficult to write this
query to find out, because you need to actually
create a product of one relation with itself.
Keyword as is optional you can just write
instructor, and then the name the new name
that you want to give and that itself field
work here. Is another Cartesian product example,
here given a relation which is which lists
a person and his or her supervisor, we want
to find out all supervisors direct or indirect
of that person.
So, I leave this as an exercise to you to
think over as to how we can actually compute
this query?
SQL supports several string operations and
of particular interest at 2 specific symbols,
characters which allow us doing certain match,
percentage is used to match any substring
and underscore is used to match any particular
character and we use a keyword like, to find
out different string patterns that can be
matched. So, here we want to find the names
of all instructors, whose name includes the
substring d a r and by writing this so saying
the predicate is formed is named like this.
So, what is there is a percentage before there
is a percentage after. So, anywhere d a r
will feature in the name, this predicate will
turn out to be true otherwise if there is
no d a r in the name the predicate will turn
out to be false and that particular record
will not get selected. So, in this way we
can using like, we can actually do different
kinds string operations as conditions in the
weight loss or also..
So now, naturally this brings in an issue
of for what if my string itself has a percentage
or an underscore character. So, the rule followed
is you will need to escape that, with the
escape character that you define. This is
a style which you have seen in C programming
as well.
Patterns are certainly case sensitive. So,
it depends it will distinguish between upper
case as well as lower case, and these are
different examples of string matching that
you can do where, you can match at this beginning
of a string, end of a string, anywhere in
the string, specific number of characters
in a string and so on. SQL supports concatenation
conversion of lower to upper case and vice
versa and different other common string operations,
those are available as functions in SQL and
can be used for convenience.
Now, let us different question let us say,
we have computed a query and then often we
would want, that the result be ordered in
according to certain order particularly the
value of certain field if we want the result
to be ordered, then SQL allows you to do that
by another clause that you add to the query,
which is called order by. So, what this will
do we have already seen this query this will
find out the names of all the instructors
and the names will occur in a distinct manner
because, distinct is specified, but then the
output will be in terms ordered by the name.
And the ordering can be descending or ascending
by you can control that, by specifying whether
you want descending or ascending by default
the ordering is ascending. So, that makes
the presentation of the result of and very
easy and you can certainly sort on multiple
fields as well, so it can be ordered based
on combination of fields.
SQL were closed also allows between as a comparison
parameter. So, between can specify 2 values.
So that, whenever the field value will be
between these 2 given values the condition
will be predicated will be taken to be true
otherwise is taken to be false. You can compare
based on people as well. So, in this case
you could have written, you could have checked
for equality of instructor.ID with teachers.ID
and department name with the literal biology,
but you can compact it by writing a tuple
notation as is shown here. So, these are common
convenient ways of writing different back
clause..
Now, we have specified that SQL does carry
duplicates. So, unlike relational algebra
which set theoretically specify that, their
duplicates should not be there if in SQL there
could be duplicate entries in the same relation.
So, there is a this is called when duplicates
are allowed in set theory, then such sets
where duplicates are allowed and known as
multi sets. So, there are multi set versions
of the SQL queries or so to say the relational
algebra operations.
So, you have a selection, which can be multi
set selection which means that, if there are
certain c1 number of copies of a tuple in
the relation, which satisfy the condition
theta then all of them will feature in the
result. And all those copies can be seen simultaneously,
because it is a multi-set condition, similar
definitions are hold for projection, as well
as for Cartesian product. So, I will leave
it to you to go through the details and convince
yourself that, these multi set relations really
extend the traditional single set distinct
definition of the relational algebra.
So, here is an example where, there are 2
multi set relations as you can see particularly
this one, which has identical duplicate entries.
So, using that you can define a Cartesian
you can define a projection of r1 on B r1
on B, which will certainly give you it is
you are doing projection on B. So, it will
give you a only. So, you will have this result
itself will be a multi set because you will
get 2 as. So, this result will be like a a,
and then you have r 2 with which you are doing
the Cartesian product. So, you will have all
possible combinations all these 6 are the
result in the SQL whereas, in set theory typically
the result should have been only these 2 tuples.
Now, we take a quick look into the common
set operations. So, it is possible to do union,
intersection, difference kind of operations
very easily with SQL queries. So, suppose
we want to find all courses, that ran in fall
2009 or in spring 2010. So, certainly the
first part of the query is simple. This will
give you all courses that ran. So, you are
taking out the course_id from section is where,
the course running information is provided
and you part putting 2 conditions, which say
that they actually this courses ran in fall
2009.
So, this is the first query the second query
says the courses, that ran in spring 2010
and you are you have an or condition in the
statement of what you are looking for. So,
you do a union, union is another keyword.
So, this will simply give you a relation of
the course_id attribute as the only attribute,
which has records from the first as well as
the second query. Similarly, you can find
out the courses that ran, both in fall 2009
and spring 2010 by using intersect, which
basically give you the intersection of the
result of the first and the second query.
You could also do difference set difference
by doing find courses, that ran in fall 2009,
but not in 2010. So, what will that mean,
that will mean that the result of the first
query from the results of the second query
be subtracted be done a difference from. So,
those that, had run in the fall 2009 and then
was again run in spring 2010 will get removed.
So, that is done through the accept keyword.
So, in this way you can very easily do set
operations, whenever that is easy to conceive;
obviously, you can write these queries in
several other different forms, but this is
just to show you how set theoretic operations
can be easily written.
You can do set operations like, this in terms
of fine salaries of all instructions that
are less than a largest salary. So, again
we are using renaming to think of the same
relation as 2, and then as if from the relation
T you are trying to look at relation S and
finding out what are the salaries, which are
smaller than that and certainly whatever comes
in out is the one which is not the largest
because, certainly the largest will not satisfy
this particular condition, because it will
get compared with itself. You can find salaries
of all instructors, and then you can find
the largest salary.
So, this is all salaries which are less than
largest, this is all salaries including the
largest. So, what happens if you subtract
that is from this if you subtract this from
all salaries, if you remove the salaries,
that are not largest naturally what you get
is a largest salary. So, this is a interesting
way to find the largest salary we will see
later on that there could be several other
ways particularly the use of aggregate function,
which make these computations easier to perform,
but these are the typical ways to use set
theoretic operations.
The set operations, so we have seen 3 of them
union, intersect and except they automatically
these operations are set theoretic. So, each
of them automatically, eliminate the duplicate,
unlike what SQL by default, SQL by default
does what allows duplicates, but set operations
will eliminate duplicates, because they are
set operations. So, if you want the SQL type
of behaviour, if you want the duplicates to
be preserved, then you can have a multi set
version of these set operations, which are
known as union all, intersect all, accept
all like that.
And naturally if you do these operations then,
here is the simple formula of the number of
tuples, that will get computed in different
cases you can study and convince yourself
that these are the correct numbers. Let us,
go to the treatment of we talked about null
values, that we said that it is possible that
certain records in a relation may have one
or more attributes where, the value is not
known and to represent, that the value is
not known we are putting a placeholder called
null.
So, let us see what is the consequence of
that null value in terms of doing these query
operations. So, the null signifies an unknown
value. So, if I do 5 plus null then naturally
the result is null. So, what you are saying
that I am adding an unknown quantity to 5.
So, then what would you say is the result
is unknown. So, that is the basic semantics
of adding null to a number. So, it is possible
to check, if particularly a field is a null
for a record, and that is done by a predicate
is null.
So, in this particular query we are trying
to find all instructors, whose salary is null
that is not known. So, this is a predicate.
So, for a particular record for which salaries
null, this will become true and that will
get included in the result, but for all records
for which, there is some value for the salary.
So, salary is known it is not null those will
not get included in the result.
So, the basic semantics of null is then, combined
with the truth values because, we know our
basic predicate logic is 2 values true and
false. But now, you have a third value unknown
that is, you may not know the value of a predicate.
So, how does it play around with the true
and false values you can reason through that
quite easily if you are comparing with a null
in whatever way, then naturally the result
is unknown. So, it returns a null, if you
are doing any connectives for example, if
you are doing or of null or true, then the
result should be true because, in or we say
that if any of the components is true then
the result is true.
So, here you do not need to know what is that
unknown well you can say it is true, but if
you do or with false or of unknown with false
the second row or of unknown with false if
you do this, then naturally this is unknown
because, since this is false the result would
be true only if unknown value is true and
the result would be false if the unknown value
is false, you do not know what that unknown
value is. So, you have to say that you have
result is unknown. So, using that same logic
you could see verify I would ask you to verify
offline at home you please verify, that all
these combinations of true false with unknown
are valid. So, if P is unknown is evaluate
will is as a predicate will evaluate to true
if P is not known..
Now, we come to the aggregate functions, there
are several aggregate functions they can be
used for convenience and these are the common
months, that operate on the multi set values
naturally aggregate functions operate on a
particular column they try to aggregate in
a particular column and return a single value
for example, average would be meaning, that
you are trying to find average of the values
of a particular column.
So, here is an example. So, we are trying
to find the average salary of instructors
in computer science department. So, naturally
what you output is average salary. So, mind
you this will this output relation will have
one attribute, which is average salary and
since, average salary is a single quantity
it will only have one, and here I have made
use of this aggregate function average. So,
it says you do average on the attribute salary
and where do you get that attribute, from
you get it from the table instructor and then
we are saying that we are not interested to
find average of salary of all instructors.
We are interested to find the average salary
of those instructors who work for computer
science. So, you put this back clause. So,
this will ensure, that you find the average
salary of instructors in computer science
department.
So, in similar way you can use other aggregate
functions like, if you want to know the total
number of instructors who teach a course in
this semester. So, you first put the where
clause, naturally you where will you find
this information you will find this information
in teachers, teachers is the relation which
tells you which instructor is teaching what
course. So, that comes in from then you have
to specify that teaching a course in spring
2010 semester. So, the where clause specifies,
that the semester is spring and the year is
2010. So, this will give you all records,
which show that the some instructor is teaching
the course in spring 2010 semester.
Now, naturally there could be multiple the
same instructor could happen multiple times,
because an instructor may be teaching more
than one course. So, you make the instructor.ID,
instructor.ID that you have here, you make
that distinct. So, that you get only those
instructors every instructor who is teaching
one course or more than one course will feature
only once in this total list, and then you
simply count it use aggregate function count
on that.
So, that will tell you how many instructors
are teaching some course in spring 2010 mind
you if this is critical to use this key word
distinct, because unless you use that, then
all that you will eventually find out is not
the number of instructors who are teaching
the course you will find out the number of
courses, that are being offered in spring
2010 because, there could be the same instructor
teaching more than one course. If you just
want to count the number of tuples you can
do count on star because, what is star is
all the attributes. So, from if we want to
find out the number of course, I suggest to
count star on course.
So, this is showing you the computation of
average salary of instructors in each department.
So now, what do you want to do is earlier
you try to find out the average salary in
one department. Now, you want that for all
the departments for each department I want.
So, my result now, is not a single row it
is not a single value it is a pair where,
I show the department and the average salary
in that department. So, this is what I want
visible and this is what I have.
So, naturally the information comes from instructor,
that is from what I want is a department name
and the average salary and I want to give
it a nice name avg_salary. So, I have done
a rename. So, I get avg_salary here, but then
what I want is I do not want an average d1
over this whole set of fields I want separate
average to be done here, to be done here,
to be done on this to be on this. So, these
are these are basically groupings by the department
as you can see, that this particular relation
has been sorted according to the department
name.
So, when I want to do apply an aggregate function
on certain subgroups of records, I use this
particular clause group by and use a name
of a field. So, what it does is if the values
in the group by field in this case department
name are identical those records are put together
and over those records and average is computed.
So, the average, that is computed over these
records are put in here, average that is computed
in terms of these records are put in here,
there is only one record, so average that
is computed in terms of that is put in here.
So, group by is a very useful feature along
with the aggregation functions and it allows
you to club information based on certain attribute
and then compute the aggregation on some other
field..
Mind you will have to when you do group by
and create the result id result table you
will have to make sure that, all your result
table attribute are used in the group by,
which is not an aggregate function. So, here
ID is not used. So, this is not a query, that
SQL would support.
You can further refine your result is saying
that, fine names and average salary of all
departments this much you have already done.
Now, you are qualifying that, whose average
salary is greater than 42000. So, of all that
we have for example, if we look in here for
example, in this music department average
salary is less than 42000. So, you do not
want that in the result you want only those
where, the average salary is greater than
42000 and the way to do that is to have add
another clause called having they say that,
the average salary is greater than 42000.
So, you are adding another predicate for actually
qualifying the aggregated value. Now, the
having clause actually applies after along
with the group by because, naturally the having
relates to the grouping.
So, once the grouping has happened groups
have been formed then the having clause will
be evaluated on that, in contrast where clause
also has a predicate, but the where clause
is applied before forming the groups. So,
this point this note has to be understood
carefully because, if you have a where clause
to choose the records they it will first apply,
then out of those records chosen the grouping
will happen and once the grouping has happened,
then the aggregate function will evaluate
and the having clause will get evaluated the
predicate of having clause will get evaluated.
Certainly, if there are null values in terms
of aggregates, then there is a question of
what will happen. So, the general strategy
is that, whenever you perform aggregation
then the null values are all ignored. So,
if on that field there is no value which is
not null, that is if all values are null then
the result is null otherwise the result is
computed by ignoring the null values..
So, these are what do you have of course,
if you count then if the collection has only
null values the count will return you 0, but
all other aggregates will return you simply
null.
So, to summarize we have we had started the
basic understanding of the basics query structure
in the last module. Now, we have completed
that with some more additional operations,
we have understood the set theoretic operations
and very importantly we have familiarized
with the treatment of null values and aggregation
functions particularly the group by and having
clauses and how do null values and aggregation
interact in terms of an SQL query.