welcome to module five of database management
systems in the previous module we started
discussions on introducing relational model
we will conclude that in this module so in
the last module we have talked about attributes
relational schemas and instances in mathematical
form and very importantly we have tried to
introduce discuss about the concept of keys
in this module we will try to understand more
on the relational algebra and familiarize
with the operations of relational algebra
so these are the different operations that
we will ah look at ah select project union
and so on some of them are simple set theoretic
operations some are newly defined operations
and we look at the aggregators so relational
operators
ok so what is a relation as we have seen already
a relation is nothing but a table it has a
set of columns and it has a set of rows or
records that fill up data according to those
columns select is an operation which chooses
a subset of rows from a relation based on
a certain condition so it is written in terms
of in relational algebra we write it with
a notion of ah notation of sigma and following
a parenthesis we put the name of the relation
so we say we are selecting from the relation
r and then we put a condition here which is
a propositional condition
so if for this all rows of r will be checked
if a row will satisfy this condition then
it will be included in the result if it does
not satisfy the condition then it will not
be included in the result so
let us look at this example so our condition
is sorry let this put this back so our condition
theta is a is equal to b and d is greater
than five so you are saying that that any
row to be selected the value of its a attribute
should equal the value of its b attribute
and when that happens the value of its d attribute
must be greater than five so you can easily
if we look through this we can easily say
by the first condition a equal to b you can
say that this row does not satisfy this condition
because a is alpha and b is beta whereas these
three rows satisfy because a is equal to beta
then you again look at d we find that this
d is less than five we say this also does
not satisfy because it fails the second condition
both have to hold so we finally come to that
this record and this record are the selected
record in the result alpha alpha one seven
alpha alpha one seven beta beta twenty three
ten beta beta twenty three ten in both of
these records a is equal to b in both of these
records d is greater than five so selection
is a process is the operation which selects
a subset of rows from a table from a relation
and creates a new relation based on a selection
condition that must be true for all the rows
for all the records that have been selected
but the set of columns do not change they
remain the same so for example if i if ah
if in the contrary if we say that sigma a
not equal to b r then naturally i will have
a relation with fields a b c d and that relation
will be only this row where that is the only
row where a is not equal to b we can i can
have a selection saying r where c is greater
than zero naturally this will satisfy this
will satisfy this will satisfy this will satisfy
so this whole relation would be the result
of the selection so it is possible that it
is not necessary that some rows will have
to get eliminated in the result i say that
ah this is is the
selection is d is less than one this will
fail this will fail this will fail this will
fail so all of them will fail so it is possible
that the result of an operation could be either
the whole relation as we saw last time or
a null relation which has where none of the
record with feature because none of the record
satisfy the condition so that is a basic select
operation
let us ah move on look at the next one is
called a projection operation so select chooses
a subset of the rows projection necessarily
chooses projects a set of columns from the
original relation so this is a quite straightforward
to see it is written in terms of this notation
pi and then you write the columns that you
want in the result of projection so we say
this is a c so which means basically the column
which is not selected in the projection you
can simply forget about that simply erase
it if you erase that you get this relation
and once you get that please recall that a
relation is a set and in a set every element
has to be distinct so after erasing b this
first and the second row have become identical
so naturally both of them cannot be there
it will have to be made distinct by erasing
any one of them and hence they become one
row in the result obviously i can project
on any of the infield single or all the fields
also i can do a projection of of this a b
c of r of course that means in this case that
will mean that it is a set which is equal
to r anyway but obviously i must have at least
one column at least one attribute to project
on i cannot project on a null set of attributes
because that does not give me a schema so
there will have to be some attribute one or
more attribute on which i project so selection
and projection ah selection has given me the
set of rows to retain and projection has given
me what are the columns to retain in the result
and combining them i can do several different
operations in a database table which can give
me several interesting results ah before proceeding
further
let us look into some of the typical ah other
operations that relational algebra allows
the next one is union given two relations
i can take a union this is nothing but a set
theoretic union the two relations r and s
must have the same set of columns a and b
because if the columns are not same then the
union does not make sense they because certainly
if the columns are different attributes are
different their types and type of data values
would be different so they cannot be put to
a same table so when two relations have the
same set of attributes then their instances
can be taken a union of so all records that
ah exist in both these relations will be put
together into a single table so here alpha
one is coming here beta one is coming here
in terms of relation alpha one is coming here
alpha two is coming here beta one is coming
here beta three is coming here and alpha two
is coming here you can see that this record
alpha two exists in both the relations and
by the set theoretic notion of uniqueness
in the union they have to be uniquified so
one of them will be removed it does not matter
because they are identical anyway so for relations
having the same set of attributes we can simply
make a union of all its records so
other the third operation is the a fourth
operation is doing a set difference it is
works simply as set theoretic difference again
the two relations must have the same set of
ah attributes and i can do a difference of
r minus s which mean that ah all tuples which
exist in r but do not exist in s will be included
so this is included because this is not here
but this is not included because it is in
s this is included because this is this does
not exist in the set s so it is the set so
you take the set r and then erase all the
records like this which exist in s and you
get r minus s so if i look into just two recap
if i look into the ah venn diagram then this
is these are set r minus s which belongs to
r but does not belong to s so there is a fourth
operation that one can do with the in relational
algebra fifth is a set intersection of two
relations so again the two relations need
to have the same set of attributes you can
take their intersection which is the record
which belongs to both it is the record that
belongs to both of them and as you are aware
now set intersection actually is not a new
operation it is not a fundamental operation
because if i have r if i have s then ah this
is r minus s now if i subtract this r minus
s which is this set from r which is this bigger
set then what will be remaining this is what
will be remaining so if i subtract r minus
s from r then what will remain is necessarily
the intersection of this is r intersection
s so set intersection is not a fundamental
operation of relational algebra but can be
used because it can be expressed in terms
of set difference
next comes ah how can we join two different
relations which have different set of ah attributes
so relation r has a b and relation ah s has
c d e so we can take a cartesian product so
taking cartesian product is making all possible
combinations so necessarily if since this
has two relations and this has three relations
so this will ah have one two three four five
six seven eight this has four relations so
these are eight eight total all possible pairing
of relations of r or records of r and records
of s are included so that is the cartesian
product all possible combinations this is
this is how we can join two relations but
ah certainly what is a important is something
which we will discuss shortly
now in the cartesian product ah then issue
may happen because there could be attributes
which are common between two relations so
if you if two attributes are common when you
take cartesian product how do you put their
name because as with the example show here
between r and s the attribute b is common
so how do you take care of that so when the
such common names happen then we actually
change the name of the attribute with the
name of the relation so b coming from r will
be called r dot b and s be coming from s will
be called r dot s and accordingly the relational
algebra gives you a way to rename a a a table
and put its name differently so this is ah
given a this is given by this relation is
given by this symbol rho so you can using
a relation r you can actually give it a different
name s and ah do that in terms of so with
that you can actually because otherwise you
cannot compute r cross r because if you try
to do r cross r then you will have r dot a
r dot b and you will again have r dot a r
dot b so you are using this to rename r to
s and then compute this so renaming a table
is another feature which is provided of course
it is not a fundamental operation of the algebra
but this is ah what makes the any kind of
cartesian product possible ah finally we can
ah make composition of ah operations that
if for example what we show here is ah we
have two relations r and s you have taken
a cartesian product and then we have taken
a selection so taken a cartesian product of
r n s to produce the table as you can see
the r process and then added a selection based
on a equal to c based on that condition so
all these operations can be combined in multiple
different ways to give you really complex
ah relational algebra operations ah there
is a nice um ah operation which is a derived
one which can be written in terms of other
operations which is called a natural join
which we will use very heavily
let me first show you an example of that ah
suppose i have two relations r and s and what
is important is there are some attributes
which are common between them now we saw earlier
that in in cartesian product in terms of common
attributes we basically the attributes got
renamed in terms of the table name but this
is not what we are looking at in relation
natural joint what we want to say is if an
attribute is common between two two tables
then while you join them the records from
two fields can be joined if their value on
that common attribute is same so it is what
it tries to do is it tries to make a cartesian
product of this two tables first take all
possible combinations but then you select
only those rows where the values are identical
between columns having the same name so for
example if you if you if you look into this
row and this row so what will happen in in
the cartesian product i will have this alpha
one alpha a one a alpha
let me write it in smaller so i am doing a
cartesian product i am looking at this row
i am looking at this row so i have a b c d
i have b d e and alpha alpha a one a alpha
now they match on b they match on d so i will
say this is this will get retailed but in
the cartesian product i will also have the
first row of r going with the second row of
s alpha one alpha a three a beta here the
b does not match d does not does match but
the b does not match so this particular entry
will not go in the final result to take the
cartesian product and you only retain those
rows where the values match for the identically
named attribute that is why so you take the
cartisan product now look at the expression
the attributes common attributes are b and
c b and d so the b attribute is r dot b and
s dot b so we say that in the cartesian product
r dot b must equal s dot b the name is common
the value will have to be same similarly d
is a common attribute so r dot d value in
the r dot d and the value in the s dot d has
to be same so based on the cartesian product
you do a selection for equality of values
on attributes which are identical between
the two column between the two relations between
the two tables this is a final selection as
you do that you get a table where there are
two b s r dot b s dot b there are two d s
r dot d s dot d but according to this selection
for all at all records for all rows the value
on r dot b and value on s dot b are same value
on r dot d and value on r s dot d are same
because that is how we have done the selection
so there is no reason to keep two b columns
or two d columns
so now you project based on a r dot b c r
dot d and e which means that s dot b and s
dot d are left out you do not project them
so after you have done this projection you
get the final result of the natural join which
has a union of all the attributes that the
two relations at a b c d and b d e union is
a b c d e and you have all those records whose
values matched on the common attributes between
relation r and relation d so you can say that
if i now do a selection if i now do a projection
on a b c or rather a b c d i will get a subset
of r if i do a projection on b d e i will
get a subset of s so this is the natural join
operation in relational algebra as you can
see this is a derived operation because we
could use the cartesian product selection
and projection to get this but as i tell you
we will see see more of this when we look
at the look at all these different aj query
coding but natural join is one of the most
widely used most fundamental relational algebra
operation that you will often need beyond
selection and projection so these were the
six operations and the important derived operations
of relational algebra besides that relational
algebra has some aggregation operators for
example ah given a a table we could ah compute
the sum of values on a column we could compute
average of values max of values mean of values
so these somehow aggregate values of multiple
rows on a particular column and therefore
these are called aggregate operators ah we
will see when we talk about s q l we will
see how this really can be coded in s q l
and used but these are this become very convenient
to use because often we will need to know
ok if this is ah i mean these are the instructors
and so let us see which instructor has a maximum
load of courses how many based on hours or
ah which instructor has what is the average
load on the different instructors and so on
so in every possible context different aggregate
operators are frequently required and they
are also available as operators in most of
the pure as well as commercial query languages
ah finally to note ah that ah relational algebra
in relational average every query input is
a table and the output is also a table so
it is always manipulating one or more tables
into a single table thats what we are i mean
in in very simple terms that is the way you
can look at it and all data in the output
table appears in one of the input tables that
is no new data gets generated its basically
taking selecting combining data from different
input tables it does not generate a new data
that is that has to be that is ah if if i
see that a we an attribute for a particular
row has a value fifteen then there must be
some input table where there is a record where
in that field as an attribute value fifty
otherwise this cannot happen again relational
algebra is not turing complete in the sense
that there are algorithms which cannot be
coded in relational algebra we mentioned this
ah earlier too and that is the reason that
is a foundational reason of why the s q l
language commercial s q l language is based
on relational algebra is not turing completely
there
so we might need to use other programming
languages along with the relational algebra
coding for solving some of the application
problems to summarize this is the ah so this
table is what you not only should remember
but you should become a expert of in terms
of the operators of relational algebra which
we will start using very heavily as we start
doing the query coding and processing so we
talked about selection which takes rows selectively
we talked about projection which takes out
certain columns of a table we talked about
cartesian product of two relations which make
all possible combined relations we talked
about union of records from two tables having
identical set of attributes we talked about
set difference which again is ah the difference
of records of one relation from another given
that they have identical ah set of attributes
we have shown that ah set difference can be
used to also compute set intersection it is
not in the fundamental operation but is the
derived one and we have shown a very interesting
ah operation based on cartesian product selection
and projection called natural join where two
tables can be joined based on one or more
common attributes they have
now i am sure you have already noted that
if i am doing a natural join between two tables
which do not have any common attribute then
the result is merely the cartesian product
because the selection around the cartesian
product has no condition to select any ah
any of the you know any of the fields any
of the rows separately so it merely turns
out to be a cartesian product so in this module
we have introduced the relational algebra
and we have familiarized ourselves with the
fundamental and derived operators of relational
algebra ah going forward in the next module
will take a deeper look into the relational
model and start progressing towards the query
design and database design