Welcome to module 39 of database management
systems, we have been discussing about query
processing and optimization, in the last ah
module.
We talked about ah the basic issues of ah
query processing, what is the overview and
ah the measures of query cost that would be
used ah in terms of ah disk seek time and
disk access ah time the read write time and
we agreed ah we assume that we will ignore
the CPU and other time for the time being.
And then we took a look into how the certain
ah SQL queries like the selection, the sorting
which is required for other operations, different
join operations and ah other aggregation and
those kind of operations can be processed
in a structured way.
In view of this ah in this module we would
like to understand the basic issues of optimizing
queries.
So, that the same query as we have seen little
bit can be ah performed executed in multiple
ways and we would like to choose the one which
is ah the least cost possibly estimated cost
should be the least.
So, we would ah need to understand 2 aspects,
one is given a query how do I generate alternate
queries that is ah in terms of the relational
expression how a particular expression can
be transformed into equivalent expressions
and then we choose from these equivalence
expressions for optimization.
So, these are the 2 topics to discuss.
So, to introduce on the query optimization
let us ah take a simple example.
So, I am referring to the university database
ah that we have discussed earlier, it has
ah 3 relations as ah listed above and ah using
that we want to do the perform the query where
we join instructor teaches and course these
3 ah relations and do a selection on that
based on department name.
So, this will give us ah naturally the instructors
who are in teaching some course in the ah
the instructor is in music department and
is teaching ah some course there and we want
the name and title of ah these.
So, we want the name of the instruction instructor
and the title of the course that the person
is teaching.
So, if we write the ah query in equivalent
relational form this is what ah we will get
to see and this is ah ah this basically is
a first join happening here then the next
join happening, find next the selection and
finally, the projection happening here which
will give us the result of this query.
Now what we observe is it is possible that
if you look at carefully the department name
ah should be music.
So, if we look into these ah relations then
we can ah easily figure out that instructor
has the department name name attribute.
So, in this after this joint if a tuple has
to qualify through this selection then the
instructors ah in the instructor relation
the department name of that ah join people
must be music otherwise it will not get selected.
So, what if instead of ah doing the join and
then doing the selection as we are doing here
if we first do a selection on the instructor
ah relation itself and then join it with the
join of teachers and courses and finally,
do the projection we should actually get the
same result.
So, these are what is it is a simple example
of what are equivalent relational expressions
that we can make use of in terms of ah our
query processing.
So, what given that this is another example
we were showing.
So, here the query is to find the the teacher
and instructor and the course name for back
the instructor is from department of the music
and the course he taught is in the year 2009.
So, we want these and ah corresponding to
the equivalent at ah SQL if we write the ah
relational expression then the in relational
algebra this is what it looks like.
So, what we can ah eventually observe from
this that ah again as we observed last time
department name is an is an instructor.
So, if we are doing a final selection based
on department name is equal to is ah music
then it is possible that I can first filter
the instructor relation with the department
name being music that should not affect the
result.
At the same time ah the other select condition
we have is year is 2000, which happens only
in the teacher's relation.
So, instead of actually filtering it after
the join I can filter the teachers relation
with ah year being 2009 and then use these
2 in terms of the join and finally, join that
with the course and finally, do the ah projection.
So, here what we show that ah along with this
ah tree the parse tree of the query in relational
algebra we are also trying to put some annotations
to say how this ah particular query will be
processed.
So, if we want to find out ah the tuples where
the year is 2009 and there is no specific
index on that or anything to for doing this
selection as we have seen earlier the best
way would be to use a linear scan.
Whereas, if I am trying to do a selection
with department name is equal to is ah music
ah there will be a could be an index one the
secondary index based on the department name.
So, I will be able to use that ah index to
find this.
So, these when we are doing this putting and
that here we will use this index, here we
will use linear scan these are what is called
annotations which tell the query processing
engine that how the query should actually
be executed.
Then they will be pipelined in the sense that
this will be put one after the other actually
these 2 can happen in parallel and then we
will use a merge join to join these 2 ah then
this merge that is joined result would be
joined with course ah ah based on now the
course is already indexed in course id and
this joined relation of instructor and teachers
will have id and course id on which ah they
they will ah have index.
So, we can use a hash join on that we did
not discuss about merge join, hash join as
processing steps in detail, but ah right now
just assume that these are different ways
of doing join which can make things efficient
and these are the annotations which are generated
in the process.
And such a query tree such a query parse tree
with the annotation is called an execution
plan so, that or the evaluation plan which
the query processing engine would be able
to use to actually execute and find the results.
So, this is the basic ah approach so, for
optimization what we need to do we need to
find out that particular evaluation plan,
that particular order of ah we the evaluation
and the use of algorithms, the use of indexes
which will ah make the query possibly most
efficient.
And that cost difference could be really really
huge in a real database it could vary between
seconds in one way of doing the query or in
terms of number of days if we do it in a non
optimal way in a non optimized way.
So, ah typical steps in this kind of query
based optimization would be to first generate
the candidates I am sorry first generate the
candidates that is generate the equivalent
expressions that is given a query I have one
relational expression and we would like to
generate equivalent expression using a set
of equivalence rules we will see what these
equivalence rules are.
So, that this equivalent queries expressions
can any one of them can be actually executed
and ah we then annotate them to with the ah
result ah the resultant expression we annotate
to get different query plans evaluation plans.
And then we put the cost estimates based on
the cost structure that say we had used in
the other ah in the earlier module and ah
from these alternate evaluation plans we will
choose the one that will have the least estimated
cost.
So, the cost can be based on as we had seen
earlier it could be based on number of tuples,
number of distinct values frequently used
attributes and so, on and we will use ah statistics
ah for also intermediate results that if there
are intermediate results to be stored we will
make estimates of what would be the size of
that result because it needs to fit into memory
for optimal execution, the cost formula for
different algorithms ah will also be used
through statistics.
So, based on all these estimation ah which
will have an estimated cost and based on that
we will choose the particular evaluation plan
which looks to be the best and that is the
crux of the query optimization strategy.
So, as we have seen the first step is to be
able to generate alternate expressions equivalent
expressions through transformations.
So, we look through the relational algebra
operators again.
And ah check what are what is meant by equivalence
of 2 relational expressions.
So, 2 relational expressions are equivalent
if they generate the same set of tuples for
any instance of the database, it is not enough
to just show that for one instance it gives
the same result.
So, 2 expressions are equivalent for in if
I take any legal instance of the database
then it must be equivalent and in this process
we can note that the order of tuples are really
relevant that we have ah told repeatedly and
also we would make sure that the results are
same provided the database ah provided ah
the relation satisfy all the integrity constraints.
If they violate integrity constraints then
it is a problem of the user then we the database
really does not care if the 2 expressions
will give equivalent or equal results.
Ah we also note that in SQL input output could
be multisets so, the same thing has to be
satisfied in terms of multisets.
So, based on this we define an equivalence
a set of equivalence rule that say that 2
expressions are equivalent so, you can use
that rule to transform one expression by the
other and vice versa.
So, let us take a look into this expression
so, ah most of these expressions are relatively
easy to understand.
They can be ah ah formally proved using the
corresponding set theoretic ah condition of
the relational expressions.
So, for every relational expression we had
a set theoretic condition that we had studied
so, using those you can prove that we will
not do the proof of these equivalence relations
here, but ah it you should be able to do that
very easily.
So, he said if we have a conjunctive selection
of a relation based on 2 conditions theta
1 and theta 2, then ah we should be able to
apply the selection first based on theta 2
and then based on theta 1 or actually vice
versa because conjunction is commutative so,
the selection operation is also commutative.
So, this gives us 2 transformation rules and
ah we might ah want to use any so, these all
will give equivalent form.
So, applying these 2 rules we get 3 relational
expressions which are all equivalent this,
this and this are all equivalent, but if you
actually think in terms of processing the
query and the cost involved you will be able
to ah figure out that naturally the cost of
doing this may be relatively more involved
because ah you have the relation and then
on the whole relation you are applying the
conditions, but here if you do for example,
if you first do say first apply theta 2 certainly
by that selection the relation would become
much smaller.
So, applying theta 1 on that would be easier
or vice versa depending on whichever is a
smaller set ah there could be other for example,
if you have a sequence of projections then
naturally in that sequence the last projection
that you have done is what is retained.
So, if we have a sequence of projections that
is simply doing the last projection all other
projections can actually be ignored.
The selection can be combined with Cartesian
product and theta join also that is taking
a Cartesian product and then doing a selection
is equivalent to doing a theta join ah this
of course, is almost the definition.
And if I have a join by theta join by theta
2 and then do a selection with theta 1 it
is equivalent to doing a theta join with theta
1 conjunction theta 2.
So, these are all equivalent forms so, these
are equivalent in the sense that left hand
side and right hand side are interchangeable.
So, it does not mean that the left hand side
implies the right hand side or vice versa
it means that either of them implies the other,
they are really equivalent in that sense.
Then theta join operation are natural or natural
join operations are commutative, we can change
interchange their relations.
So, this might impact for example, you have
ah seen the algorithms of nested join and
block join block nested join algorithms; obviously,
depending on the size of the relations the
cost of doing theta 1 E1 theta join E 2 or
E1 natural join E2 and E2 natural join E1
may be different and we would choose the one
which has a lesser cost.
Next set of transformation rules tell us that
the join operation is associative which is
obvious ah theta joins are associative in
the in this specific manner also, that is
if I do a theta join with condition theta
1 and then I do a theta join with condition
theta 2 and theta 3 then we may be able to
take out the condition theta 3 outside ah
provided ah theta 2 the condition theta 2
uses only the attributes of theta E1 and E2
so, it should be possible to do that ah.
Look here that on on the left hand side that
restriction is not there on the ah condition
theta 2 it could also use ah attributes of
E1, but if it does not then it is possible
to simplify it in this manner and these are
the equivalent rules that we have.
So, often we will draw the rules in this form
so, just to explain you one so, this ah shows
the associativity of join.
So, here what you are saying is first you
do E1, E2 and with the result you join E3,
here you are saying first you do E2, E3 and
then you join with E1.
So, this is basically associativity this basically
is commutativity of theta join.
So, we will often draw them in such forms
of ah parse trees and show the equivalence
that becomes ah easy to understand for example,
in this case you are doing a join ah and then
doing the selection and here you are doing
it select early you are doing a select early
on this relation E1 of course, you will be
able to do this provided theta contents only
attribute from E1, if theta contains attributes
from both E1 and E2 this transformation will
not be applicable this transformation will
not be possible.
So, these are some more of the transformation
rules the selection operation distributes
over theta join operation.
So, I can you can ah I can see here that there
is a theta join and then I am doing a selection.
So, I can first do the selection and then
do the theta join of course, for the selection
it must involve only the attributes of E1,
otherwise this will not be valid.
And similarly, another ah distribution rule
is shown here where you are doing a selection
on conjunction on theta 1, theta 2 on a theta
join by theta then you should be able to actually
ah distribute based on the condition theta
1 and theta 2, if theta 1 involves only the
attributes of E1 and theta 2 involves only
the attributes of E2.
These are these are pretty straightforward
rules if you ah think about the corresponding
set theoretic ah reason.
So, ah the other rules are will be in terms
of projection so, you can have if you have
union projection like this then you would
be able to break it down ah over to do separate
projections and their theta join and in case
you have a theta join of E1, E2 based on theta
and if L1 and L2 are the attributes of these
2 relations.
So, if L3 be the attributes of E1 that are
involved in the join condition theta and L4
are water.
So, you have the join condition theta.
So, what you are saying that the attributes
3 of you are not involved here and attributes
L4 of E2 are involved here ah, but they are
not so, in terms of L1 union L2 so, then this
kind of ah I should be able to ah distribute
the projection in steps and make the results
smaller.
So, this is another possible transformation
that now finally, the set theoretic operations
have their normal set rules so, union and
intersection are commutative, naturally set
difference is not commutative, union intersection
are associative as well.
The selection operation distributes over union,
intersection and ah set difference and ah
the projection also distributes over union.
So, you can see the exceptions here you can
reason that out.
So, we have ah in short we have presented
a set of ah different transformation rules
by each which you can make equivalent expressions
and between 2 equivalent expressions or more
equivalent expressions our objective will
always be to choose the one whose evaluation
plan will have a lesser cost.
So, as an exercise I have left that you can
create equivalence rules that involve group
by or aggregation operations or ah different
kinds of outer join, left outer join, right
outer join and so, on so, please work those
out.
Let us move on to a couple of ah examples
so, here is a query here the relations ah
from the university database, here is a query
find the names of all instructors in the music
department along with the titles of the course
they teach.
So, a while ago we saw this so, this is what
the query is in ah the relational algebra
form and if you use the transformation rule
of select early the rule 7a, whose transformation
I have just shown here then you should be
able to hear what you are doing is you are
first doing a join of teaches and the projection
of course.
And then joining instructor with that and
finally, doing the selection, but you should
you would be able to do this select early
because it involves ah the attribute ah department
name which is ah the attribute of instructor
alone here.
So, you should be able to first do this selection,
mind you ah here courses also show that there
is an attribute department name, but actually
the courses is being used after projection.
So, after projection in the projected relation
there is no department name.
So, department name is involved only the instructor.
So, I can first I can take this do early,
I can do this selection early and take this
out and then do the final join operation.
So, in that process ah possibly ah the this
will reduce the size of the relation to be
joined significantly because you do not naturally
expect to be to have too many instructors
in the music department.
So, the instructor relation after the selection
would become much smaller.
So, this is one example ah, this is another
example query we are taking find the names
of all instructors in the music department,
we have taught a course in 2009 along with
the titles of the course they taught.
So, here is a the corresponding here is ah
the corresponding relational ah query which
you can convince yourself is indeed the same.
And then we can transform using the rule 6a
which I have shown here which is basically
the associativity of joint because there are
2 join relations and we are using the associativity
of join to first join the here then second
and third relations are joined first and then
the first relation is joined with that.
Here we are using associativity of ah joining
the first and second and then using the third,
now if you join first and second and then
it is possible that the department name actually
ah the department name is an instructor and
the other condition is here which is in the
teaches.
So, this department name is in the instruction
here is in the teaches.
So, I should be able to do select early, I
should be able to select on the instructor
based only on the department name being music
and also select early on the teachers by using
a year as 2009 and then do their joint.
So, naturally each one of these will become
much smaller corresponding to the whole instructor
or teaches relation therefore, their join
will also be smaller.
So, which means eventually this part this
part of the query will become much smaller
in size in the result and the consequent second
join would be much smaller to perform.
So, this will naturally give it whereas, if
we had done all of these join earlier we would
have used the whole of the teaches and the
instructor ah relations and that would have
been quite a lot of ah tuples would have been
there.
So, these are different example so, this is
a the same example being shown in terms of
the 3 parts tree structure so, we can convince
yourself by using the transformation rules
that they are actually equivalent.
And then certainly they give you a significant
advantage and now ah this is an example which
show that you can push the projection.
So, here is what you wanted to do and ah while
we compute this we will get a relation of
ah this form and we can push, we can use these
rules rule 8a and 8b, this is rule 8a, this
is rule 8b by this we can push the projections
inside and make the relations smaller because
now if you push the projection then you are
actually cutting down on the ah on the number
of columns.
So, your relation becomes smaller that will
make the with the projection this will reduce
and when you project also there will be duplicates
which will get removed so, in every way your
relation becomes smaller in size and your
subsequent join operations would be more efficient
.
You can also the these are examples where
you can ah take care of the fact that you
can reorder joining to get ah better result
for example, the you can if I have to do join
3 relations like this, I could do either this
first or this first.
Now if I do this first then this is a temporary
relation which I will need to maintain in
memory and then join with r1.
If I do this first then this will be a temporary
relation and then I will join it with r3.
So, if this is large enough then compared
to this then I will be better off by doing
this and will be able to have a more optimized
execution of the query.
So, here is ah an example of that again 2
joints.
So, what we are trying to show is ah when
we are having this instead of actually are
actually trying to compute this join first
because we expect that this set to be much
smaller, if this set is much smaller then
naturally this joint would be much smaller
and it is more likely to fit into the memory
then if we had just done teaches and course
id's which I expected to be large relations.
So, basically ah therefore, the strategy turns
out that given a query you will have to ah
generate it whole lot of equivalent expressions.
So, the number of equivalent expressions could
be really really large.
So, we will have to systematically generate
all these alternate equivalent expressions
and apply by applying these transformation
rules that we have just seen and ah we will
have to continue till no new expression can
be generated and then we have to evaluate
each one of them based on their evaluation
plan.
So, this could be very expensive because the
number of alternates could be really really
large ah.
So, the optimize plan generation is ah also
based on the transformation rules and we may
have only different special kits approaches
to take care of the common optimization plans
that we might have.
Now, one way to do that is for example, if
we are ah looking at say the the join of 2
relations E1 and E2 here then; obviously,
ah if we do certain transformations with this
join ah that does not change the way E1 and
E2 are actually evaluated.
So, if ah that be the case then in terms of
generating the alternate we do not really
need to keep or evaluate all of the expressions
the whole of the expression in every alternate.
We could actually do something like ah sorry
ah we could actually do something like we
could ah have a join and then instead of really
replicating the whole of the evaluation of
E1 and evaluation of E2, we can simply make
pointers to the same sub trees which are called
basically sub expression optimization.
If you have studied ah the expression optimization
in compiler at any point of time you will
understand this very well, this is the same
strategy which is used here.
So, if you can detect duplicate sub expressions
then you can have only one copy and you can
make the things more ah efficient to run.
So, the general strategy for doing this is
a dynamic programming we would not be able
to cover that in the current course, but just
know that ah all these explosion of generating
alternate and choosing the best one is usually
handled in terms of dynamic programming which
is a strategy to make sure that if we have
solved a sub earlier then I do not need to
solve that sub problem again we can just reuse
that same ah earlier result and go ahead with
that.
So, by this way we can common sub expressions
we may only find the plan for a best plan
for a common sub expression only once and
then use it subsequently again.
So, in this module ah covered starting ah
from the notions of query processing in the
earlier module, we have ah discussed the basic
issues of optimizing queries and we have shown
that ah using a set of simple transformational
rules you can convert a relational expression
into a number of equivalent relational expressions.
And then you can evaluate them based on the
estimated cost that the model that you are
using and choose the best one and dynamic
programming is usually a good way of doing
that.
So, in through the previous module and this
one we have taken a very elementary look I
should say, but this will give you ah some
idea of how actually an SQL query is transformed
into relational algebra ah parsed and translated
into relational algebra and how equivalent
expressions for that relational algebra expression
is generated and evaluated.
And finally, an evaluation plan is met where
specific choice is made for the different
algorithms for doing different operations
and that final plan which is which has the
best cost is passed on to the query processing
engine to query evaluation engine and that
ah then goes forward and does the b tree and
disk operations in according to the plan and
produces the best result in possibly the best
shot is possible time period.