Welcome to Module 16 of Database Management
Systems till the last module which closed
with ah the third week.
Specifically in the third week, ah we talked
about certain advanced features of SQL and
ah the formal query language ah in terms of
ah relational and algebra and calculi and
then, we talked in a depth in terms of the
entity relationship model, the first basic
conceptual level representation of the real
world that we can do in terms of designing
a system.
Now, our next task would be to take it to
more proper complete relational database design
and this will have a lot of theory at different
levels that we need to understand.
We will slowly develop that and this discussion
will span 5 modules that is ah we will take
the whole week to complete.
So, the objective of ah the current module,
the first of the Relational Design Module
is to identify features of good relational
design ah having done the year module.
We have yeah we do the year model, we have
the entity sets relationships, we convert
them to schema.
We have seen how to do that and immediately
we have some design, but the question is,
is it a good design.
So, we will discuss about what are the features
of a good design and then, we will ah introduce
the formal definition of what is first normal
form and we will introduce a very critical
concept of ah relational database design,
the functional dependencies.
These are the ah module outline for that.
So, to start with the features of good relational
design, let us take an example.
Suppose we have seen the instructor, relation
instructor entity set as a relation.
You have seen the department ah relation.
Now, let us consider that if these two were
not two separate relations, if they were all
kept in a common relation that is all the
attributes are kept in the common relation,
so earlier if you recall that your instructor
relation was this and your department relation
was this much.
So, if we keep everything together, of course
we are calling it inst dept, but ah please
keep in mind this is not the same inst dept
that we discussed in terms of the ER model.
This is just putting these two together.
Now, the question is if you look into this
data carefully, for example if you look into
ah this particular row, if you look into this
particular row and if you look into this particular
row, these are rows of instructors who all
belong to computer science . Now, earlier
we were representing the information of instructor
only in this part.
So, we just knew that it is computer science
and we represent the information of department
in this part.
So, given a department name say computer science,
we knew where does it, ah where is it located,
the building and what budget it has.
Now, when we are combined, we will see that
naturally since computer science is located
in the tailor building, we know that it has
a budget of say 100,000.
So, all of these records will have this information
repeated.
So, this is not a very good situation.
This is not a good situation because this
kind of situation is typically in database
is known as redundancy, that is you have the
same data in multiple places.
So, what is the consequence of redundancy?
For example, there could be ah different kinds
of anomaly when you have redundancy.
What is an anomaly?
An anomaly is the possibility of certain data
getting inconsistent.
For example, let us say computer science department
moves from tailor building to painter building.
Now, what will have to happen if it moves
to painter building?
Then, I will need to remove this, make it
a painter, make this value painter.
I have to also do this, make this painter
. I have to also do this, make this painter
. So, if I have a change, then I will have
to make the change at multiple entries.
Think about the earlier situation where I
just had these three in my department relation,
then naturally computer centered only one
row and therefore, ah this ah change, this
update could be done at only one place.
So, it is not only that if while doing this
in case of this redundancy, I have to do this
multiple times.
It also has the ah difficulty that if I forget
to update any one of them or more of them,
then I have inconsistent data . Similarly,
if I want to insert a new value, I will have
to do that for all this redundant information.
If I have to delete say ah for some reason
let say the university decides to wind up
the Physics department, then I have to delete
all these rows which have physics as an entry
and the consequence of that is the department
is deleted, but as a consequence of that I
will delete the whole row and therefore, I
will not only remove the department, but I
will also remove the corresponding instructor
who was enrolled for that department.
So, these kind of redundancy can lead to different
kinds of anomalies in a database design . On
the other hand, if you look at, ok well why
I am complicating ah the whole situation?
We have already had a good design ah in terms
of where these anomalies were, not their department,
were separate instructor was separate.
In that case, the situation is that to answer
some of the queries, I may have to do a very
expensive joint operation.
For example, if I want to know if ah Einstein
wants to know what is the budget of his department,
that cannot be found out from the earlier
instructor database, instructor relation which
had only these fields.
So, I have to pick up Einstein from here,
do a join based on the department name, depth
name with the department ah table department
relation and then only, I will be able to
find out that an Einstein belongs to Physics.
Physics has a budget of 70000.
So, Einstein's department has a budget 70000.
So, there is a tradeoff between how much if
data information you make redundant and lead
to different anomalous situations or how much
data you optimize in the representation, but
get into the possible situation of having
a higher cost in terms of answering your queries.
So, this is ah one of the core design issues
that we will start with.
So, ah let us look into some more of these
examples, let us say we look into another
ah combined combination of schema.
Suppose section is a relation which have the
sections of a course which give the section
id semester year and say section class is
another relation which tell me for a section
id, what is the building and room number where
it is located.
So, if we have this ah kind of ah relations
combined into a common relation, then I have
all of these ah coming from the section and
this and these coming from the section class,
but we can see that there is no repetition
or ah redundant information in this case.
So, it is note that combining schemas is necessarily
always bad in terms of repetition or in terms
of redundancy.
So, different situations will have to be assessed.
So, if we want to look at the other side that
if we just as I said that if we make the schema
smaller, so that we avoid redundancy and then,
what we see that 12 hm from the combined inst
dept ah relationship that we saw.
So, let me just ah show you once more.
So, this is if we look at the inst dept, then
in this we can we know that from the earlier
ah information about the department relationship
that department name is a key, is a primary
key of the relation which has department name,
building and budget . What is the consequence
of being a primary key?
If it is a primary key, then no two records
can match on the department name and be different
in terms of the building and the budget.
If two records are there which have the same
department name, they must be identical.
So, they are distinguishable completely by
that.
So, let us see what is the consequence of
this.
So, we are saying that we write it as a rule
that if there is a schema department, name,
building, budget, then department name would
be a candidate key and we write this observation
that if two records match on the department
name, they must match on the building and
budget and very loosely, we will come to the
formal definition.
Very loosely we call this the functional dependency.
We say that the building and budget is functionally
dependent on the department name and that
is a situation where we can split this inst
dept and ah create a smaller ah relationship
because department name is not a candidate
key in the inst dept.
It does not decide the records of inst dept
uniquely.
So, since it does not, so when the values
of this key, ah this attribute department
name is duplicated or triplicated, the values
of the building and budget are repeated and
we have the redundancy.
So, this is a situation, very common situation
which is indicative of the fact that we need
a decomposition into smaller , but at the
same time we can also observe, I mean let
us take a different example.
If we are thinking that decomposition is the
panacea of ah solving these kind of ah redundancy
and related problems, then let us try to see
a different relationship employee which has
id, name, street, city, salary and we want
to make it smaller ah and want to make two
relations id and name and name, city street,
salary.
So, if we do that, then how do we get the
salary for a particular id?
We will naturally have to join these two relations
in terms of the common attribute name.
We have seen that in the query and the question
is when I do this joint, do I get back the
original information or I lose some information.
Look at an example.
So, here is an example of the combined ah
instance and I have two different ids, but
incidentally the names are same.
The names of these two distinct employees
are same.
So, when I decompose, I get this relation
which shows id and name.
I get this relation which is against the name
shows this, but when I try to join them by
national joint, I not only get the combination
of this with this which is what I need, but
I also get this combination.
So, if I say this is what I get as well in
terms of natural joint, this is what I get
as well in terms of the natural join which
are really not there in the original relation.
So, you can see that in the natural join,
I get four records, I get four rows whereas,
in the original one I had only two rows.
So, I get some entries which are actually
erroneous.
These are not there in the database.
So, this is when this happens.
We say that we have loss of information and
such joints are said to be lossy joins.
So, when we decompose, we need to make sure
that our joins are lossless in nature, otherwise
that is not a good design.
So, you can see this is again a hypothetical
example which shows three attributes in relation
having three attributes.
You have decomposed it into two relations
having two attributes each and we have shown
an instance and in this case, it shows that
ah when I take the join, the original information
I am sorry wait .
When I take the join, the original information
is completely retrieved.
I get back the same table and when that happens,
I say that the join is lossless.
So, what we need to understand is ah on one
side there is ah a need to decompose relations
into smaller relations to reduce redundancy
and while we do that, we will also have to
keep this in mind that the smaller ah relations
must be composable through certain natural
join procedure to the original relation, and
I must get back that original relation, otherwise
I have a lossy joint which is not acceptable.
Also, the decomposition will have the costs
of ah doing natural join every time I want
to answer those queries .
The next that we look at is ah the way the
relationships are categorized as first normal
form ah.
We consider that the domains of attributes
are atomic if they are indivisible.
So, anything that is a number string and so
on is considered to be atomic and we say a
relational schema is in its first normal form
if the domains of all attributes are atomic
and all attributes single value, there is
no multi value attribute.
If these conditions are satisfied, then we
will say that every relate that relational
schema is in its first normal form.
So, we will slowly understand the purpose
of ah defining such normal forms, but let
us initially understand the definition.
So, if we have ah attributes which are composite
in nature, naturally my relationship, my relational
schema is not in first normal form if we have
attributes which are ah multiple valued, it
is not so.
So, if we say that we have possible values
are like this, then if we just treat them
as strings, then the corresponding relational
schema is in first normal form, but if we
say that from this string we can extract the
first two characters which is CS which tells
me what is a department.
The next four characters gives me a number,
the serial number ah of the particular student
in the role.
Then I am not actually using an atomic ah
domain because my domain needs to be interpreted
separately than just being a value.
So, these are not parts of what can be a first
normal form.
So, I have given ah some examples of ah what
is not and what is first normal form.
So, this is an example where at the telephone
number ah field exists and there can be multiple
telephone numbers.
So, this is not in first normal form because
the telephone number itself is composite because
it has different components and also, you
can have multiple telephone number.
So, this relation is not in the first normal
form.
What you can do?
You can ah separate out these phone numbers
into two different attributes; Telephone number
1 and 2.
Even ah then it is not exactly in first normal
form because ah you do not know in which order
they should be handled.
If you have to search for a telephone number,
then you will have to search multiple attributes
which are conceptually same and then, the
question is why only two attributes.
Cannot anybody have ah 3 phone numbers, 7
phone numbers and so on.
So, this is really not a good option.
So, the other way could be that for every
telephone number, you introduce a separate
row.
Once you do that you already know you have
redundancy and you have possibilities of varied
kinds of anomalies that could happen.
So, one way it could be achieved is ah we
follow the principle that we had seen in ER
modelling that ah this multivalued dependency
can be represented in terms of a separate
relation where against the customer id we
just keep the telephone number.
So, we can keep multiple of them and we take
that out from the customer name.
So, one to many relationship between the parent
and the child, ah between the customer name
and telephone number, every customer may have
more than one ah telephone number is possible
and ah that makes it 2 NF ah relation, first
normal form relation and we will later on
see that it also is 2 NF and 3 NF, but that
is a future story .
Now, finally we ah come to the core of what
the mathematical formulation which dictates
much of the data base, relational database
design is known as functional dependencies.
I just talked about little bit of ah that
while talking about department name ah building
and budget.
Now, to decide whether a particular relation
is good or rather a particular relational
scheme is good, we need to check against certain
measures and if it is not good, we need to
decompose it into a set of relations such
that these conditions satisfy that every,
each one of these, R 1 R 2 R n.
So, I mean if you have ah you know got rusted,
then it is basically R i is a set of attributes
because it is a relational schema.
A relational schema is a set of attributes.
So, naturally R will be the union of all of
these, R i the total set of attributes.
So, instead of keeping all the information
into one relation in one table, we are basically
decomposing it into n different schemas.
So, what we need to guarantee is each one
of these relation R 1, R 2, R n is in good
form.
How do I get back the original relation?
Original relation that was represented by
all that attributes enough is to take a lossless
join.
This would take a join and that this decomposition
must give me a lossless join.
So, to ensure that we make use of two key
ideas more foundationally; functional dependencies
and then, multivalued dependencies .
A functional dependency is a constraint on
the set of legal relation.
So, ah mind you it is a constraint on the
schema and once that constraint is defined,
it must hold for all relations that the schema
satisfied . So, here we need that the value
of certain set of attributes uniquely determined
the value of another set of attributes.
So, I know the value of three attributes,
I should be able to say that the values of
the other four attributes would be fixed.
So, you have already seen this notion in terms
of ah key or super key.
You have seen that ah similar type of concept
exists where we said a key is a set of attributes,
so that if the values of two rows are identical
over these set of attributes, then the two
peoples, the two rows must be totally identical.
So, key is something which ah does a similar
thing as a functional dependency, but is more
specific.
Functional dependencies are generalization.
So, let us formally define that let R be a
relational schema which means that it is a
set of attributes and let us say alpha and
beta are two subsets of R , then we write
this and ah note this notation . Alpha is
a set of attributes ; beta is another set
of attributes.
Both are subset of the same R and we say alpha
functionally determines beta that is if I
know the value of a tuple over the attributes
of alpha, then the values of that tuple over
the attributes of beta would be fixed or in
other words, they say that if I have two tuples
t 1 and t 2 and their values over the set
of alpha attributes are same, then necessarily
their values over the set of beta attributes
must be same and mind you this is something
which is a design constraint.
It is not just an incidental property.
It is not just the fact that a particular
instance of a schema satisfies this, but when
you say this is a functional dependency, we
need all possible past, present and future
instances of the schema must satisfy this
.
So, consider this if you take a relation,
a schema with an instance as given here between
two attributes a and b, then we can say at
least given this instance not we still do
not know what happens in the whole schema
for all instances, but on this instance we
can say that functionally determines b does
not hold because between the first and the
second record, the value of a is same one,
but the value of we are different 4 and 5,
but we can certainly say that on this instance
at least we functionally determines holds
because whenever the value if we take any
two tuples, their value over b does not at
all match.
If they does not match, then naturally there
is no question of what happens to the value
of the tuple over the set of attributes a.
So, we will say that b functionally determining
a holds in this instance .
So, given this definition of functional dependency,
now we can have a formal definition of what
the super key is.
Super key is naturally a ah subset of attributes
which functionally determines the whole set
and a candidate key is a super key which is
minimal which means that k is a candidate
key.
If the two conditions have to satisfy this
condition say there is a super key that it
functionally determines all the attributes
and the other condition says minimality that
there is no subset alpha of k, such that alpha
functionally determines r if there exists
a subset alpha of k, the proper subset alpha
of k.
So, that alpha functionally determines r,
then k would not be a candidate key.
We will have to check for alpha.
So, these two what we had stated earlier in
qualitative terms and now mathematically established.
So, we can say that there are different functional
dependencies.
For example, in stepped combined relation
if we look at, then we know that department
name functionally determines building functionally.
So, these are functional dependencies that
must hold, but certainly we would not expect
department name to functionally determine
salary.
That would be too much, right.
So, ah functional dependencies are facts about
the real world that we try to understand from
the real world and then, represent in terms
of ah the functional dependency formulation
in the database.
So, we can use ah functional dependencies
to test relations if they are valid under
the set of functional dependencies.
So, there could be multiple functional dependencies
in the set and if a relation we are using
small r here just to remind you that a relation
means that a particular instance is legal
under a set of functional dependencies.
We will say that r satisfies that and if we
have that it holds F will be satisfied by
all possible instances of a relational schema
capital R, then we say F holds on R.
So, a relation satisfies a functional set
of functional dependencies and a relational
schema for a relational schema,.
The functional depend set of functional dependencies
holds on that schema which means that for
all possible past, present and future instances
relations, the relations will satisfy the
functional dependencies . So, we have ah for
example id.
We know id functionally determines name that
if the id is distinct, then the name has to
be distinct, but ah we may find that instance
where name functionally determines id.
So, we can say that names functionally determines
id is satisfied by a particular instance where
it so happens that there is no two ah rows
where the name is identical, but we cannot,
may not be able to infer that as this dependency
holding on the relational scheme as a whole
because tomorrow we can get another entry,
so that two rows might match on the name,
but could still be distinct entries not matching
on id.
So, that is how this will ah have to be looked
at ah in specificity.
We say that a functional dependency is trivial
if the left hand side is a superset of the
right hand side.
So, if I have a bigger set of attributes on
the left hand side id and name, then obviously
id and name will functionally determine id,
id and name will functionally determine name,
name will functionally determine name.
So, if you just think about because in a functional
dependency the left hand side attributes that
tuples have to match on the left hand side
attribute and if they do, then they must match
on the right hand side attribute.
So, if the right hand side set of attributes
is a subset of the left hand side, then obviously
the functional dependency will be vacuously
true and these are called trivial dependencies
.
So, in the next couple of slides, I have shown
ah few examples of functional dependencies
of different tables.
Here student id functionally determines semesters
which mean that we are trying to model ah
that ah a student cannot be at the same time
in two semesters, then student id and lecture
together functionally determines who is TA
and so on and you can see for this ah particular
relation student id and lecture, pair also
happens to be the candidate key .
These are ah another example.
So, these are just go through them, try to
convince yourself that these functional dependencies
are ah very genuinely real world situations
that can be modeled in this way .
Given a set of functional dependencies, we
can ah actually compute a closure.
For example, if A functionally determines
B and B functionally determines C, then we
can infer that A functionally determined because
if two peoples match on, A determines b says
that they match on B. Now, if B functionally
determines C also holds, then if match on
B, they match on C. So, if the match on A,
then necessarily they may have to match on
C. So, this is called the logical implication
of a set of functional dependencies and we
will see more of this ah later, but if we
take all functional dependencies of a given
set F, that are logically implied from this
set F.
We said that is a closure set and we represent
that by F plus.
So, F plus necessarily is a superset of F.
So, here in that above example, this is F
and this is F plus.
So, we will continue more on the theory of
functional dependencies, but ah let us conclude
this module by summarizing that we have identified
the features of good relational designs tradeoff
between decomposition and lossless join properties
that we need.
We are familiarized with ah the first normal
form and atomic domains and we have introduced
the notion of functional dependencies on which
we will build up more and try to get 0 on
very concrete strategies for good results.