Welcome to module 19 of Database Management
Systems; we have been discussing relational
database design and this is the fourth part;
fourth module in that series.
In the last module, we have discussed about
algorithms for functional dependencies lossless
joint decomposition and dependency preservation.
So, based on this ah foundational algorithms
and concepts.
We will in today's module get into understanding
the core design aspects of relational databases;
that is a normal forms and how important they
are in terms of the relational design. We
would specifically learn about decomposition
of a relational schema into the third normal
form and into Boyce Codd BCNF form.
So, our ah topics ah will be the three normal
forms decomposition of 3 NF and into BCNF.
So, starting with the normal forms. So, normal
forms or normalization of a schema is a technique
of refinement to organize the data in the
database. So, the question naturally arises
as to why do we need to do this refinement
after we have done a design ah based on possibly
the E-R diagram based approach that we had
talked of we had ah identified the entities
and we had identified the attributes for the
entities their relationships; then why do
we need to normalize?
The answer to this question lies in the fact
that ah ah a design for a relational schema
may give rise to a variety of anomalies in
terms of the data. These are typically three
anomalies which concerns us most the insertion,
the update and the deletion anomaly. So, the
anomaly is happen when there is redundancy
in the data in terms of the schema. And whether
there will be redundant data and how much
ah what kind of redundant data would be there
depends on the design of the database schema
depends on the design of the normal form that
we are using for it.
But if we have redundancy then there is potential
for anomalies and therefore, we want to reduce
the redundancy and get rid of this anomaly.
So, we will quickly take a look into the anomalies
that are ah that we are talking of first one
is ah called an update anomaly. So, we are
showing you a snapshot of an instance ah of
a database which has three attributes and
you can look at the row having two entries
the last two rows for employee code 519 and
there are two different addresses in these
two different rows. So, if we know that the
employee will have a unique address or in
other words if employee ID would determine
the employee address functionally determine
that employee address then this situation
is not possible.
So, but when we try to update then it is ah
for example, the employees address has changed.
And while making that change this change will
need to be incorporated in all the records
having the same ID. And if because of some
coding error or something we miss out to update
any of the address fields then we will have
a difficulty and that difficulty is having
inconsistent address data as in this case.
So, this is known as update anomaly similarly
I could have an insertion anomaly which I
am illustrating here in terms of another ah
database schema which has four attributes.
And ah we have faculty ID name the hiring
date and the course name naturally given the
faculty ID the faculty name and hire date
should be unique. Now suppose a new faculty
joins and as soon as the faculty joins he
or she may not have an assigned course.
So ah if we want to enter that record here
we will not be able to do that because we
do not have any value for the course code.
So, either we use a null value or we cannot
actually enter this value; this kind of situation
is known as a insertion anomaly. Similarly
I could have a deletion anomaly in the in
the same table ah we are showing that in the
table the first highlighted row; the for faculty
ID 389 if that faculty stops taking any course
for the time being.
So, the association between 389 and the corresponding
course code will be removed and once you remove
that you remove this whole record in the process
you actually lose the whole of the faculty
information the ID, name and hire date. So,
these are difficulties in these ah relational
schemas and that lead to ah a whole lot of
problems.
So, the resolution for this lie in terms of
decomposing the schema that instead of having
one relation, I will decompose this set of
attributes into multiple different relations.
So, for example, the update anomaly can be
ah removed if we have two different tables;
one that maintains ID with address and one
that maintains ID with skill. So, in that
case what will happen if the the for every
ID the address will not be repeated.
So, if the address is updated; it will be
updated only at one place and it will not
feature in the other table. Similarly to avoid
insert or delete anomaly the other table schema
can be split into ID name and hire date as
one table and ID and code rows code as another
table. And you can you can easily understand
that if this is split in this way then you
cannot have an insert anomaly because you
can insert a new ah faculty without assigning
a course to him because that will feature
in as a separate record in a different table
similarly in the same way the deletion anomaly
also disappears.
So, these anomalies are ah resultant of ah
the redundant data that we are having and
can be removed by taking care of the process
of decomposition.
Now, when we decompose then we would desire
certain properties to be hold held and we
talked about this ah loosely earlier as well.
We would require the lossless join decomposition
property that it should be possible to take
any instance of the two or more decomposed
relations and join them by natural join using
common set of attributes and get back the
original ah instance of the relation if that
does not happen then the relationship is lossy
we have discussed it at length in the last
module. At the same time we would want that
all functional dependencies that hold must
be; can must be testable in the decomposed
set of relation.
So, all functional dependencies when they
are projected in terms of the decomposed set
of relations; they must be testable within
them. So, that to test for a dependency I
do not need to carry out a join this is a
point we discussed in the last module as well.
So, based on that once you start with the
original schema, you can check for what are
the different possibilities or sources of
redundancy define constraints based on that
and step by step; you could convert a schema
into a one normal form have more constraints
put onto it convert it into two normal form
have further constraints decompose it into
third normal form and so, on.
So, normalization is a process through which
we do this kind of decomposition and make
sure that once a relational schema is expressed
in terms of a normal form; it satisfies a
given set of properties that that normal form
should adhere to. And the common normal forms
are 1 NF, 2 NF and 3 NF and loosely speaking
when we say if a database schema is ah is
normalized; we normal usually mean that it
is in the 3 NF form a third normal form. And
most third number form relations are free
of insert, delete or update anomalies. So,
that they are a good positive in the design.
Ah Of course, ah these are not the only normal
forms as you can see there is a whole lot
of lists of variety of normal forms; we will
not study all of them we will study ah further
in the next module the other two highlighted
ones.
But first let us get started with the first
normal form which we had talked about earlier
as well; that first normal form is one where
the multivalued attributes are not allowed.
So, if you think about a think about a relationship
where you have a student relationship between
student the her name and the courses taken
by the student then since the students take
multiple courses; the C name in this case
can take multiple values. So, we do not allow
that we expand them into different rows and
ah that once we have done that we say that
relation is in the one normal form.
But one normal form may give rise to a variety
of ah different redundancies and therefore,
anomalies. So, this is another instance; in
fact, the earlier instances that you saw all
of them were ah also in one normal form, but
they had deletion insertion and update anomaly.
So, here is another example where we are illustrating
that.
So, it is a possible that if I have a functional
dependency X determining Y which is nontrivial
ah functional dependency over the set of attributes
and X is not a super key; then there exists
a redundancy between X and Y attribute set.
So, on the left the we have shown an instance
of ah ah this relationship on only on the
X and Y attributes and you can see since X
is not a key; I can have two rows having the
value one in X.
And since the value is 1 in X; the value Y
will be same for these two rows and we have
redundancy of that please all. Please remember
that X is not a super key; so, there are other
attributes which actually form the super key
and therefore, such instances are possible.
Whereas if you look at the right column where
the left hand side X is a super key then such
instances will not happen.
Moving on ah the second normal form which
ah is ah; obviously, a relation is is in second
normal form if it is in first normal form
and it does not have any partial dependency.
So, what is the partial dependency? I have
given the definition here partial dependency
why determining A if that that can hold in
the set of functional dependency then if I
have that Y is a proper subset of a candidate
key and A is a nonprime attribute in nonprime
attribute is one which one nonprime attribute
we defined in the last module is an attribute
which does not feature in any of the candidate
keys.
So, if Y is a proper subset of a candidate
key which functionally determines a nonprime
attribute; then this is known as a partial
dependency and if there is partial dependency
then the relationship is not in second normal
form. So, second normal form will require
that the relation is in 1 NF and there is
no partial dependency.
So, here I were showing an example where on
the left you can see that ah SID and C name
together forms a key and SID determines S
name. So, SID and C name together also determines
S name naturally SID determining S name is
a partial dependency because the left hand
side SID is a proper subset of the candidate
key SID C name. And S name is not ah featuring
in any candidate key. So, S name is actually
a nonprime attribute and the result of that
as you can see in the first two rows or in
the third and fourth row you can see that
S name is ah repeated.
So, there is redundancy and therefore, consequently
we will have anomalies that we have talked
of, but we can normalize we can decompose
this into two separate relations R1 and R2
as I am showing on the right; where you associate
SID and S name in one table and SID and C
name in other table. Naturally then the the
dependency that the partial dependency that
you had disappears because SID determining
S name in R1; now becomes is not a partial
dependency because in that table SID becomes
a primary key. So, it does not qualify as
a partial dependency.
So, R1 and R2 both are in second normal form
and you will get rid of the redundancy that
you saw and this decomposition is ah ensures
that it has a list lossless join incidentally;
this is we have not guaranteed that it is
in second ah normal form and it has also the
dependency preservation.
But it is ah possible again in second normal
form a relation could be in second normal
form yet it could have some possible redundancies.
So, there is a design instance that I am showing
with ah the supplier ID, SID the status key
which are ah functionally determined by SID
and the product and quantity values.
So, that in the table supplier SID and PID
together form say key whereas, and ah as that
happens you can clearly see that there is
a lot of ah redundancy that you can see in
terms of the status happening and which will
cause you different anomalies to occur. So,
if I normalize in the second normal form on
the right then I will have a supplier city
say with the three attributes SID status and
city and another supplier quantity which has
SID PID and quantity naturally in this there
is no partial dependency anymore.
Earlier we had SID determining status as a
partial dependency because SID is a proper
was a proper subset of the primary key which
is SID CID, but after I normalize this dependency
does not exist, but yet there will be redundancy
in this ah relationship and there the status
will continue to be redundant.
And for that reason we have to move on to
the next type of normal form. So, this I am
just explaining here as to what are the possible
redundancy sources of possible redundancy
that you can have in 2 NF.
In the 3 NF; third normal form what you define
is your relation first of all has to be in
2 NF. So, we are looking at the the first
definition these are there are three forms
of definitions given all of them are actually
equivalent, you do not have to worry about
why and how they are equivalent slowly you
will start understanding.
But we take it in in three different forms
because each form of the definition allow
us to understand certain aspect of the three
normal form. So, the first thing which is
true for everything is ah it has to be in
the second normal form and it should not contain
any transitive dependency which means that
I should not if I have X determining Y and
Y determining Z; then I should not have X
determining Z which can be ah inferred transitively
as you know through the angstrom axiom.
Alternatively there was an alternate definition
given later on ah by Zaniolo and ah I have
stated a simpler simplified version of that
at the bottom. So, we will say that a relational
schema is in 3 NF if for every functional
dependency X determining a that holds on this
schema either it is a trivial dependency which
is X is a A is a subset of X or X is a super
key.
So, this is kind of the condition also as
you had seen earlier this also is a condition
to be in Boyce Codd normal form. So, you can
easily understand the 3 NF is a ah any relation
which is in 3 NF is also in the Boyce Codd
normal form, but we add a fourth third condition
where you say that we will say this is in
3 NF; even if the first two conditions are
not satisfied, but a is a part of some key
just note the wording is a part of some key
not just the super key.
So, if A is a part of some key then and the
first two conditions are also not are not
satisfied even then we will say that the relation
is in third normal form. So, to check for
a relation to be in third normal form; we
will actually check for whether any one of
the three conditions hold .
So, this is a definition of ah transitive
dependency which I have just loosely told
you. So, I will skip over this ah.
There is given another example of a very different
kind of a relationship book genre author and
author nationality as you can understand.
Given the book you know the author there is
a functional dependency given the author do
you know the author nationality and the, but
author does not actually determine the book
because the author may have written multiple
books ah. But given that book determines author
and author determines author nationality we
have that book determines author nationality
and therefore, we have redundancy possibility
of redundancy in here which is a transitive
ah redundance due to this transitive dependency
that we have.
So, here is a the earlier example where you
can as you can see see clearly in this diagram
you can if you note this diagram you can see
that SID determines ah ah city and city determines
status. So, this is it this is the transitive
dependency that SID determines status.
So, if that happens and status becomes ah
redundant and therefore, there could be anomalies.
And we can easily normalize by ah making them
into SID and city and city and status. And
in that naturally that that redundancy goes
away because you have no more the transitive
dependency in the relationship; you only have
ah SID determining the city which is a primary
key in S C and city determining status which
is the primary key in the C S.
So, there are ah these are other examples
that that you can go through where we have
I have taken the example of a ah student ID
I ID and the department name and ah shown
that what kind of ah problems, you might get
into in this. In this case you can see that
the relationship actually is in ah the ah
there because there are two candidate keys
and ah. So, this SID department name is a
super key and this relationship is in the
third normal form. Because IID determining
department name is contained in a candidate
key. So, that is the it is a it is in 3 NF
due to the third condition that we have had
shown.
So, when you, but this is a where you can
ah there is some redundancy in this schema
that you can ah observe. So, this is just
constructed and you have been because of this
redundancy you have been able to we have had
to use null values in this case. So, in a
third normal form there is possible ah redundancy
coming in and ah these are the different cases
that we have to check through.
So, next what ; so, we have seen the different
normal forms first normal form no multivalued
attribute then the second normal form no partial
dependency then the third normal form where
you do not have any transitive dependency.
So, all these are ah cascading ah definitions.
So, in third normal form you have low multivalued
attribute, no partial dependency and no transitive
dependency.
So, now what will take a look into is how
if I am given a relational schema and if it
is violating any one or more of this condition.
So, that the schema is not in the three three
normal form third normal form then how can
we decompose it into the third normal form?
So, the question naturally is ah certainly
is ah is can can it always be done is the
basic question that can I always decompose
a schema into third normal form the answer
is yes you can and that is always a lossless
join and dependency preserving decomposition
into third normal form which is of great value.
Because that is we said is that desirable
properties of our decomposition and if you
recall our discussions in the earlier part
of ah the relational design ah modulesm, then
you would recall that Boyce Codd normal form
also we had discussed at the early stages.
And that gives you a decomposition which is
lossless join, but it does not guarantee preservation
of the dependencies with third normal form
does that .
So, naturally there are different ah algorithms
first the question is can you test if a relationship
is in third normal form; I will not go into
the details of that and the computer science
result here is testing for third normal form
is an NP hard problem. So, there is no known
polynomial time algorithm for that, but the
interesting thing is the actually that decomposition
can be done in very simply in polynomial time.
So, what do you have what is the decomposition
algorithm very written in very simple terms
you want to ah you have given a relation R
and a set of functional dependencies that
hold on you. So, you first compute a canonical
cover you you know what is a canonical cover.
So, you compute a canonical covers you eliminate
extraneous attributes eliminate redundant
FDs and you have the canonical cover F c from
F then you create for every functional dependency
X determining Y that exists in the canonical
cover.
You compute you make a relation say the ith
relation taking union of X and Y. So, you
call it the relation X Y and you do that for
all the functional dependencies in the cover.
And after that if you find that the key does
not occur in any one of these ah decomposed
relations as generated, then you generate
one separate relation to represent the key.
That is a very simple algorithm and I I just
wrote it in ah simple hand. So, that you can
understand it easily, but here is the formal
algorithm. So, if you are interested to ah
rigor I mean in the in the rigor of how 3
NF decomposition will happen here is the algorithm,
but I will not go through these in steps.
So, that ensures that each relation ah R i
that I have decomposed and generated is actually
in third normal form and this decomposition
is dependency preserving and is lossless join
we are not proving that but we are just using
that result.
So, here is an example of a schema; so, we
have a customer banker branch. So, these are
the four attributes and these are the different
functional dependencies that exist. Now naturally
given this first thing you will have to do
is first thing you have to do is to ah look
at the different to look at taking the canonical
cover the minimal cover.
So, if you compute try to compute the minimal
cover; you will find that branch name actually
is extraneous in the first dependency. So,
you can remove that and there is nothing else.
So, your canonical cover turns out to be this
set of dependencies and then you go over and
for each one of them. So, you you take each
one the first one is customer ID employee
ID determines type. So, for that you generate
a schema customer ID, employee ID and type
again you ah take the second functional dependency
employee ID determines branch name. So, create
employee ID and branch name as a different
schema and in this way you will generate three
decomposed schema in the third normal form.
Now, once you have done that then you find
that your if you look into the original key
it was customer ID and employee ID and you
find that here in the third ah second and
the third you already have that. So, you do
not need to add a separate relation for ah
accommodating the key and also ah the third
relation. So, we can now declare that no further
key needs to be added and we have the final
3 NF decomposition.
So, at the end of the fault detect and delete.
So, this is this is a stated in terms of the
detailed algorithm, but this is ah you can
say that the employee ID and branch name the
second ah relation in the decomposition is
actually a subset of the third relation. So,
you can remove that as well. So, you will
be left with only two relations in this decompose
schema which both of which are in third normal
form and this decomposition is guaranteed
you lossless join and dependency preservation.
So, I have ah given some practice problems
for you I have also given the solution, but
the solution is not in the current run of
the presentation; you will get see them in
the presentation as hidden slides. So, you
first try solving them and once ah you have
solved them then you look at the solution
in the slide.
So, there are two problems; so, this is a
second one and you can solve them in that
way.
Next is the we will quickly recap on the decomposition
of BCNF Boyce Codd normal form which we had
seen earlier.
And we know that the Boyce Codd normal form
guarantees that there will have be every dependency
that exists must be either trivial or the
left hand side must be a super key. So, using
the algorithms, you can test for the Boyce
Codd normal form which is described here I
am not going through in in steps.
And ah here is the more detailed formal algorithm
to find ah determine whether a ah Boyce Codd
normal form is in a a decomposed form is in
Boyce Codd.
So, I will just quickly recap on the algorithm
to do that naturally for all ah dependencies
you first determine the super key and check
if A determining B is a super key or not if
it and that you can easily do using attribute
cover. If it is not a super key then you choose
a dependency A determining B which violates
and you form by Boyce Codd goes in in in ah
every step it decomposes one relation into
two separate relation.
So, one that you take by taking union of ah
the attributes of A and B and the other where
you take out B minus A; these attributes this
difference attributes you take out from R
and then you add A and make the other relationship.
Naturally ah in between these two A is a common
attribute and since ah and that will ah determine
A B because A determines B.
So, A will determine A B that is whole of
R1. So, naturally the lossless ah join is
guaranteed and you ah repeat that ah keep
on doing that for the resultant relations
that you have got. keep on decomposing them
till you finally, close and you have no more
ah violating dependency and you will have
a decomposition into Boyce Codd normal form.
Here is the formal algorithm again for ah
you to go by steps ah if you are interested.
Otherwise you know how to do this; again I
have shown another example here which is ah
showing that ah how to decompose in BCNF.
So, you should practice this ah that is why
I have work them out in steps here. So, here
A determines B; B determine C naturally A
is the key R is not in BCNF because B determining
C is ah is a functional dependency where B
is not a super key.
So, you can ah decompose them in terms of
ah. So, you can decompose in terms of ah B
C as one relation and A B as another relation.
Here is ah another example a more detailed
one of a class relationship which has a whole
set of attributes and these functional dependencies
and based on that the candidate key is course
ID, section ID, semester and year and you
can proceed with the BCNF decomposition; taking
the first functional dependency that holds,
but the left hand side the course ID is not
a super key. So, you will replace it by a
one relation; which is say new course relation
and a new class relation which is the remaining
attributes.
And then you you get convinced that course
is in BCNF, but the other one the class is
not because building and room number determines
capacity where building room number together
is not a super key. So, you split it again
and you replace class 1 in terms of 2 new
ah relations class room and section and both
of them are in BCNF and you are done with
this.
But BCNF as I would again warning you BCNF
does not preserve ah dependence it gives you
lossless join, but it does not preserve the
dependencies. So, it is not always possible
to decompose into BCNF with dependency preservation.
So, here is an example which we saw little
earlier and there are two candidate keys R
is not in BCNF, you can clearly see and any
decomposition will fail JK determining L and
that will require a join. So, this will not
preserve the dependencies ah in terms of ah
the decomposition.
Again I have given a set of ah practice problems
here which we you should try and get confident
in terms of the Boyce Codd from normal form
normalization.
Now, it is ah always possible to decompose
a relation into a set of relation in 3 NF;
if the decomposition is lossless and the dependencies
are preserved. Whereas, in case of BCNF it
is not possible; so, here is a table which
summarizes the relative comparison between
Boyce Codd and third normal form because they
are the common once Boyce Codd naturally is
more strict it gives you lesser dependent
lesser redundancies, but it cannot guarantee
that your dependencies will be preserved.
So, ah more often we will accept 3 NF as an
acceptable normalized decomposition with some
redundancy still existing it is possible and
we cannot get rid of them.
So, we have ah studied about the normal forms
and their importance and how progressively
we can increase the constraints to minimize
redundancy in the schema and learned how to
decompose a schema into third normal form
and also in the Boyce Codd normal form.