Welcome to module 33 of Database Management
Systems. This is on transactions again there
is a third and closing module on transactions
and, we will ah discuss ah recoverability
issues and some more of the serializability
issues in this module. In the last module
we have talked at length about serializability
and specifically, we looked at what is known
as conflict serializability and the algorithm
to detect that. ah
Now, we would bring in another perspective
is if while a transaction is in execution
what if the system would fail the failure
may be due to hardware software, various different
reasons power outage, disk crash and so on.
So, why when that happens the database is
likely to come into an inconsistent state.
So, we would like to discuss how to recover
from that inconsistent state and bring it
back to a consistent state.
We would also look at that going forward from
conflict serializability, what are the other
notions of serializability, that can be used
to serialize transactions and we will look
at a weaker definition of serializability
known as view serializability, which can serialize
more schedules than what conflict serializability
can give us. So, these are the topics to discuss
and we start with recoverability and isolation.
So, what we have done is we have seen the
serializability help us, if we think in terms
of the acid properties ah that ah we started
by defining as the desirable properties of
the transactions, we have seen that the serializability
significantly helps us to achieve isolation
and consistency of a schedule, yet the atomicity
and consistency may be compromised, if there
is a system failure.
So, we had talked about this example a bit
earlier again let us take a look. So, this
is a transaction where an amount of 50 dollar
is being transferred from account A to account
B. So, he first read debit and then write
on account A and then read credit and write
to account B and we have added a 7th instruction,
which is commit and I will talk more about
that ah in this module which makes that changes
to a and B permanent and shows a result to
the user as well.
Now, what happens if the system fails between
step 3 and after step 3 when a has been written
and between before step 4 step 6 when B has
finally, been written. So, naturally 50 dollars
will simply disappear because what has been
debited from A and will be available to be
seen in account A will the corresponding credit
will not be visible. So, this leads to inconsistent
state and to handle that what we need to do
is to roll back the transaction, which means
that we need to undo the changes that we have
already done. So, we have to again go back
to account A and write a new value which was
the earlier value the value before the debit
had happened. And this process of ah restoring
the consistency back to the database is known
as the recovery process.
So, we say that a so, let us define a schedule
to be recoverable if a transaction T j reads
A data previously written by a transaction
T i, then the commit operation of T i must
appear before the commit operation of T j,
if that happens then that is the earlier transaction
which has written the data and T j the later
transaction which is reading the data the
earlier transaction has to commit that is
make the changes permanent in the database
before T j actually reads it. If that happens,
then we say that that schedule is a recoverable
schedule.
So, consider a following schedule of transactions
T 8 and T 9 where ah T 8 has read and written
A, but has not committed; that means, some
more tasks in T 8 are still pending it has
not finished, but T 9 then reads A which is
a in terms of serializability it is fine,
but then T 9 commits and then T 8 is again
trying to read B the continues. So, what happens
is what if the transaction will fail the transaction
T 9 will fail immediately after the read operation.
So, what will happen I am sorry, if T 8 aborts
in between, then what will happen that T 9
would have read because, say in read B or
of T 8 T 8 aborts that it fails, then T 9
has already read the intermediate value of
A and has committed which means it is possibly
shown it to the user, but T 8 since it has
aborted sent it has failed, it has to be rolled
back and the original value of A will be rolled
back which is different from what has already
been shown to the user and he will reach an
inconsistent state.
So, this is an example of a schedule which
is not recoverable. Now let us also observe
that a single transaction failure not only
means that one transaction needs to be rolled
back, but it could have a cascading effect,
that is a series of transaction may require
a rollback. So, here is an example of T 10
T 11 and T 12. So, T 10 reads A and B and
writes A and then T 11 reads and writes A
and T 12 reads A and at that time if T 10
fails if that aborts, then naturally it is
not enough to simply ah roll back T 10 because,
if we roll back T 10, then we the value of
a goes back to the original and T 11 would
have a wrong value which T 10 had written,
but has now been undone has now been rolled
back.
So, it means that T 11 will also have to be
rolled back. Similarly if that is rolled back
then naturally T 12 also have to be rolled
back and so on and when this rolling back
goes from one transaction to the other we
say this is the cascading roll back. And this
can lead to a significant amount of work.
So, what we would prefer is if we could have
schedules where such cascading ah roll back
is not required. So, and and there is a there
is a condition through which you can achieve
that. So, if we have a pair of transaction
T i and T j. So, that T j reads A data item
previously written by T i, then the commit
operation of T i has to happen before the
read operation of T j which means that said
in other words that T j should read only read
values which are already committed and not
read intermediate temporary values of other
transactions.
So, every cascadable ah schedule is also recoverable
because, you can individually recover that
and it is desirable to restrict schedules
to those which are cascade less as far as
possible, we will see that in non not all
cases that is possible, but if it is possible
you would like schedules which are cascade
less. So, that covered a rollback work the
extra work can be minimized. So, here is an
example which we had just seen which is not
a cascadable schedule.
So, wait for word let us take a couple of
examples of very similar ah transactions and,
ah we would see when their schedules are irrecoverable,
when their cascade dead recovery is possible
cascaded rollback is possible and, when cascade
less rollback is possible. So, if you so,
here what I have done is I have shown here
the 2 transactions T 1 and T 2. And this is
what transaction T 1 is doing and we assume
that in the in the database the initial value
of a is 5000.
So, what will happen is read here and this
value is is a different A this is in the buffer
or the memory of T 1 transaction, where A
becomes 5000, then you subtract 1000 and then
you write back the moment you write back in
the database in between the value in the database
is not changing, it is only that value is
only in the buffer and, when you write back
the value in the database has changed.
And then transaction T 2 reads that value.
So, in its local buffer a becomes 4000 it
increments by 500 and then writes it back
and when that happens, then in the database
also the value has changed to 4500 and then
T 2 commits and at this point let us assume
that there was if there was a failure. So,
this is the point where there was a failure
there were other instructions in T 1 as well
which is not of our interest right now, and
then T 1 would have committed, but what happens
if the failure happens at this point naturally
the T 1 needs to roll back T 1 needs to undo
this and set the this value 5000 back into
the database.
But that would mean that what T 2 has committed
T 2 has already committed this value 4500
in the database and therefore, that has been
probably been used in other places and shown
to the user that will create an inconsistency
in the database. So, these are this is a schedule
of T 1 and T 2 which cannot be recovered from.
So, let us and so what it has what has been
violated that T 2 has actually read A value
which was in transit and, then it has already
committed based on that read value.
Now, let us look into the next. So, what has
been done here that all the changes are the
same, but the only point that we have done
is we have changed the point where the comet
happens again still the T 2 is reading the
same value in our in a and is making the updates
4500, but the commit happens at a later point
of time after the commit of this transaction
T 1 has taken place.
So, this is recoverable, but if we want to
recover T 1 naturally; that means, that for
T 1 to be recovered, I also need to recover
T 2 because T 2 is used a value which is not
going to be the value in after the rollback
of T 1 has happened T 2 has used 4000, but
after the rollback the value in the database
will be back to 5000. So, it is the rollback
is required for T 1 as well as in T 2. So,
this is a case of cascaded cascading roll
back that has happened. So, some more work
is being done and that has happened because
T 2 now here the rollback is possible because
T 2 is committing after T 1.
So, the transaction it is reading from it
is actually committing the changes after that
source transaction has committed. So, that
satisfies the condition of recoverable schedule.
So, you are able to recover, but it still
required the cascading because T 1 had read
A value in here of A which was not yet committed.
So, if we would have committed that, then
we would have been able to actually create
a schedule which is cascade less as we see
in the next slide.
So, now I what the change that has happened
is a commit is done, right after writing the
value of A and T 2 reads that only after that
commit has happened, earlier it was reading
before that commit has happened. So, once
T 2 reads it after this commit. So, if there
is some there is some requirement of if there
is some situation of rollback, then only T
1 needs to be rolled back and T 2 does not
need to be a rollback because, it has used
a value which is already committed.
So, this is the basic through the example
you can clearly see, what is how the rollback
can happen and in a later module, we will
discuss the processes of how to do this kind
of rollback the cascading and non cascading
both kinds and show how to go ahead with that,
but now for now what we learned is schedules
need to be recoverable and, preferably cascade
less rollback recovery schedules are preferred
in case of database transactions.
Now, let us move on and talk little bit about
what is available in SQL language in terms
of handling transactions. So, SQL we have
seen the kind of DDL data definition and data
manipulation language paths and those were
discussed in terms of our interactive session
as well. As a part of data manipulation it
is also possible to specify certain specific
transaction events. So, a transaction in SQL
typically begins implicitly and, it ends by
a commit work which says that let us, you
commit the current transaction that is make
all the changes permanent, in the database
make it visible to the user and begin a new
work, or it could roll back the transaction
which means that all the changes that you
had done are rolled back and the transaction
basically aborts.
So, in almost all systems by default every
SQL statement commits implicitly and, if it
has been able to execute successfully, otherwise
it rolls back and this implicit commit can
be controlled also, it can be in different
system there are different ways to control
that and say that I do not want implicit commit
I would only want commit to be done explicitly.
So, for that purpose a part of SQL called
the transaction control language has different
instructions commit to save the changes roll
back to roll back, the changes undo the changes
and also to do some do,it in some controlled
way by defining save point and you can also
set the a particular name to a transaction
and it is behavior.
So, let us look at examples for doing that
soon and these TCL commands are are used with
specific DML commands they are meaningful
in terms of insert update and delete only
for example, if you are creating a database
or you are doing a select to data retrieval,
then these instructions have no role in those
transactions.
So, commit is a transaction command which
is used to save changes and make them permanent
based on what has been invoked. So, here you
see the example of a customer database and,
what I am showing is if you this is the initial
state of that table and, before any value
has been deleted and if you do select star
from customers these 7 records is what you
get to see, in view of that you do a delete
and then you commit the delete.
So, we say that I have deleted and make that
deletion permanent. So, deleting based on
age. So, this record is supposed to be get
deleted and this record is supposed to get
deleted and, after I have done the commit
then again if I do the same ah data retrieval.
And now I get to see 5 records only the 2
record number 2 and record number 4 have been
permanently deleted. So, this is the way you
can explicitly do commit and make the changes
permanent.
In terms of rollback it is a command which
is used to undo transactions that is the changes
that have already not been saved to the database
you can roll back.
So, you can roll back or undo transactions
only back up in history up to the last commit,
or the last rollback command was issued on
this. So, again looking at the same example
this is the initial state and, then you did
a delete as we did last time. So, these 2
records are to be deleted, but then instead
of commit we have given a rollback. So, as
you give rollback this deletion operations
get undone. So, these 2 records are again
back to the table and so, after the rollback
if I again do the select I will get to see
the 2 records back in my list. So, this is
the purpose of the rollback command.
Now, you can a transactions often could be
long. So, within the transaction you may want
to mark certain points. So, that in case you
roll back or you need to roll back, you can
roll back to that particular point and those
points are in the transaction are known as
the save point. So, this is the format use
a save point and give it a name and, then
later on you can use those save points for
your purpose of rollback.
So, you are again if you are doing a rollback,
then you instead of just doing rollback, you
now use the save point ID that you had used
in naming that particular point up to which
you want to roll back and, do a rollback and
that will happen only up to that point. So,
let us look at an example so, here it is a
series of instructions in a in a DML transaction.
So, I initially set SP one as a save point
that is I may want to roll back to the beginning,
when I delete one record say ID 1. So, 1 record
gets deleted, then I again save another save
point another save point SP 2 this was SP
1 and, then delete a second record another
save point delete another record.
So, now I have a control to undo at this point
have a control to undo to 3 points for example,
if I do a rollback 2 SP 3 I will roll back
to this point, where only this record will
be deletion of this record will be undone,
but the first 2 records will still look show
as deleted, but if I roll back to save point
SP 2, then 2 records ID 2 and ID 3 that were
deleted their deletion will be undone and
only 1 deletion will look up. Similarly if
I roll back to SP 1, it will show that no
deletion as it all happened.
So, if I do that on the this is the initial
state on the left to the initial state of
the database 3 records have been deleted and,
then I do undo off the first deletion of the
first 2 and I roll back to SP 2. So, then
when I undo the deletion of the last 2 records,
then the what I see is the records which are
marked as ID 2 and ID 3, which were done after
SP 2 was marked which were deleted after SP
2 are marked, they are back into the table
whereas, the deletion of SP 1 is still in
effect and therefore, deletion that was none
after SP 1 that is of record ID 1 is still
missing and in this way you can control and
roll back to any specific point in a database
in a database transaction.
You can once you have marked a safe point
you can also, release the safe point that
is you can choose to forget that safe point.
Once a safe point has been released you cannot
roll back to that safe point naturally.
You can use set transaction command to initiate
a database transaction also and, it is typically
used to specify the characteristics of the
transaction, particularly if you want to say
whether a transaction is a read only transaction
or a read write transaction, then you can
do it in this way, you can say set transaction
and give a read or write flag read or write
or read only flag for that.
Let us quickly take a look at a different
form of serializability besides the conflict
serializability is called view serializability.
So, in terms of view serializability we again
define what is known as when are 2 tran schedules
defined to be view equivalent, earlier you
remember we define 2 schedules to be conflict
equivalent, now we are defining view equivalent.
So, there are 3 conditions the conditions
are simple what conditions say is a to try
a schedules are view equivalent, if the transaction
the initial value that a transaction reads
is same in both these schedules, for every
transaction the initial value that it reads
must be the same between the 2 schedules.
Similarly, the third condition says that the
final write that is done, final value that
it writes every transaction writes in both
the schedules must be the same the same same
rights should operate. And the second conditions
is a is a read write pair that every transaction
when it performs a read on the data item,
it must read from the write corresponding
write in the other schedule in by the same
by the transaction that which did the right.
So, I always initialize start with the same
initial values for every data item in both
schedules, I always read from the corresponding
right in the same schedule in the 2 schedules
and, I must write the final in every transaction
every data item must be written in the same
way in the 2 schedules.
So, this is again and the key balance is based
purely on read write alone as is the case
of conflict equivalence also.
So, given the definition of view ah equivalence,
we can say schedule is the view serializable,
if it is view equivalent to a serial schedule
earlier which said said that a schedule is
conflict serializable, if it is conflict equivalent
to a serial schedule. Now we are defining
the view serializability, ah with a little
bit of thought you can convince yourself that
every conflict serializable schedule is also
view serializable, but the reverse is not
true.
So, here is a schedule which is view serializable,
but it is not conflict serializable, you know
this is not conflict serializable because,
certainly you cannot make it into a serial
schedule make it equivalent to a serial schedule
because, you cannot move this right Q above
the right Q of T 28 or of T 29, but you cannot
move this either. So, given that but if you
in terms of the view equivalence we balance,
then you will say that this is ah equivalent
to a serial schedule and what should be the
serial schedule; obviously, there are 6 choices
because there are 3 schedules.
So, there are 6 possible permutations which
give you 6 different serial schedules and
if in that so our first condition says that
I must read from the same value so; obviously,
T 27 reads the initial value of Q. So, T 27
has to be the first transaction, if the third
condition says that I must do the same right
T 29 does the final right here. So, the in
the serial schedule also T 29 must be the
last 1. So, T 28 has to be the middle 1.
So, the serial schedule that this is equivalent
to is T 27 T 28 T 29 and, the 1 reads and
the other 2 rights and T 29 performs a final
right. So, you can see that this is a this
is not a conflict serializable, but this is
view serializable and if you note the view
serializability moment, you have you view
serializability and you may not have conflict
serializability, then you must be having certain
blind rights, these are called blind rights
this is a blind right, in the sense that here
you are writing the value of Q in T 28 without
having read it is current or previous value.
So, you have just blindly you had just computed
some value and you are writing to that.
So, if a schedule is not conflict serializable,
but is view serializable it must have performed
some blind rights where it has written data
without actually reading it. So, this is a
weaker form of serializability that is possible.
Now, the question is similar to conflict serializability,
where we saw that it schedule can be conflict
serializable, if it is corresponding precedence
graph is a cyclic. So, we would like to extend
find out similar test for view serializability,
but ah as it turns out that trying to find
out this is exponential in cost in terms of
the size of the precedence graph.
So, it has been proved that the of checking,
whether a schedule is view serializable is
in the class of NP complete problem. So, if
you are good in algorithms. So, you will know
what NP problems are and when are problems
called NP complete, in very simple terms even
if you are not familiar with that depth of
algorithms, you can simply issue note that
if an algorithm is NP complete, then it is
extremely unlikely that there exists in efficient
algorithm for.
It there exists any kind of polynomial time
algorithm, it is extremely unlikely still
not it is still an open problem in computer
science, whether a tall polynomial algorithm
exists for NP complete problems, but it is
extremely unlikely that an efficient algorithm
will exist, you may have some approximate
algorithms which can give sufficiency conditions
which can say that well if these conditions
are satisfied, then necessarily a schedule
is view serializable, but not a sufficient
condition are not a necessary condition, that
is in other words that there may be some schedules
which do not satisfy the sufficient condition,
but are still view serializable.
So, using view serializability have certain
problems. So, here I have worked out a longer
problem in terms of the view serializability
to check that. So, it is kind of a brute force
algorithm. So, if you see this is the schedule
given there are 2 data items A and B and there
are 3 transactions T 1 T 2 T 3. Since there
are 3 transactions, then if I want to prove
if it is view serializable, then what I will
have to do I will have to find a one of the
possible serial schedules which is view equivalent
to this?
So, first I list out all the serial schedules
given 3 transactions, there are 6 serial schedules
and then I first start with condition 3 which
is who is doing the last update. So, there
are rights are only on B. So, and last of
that are being done in all the 3 transactions.
So, there is no write on A so, the list of
final update on A is empty and for B the order
is T 1 T 2 T 3 so, T 3 does the last. So,
it must whatever schedule this whatever serial
schedule this given schedule S has to be view
equivalent to must have T 3 as the last transaction
to execute. So, only these 2 are the candidates
which may be view equivalent to this schedule
S.
So, we reduce down and now we have only to
decide whether these 2 any of these 2 are
view equivalent to the given schedule S. So,
moving on with that now next we check condition
1 and condition 2 together. So, condition
one checks that they must read the same value
in both the schedule. So, we see that these
are the reads that are happening on A. So,
we see that on a there are reads happening,
I am sorry this is these are the 3 that is
reading A. So, it happens in the order of
T 2 T 3 T 1 and T 3.
So, this is what you find and in terms of
B we find that transaction 2 reads B and writes
it. So, it has to be in that order. So, it
reads it does an initial read in terms of
T 2 and, then the first right of that read
value is happening in the transaction T 1
after the update of the read. So, ah that
means, that whatever schedule we we look for
in terms of view equivalence, they must have
in that schedule T 1 must follow T 2. So,
T 2 must happen first because it needs to
read the initial value and, then that initial
value is is used by then there is a right
on by T 1. So, T 2 has to come before T 1
so; that means, we are already in terms of
only 2 we have seen that there are 2 possible
candidates based on condition 3, it is T T
1 T 3.
So, in these 2 we only can have this one which
is satisfying the other conditions and there
is no read write sequence. So, we conclude
that indeed T 2 T 1 T 3 satisfies all the
3 conditions of initial read write after read
and the final right conditions and therefore,
this given schedule S is actually view equivalent
to a serial schedule and, it is a view serial
schedule and can be used safely for the transaction.
There is ah another example given here, where
there is there are 4 transactions R one R
2 R 3 and R 4 and there are 2 data items A
and B and, you have to find out establish
whether this is view serializable or not,
I am not working out this one this is worked
out in the presentation slide, but I will
not show it here you are you should first
try it out and, then once you have been able
to do it or you are unable to do that, then
you check the solution from the presentation
slide.
ah There are different other complex motions
of serializability also for example, if you
look at this particular schedule this actually
is a serializable ah schedule, this is the
effect that it produces will be same as the
serial schedule of T 1 T 5, but if you go
through the definitions of conflict equivalence
and, view equivalence you will be able to
show that this schedule is neither conflict
conflict serializable not view serializable,
but yet given the particular.
So, if you just look at the read write this
is not a serializable schedule in terms of
conflict or view equivalence, but given the
fact that it actually performs simple add
subtract operations on these variables, using
the properties of add subtract operations
you would be able to you can actually see
that this particular schedule actually is
a serializable schedule and, you will get
whatever initial values you start with the
value that you will achieve ah through this
schedule and the value that will achieve with
the serial schedule T 1 T 5 are indeed same
in every case.
But this is determining this requires the
understanding of other instructions other
operations, besides the read and write. So,
this is just to show you that using the read
write model and conflict and view equivalents
and the only not the only ways of getting
to serializability there are more complex
models, but we will not go into the depth
of these complex serializability aspect.
So, we have shown that with we have shown
here that with proper planning, a database
can be recovered back to a consistent state
from an inconsistent state, in case of system
failure. And this such a recovery can be through
cascaded or cascade lists rollback and, we
have also introduced a simpler model of serializability
in terms of the view serializable, but testing
for view celerity is MD complete. So, as an
effective algorithm it is not that powerful.