So, today we want to look at this well known
A star algorithm and this was devised by
Hart, Nelson and Raphael essentially.
.
So, out of these Nelson is, we have met these
characters very briefly in the introduction.
Nelson is one of the founding fathers of a
i along with Simon and Noel and Minsky and
McCarthy. In fact, the first text book on
a i written around nineteen seventy two also
was
written by Nelson essentially. Problem solving
methods in a i and it discusses most of
the search algorithm that we have seen accept
the randomize algorithm and things like
that. The best first search and heuristic
functions and effective branching factor and
all
this kind of stuff was written in that book
essentially.
Nelson was teaching at Stanford, Hart some
of you may know because Doodah and Hart,
they wrote a very well known book on pattern
recognition. And Raphael, we had
mentioned very briefly in passing, he was
one of the first people to write a program
to do
automated theorem proving essentially. Anyway,
today we are interested of course, in
.this algorithm A star, but further moment
we will just first call it A and then we will
see
in what condition we can call it A star.
Generally, when we look at some of these algorithms,
that star implies that, it is
admissible essentially, and by admissible,
we mean that it is guaranteed to final optimal
solution. So, branch and bound in that sense
is admissible essentially. So, before I move
on our librarian informs me that, my book
which I do not know how many of you have
seen is now available in the department library.
There are about 5 copies and we are in
chapter 5 of this books at this moment, so
you should catch up with that essentially.
.
So, let us first get the motivation into place
which we have just discussed is that you are
at some start node S, and you want to go to
some goal node g, assuming this is a city
map or something like that. And you have some
kind of a open list, and there are nodes
on this open list which you have to pick a
node from for expansion.
This is a old style algorithm that we wrote
depth first search, breath first search, heuristic
best first search and so on. We dint use this
terminology in branch and bound, but you
can see that branch and bound also always
picks the lowest nodes in lowest leaf in the
tree that we were drawing which is like you
know open list that you can maintain.
Now, we saw that what best first search use
was a function which kind of estimated the
distance of every node to the goal node. And
we call that function h of n and best first
.search basically maintain a priority queue
on the heuristic value and always pick the
lower which appears to be closest to the goal
and in the hope of finding the solution
faster essentially.
Branch and bound on the other hand keeps track
of the parcel cost found so far, which
are these cost. So, these are actual cost
in the sense these are cost of actual partial
solutions found. They may not necessarily
be optimal though for diastral algorithm one
can argue and prove that every time it picks
a node it has found an optimal cost for that,
but we will come back to that argument a little
bit later. So, this is a actual cost that
we
have found to a given node so far essentially.
So, if you try to visualize this as some sort
of a physical system, you can see that branch
and bound like breath first search which was
a simpler case of branch and bound tries to
stick as close to the source as possible always
picks a node which is as which has a
lowest known cost essentially. So, it tries
to stick as close to the source as possible.
So, it
is like a pull on this thing which is pulling
it back essentially. Best first search on
the
other hand always tries to go as close to
the goal as possible essentially.
Because, it is using the heuristic function
which is an estimate of given note to the
goal
essentially. So, in some science that is a
pull in that direction essentially. What we
want
to do in this algorithm A star is to use a
combination of these two pulls and that is
as it is
as simple as that we just need to fill in
the details essentially.
So, in A star terminology this value is called
g of n and it is a actual cost of actual known
cost of a path which is from S to n. So, this
actual cost for this path is to n the kind
of
path that we were drawing in branch and bound
we will call g of n the cost that we were
using in branch. And bound we will that label
we will call g of n, h of n is an estimated
cost of the segment from n to g, that we have
used in best first search that the h of n
tells
you how far this goal is from this from the
goal node essentially.
..
So, in this algorithm A, we use a function
called f of n which is basically the sum of
g of
n plus h of n. And essentially we keep the
priority queue sorted on this value of f of
n
essentially. Now, notice that what is happening
in this search algorithm we are starting
with the source node of the start state and
we are gradually making this implicit graph
explicit essentially by a kind of a search
tree that we are generating and whatever we
have made explicit is divided into two parts.
One is called the closed set or closed list
which is the internal nodes and the other
is the leaves which we call as a open set.
As we build this explicit graph this g value
are computed, as we find partial pots paths
we can compute their values and that is the
g value. H value is independent of what we
are doing, H value is simply a property of
a given node. So, it is like saying how far
Mailapur from Chennai central. We are just
asking that question we has no question of
paths here or some measure we said ((Refer
Time.) distance we can use or
Manhattan distance we can use.
A heuristic function is just a property of
the node. So, the algorithm that we will dip
implement this A star every time we generate
a node you can simply compute its h value
which is this heuristic value once for all
and you are done essentially. Whereas, this
g
value may change, why because you as we saw
in the example first you may find the
cost of length 15 to a node and then you may
find another paths of cost 14 to that node.
So, g of that node may change from 15 to 14.
.So, it is a quantity which keeps changing.
So, it is a actual known cost or actual known
cost of a known path I should say because,
there is some path that you have not yet
explored and which could be cheaper. Now,
we use this term f star of n is equal to g
star
of n plus h star of n and these are optimal
cost. So, whenever we use the term star, they
just denotes the optimal cost, we may or may
not know them essentially. In fact, we do
not know them most of the time essentially.
Even if we have found the path from some node
to some intermediate node, we do not
know what the actual cost, what is a relation
between g of n and g star of n, is it equal
lesser than or greater than? Greater than
how many people, feels it greater than only
one.
You said greater than right? Greater than
equal to, why greater than equal to? So, g
of n
is a path that you have found to that node
n so far, it may be not the best path. So,
it
could be cost greater than g star of n.
So, this f of n is basically or S star of
n is the optimal the cost of optimal path
that starts
with the start node goes to node n and then
goes to the node g. So, for any node n, f
star
of n is optimal cost optimal path cost which
passes through the node n essentially. And
if
that path is an optimal path, so if, so there
is a distinction between these two. Here we
are
saying that for any node n what is the optimal
cost going through that node n. Here we
are talking about an optimal path from S to
G. We can assume that, if this is equal to
S n
1 n 2 n k G, then we can write f star of S
is equal to f star of n 1.
And, so on f star of g because, it is a same
path remember. When we say this is optimal
path then whether we say f star of n any node
on that path or f star of start or f star
of
goal they have the same cost because this
is only one path that we are talking about.
So,
for an optimal path these two this sources
this we will use as some later point.
..
A star is admissible if now, we come to the
same question again the relation between h
of n and h star of n what should be the relation.
So, I am giving you two options here
include some we do not have equality. So,
we have included an equality in both the sides
which one is better. A first option or the
second option? What should my heuristic
function do? Should it what is this one doing.
This is this underestimates, and this
overestimates. And I making a claim and this
claim we will show more formally
probably in the next class. That if I choose
a right condition here, then the algorithm
A
star becomes admissible and by admissible
we mean it will find you the optimal cost
path essentially.
So, should my h of n be an underestimating
function which means h of n should be less
than h star of n. Remember h star of n is
the optimal cost of going from n to the goal
or
should it overestimate the cost of going from
n to the goal, which one will make my
algorithm admissible. Should I take a vote
on this or somebody going to volunteer in
answer?
So, let us take a vote, how many people feel
it should overestimate the cost? Only one,
two can I use negation by failure, no. How
many people feel it underestimates a cost?
A
very small number essentially. So, let me
we will come back to this. So, let me, let
me
take an example to illustrate this whole point
essentially, and then you will see or let
it
let me put it this way.
.It is an analogy that, I often tend to use
that supposing you are buying a new, you want
to
buy a new, mobile phone the most popular object
now a days and you want to get a, you
have decided what phone you want to buy and
but there are three or four shops which are
selling it. So, you go to the first shop and
let say I do not know what is the good price
for
you people. So, let us say it is 10000 rupees,
this fellow says I am giving you this phone
for 10000 rupees.
Now, there you have some estimate of how much
the other people will charge, will they
will you go to them if you think they charge
less or will you go to them if you think they
charge more than 10000. Charge less essentially
which means that you think that they are
that value of that node is underestimating
the cost essentially. So, let us then look
at this
example.
.
Let us say I have only two nodes in open let
us call them A and let us call them B and
let
say this is the actual path found to them
and let us say that they are just one step
away
from the goal this just to illustrate the
idea. So, that is the edge that they are just
likely to
explode let us say that this cost is 100 just
to simplify a maters let say this cost is
also
100 and let us say that this cost is 40 and
this cost is 50 that is the edge cost A G
is the
cost of edge A G is 40 and the cost of edge
B G is 50.
So, what do we have, we have this 100 is equal
to g of B this is also equal to g of A and
that is a actual cost we do not that is you
might say the h star of A is 40 and h star
of B is
.50 in this case of course, if there is only
one edge it is basically a falls on to the
edge cost
essentially where it could be more than one
I think. So, let us look at examples of both
this functions.
.
So, let us say h 1 underestimates the cost
and h 2 overestimates the cost. And let us
pick
functions which are not very good in the sense
that both of them are giving you wrong
information, both of them are telling you
is that B is actually closer to the goal then
A is
closer to the goal, so let us work with this.
So, h 2 let us say h 2 of B equal to it is
actually 50. So, let us say this is 70 and
h 2 of A
is actually 40, but let us say it is 80. So,
what does it means that this function h 2
which
is a heuristic function. So, remember we did
this example with this blocks world where
we tried to define its functions when we saw
that one of them was better than the other.
This is looking at another aspect of heuristic
functions which is one of them is
underestimating and the other one is overestimating.
So, first we are looking at a function which
over overestimates the costs which means
that this actual cost for this is 50, but
this function thing it is 70, actual cost
for this is 40,
but this function thing it is 80. So, in actual
practice A is closer to the goal which means
this part should have been better, but this
function will think that B is closer to the
goal
because of the estimate it has h 2 of B is
70 which is less than 80.
.So, f 2 of B will be g of A which is g of
B which is the same is equal to 100 plus 70
equal to 170 and f 2 of A is equal to 100
plus 80 equal to 180. So, remember that we
said
that basically what this algorithm A star
does is it maintains a priority queue of on
f
value essentially. So, in this small example
there are only two nodes in the open list,
one
is A one is B and it has to decide which one
to pick it uses is f values f 2 is 180 f 2
of A
is 180 and f 2 of B is 170.
So, it will pick this node which means it
will now what disaster would have said relax
the edge here which means it will compute
g of g. So, g 2 of g is equal to g 2 of B
plus
the actual cost which is sorry which one have
we picked we have pick B which is 50,
correct? The actual cost was or let me write
which is 50 which is the actual edge cost
which is equal to 100 plus 50 is 150 and h
2 of g is equal to 0. We assume that our
heuristic function can at least tell us if
we have reached the goal. So, the heuristic
value
at the goal is 0 which means f 2 of g is equal
to 0 plus 150 is 150. So, what is happened
in our search space?
.
We started with S, then we had this two paths,
this is A, this is B, then our algorithm h
has pick B and found a path to g, then we
have this two node on open A and G. A has
estimated cost now, estimated cost we mean
the complete cost of going to the goal via
this node A is estimated to be 180 because,
the heuristic estimate from A is 80 and the
.cost up to A is 100. So, 100 plus 80 is estimated
to be 180. The estimated cost of g is the
cost found, so far which is the g value which
is 150.
So, here we have this node sitting with 150
and this node sitting with 180. So, the
algorithm will pick g and terminate, the same
algorithm that we talked about in the last
class when the completely refined solution
is becomes a cheapest. It will automatically
get picked in this priority queue and then
the algorithm will terminate. So, it will,
it will
find this path essentially.
.
Let us try the other option which is h 1 of
A. It underestimate, so let us say h 1 of
B
equal to it is actually 50, but now we are
underestimating. So, let us say it is 30 and
h 1
of A is actually 40.
So, let me say this is 20 it is actually 40,
but let us say this function thing it is 30.
So, in
the manner h 2 and h 1 are similar the both
of them think that B is closer to the goal,
the
only difference is h 2 overestimates the cost
and h 1 underestimates the cost essentially.
So, in which case as you can see f 1 of B
equal to 20 plus 100 120 and f 1 of A is equal
to 130.
..
Again this is a very similar situation, this
algorithm, so originally this was 180, this
was
170 and this became 150 with this new algorithm
f 1 this is 130 and this is 120. So, again
this algorithm will explode B first, but what
will happen now after picking B it will relax
this edge from B to g which actual cost is
50. So, g to g or g 1, g is equal to 150 which
means f1 G is equal to 150.
See after they have found the path going from
S to B to g both of them know the actual
cost there is no longer this estimation done
by h because, h is 0. So, the actual cost,
so f 1
G is 150 as well as f 2 G was 150, but now
you can see that this is with the same cost
150 and this algorithm let us call it A 1
star has to choose between g and A. It terms
out
that A is lower estimated cost 130. So, this
algorithm will pick A, and when it picks A
it
will find a cheaper cost to g exactly like
diastral algorithm would have done, and this
cheaper cost is the cost of 100 plus 40 which
is 140.
So, this will revise this cost to 140. Originally
the estimated cost was 170 and it got
revised to 150 here, it was 180 it never got
revised to 150. Here it was 120 it got revised
to 150, but when this expanded this it got
again revised to 140 essentially. And at that
time this is the only goal only door left
in our open list because we have finished
with A,
we have finished with B both and only g is
left and g will be picked with the cost of
which is the optimal solution.
.So, you can see that using h 1 of h 1 we
could find the optimal solution using h 2
we
could not find the optimal solution, even
though both of them thought that B was the
better choice using h 2 we picked B and then
we picked the goal using h 1 we picked B,
but then we were forced to pick A and then
we were forced to pick the goal essentially.
So, we found the optimal cost.
.
So, this is the criteria we are looking for.
If h of n is less then equal to h star of
n. So, the
algorithm is admissible if the heuristic function
underestimates the cost of the goal
essentially. So, let us quickly describe the
algorithm completely because there are one
or
two things which were not there in the best
first search algorithm. So, I will do a quick
description and then we will do it we will
take it up again in the next call essentially.
So,
the algorithm is very similar, except that
we keep track of this cost explicitly g of
a node
n, h of a node n, so on.
..
So, the steps are very similar at. So, I will
just write the outline here and you can fill
in
the details. So, I will just very briefly
write open gets S which means open gets the
start
node, but we want to keep track of parents
and so on and so for.
So, let us just write here parent of S is
nil and h of S is computed we always we can
always compute the heuristic value of a node.
So, in as a matter of principle we compute
the heuristic value and we initialize close
to nil as before accept that here we have
talked
of this parent point of, rather than having
this node pair that we had earlier you can
use
that it does not really matter, this is simply
easier to describe. So, as before if open
is not
equal to nil, pick best node
n and add it to closed. I will just write
it as an outline I want
to focus on the part of what do you do with
this node n essentially
So, if n, so if I use the older terminology
if gore test n than the reconstruct n. So,
we
assume that we can trace back the path and
reconstruct the path and then. So, all that
it is
very similar to what we did in earlier search
algorithm, else successors is
the move gen
of n. So, we I am using the same function
that we have defined earlier and for each
m in
successors we do the following essentially.
So, let me also draw the situation at the
point
where this algorithm is doing working.
..
So, this is S and then somewhere we have this
open list, this is the set of open node and
let us say this node n is here essentially.
So, this line that I have drawn represents
open
list and we picked some nod, nodes with the
lowest f value have I said that here, ok I
have said best node n and by best I mean the
lowest f value and f is g plus h and we it
was not the goal nod. So, we generate successors.
So, let us say these are the successors of
n. All neighbors if you want to say or what
are
reachable from there. Now you can see that
there are three kinds of nodes here one is
one
kind which is on the open list already. So,
these two I mean to draw is that they are
already on open there are some which are already
in closed and there is some which are
new nodes essentially. So, this one represents
that new nodes essentially.
..
So, for each M, so case one m does not belongs
to open and m does not belong to close
which means it is this node here that I am
talking about, it is a new node that has not
been seen earlier essentially. Basically we
want to add it to our search space. So, what
do
we do we say add compute h of m then.
So, we have some heuristic function that we
use. Then we say parent m is n and g of m
is
equal g of n plus I will use k as a cost function.
So, that k of n m is the cost of that edge
going from n to m. So, we update the value
of or the compute value of g m is equal to
g
of n. The g value of the parent exactly as
we were doing in this branch and bound kind
of
a thing and then we compute f of n
and we say add n to open.
So, there are three cases the first case is
when m is a new nod. So, we compute its edge
value we compute its g value which means we
can compute its f value, we mark the
pointer of m as its parent that it came from
and add it to open essentially. The next case
that we want to look at is when it is already
on open.
..
So, case 2, m belongs to open which means
what, that we have found this edge here. So,
we are dealt with this these two cases. So,
now, if this one of these two was m, it means
it is on already in open which means it is
already has a g value and h value and a parent
point. So, this n has just been expanded.
So, before that, this was pointing to let
us say
this one for argument sake, let us say this
was pointing to this and this was pointing
to
this. So, they already had this parent pointer,
what do we do for such nods, or what do
we want to do?
We want to see if we have found the cheaper
path to that node or not, correct? We
already have a path to this node m it is coming
through some sequence of nodes n always
remember is a parent point. So, it already
has a g value and an h value as well. So,
if m
belongs to open, then we do a check if g of
n plus this value A of n m. What is this
value?
This value is a new cost that we have found
to this node m, this node m was already on
open. If this is less than the cost that was
already stored for m, remember it is all open.
So, it is must be having a g value, but if
this new cost that we have found is better
than
the old cost, then we have to do some readjusting
of pointer which is that parent of m
becomes n and g of m becomes this value. And
f of course, becomes in all these h of m is
not changing at all because, it is just a
property of that node, it is not the property
of that
what path we have found to this node.
.So, these are the two cases. One case for
new nodes, we simply add them to the graph,
and create the parent pointer, compute the
g value, compute the h value, compute the
f
value and we are done. If we have found a
new path to a node in open then we need to
check whether this path is better which is
what we are doing here, if it is better than
we
readjust the parent pointer and readjust the
g value essentially. So, this is where we
are
readjusting the g value, this is where we
are readjusting the parent pointer and then
this
of course, taking into account the new g value.
.
Case 3, m belongs to closed. Which means we
had already visited m and expanded m
and generated children of m n, so on and so
for, so let us take this as a case.
..
So, let us say now this is m, which means
it was already generated before which means
it
could have other children. So, let me use
a different color here. So, this node could
have
been a child of m and maybe this node could
have been a child of m which could have its
own children child here anything is possible
essentially. The difference between the node
on open and a node on close is that a node
on close may have children of its own
essentially. So, these purple nodes represent
children of m essentially. So, if m is on
close first of course, we have to do what
we did for case 2.
.
.So, first I will say do like in case 2, which
means that this node m we have found a better
path to this node m.
.
Originally this m had some other pointer let
us say this pointer. So, remember this are
pointed to parent nodes. So, m was pointing
to its parent here and if we find a better
path
to m, we must shift this pointer here and
say that this is the new parent, exactly like
what
we did for n. Originally this node first pointing
to this, but now we have removed this
and we have said this is a new pointer if
we have found a better path likewise for close
nodes essentially. So, do like in case 2.
..
So, if let me use this if better path found
which basically means this condition g of
n plus
k of n m is better is less than g of the old
value of m then. So, actually I should do
like
this then like case 2 which means readjust
the pointer, parent pointer readjust g value,
but
now the g value has changed essentially.
.
So, we need to, so just to take an example,
if the old g of m let me say old is equal
to 50.
And if g of m gets a new value which is let
us say g of n plus 10, and let us say g of
n is
20 equal to 20 plus 10 equal to 30.
.So, if the old value was 50 and the new value
was 30, then we have found a new path to
this m which is 20 unit cheaper than the old
path which means that all path going from
m
to other nodes we must pass on this improvement
to them essentially. So, you must
reduce the cost of this by 20 reduce the cost
of this by 20 and then reduce the cost of
this
by 20 and so on and so for.
.
So, I will just write this and propagate improve
cost
to sub tree below m. How can we do
this propagation? You can just do a depth
first traversal or something like…
.
.that of this purple tree which is rooted
at this m, which means this part of the tree
to this
node to this node to this node that improve
cost must be preoperative to them.
So, that is a third case, if you have found
a new path to a node in the closed. A better
path to a node in the closed, then that improvement
has to be passed on to children of
that node essentially, which was not the case
in disaster. I mentioned, when we were
talking about disaster algorithm, that if
you have found the path to a node in disasters
algorithm you have already found optimal path
to there. But in A star that is not the case
essentially, like we saw in the example that
we saw, if you have found a path to g which
was through the node B which was a more expensive
path you can find a new path from
that node essentially.
And it is also possible for nodes and close
you can easily construct an example. So, we
need this extra step that if we have found
better path, so node that we have already
expanded earlier we need to propagate this
improvement to their children essentially.
So,
which is a little bit more work then case
2. Where? This one? And here, no that is all
and
add m to correct. So, under the conditions
when heuristic function underestimates a cost
to the goal this algorithm is called A star
and it is admissible essentially.
In the next class, when we meet we will prove
that it is admissible. So, this is one of
the
few cases where we will give a formal proof
of admissibility because, A star is a very
well known and often used algorithm, but this
is not the only condition for admissibility
I
mean this was the condition only with respect
to the heuristic function.
So, what we have shown with an example today,
that if a heuristic function
underestimates the cost of the goal then the
algorithm is admissible. And you can see
branch and bound is a special case of A star
where h of n is always 0. That is why we
said that you can think of this as an estimated
cost, if you just assume h of n is 0 for
every node then this algorithm becomes branch
and bound essentially, but this is not the
only condition.
So, what I want you to do is, to think just
imagine that. So, A star is actually some
people
just call it graph search. It is a weighted
graph and you have to find the least cost
path
from one node to another nod. We make some
simplifying assumptions, but it is different
from disasters algorithm in one respect and
disasters algorithm assumes that the
.complete graph is available to you and it
is a kind of an old in the sense that, it
finds the
shortest path to every other node from a single
source essentially.
We are not interested in to every other nod,
we are only interested in finding a path to
a
given goal node and we do not have the graph
available to us, the graph is generated on
the fly as we go along essentially for some
were we have this function, move gen
function. The graph is generated as we go
along using the move gen function. So, we
start with some node we keep adding more nodes
to the graph and then we work with
that under these conditions A star is a little
bit different from disasters algorithm.
It also uses this idea of a heuristic function
diastral algorithm did not need to do this
because it was anyway going to find shorter
path to all nodes in the graph essentially.
It
did not have a goal in mind, A star has a
goal in mind. If you want to say it has a
goal in
mind and therefore, it benefits from the use
of a heuristic function, and if the heuristic
function is underestimating function then
that is one of the conditions for admissibility.
So, I wanted to think of what other conditions
you can might require for admissibility,
just imagine that this is some obituary graphs
such problem some graph is given to you
and under what conditions will you, will this
algorithm find an optimal path. And we will
take this up in the next class we will do
a formal proof of this essentially after we
do that
we will compare heuristic functions again
formally and show that heuristic functions
are
which are more informed they do lesser search.
So, remember that when we were talking about
branch and bound we say that this
estimate must be as high as possible, it must
be a lower bound even this is a lower
bound, but it must be as high as possible,
and we will formally show that the higher
the
estimate the lesser the number of nodes that
this algorithm will search before termination
essentially, we will do that these two formal
things in the next class.
So, we will stop here.
.