We are looking at the A star algorithm. In
the last class, we saw that the algorithm
is admissible,
provided the heuristic function underestimates
the distance with the goal, and provided,
every
edge has the cost, which is greater than the
some small value, epsilon, and there is finite
branching. We also saw that if two nodes,
if their two heuristic functions, one of them
is more
informed than the other, which means h 2 of
n is greater than h 1 of n, for every n. Then,
we said
that algorithm a 2, which uses h 2 or a 2
star, which uses h 2, will explore a smaller
search space.
If you can depict as follows; this is the
start node and this is the goal node. Then,
one algorithm
will search something like this, and the other
algorithm will search something like this.
So, this
would be h 2 and this would be h 1; this is
what we expect, that the more informed heuristic
function will be more focused towards the
goal. So, it will search less away from the
goal,
whereas, what branch and bound would search,
would have been full circle around of that
length.
So, the fact that using a heuristic function
actually, focuses a search towards the goal
and more
informed heuristic function is, the more it
focuses towards a goal; which means, search
becomes
.narrow and narrow. With a perfect heuristic
function, the search would be just one pass
that
would take place, essentially. Unfortunately,
we do not have perfect heuristic functions.
So, we
try to look for as good functions as possible,
which means, that the heuristic value must
be as
high as possible, but it should not cross
the level of the optimal value, especially.
For example, in
the 8th puzzle, it has been observed, that
if there two tiles, let us say, 8 and 5; and
they should be
reversed, let us say, in the whole situation;
5 and 8 are here, but they should be 5 and
8, instead
of 8 and 5. Then, one way, one of the functions
that we saw was; simply count how many tiles
are out of place, in which case, two tiles
are out of place; both 8 and 5 are out of
place. The other
function that we saw was the Manhatten distance
function, which said that you need one step
to
take 8 to this position, and you will take
one step to get 5 to this position. So, the
cost would be
2, essentially, or the contravention of these
two tiles would be two, essentially. Now,
if you have
solved this 8 puzzle kind of thing, you know
that you cannot exchange them, essentially.
If you want to interchange the position of
two tiles, you have to do some round about
movement.
So, you will need to add a certain value to
that, essentially. About 7 to 8 years ago,
somebody
enhanced the heuristic function to count for
such things, that they are in the correct
row, but in
the wrong order. Then, you add a certain amount,
and that search was able to find optimal
solution such faster for bigger problem, which
means for the 15 puzzle and the 24 puzzle
as well,
essentially. Now, today we want look at the
other property, which is that; consider two
nodes, we
consider some path to the goal node, and two
nodes m and n, on the path will (Refer Time:
04:48).
..
If you take any such two nodes in the search
place, and if they satisfy this property,
that h of m
minus h of n, is less than equal to k of m
n, in a sense, you can think of this, saying
that it under
estimates the cost of every edge, which is
on the path to the goal, essentially. So,
h of m says that
it is an estimate to the, from m to goal;
h of n says the estimate from n to goal, and
h of m minus
h of n in some sense, is the estimate of the
edge cost from m to n. If this is less than
the actual h
cost, in some sense, we are saying that it
is underestimating the edge, every edge cost,
essentially. This condition is called monotone
of consistency condition, and what we want
to
show is that if this condition is satisfied,
which means that it is the property of the
heuristic
function; a heuristic function is such, that
this property is satisfied for any two nodes,
which
connected like this. Whenever, A star picks
some node n, because already found
an optimal path
to n. You want to show that, you will do that
in a moment, First, let us look at that what
this is
saying; what is the implication of this, essentially?
We are saying that, under certain condition,
which is this fact that heuristic function
satisfies this condition which is called monotone
or
consistency condition.
If this is satisfied, if the heuristic function
said that it satisfies this property, then
the algorithm
which is using that A star, which is using
that heuristic function; whenever, it picks
a node, any
node n; picks meaning, it picks some open,
right; it has already found an optimal path
to n. What
is the implication of this on our algorithm?
If you look at, if you think about the A star
algorithm,
.what does it do after it picks a node and
it takes for, whether it is a goal or not;
if it is not a goal,
it generates its children, and the children
are of three kinds, either new nodes or nodes
on open or
nodes on closed. For nodes on whichever, is
open and closed, it checks for, and found
a better
path. For nodes on closed, if it is found
a better path, has propagated that improvement
to its
children, essentially. So, the application
of this statement, if this statement were
to be true, it
means that it, the moment it puts a node into
closed, it has already found a better path,
best path
to it; optimal path to it, which means you
have to revise that path, so that, the third
stage of that
revision process, we can do away with, essentially.
You can be showed that if node is in closed,
you already have the optimal cost to it, essentially,
which of course saves a lot, in terms of a
this propagation that you have to do, and
in later
classes, which is in next class, you will
see that this allows us to design some algorithm,
which
can save on spaces, but that we will do in
the next class. Now, let us try to prove this
property,
essentially. What are we saying? We are saying
that when it picks node n from the open list,
at
that point, g of n equal to g star of n; this
is the optimal value. We can rewrite this
condition as
follows; h of n is less than equal to, plus
h of n; I will take just h of n to that side
and then, I can
add g values; plus g of m. So, I can add this
g of m to both sides; same value I am adding
to both
sides, so that does not change things. But
this one, g of m, if you look at the figure;
g of m and k
of m equal to g of n. Let me rewrite this
in this order. In other words, f of m is equal
to f of n;
that is a first observation we make.
What are these values saying here? When we
are looking at this criterion, we are saying;
is that
the farther we have from the goal; the less
accurate our estimate is, and the closer we
go towards
the goal, the more accurate our estimate becomes.
As we move from node m to node n, our f
value actually increases, essentially. Now,
remember the f value is an estimate of the
cost of the
path, going through the node. Since, the path
is going through both f, and both m and n,
the
estimate should be ideally the same. But when
you see from m’s perspective, it is actually
less
and when you see it from n’s perspective.
What is the difference; that you have n is
little bit
closer to the goal. So, that is one of the
reasons for, this is called a monotone criteria.
A
monotone condition is that, as you move closer
to the goal, the f value monotonically increases.
Since, this is, this goal, as go closer to
the goal, the f value monotonically increases.
That is one
observation, which holds for any, by transitivity,
this will hold for any two nodes on a path
from
.to the goal, essentially. Now, let us assume
that there is a node n which, let us remove
this, that
depicts a search space that we are exploring.
There is node n which A star is about to pick,
which
means, it must be on open; this is open at
that stage of time, or that stage of the algorithm,
and n
is about to pick node n. We want to make this
clean that if A star is about to pick that
node n, it
must have found that optimal path to n. So,
we will do this proof by contradiction. We
will say
that assume, that when it picks this node
n, it has not found optimal path. So, assume
that g of n
is greater than g star of n. At the point,
where it is about to pick n and we will show
that this
leads to a contradiction.
.
Let this be the optimal path. Let this be
the optimal path to the node n, and let us
say that this is
in closed; this is in closed. Let us say that
A star has found some other path so, this
is open. And
let us say that A star is about to pick this
node n, and let us assume that at point, g
of n is more
than the optimal cost, and let n l be the;
so, this optimal path to n, let us say it
is this, and n l is
the last node, A star has inspected on that
optimal path, and n l plus one is the node
which is on
open, which is child of this node. But A star
has not expected. So, what we are saying that
A star
has not found this path, which is the optimal
path, but A star has found this path, which
may not
be an optimal path; we are trying to say.
So, n of l, last node on optimal path to n,
last node seen,
and n of l plus one is the first node on optimal
path, which is not seen. So, I am saying that
this is
.the optimal path. This of course, is one
edge and then, they added some more; that
is the optimal
path to n.
We are assuming A star has found some other
path to n, which is not the optimal path.
Now, we
can apply this criteria here, f of m, sorry.
This monotone criteria that we observed, assuming
that
heuristic function satisfies this property
from any path to the goal, this property holds
that, as you
go closer towards the goal, the f value increases.
As we move from f of this last node n l to
n l
plus one, and so on to n, the f value will
increase, or at least not decrease. In particular,
we can
write that g of n l plus one, plus h of n
l plus one, is less than equal to g of n plus
h of n. I am just
expanding this one here, and that one there,
and I am skipping the transitive steps, and
because
they are in optimal path, we can replace g
with g star. So, we can write g star of n
l plus one plus
h of n l plus one less than equal to; so,
we can put this star, because we are assuming
that these
nodes, these three nodes that we are talking
about. These two nodes, n l and n l plus one,
are on
the optimal paths to n. So, on this path,
these properties will hold, essentially. Now,
if this is the
case
we can write this as, I am just adding plus
h of n to both sides, essentially. So, g of
n plus h
of n greater than g star of n plus h of n.
Anyway, that is not so important. What is
really
important is that f of n is less than equal
to f of n l plus 1, why because we are said
that A star is
about to expand this node n. This whole property,
we want to say that when is about to expand
n,
it must have found an optimal path to that,
essentially. So, this we can write as g of
n plus h of n
less than equal to g of n l plus one plus
h of n l plus one. So, I want to look at this
one, and this
one, see I want basically, this g of n is
less than equal to g star of n using these
two, but I have a
star sitting there.
So basically, I have to put this star here,
because we have assumed that in this graph,
this is
optimal path. So, this g of n l plus 1 is
equal to g star of l plus one; this is what
I did here. I said I
could replace this by the optimal path. I
can do it here as well. Now, of course, this
becomes the
same, which becomes the same as this. So,
this is less than this, and if you remove
h of n, you get
this is less than this. What is this saying?
This saying that g of n less than the optimal
cost, less
than equal to the optimal cost, but that can
only be the case, if g of n equal to g star
of n. By
definition, it cannot be less than optimal
cost; it must be the optimal cost.
So, what we are said? There is a contradiction
between this and this, and this and this.
If you do
not even assume this, you can simply show
that g of n is less than equal to g star of
n, which you
.can interpret the same; g of n equal to g
star of n, which is the statement we are making
here.
Whenever, it picks this node n, it has found
optimal path to that node, which means g of
n is
equal to g star of n. The implication of this,
as I said is that you do not have to revise
the cost of
those nodes, which have been put into closed.
Once you put a node into closed, you know
that
you have the optimal cost, essentially. We
have shown a serious of properties about this
A star
algorithm. The conditions are that the heuristic
function must under estimate the cost to the
goal
h cost, must be more than some specified amount,
some small amount, then A star will always
find optimal paths to the goal node; that
is what we showed in lemmas 1 to 6, I think,
and this is
actually in lemma 7; the last of the statements
that you want to make. In addition of this
condition is satisfied, then you do not have
to keep revising cost to the nodes in close;
the
moment you pick a node from open and put in
close, at that moment, you found the optimal
cost
to the node.
If you go, take this figure seriously, then
essentially, what you are saying is that both
these costs
are initially of the same, this thing, whether
this path or this path, it is the same cost;
g value
must equal to the optimal g value. So, let
us compare this with the earlier algorithm
we have
seen. In terms of the four parameters, we
talked about time complexity, space complexity,
quality of solution and completeness. As far
as the last two of these are concerned, the
quality of
solution and completeness, we have proved
today, that A star will find a path to the
goal, if there
is a little, find an optimal path, always.
That leaves the question of time and space
complexity.
Again, like we said in case of best for search,
time and space complexity, both depend upon
the
quality of the heuristic function. The better
the heuristic function is, lesser the amount
of space,
that your algorithm will explore, and that
is what we said here.
Now, sometimes what people do is now, unfortunately,
both space and time requirements have
been observed to be large in nature, essentially.
We will look at the examples where, space
is
cognatic in nature, for example, city, if
you imagine a 2-dimensional city, then the
farther you
are go away, you can see the area that you
have to explore grows as a square, essentially.
But the
combinations make low exponential, essentially,
and we have seen this property, that the higher
the heuristic value, the heuristic function
that we are using, the better for you. But
if you want to
guarantee admissibility, the heuristic function
must be less than the optimal heuristic value,
essentially.
..
So, what people have often done is that, they
have tend to use a function like this; f of
n equal to
g of n plus k times h of n; this is known
as weighted A star, essentially. So, you use
a parameter
k to decide, how much influence the heuristic
function has. Now, notice that there are two
influences on A star algorithm; g of n is
trying to keep it, because we always going
to pick one
with a lowest f value. So, low g means, it
is close to the goal; low h means, it is close
to the;
sorry, low g means it is close to the source;
low h means, it is close to the, at least,
thinks it is
close to the goal. The effect of g is that
tries to keep the algorithm like branch and
bound, as
close to source as possible. The effect of
h is like, best for search to pull it towards
a goal,
without any regard to what was the time spent
in reaching that node n. If you use a parameter
like k, you can actually control the effect
of heuristic function versus g of n. If you
put k equal to
1, then we have the A star algorithm to just
describe, if you put k equal to 0, for example,
then
you have, simply, branch and bound. You do
not even look at the effect of h. If you put
k as very
high, which I am also saying, that j is 0,
there is like best for search. It only looks
forward; it
does not look behind. But if you put a value
of k greater than 1, then you are giving more
emphasis to the heuristic function, which
means the search will become narrower and
narrower,
essentially. It will be given more by the
heuristic function and less by the tendency
to keep track
of, whether you are finding optimal paths
or not.
.So, obviously, the moment you put k greater
than 1, you are losing admissibility, but
you can
expect that your solution would be close to
optimal solution, and depending on some trade
off
that you may have to make, you can choose
the value of k higher than 1, essentially.
Very often,
people tried 4, 5, 6, values of k and seeing,
that their algorithm runs much faster. This
is simply
to guarantee faster running time. So, what
I want to do is to, now, focus on saving space.
This is
what people have done. After A star was discovered,
it is quite a well-known algorithm. We
want to look at how we can save on spaces.
One of the first ideas that was explored,
is an
extension of an idea that we have seen earlier,
which is; let us do depth first search. Instead
of
best first search, do depth first search.
Now, if you remember the algorithm DFID, what
DFID
does is that it does the sequence of depth
first search, with increasing that bound,
but there, we
have the motion of level, because we had no
cost associated with edges. So, all edges
were
supposed to be of equal cost. Since, we have
graduated to h cost and we looked that algorithm
like, branch and bound, and so on; we need
a variation of that and that variation is
called IDA
star. It was given by a guy called Richard
Korf. I do not remember, whether we have discussed
cost work earlier, but he has done a lot of
work in search, essentially. His PHD thesis,
which was
in the earlier 80s, was finding macros, operators.
In fact, his PHD thesis is also available
as a
book at some point of time. If you remember
the puzzle like Rubics cube, in fact, he was
working on Rubics cube and the eight puzzles.
We have seen that it is very difficult to
devise
heuristic function, which will drive actually,
climbing like, algorithms to solutions. So,
what we
tend to do is that we have the set of macro
moves, which says, if you have done the top
layer,
then if you want to; let us say the next objective,
which is to get; Let us say one cube, let
into
place in the middle layer; you say do this
sequence of moves; left, right, left up down,
whatever,
we have some notation for that. That is the
macro move.
A macro move is a sequence of moves, packaged
into one abstract move. The question is; how
do you get macro move? Of course, most of
us learned from friends, at what cost rate
for this
PHD work was that he wrote an algorithm, which
will search in the Rubics cube problem and
the
eight puzzles problem, and tried to learn
macro move, essentially. His algorithm actually,
built a
macro table, which of course, once you have
a macro table like, we saw all the Rubic cubes
and
we do not do any search; we say, ok, I will
do the top layer first; then, I do the second
layer and
then, I will do the third layer. Korf’s
PHD thesis was to build that table, which
listed all the
macro moves, essentially, But this IDA stuff
is also by Richard Korf, and we see a bit
more of
.him, as we go along. This was in 1985 also.
And IDA stands, IDA star stands for iterative
datening A stars. It still, A star in the
sense, guarantee the optimal solution, but
is iterative
datening like, DFID essentially.
.
The algorithm idea is very simple. What it
says is that if we were the start node, you
create a
boundary. Now, first, let us see, what DFID
would do. Ignore, because it does not say
cost of the
edges; it basically, sees it as level by level.
So, it would first do depth first search up
to some
level, then up to some next level, then up
to next level; so we are assuming that edges
are sort of
roughly similar in cost in source.
Even if we have these edges of equal cost,
IDA star has some value. So, they finally,
would have
basically expanded it search space gradually,
and if this is the goal node here, it would
have
found eventually, at one of the expansions,
it would have found a path to goal and since,
it did
not find it in previous round; it means, its
new path must be the shortest path, because
it is only
in this last situation, that you extended
this step by 1, but it uses linear space,
because it does the
first search, essentially. IDAs are basically
variation of this. It says that you draw a
boundary,
which you use for controlling a search, and
the boundary is essentially, those nodes.
Well, it
should not come here. It falls short of this,
actually, something like this; just would
depict this,
essentially. This is the curve which is defined
by f
star of s. This is the locals of f star of
s, which
.means, all the nodes on this boundary have
value equal to f; f value equal to optimal
cost,
essentially. Sorry, not f star of s; f of
s. The estimated, because you do not know
f star of s; you
know f of s. That is the estimated cost from
start to goal, as which is equal to h of s,
because g of
s is 0. So, these are the nodes whose f value
is equal to that value h of s, and nodes inside
will
have lesser value, and the nodes outside have
greater value. Now, one of the things that
you
should observe is, that is boundary is ellipse
towards the goal and that is, because it is
using the
heuristic function, essentially. Nodes which
are closer to the goal will have lower heuristic
value,
whereas, nodes which are away will higher
heuristic value, essentially. So, what IDA
star is, that
in the first situation, you said that bound,
well, depth is not the value.
.
Let us say a bound, its starts with saying,
bound equal to h of s, and it does DFS, as
long as h
value is, f value is less than the bound.
So, it is like a boundary it is drawn for
edges, and it is
saying that within this boundary, I will do
the depth first search. So, let us say, it
explores a node
here; we have some children here; another
node, it explores here, somewhere here, let
us see. It
may have some child here. Another node is
here, which may have some child and so on.
All of
them will have their f values that you would
have completed. If it does not find goal in
this depth
first search, now, this is depth first search
with a bound; that it cannot go of in this
direction, and
it cannot go from this direction; only has
save within this boundary. It augments this
boundary
by another boundary, which is little bit bigger
than this; so, increment. For the lowest f
value of a
.node, which it is not picked, which means,
it beyond the boundary, it increments a bound
to that
and then, puts a simpler loop, essentially.
So, you can see this similarity with DFID.
The DFID, if you did not find a path to the
goal, you
would increment the level by one and then,
try the DFS again. What this is doing is it
increments
the bound to the next. So, with all these
nodes, which it has; this is explored; this
is explored, but
all these nodes, which is not explored, generated
but not explored; it keeps track of a what
is the
lowest f value and increments the bound to
that in the next round, and does another depth
first
search. It repeats its process till it finds
a goal. What do you have to say about this
algorithm?
First, we should convince ourselves that it
is admissible. It is worthy of that star on
top of that
name, that it will guarantee an optimal solution.
Can you argue for that? Well, when it starts,
it
starts with a bound which is equal to h of
s, and given that h of s is an underestimating
function;
it is not possible that a path of length greater
than optimal path, will exist within h of
s, because h
of s is an under estimative function.
If the actual cost of going to the goal is
h star of s, h of s is less than h star of
s. So, this boundary
will never take you to a node, which is more
expensive than the optimal cost. If it does
not find
the value, if h of s was perfect, then within
the first situation itself, it would have
found a path to
the goal. But if h of s is not perfect, it
would just be short of goal little bit and
then, you are going
to increment the bound. Looking so, I have
not written the word incremented, but it is
the lowest
unexplored, if you can read this word; this
word must be unexplored. The node unexplored,
f of
n prime where, n prime are all these nodes,
which have not been taken, essentially. So,
because it
is only incrementing the boundary to the lowest
unseen f value, if it finds a goal of f that
value,
then it will be an optimal cost. Because that
is only making very conservative increments;
it is
guaranteed to find the optimal cost. But you
can imagine that in the search space like
this, the
number of iterations that, it will have to
do is going to be very many, essentially.
So, it is going to be optimal; it is going
to save on space; why? Because it is a depth
first search;
it is a sequence of depth first searches,
which only requires linear space, but its
time complexity
is going to go up, by many times, because
it will do many iterations, essentially. So,
some
variations that people have tried is that;
instead of incrementing it by to the next
lowest unseen
value, increment it by a fixed cost, that
you are willing to bear, essentially; some
delta. So,
instead of this, if I write bound, it means
that I am making a bigger jump in this, essentially.
That
.means, let us say, this is my next value.
So, let us say this is plus delta. So this
was the original
bound, and this was a bound plus delta. What
is the danger here? The danger here is that
there
may be a goal node, just beyond this, but
there may be a goal node, here. Because it
is doing
depth first search sweeping the space like
this, it will find this goal node; but it
will not find this
goal node. This goal node is cheaper, I mean,
if you just assume that this is kind of two
scale, in
some sense. This node is cheaper than that
node, because it being depth first search,
sweeping
the space like this, it will find this node.
But this, of course, this delta allows you
to control; how
much sub optimal you are willing to go essentially?
So, this distance, this is delta that you
have
increased the boundary by. Basically, says
that in the worst case, you may have optimal
cost plus
delta, but in this big jump, you would cover
many nodes, so the number of iterations that
you do
would drop, essentially. So, it is nice in
the sense, that it takes linear space, and
it gives currently,
optimal cost so, it is an extension of DFID,
in that sense, which uses this fact that there
are edge
cost and there is heuristic function and things
like that. What is not nice about this algorithm
is
what was not nice about the original algorithm;
it is a blind algorithm, now essentially.
Except of
course, it retains a boundary that it draws,
which is determined by the heuristic function,
it is
uninformed; it does not move towards a goal,
which is why, we started with best first search
in
the first list. This is why, we used the heuristic
function in the first list, but this is not
exploiting
the heuristic function; it uses the heuristic
function only to determine this boundary.
In the next class, we will look at another
variation, which exploits the heuristic function,
and
which is also linear space algorithm. That
algorithm was also given by Richard Korf,
may be, if
you want to think about that little bit, essentially,
it is a little bit like saying, that it is
hill
climbing with back tracking, if we can think
of it along those lines. The algorithm is
like hill
climbing, but allowed to back track, essentially,
and then, try another path; which means, it
will
not have exponential space; it will have only
one path always in the main way. We will look
at
that algorithm in the next class and then,
we will look at some more recent algorithms,
which
have come in this century, I should say, which
are space saving algorithms, which are quite
interesting, essentially.
So, I will stop here for today.
.