So let us begin, we are looking at the A star
algorithm, and if you remember what A star
does is that it uses a function f n is equal
to g n plus h of n, where g n is the known
cost
up to node n from the start node, because
it has explode part of the space and h n is
the
estimated cost from node n to the goal node
essentially. So, it uses the combination of
these two functions; and basically picks node
with lowest f of n at every point of time
from the open list essentially. So, if you
remember g n was the function which we sort
of
inherited from branch and bound which tries
to keep it as close to the goal as to the
start
at possible, and h n is the function we have
inherited from best first search which tries
to
pull it towards the goal node essentially.
So, with the combination of these two functions,
the idea is that the algorithm will find optimal
paths from start to the goal essentially and
today we will show formally that this is how
this is done; but before we do that, just
a
quick recap.
..
Any time it generates a new node n, it gets
different kinds of children - three different
kinds of children.
.
So, we had said, so, when we say moveGen it
gives new nodes, it gives nodes on open
and it gives nodes which are already on closed.
So, when you generate, when you expand
.the new node which means you call the move
gen function with this node n. It can
generate three different kinds of nodes either
they are completely new or they are already
on opened or they are on closed essentially.
.
So, completely know new nodes are like this,
and what we do is essentially compute the
g values for these nodes, which is the g value
of this node plus the cost of this arc
essentially and put it into open; and we markup
parent pointer from these nodes to this
node n; so, these steps we do. For nodes which
are on open and on closed we need to
revise g of m where m is a child, because
we make might have found the cheaper path
to
a node.
..
So, for example, if this is a node on open,
these two nodes are on open, there is possible.
So, since they are on open it means that they
already had some parent in the closed of it
is, it was a child. So, this could have been
this one this could have been this one;
remember that this double cycle we will use
for closed nodes. So, they already have
some parent, but we have found a new path
to these nodes on open; it is possible that
we
might have found the cheaper path and we want
to update the cheaper path. So,
essentially we revise g values of node essentially
and lastly you may get nodes which are
on closed. So, for example, these two nodes,
in which case not only you have to update
the g values of those two nodes which are
on closed, but also any nodes which might
be
pointing to this essentially.
So, for example, if the cost if the g value
of this is let us say 50, and the edge this
edge is
let us say 10 and if this g value was 70,
some for some reason then we need to update
that g value for that node, because now we
have a cost of 50 plus 10 – 60, so we want
to
make this 60. And we have gained an value
amount of 10 which must be passed on to
this, so this become must become minus 10
whatever it is value was it must become
minus 10 and any children it might have and
thinks like that. So, you need to propagate
that.
.Now why do we need to do this updation? open
and closed list why do we bothered to
update this g values in finding optimal solutions
or the shortest paths essentially.
.
So, by as and when, so let us take this example
that we have been looking at if this is a
river, and you are at this place, which is
the start node and your goal is somewhere
here
on the other side of the river, we have looked
at this example before when you look
looking at best first search. So, you may
generate some children and you may follow
some path because the heuristic function is
driving it in this direction; or at that point
you
can see that there is the, the river on the
way and let us assume that the bridges
somewhere here or there is another bridge
somewhere here, then the search will drive
it
towards that path essentially. So, it may
go from here to here, and then it may go from
here to here.
Now best first search what have done the same
thing, but it would have remember this as
the path which takes you to the goal node,
and that is why we said that best first search
does not guarantee the optimal paths. Where
as so this was the this is the path that you
have you have just found for this node, this
is the new parent that you have just found
it
is possible that as search progresses you
may generate a node here, and you will find
that
the shorter paths to this node is via here
and not like this. So, this is the kind of
situation
.we are trying to depict here; that you may
want to revise you may want to say this is
not
the parent, but this is the parent and because
there is a shorter path here. So, may be you
found a path like this.
So, the paths that you are looking for may
be something like this; go like this; instead
of
the search would have generated first gone
in this direction, because that is what the
heuristic function is saying the goal is here
go towards the goal, and then it will away
from that path essentially. But a star does
is that when you does something like this
it
reallocates parents too shorter paths to any
node on the way. So, which is why we say
that whenever we expand this node n for nodes
on open like these 2 or for children on
closed like these 2; if you have found the
shorter path, we must update that essentially
and that is 1 reason why it ends of finding
the shortest paths essentially.
.
So, today we want to prove that A star is
admissible
and by this we mean that it will
guarantee an optimal solution or or shortest
path if you trying to think of it as a path
in
the graph, the graph may be an abstraction
for some other problem where the cost could
be something else, but basically every edge
this is the cost associated with it. So, under
what conditions will this algorithm...? Now
just think of this purely has an algorithm
and
what is the algorithm the algorithm says that
pick the node with the lowest f value from
.open, expanded, this is what we are doing
here, and treat these three different kinds
of
nodes new, open and closed separately. For
new nodes just set up the graph for nodes
are
opened check if you have found the cheaper
path; for nodes on closed also check
whether you have find found cheaper paths,
but also propagate the cheaper path like that
example to it is the children of the closed
node, because the node is on closed it will
have
some children.
.
So, under what conditions would a star guarantee
an optimal path we have stated one
condition earlier. So, let me write this conditions
for optimality, the first condition is
finite branching factor
every node will have a finite number of children
essentially. Now
obviously you can imagine some continuous
problems, where there may be infinite
neighbours; now, if there are infinite neighbours
then we cannot use this algorithm we
will assume that every node has the finite
number of children. So, the branching factor
is
finite essentially that is one condition.
We will allow infinite graph which means that
we will allow for infinite number of nodes
to be presented in the graph, but branching
factor cannot be infinite which mean that
you
can always move away from some node; if the
branching factor was infinite then you
know you will spend all your time infinite
amount of time generating the children of
that
.node essentially; so obviously, it would
not work. There is a condition on the cost;
so we
will use k for cost function. So, k m n stands
for cost of edge going from node n to node
n, we will assume this is the symmetric cost,
what condition should look cost function
satisfy, for the a alba for the algorithm
to guarantee optimal solutions.
So, can I allow negative cost? Why?
Sorry
If there are cycle with some of it is say
just negative, then the algorithm will just
keep
repeating the cycle and it is total cost will
keep going down essentially, which is also
conditions with the algorithm demands algorithm
works only for positive cost there are
other algorithms which handle negative cost,
but we are not looking those kind of thing.
So, for the moment, we will assume that this
should be greater than 0, where we will not
even allow 0 cost essentially. So, that is
for the moment know but will come back to
that
little bit later.
.
A third condition that i have already mentioned
and we have seen as example what it
which say that h of n should be less than
or equal to h star of n, which means that
the
.heuristic function must be an under estimating
function, it must only always under
estimate the distance to the goal, never over
estimate the distance to goal. And the
intension behind that is if you over at estimates
the distance of some node from the goal
then you will never explode that node further,
because you will think it is too far from
the goal essentially. So, in generally if
you think it is closer to the goal where it
actually
is then you are liked to explore that node
and that is a key factor for A star being
admissible.
So, we if you remember we saw an example in
betweens of 2 heuristic functions h 1 and
h 2, one of them underestimating the distance,
other was the overestimating the distance
and both of them had a wrong notion of which
of those two candidates was closer to the
goal, but the underestimating function did
find that optimal path and the other one did
not; today we show this little bit formally.
So, if these three conditions are true then
a
star is admissible and admissible we mean
it always finds a optimal path if there is
if
there is a path from start to the goal, then
it will find the optimal path from start to
the
goal and it will terminate to the goal. So,
we will do this through a series of small
lamas
through a series of statements then eventually
conclude with this property of
admissibility and the couple of properties
we will compare heuristic functions to see
if
how can we say that one heuristic function
is better than another heuristic function.
.
.So, we will have a series of lemmas, so L
1 simply says that it terminates for finite
graphs; the algorithm will terminate for finite
graphs; that is the only statement we want
to assert at this movement. What is the justification
or what is the reasoning to say that it
will always terminate for finite graph?
()
Yes, but that is not to the justification
that we are looking for. You should at a algorithm
look at a algorithm and comment on what the
algorithm is doing.
()
If the graph is finite then the algorithm
in every cycle moves one node from open to
closed it starts by putting the start node
on open list and closes empty and in every
cycle
it inspects one node from open the one, which
has the lowest f value and if it is not the
goal it puts that into closed and generates
it is children and puts those children into
open,
which is the priority cubes on f. So, if the
number of nodes are finite in the graph, if
the
graph is finite then this it can do this only
a finite number of times. So, it will exhaust
the
whole graph. Now supposing the supposing in
this problem that we have here, which is
this problem how this city travel supposing
this bridges were not there essentially, and
you know there was a small hamlet here, which
you could only explore that essentially
then the graph then A star would end of exploring
all those nodes and say i have nothing
else explore because open has become empty.
..
So, remember there are two conditions for
exit; one is when open is empty exit and
report failure, other condition is if the
node that you have picked is the goal node,
then
we construct the path turn it on the path.
So, in this case, if these bridges are not
there
and the goal was there it would never a find
the path, but it would terminate that is all
we
are talking about here essentially; the graph
is finite, it will terminate.
.
.Then the second lemmas you want to says that
at all times
before termination
there exist
a node we call this node n prime; and this
node is on open and which is on the optimal
path. So, I will just say an optimal path,
because a could be more than one optimal paths.
So, the next statement that we are making
is in that before the algorithm terminates,
it
will always have in it is open list one node,
which we will call n prime which is on the
optimal path from start to goal essentially.
.
And the argument for that is the following
that initially we put s on to open. So, let
us
say this is the optimal path, this is the
optimal path, let us say there is only One
optimal
path to start with n 1, n 2, n 3, let us say
this is the optimal path. What we are claiming
now that from this path before the algorithm
terminates, they would always be one node
in the open list, which means the optimal
path will always be in the sites of this
algorithm in some sense. Now when we start
the algorithm we put s on to open list. So,
at the beginning s is in the open if the algorithm
is terminated by finding the path then it
is terminated we are not talking of that condition
essentially. So, we as talking about it
condition before termination which means there
is a paths to the goal we assuming there
is a path to the goal and it has not yet found
a path or the path whatever you want to say
we will show.
.That when it finds the path it will always
finds an optimal path. So, initially we put
s on
to open. So, the condition is true in the
initial situation when we remove s from open
we
put it into closed and then we end of putting
n 1 on to open essentially if we remove n
from open then you put this into close and
this process will continue essentially if
we
remove g from open which is the last in this
line; that means, algorithm is terminated
by
founding a finding a path essentially. So,
this condition says that at any time 1 of
these
nodes is always in the open which is available
to a star to inspect next.
.
Further we say
the f value of this node is always less to
or equal to the optimal cost from.
So, s is the start node, and remembers, s
star is a optimal cost of going from start
to the
goal node essentially. So, this is this is
part of the statement, we are saying that
not only
the such a nodes node exist it will always
have f value which is lower than or equal
to the
optimal cost.
..
So, what is the argument behind this you can
say that f of n prime is equal to g of n
prime plus h of n prime it is by definition
of what the f value is now, because it is
the
known optimal path we know that this is g
star of n prime plus h of n prime. Remember
that we are talking of optimal path. This
will be less than equal to g star of n prime
plus h
star of n prime, because of the condition,
condition number 3 which we are said that
the
heuristic values always less than or equal
to the optimal value, which means this is
equal
to less than or equal to f star of n prime,
where f star of n prime is the cost of the
optimal
path which passes through n prime; not necessarily
the globally optimal path to the
optimal path passes through n prime. But these
n prime that we have chosen is on the
optimal path itself; so this must be equal
to f star of s because after all it is it
is the same
paths that we are talking about.
So, whether we say it is a passing through
n prime or a. So, whether we say it is passing
through s or n 1 or n 2 or n 3 or g it does
not matter the cost is in the same. So, this
is the
condition that we are looking for; and this
is less than or equal to this f star of s
that is
what we have written.
..
Then the third thing we want to say is that
algorithm terminates if there is
a path, and it
should had even for infinite graphs remember
that an infinite graph is only be that which
has an infinite number of nodes factor. So,
this the third statement we have making is
that the algorithm terminates with a path;
that if there is a path from the starts to
the goal
state, the algorithm will always terminate
with the path from the start to the goal state
we
are not yet talked about optimal path, we
are saying the it will find the path; and
we are
saying making this claim that even of the
graph is infinite when you say that infinite
number of nodes, then algorithm will find
a paths to the goal. What would be an
argument for this? In other words we are saying
that the algorithm will terminate that
picking the goal node of the two termination
criteria that we have one is the open is
empty in this for infinite graphs open can
never be empty. So, for infinite graphs it
can
only terminate by picking a goal nodes essentially.
So, we are saying you want to argue that it
will necessarily pick the goal node at some
point of time just you to imagine this graph
just imagine it doing a search in a city or
something like that, how the open front yard
will move essentially. You remember that it
always picks the node with the lowest f value
essentially for a goal node the f value is
equal to the g value of that node, because
h is 0 you already at the goal. So, we want
to
argue that this node is the goal, which is
the goal node will the at some point come
to the
.head of this sorted list or at the at the
root of the way of maintaining the priority
queue.
In other words we are saying that all other
nodes on open will at some point become
more expensive then this node g. And why is
that?
.
No no no . So, what I am saying I am saying
that let us say this is my start node, and
this
is my paths to the goal it has some cost essentially.
What I am saying is that this search
cannot ignore this whole node that eventually
it may have it may end of looking at a
node here.
.
It may end of looking at a node there in this
direction or that direction, but it cannot
go
indefinitely in any direction. And the reason
for that is that whichever direction it goes,
the g values, think of the g values supposing
there is a node here let us call it n 1 or
something if that is on the open list. So,
let us say the open is looking something like
this, you know refusing to go towards the
goal node, but there is a node n 1 g value?
What is going to be this g value of this node
is going to be the length of the path from
here to here, let us say it picks this node
n 1 it will have some other node let us collate
n
.2, and then it let us say picks n 3, can
it keep doing in can it keep going in indefinitely
in
along some other direction, because the g,
because the paths are becoming longer and
longer in those other direction; g value remember
is an is an length of the path found up
to that point. And at some point this f value
will become the smallest that is say
condition that we have that the paths are
edges are positive in cost essentially. So,
if you
go in some direction and some point your cost
will becomes. So, what is the value of this
sum g of g the some value at some point all
other nodes that you have in open will have
paths which are longer than this; or to think
of it in another manner, there are only a
finite number of paths which are shorter than
this lengths g of g; and even if the
algorithm will explore all those paths and
then it will take of g of g. Is this they
seems to
be a gently silence about this essentially.
All we are saying is that if you go of in
some other direction your path cost will become
more than the cost of this g value and remember
that the heuristic function
underestimate. So, you can never over estimate
the cost to in any case g will come at
some point and the some point this will become
the smaller. So, it will have to pick the
node. So, as it turns out this was many years
ago, when I was teaching the same very
point in the class 1 of the students in the
class, he is now professor in Princeton raises
hand, and said this is not correct; and it
something you do with this condition that
is why
i said for the moment let us assume this this
condition is the paths the edge of e, the
cost
of each edge is greater than 0.
So, it is possible to assign edges, edge cost
for example, I will assign 1 to the first
edge,
half to the second edge, one-fourth to the
third edge 1 8 to the fourth edge and keep
dividing by 2. What will happen, I will have
an infinite path whose total path length will
be finite essentially, and that finite could
be less than this g value, which means that
it
could get actually trapped in that infinite
path essentially, which has the finite total
cost.
So, this is like you know that paradox is
that . in the hair paradox that epidemics
paradox. That you say that the diabet, the
tortoise tells the rabbit that i if you give
me a
lead of let us 100 meters then you can never
beat me in the race and this argument is the
following.
So, let us say rabbit is at starting point
and the tortoise is 100 meters away, the tortoise
.say that by the time you come to this 100
meters point, I would have to move to some
point let us call it x 1 essentially and by
the time you come to x 1, I would have to
move
to x 2 and by the time you come to x 2, I
would have to move to x x 3 and this will
ofcourse keep happening infinitely and so
you can never over take me essentially. So,
is
1 of the paradoxes which comes into picture
and something similar would happen if you
go to allow arbitral small edge cost essentially.
So, if you cannot allow arbitral small
edge cost then this will not happen.
.
So, which is where the correct condition is
not greater than 0, but greater than some
value some positive value and as long as that
is the case, it cannot be infinite especially
small then every path fill at some point become
longer than this path to g, and then g will
come into. So, i will take it that this point
has been accepted.
..
So what have we done so far? So far we have
said between statements 1 and 3 1 means
said that the algorithm always terminate;
in 3 means said if there is a path to the
goal it
will always find the path to the goal. Now
we are saying that it will always find the
optimal paths to the goal essentially. And
it has very simple argument, the argument
is as
follows that so the proof for this I will
write here.
.
.Let A star terminate with a non optimal path,
which means it is found some paths to the
goal where the g value of that path. So, let
me just call a g 1 is greater than f star
of s,
remember f star of s is the optimal path;
whenever you use the star it is an optimal
path,
whether we know in the value or not essentially.
So, we are saying that let proof a
contradiction that a star terminate with a
by picking a goal node g 1, whose g value
is
more than the optimal cost, and now I want
to make a statement that this cannot happen
let me ask you, why can this happen, why can
it not terminate by a finding a non optimal
path.
So, if it is picked goal node it will terminate
that is the algorithm; that you must
remember like the algorithm. If it picks the
goal node for open; that means, it will
terminate; it will say I found the goal and
so on. Now we are saying that let it terminate
by picking the goal node g 1 such that it
is cost is more than the optimal cost; remember
f
star of f star of s is equal to f star of
g, and in fact, it f star of any value on
this node
essentially, all of them the values are the
same, it is cost of the optimal it is a cost
of this
optimal path. So, we are saying that assume
that a star terminates by picking a value
which is more than the optimal.
Now what I am trying to say that we cannot
make this assumption, I mean it is not the
long proof or something it just 1 statement
it say that it can never pick this such a
node
and terminate. So, if you look at the statement
number 2 that we have written here; there
is reason for every statement. That statement
says that at all point before termination
there exist a node n prime, which is on the
optimal path, and whose f value is less than
f
star of s. So, so simple answer is it cannot.
Why because, it would pick n prime as simple
as that the algorithm simply says pick the
one of the lowest f value.
So, just imagine there it is about to terminate
by picking this goal g 1, and this goal g
has it is cost more than the f f f. So, it
will never be at the head of the priority
queue
essentially, because we have said that at
all points before termination, there is always
a
node n prime which is on the optimal path
and which is on open. So, f this n prime is
on
open and it is value is less than f star s.
..
So, we it has if a star also choose between
these 2 nodes 1 whose value is less than or
equal to f star s and one whose value is definitely
greater than f star s. Remember I have
written g of g i could have written f of g
is a same thing, because f of g is equal to
g of g
plus 0, because h is 0. So, you can write
f of g or g of g does not matter, it is a
same
thing.
.
.So, if a star at to pick between these 2
nodes n prime and g 1, it would pick n prime
which mean it cannot terminate by picking
g 1 like this essentially. So, the only time
it
can pick a goal node is that if it is at least
as good as the optimal cost node essentially.
So, it will always terminate only with an
optimal path; is it okay? So, now we want
to
look at 1 more property and this is as for.
.
So, one more statement before that property
that I am talking about is that for every
node
N that a star picks f of n is always less
than equal to the optimal cost. So, we are
saying
that a star will only pick nodes whose f value
is less than the optimal, all this is coming
from fact that the heuristic function is under
estimating, because the heuristic function
under estimates we are shown that you know
nodes like this will always be less an
optimal cost or they will always be such a
node less an optimal cost.
And now we are saying the same argument as
we as we did for this case 4 that if f star
is
going to pick this node n, it must be better
than n prime, because it has picked n and
if it
is better than n prime it must be less than
or equal to f star of s essentially. So, it
only
pick nodes which the better than equal to
optimal cost node. L 6 is the question; so,
let
there be 2 functions. So, we say h 2 is more
informed than h 1 if for all nodes h 2 n is
greater than h 1 n. So, if the heuristic value
h 2 is greater than h 1 n, then we say that
h 2
.is more informed. Just a definition, we say
then if this is the case then every node seen
by a 2 and a 2 is 1 version of a star, which
is using this h 2 function is also seen by
A 1
star.
So, let us say we have this two versions of
a star algorithm 1 uses this h 2 function
heuristic function the other uses the h 1
heuristic function and h 2 is always greater
than
h 1 of n we say that the h 2 is more inform
than. So, take the extreme case when h 1 is
equal to 0 h 1 is equal to 0 it always thinks
that the cost goal is 0 essentially which
is
what does where as the h 2 thinks that it
is at least some value. So, such a function
is
called and we are making a claim that if h
2 is more inform than h 1 so I should write
if
here if h 2 is more informed than h 1, then
every node seen by a 2 star is also seen by
a 1
star, which means a 2 star will see in general
a smaller number of nodes, of which means
it will explore a smaller part of the search
space essentially, it will be more focused
towards the search.
So, we will do this proof by induction, and
you can see that for the start node does
properties true. So, what is the property
we are trying to prove that if even if A 2
see
some node then A 1 also sees that node we
want to prove that let us call this property
p
that if A 2 sees the node A 2 star why star,
because both are admissible. So, what is the
situation? Situation is like this for any
given node n, there is a band starting from
0 to h
star of n.
..
What we are saying is that h 2 is somewhere
here and h 1 is somewhere here this is what
we mean by more informed closer to h the optimal
value. And we want to make a claim
that if this is the situation, then the search
space explore by the algorithm using h 2 will
be smaller than the search space by algorithm
using h 1. And we will this proof by
induction. So, you can see that for s. So,
we call the statement p; so p is true for
s which
is a start node. So, we are just saying that
if if a 1 sees if a 2 sees the start node
and even
will also see start which is really true,
because both the algorithms are the A star
always
starts were picking the star node essentially.
So, the second part is the hypothesis, which
says that let so I will just use this for
this whole statement.
..
So, instead of every let me say any node which
is the same thing essentially. So, let p be
true for depth k 1 or depth k. Now we want
show that this is also true for depth k plus
how much is the induction step, and this you
will do by contradiction. So, let n be a node
at depth k plus 1, which is picked by A 2
star and let A 1 star terminate without picking
n. So, the induction step, you will do by
contradiction. So, we are making an assumption
that there is some node we have call this
capital N at depth k plus 1 and we are saying
a 2
star has pick that node, but a 1 star terminated
without ever picking that node essentially,
which means a 1 star found a paths to the
goal. Now if you look at this value h f 2
of n,
so f 2 is further second algorithm which is
using h 2 is g 2 of n plus h 2 of n.
So, we can rewrite this as H 2 of n and this
is less than f star of s; remember that any
node that you take the statement 5 that view
it that will have this value less than f star
of
s. So, we are just writing f star it has does
not matter f 1 or f 2 it is a optimal cost
f star is
starts for the optimal cost. So, we can write
this as h 2 of n is less than equal to less
than
equal to f star of s minus g 2 of n.
Now even star has terminated without picking
this node n, which means that f 1 of n is
greater than or equal to f star of s. It cannot
be less than f star of s, because is a a 1
star
has terminated and it will terminate by picking
a node with the optimal cost value, and it
.has not picked n. So, if this equal inequality
must hold; that it must be at best equal to
that, but it cannot be less in that essentially.
So, this we can write rewrite as following
f
star of s is less than equal to g 1 of n plus
h 1 of n, I am just rewriting this I am replacing
f 1 of n by g 1 of n plus h 1 of n, and I
just inverted the sign in equality sign essentially
.
Now the question I want to ask is what is
the relation between g 1 of n and g 2 of n
this g
1 this g 2 of n and g 1 of n; if I have if
I have to put a in equality what would I put
or
equal to what is relation between this. What
should I put, what symbol should I put in
between here g 2 is greater than equal to,
you are the only one who are saying that.
why is other case?
.Need be optimal there only the path found
so far path found so far by A 2 need not
be the optimal you are not getting the exactly,
but you must remember this statement we
made let this condition be true up to depth
k the induction hypothesis, which means that
every node that is been seen by A 2 up to
depth k has also been seen by a 1. So,
whichever path A 2 found a 1 would have also
seen that path, but may it had seen some
other path as well be equal, but we are saying
it does not have to be equal.
..
So, if this will be greater than so, is possible
that A 1 might find a shorter paths to n
because it is explore more nodes on the way
to n essentially.
.
It could always so the point of this whole
exercise is that we can replace this by g
2 of n,
we can rewrite this as we can replace it by
g 2 of n plus h 1 of n, which means we can
.write this as f star of s minus g 2 of n
less than equal to h 1 of n. So, I just wrote
g 2 on to
the left hand side and rewritten the statement
here. So, I have this f star of s minus g
2 of
n is less than equal to h 1 of n, n is that
node, which even did not pick and that is
why we
could write this in equality.
.
Here we have said the same thing that this
is less than this and therefore
simply by a
transitivity here h 2 of n is less than equal
to h 1 of n which is the contradiction, because
we assumed this that is h 2 of n is greater
is always greater than h 1 of n and here we
have said that if this and this is only assumption
we have made that let a 1 star terminate
without picking n and that was select to this
statement with contradicts over original
statement essentially. So, this cannot be
the case.
..
And therefore, it cannot terminate without
picking n, which means that if a 2 has pick
this node n, A 1 also must pick this node
n and which is the statement we are making
that
every node seen by A 2 will also be seen by
A 1.
.
So, the effect of this is that the space explored
by a 2 is contained not necessarily strictly
.contained, but contained in the space explored
by A 1 essentially. So, it always space to
have a better heuristic function; the higher
the h 1 h 2, the better .. Any questions
here? So, there is one more property which
needs to be looked at, but we will do that
in
next class. So, I will stop here, and will
sort of come back to this A star and it is
behavior
will do a quick recap in the next class, and
then will start again. So, I will stop here.
.