We are back. Having looked at the mechanical
side of this history of AI, we want to now
look at the philosophical side as you know;
this notion of the mind. What is the notion
of
the mind? How did this notion of the mind
ever come out? And how can we get it across
to the machines, essentially?
.
So, the medieval view, world view in Europe
was basically, a Christian adaptation of
Greek ideas, essentially. There was a big
gap between the Greeks and medieval Europe,
but the ideas that Greek started off with,
eventually, ended up with medieval Europe.
The
view of the world was of course, that it was
a very anthropocentric view of the world;
humans were at the center of the universe,
and everything revolved round the earth,
essentially. We look at some of those ideas.
What we are trying to see is how did human
beings, as gentian beings, have come up with
the notion of the mind? How would you
even imagine that there is something called
a mind? I mean, of course, you are there in
.the world; you are immersed in the world,
and you are interacting with the world. But
how do you come to this conclusion that you
have thoughts and ideas, which are in some
sense, existing independently.
We start with the platonic view of the world;
the idea of which came from Plato. He said
that in the perfect world, there are this
creator's ideas; the God’s ideas. Our ideas,
the
humans’ ideas are derived from God’s ideas,
and the world itself, is derived from God’s
ideas. So, it is a very platonic view of this
whole world, and the world was corruptible
materialization of God’s ideas. You know,
that is why things were not perfect in the
world. Even though, God’s ideas are perfect;
the world is not perfect. Likewise, our
thoughts are true to the extent that they
are accurate copies of God’s ideas; that
was the
first starting point; Plato.
When we move we move on to Aristotel, Aristotel
derived the idea of the God and he
said that the world is out there, and human
ideas are human ideas, and they, in some way,
correspond to the world, essentially. So,
our thoughts resemble the objects at they
stand
for. If I am thinking of an apple, then my
thought of an apple resembles the apple,
essentially. This is known as the correspondence
theory of truth, essentially, and one
branch of philosophy, which was, it was taken
up by Ludwig Wittgenstein, who in his
early works, postulated something called the
picture theory of languages; that behind
every word, there is a picture; an image which
is sitting out there, essentially. So, this
is
how the world as we saw it. The earth was
flat at the center of the universe with the
Gods, heavens, rotating around it essentially.
The sensible world, the world at we could
sense, was composed a five elements
..
Quintessence, which was constant in the heavens,
did not change; constant in that sense.
Four are the elements, which are fire, air,
water and earth; listed in decreasing order
of
weight, essentially. So, you can find similar
ideas all over the world about, you know
what are the basic elements of the world,
essentially. So, if you ignore quintessence,
which is there in the heavens; we have fire,
earth, water and air. They are all jumbled
up
on the earth, trying to find or striving to
find a rightful place; rightful place, meaning
by
order of weight, essentially. The earth should
be the lowest, and then, there should be
water, and then, air and then, fire. Different
materials had different amounts of these four
elements in them, and that is why, they behave
differently. For example, wood had more
water, and therefore, and some air, and therefore,
it floated on water, essentially.
Whereas, iron had more earth and therefore,
it sank in water, essentially. So, they could
explain why wood floated, whereas, iron sank
and so on. If wood were to catch fire, then
you know, it tries to escape into air. So,
there are this kind of explanations about
the
world, essentially.
..
This is how; the color inside this circle
is supposed to represent the color of the
sky. So,
you know, we have morning, day time, evening
and night. As the sun; it depends upon
the position of the sun; as the sun rotates,
our day changes, essentially.
.
So, this is a small animation I created of
what we thought about the world to be like.
This
.is how the world was; all the heavens were
rotating around the earth, and the earth was
the center of the universe, essentially. Now,
in those days, astronomy was for many
reasons, are very important science, and to
very empirical science; but it was difficult
to
explain the motions of the planets. For those
of you, who are interested in astronomy,
you would know that the stars are always in
the same position; the constellations that
we
see, Leo or Virgo or any of these. The constellations,
they always appear in the same
fixed pattern, throughout the year. It is
only the planets, which you know, move from
one
constellation to another, and it was very
difficult to explain; how they were operating,
essentially.
King Alfonso of Spain in 13th century got
so upset; that he said that if God had
consulted me when creating the universe, he
would have received a good advice. You
know, why have this planets move around in
erratic fashion, essentially. It is a quotation
I have got from book; I should have mentioned
it there.
.
Then, along came Copernicus. So, this is the
first, and this what (Refer Time.
says; the verge between thought and reality,
the first verge between thought and reality
was inserted by Copernicus, who says that
what we see, is not what really is. So, up
till
now, remember, this picture theory, the truth,
the motion of correspondence that our
.thoughts are in the image of what we see
around us, and that kind of a thing, that
our
thoughts reflect the world as it is. Copernicus
was the first person, who came and you
must be familiar with his book on the revolutions
of the celestial spheres. He said that
our Earth is not at the center of the universe.
In fact, the earth revolves around the sun,
and earth rotates, and creates the illusions
of day and night, and that kind of stuff,
essentially. The important thing from our
point of view is that what we see, is not
what
really is out there, essentially; so, the
verse as hogelensay between thought and reality.
.
So, all these famous characters; you have
encountered them in one way or the other.
We
know Galileo Galilei, because of the equations
of motion, for example, we always
attribute them to Galileo; v is equal to u
plus a t, and you know, that kind of stuff.
But
Galileo made this very important observation.
He said that perception is an internal
process. He says, and this is quoted to him;
I think that tastes, odors, colors, and so
on,
are no more than mere names, so far as the
object in which, we locate them, are
concerned. So, if you are smelling a rose
and you feel that the rose smells nice, it
is
nothing to do; the notion of the smell of
the rose is not located in the rose, but it
is
located in our minds.
So, he says tastes, odors, colors and so on,
are no more than mere names, so far as the
.object in which, we locate them, are concerned
and that they reside in consciousness in
our minds, in other words. He says that hence,
if the living creature were removed that
we as a perceivers of this tastes and smell
and odors were removed, all these qualities
would be wiped away, essentially; that this
notion of taste and smell and color is
something that we have in our heads; it is
not the property of the object. So, he goes
on
to explain, for example, he imagines that
the notion of smell actually, happens, because
they are this particles, which are impinging
upon the inside of our noses, which results
in
certain sensation, which we call as smells.
It is very accurate as you can see, but Galileo
said that in the 17th century that perception
is an internal process, essentially. So, we
are
exploring this notion of thinking; how the
notion of the mind evolves? So, all these
are
European history, because AI, as we know it,
came out of European thought, essentially.
Even though, for example, other civilizations
like Indian philosophy, has a lot to say
about some of these concepts, like knowledge
and so on, but we are not, I mean, AI did
not come out of that, essentially.
Then, Galileo says that philosophy is written
in this grand book; The Universe. It is
written in the language of mathematics, and
its characters are triangles, circles and
other
geometric figures. So, when Galileo was doing
all these reasoning, algebra had not been
invented, essentially. In fact, his proofs
of the equations that we attribute to him,
like v is
equal to u plus at; are essentially, geometric
in nature. So, if you look at Hoggland’s
book, you will see some idea of how he draws
triangles, and says that this side represents
this; this side represents that; and the area
represents this; and that kind of thing. All
these reasoning were done; for him, mathematics
was geometry, and he says that the
whole world can be described in mathematics;
the language of mathematics; and its
characters are triangles, circles and other
geometric figures. So, you can say, this is
another step away from the fact that our ideas
are reflections of the real world out there.
He is saying that you can think of motion;
the laws of motion are about moving bodies,
using the language of mathematics. So, the
very already, the representation has moved
to
something, which is different from the real
world out there, essentially. Next, we look
at;
so, Galileo showed that geometry could be
used to represent and reason about motion;
this is what we just said.
..
Then we come to the person, who Haugeland
calls as the grandfather of AI. It was the
English philosopher, Thomas Hobbes, 1588-
1649, who first put forward the view that
thinking is the manipulation of symbols. This
is fundamental to AI, because after all, we
are talking about representing symbols and
manipulating them, and creating intelligence
out of them, essentially. So, Galileo had
said that reality is mathematical, in the
sense
that everything is made up of particles, and
our sense of smell or tastes as, how we
reacted to those particles. Hobbes extended
this notion to say that thought too was made
up of, or expressed in particles, which the
thinker manipulated. So, Galileo was talking
about the external reality, and how we can
represent, think about that, or talk about
that.
Hobbes is talking about the internal process
of thinking and saying that even thinking
is
basically, the manipulation of something,
which we called as particles, which we now
call as symbols, essentially.
However, he had no answer to the question
of how can a symbol mean anything, because
we will see that; for us, intelligence is
manipulating of symbols in a meaningful fashion.
Hobbes could never say how can a symbol, mean
anything. In fact, as Haugeland says he
could not distinguish, he could not tell us;
how minds are different from books. In the
sense that books are also collections of symbols,
and mind are also collections of
symbols, which we are manipulating; how can
the two be different, because the idea of
.meaning is very elusive. So, if I were to
ask you; how do you know the meaning of a
word? How would you, what would your answer
be? You just take any word. Let us say
Student: in terms (( ))
Prof: You could use examples.
In particular, I am talking about our standard
source of meaning, which is a dictionary.
So, if you want to look up a meaning of a
word, you go, and look up a dictionary. How
does a dictionary give us meanings, essentially,
because dictionary is only describing
words in terms of other words, essentially.
When you give examples; also, you are giving
examples in terms of other words. Where does
the meaning originate from? I mean is
there a fundamental source of meanings, essentially?
This is a kind of difficulty, which
Hobbes faces. Where does meaning come from,
essentially? We are also not able to see
where, the meaning comes from. See, for people
before him that the notion of an apple
is, because you see an apple, and that is
what it means. But when you talk about
language and thought and symbols; we have
this difficulty of saying where, does this
meaning come from, essentially; as a question
that we do not, we are not yet, answered.
.
.Here, is the picture of Thomas Hobbes in
the 16th century. In his book called De
Corpore, Hobbes first describes the view that
reasoning is computation. So, he is saying
reasoning is computation. By reasoning, he
says I understand computation, and to
compute is to collect the sum of many things,
added together at the same time, or; these
are very arcade languages; or to know the
reminder, when one thing has been taken from
another to reason, therefore, is the same
as to add or to subtract. Again, like I said
and
adding, subtracting, arithmetic is similar
to other kind, reasoning is similar to this
kind of
process, essentially. So, this quote, I have
taken from this source, which is the Stanford
encyclopedia of philosophy, and as we have
just mentioned, Hobbes was influenced by
Galileo; just as geometry could represent
motion, thinking could be done by
manipulation of mental symbols, essentially.
Does not name Hobbes ring a bell? Kelvin
and Hobbes; in fact, Hobbes was named after
Thomas Hobbes. Kelvin and Hobbes,
named after Thomas Hobbes; that is why he
is such a philosophical character.
.
When we come to Rene Descartes, again, another
great thinker from the middle times.
We know for many things, including in Cartesian
coordinates is named after Decartes.
He had come; remember, that all these things
was going on, these talking statues, moving
things, and so on and so forth, and it had
become surf acceptable in Europe to talk about;
these machines has being liked, in some sense,
essentially.
.So, Descartes, in fact, goes on to saying
that animals are wonderful machines; he just
makes the next step that they are not like
machines; they are machines, essentially.
Then,
he says human being were to, except for that
they process something, called a mind,
essentially. We will come to this Decartes
problem in a moment. So, just as Galileo said
that motion can be expressed in geometry;
Decartes said geometry could be expressed
in
algebra. Decartes is the one, who invented
this; we called coordinate geometry and, but
he went further; he says that even thought
can be expressed in the language of
mathematics and thoughts themselves, are symbolic
representations. So, you can see, he
is building upon what, Hobbes says. Hobbes
says that thoughts are symbols, and now, he
says that thoughts are symbolic representation
that we operate up on, essentially.
.
But this is something, which is new which
Decartes brings in; the notion of the mind
and
the body. So, Decartes is what we call as
the dualist, or belongs to this thinker, which
says that you know mind and body are two separate
things. So, we also, often called the
mind body dualism. So, as opposed to dualism,
there are schools of thought, which are
monoist in nature, which believe that there
is only one kind of thing. For the first time,
Decarte is saying that two different kinds
of things in this world; one is this material
world, which he calls a body, and the other
is the mental world, which he calls as the
mind. He says that they are two different
kinds of things. The material world, of course,
.would obey the laws of physics and things
like that. We will see later that you know
philosopher said that mental world also, should
obey such laws and so on, but they are
different world. The world of mind is separate,
and the world of body is separate.
And this is opposed to other kinds of philosophies,
other kinds of views in philosophy
that there is only one kind of thing. So,
there is the world of idealism, which says
that
there is only the world of ideas. So, for
example, in India we say that everything is
Maya; everything is the world of ideas and
matter is basically, a construct that comes
out
of our ideas, essentially. Very complicated
to think about, but may be you can reflect
upon that, a little bit. As opposed to idealism,
the other world is materialism, which says
that everything is matter, and the whole world
is matter, and the matter interacts in the
certain way. Ideas and minds and all these,
kind of stuffs; they emerge out of this
somehow, essentially. So, they are different
viewpoints about what the world is like
there, and Decartes is a dualist. He said
that mind and body are two separate things.
He
says that a symbol and what it symbolizes
are two different things.
So, if I say chalk is a symbol, it is a compound
symbol made up of these letters, but it is
nevertheless, a symbol. So, chalk is a symbol
and this thing that I am holding in the
hand, is what it symbolizes. So, this notion
that chalk; symbol chock is separate. Then,
we have this problem that a symbol is amenable
to algebraic manipulation. So, you can
do thinking, what we call as thinking is basically,
symbol manipulation, which you can
manipulate symbols. The subject of thought
is a world; the real world out there what,
it
symbolizes. They are different things; the
mind is different and the body is different.
Of
course, he had to answer questions like, you
know, because see, the body or the material
world obeys laws of physics. The mind, of
course, was not clear how to operate it, but
it
was separate. He had to answer questions like
this; when, what makes a notation or a
symbol notation, suitable for symbolizing,
and secondly, what makes a suitable notation
actually symbolize?
See this problem has occurred, because he
has separated the world of the mind and the
body. He says the mind is one thing, and the
body is another thing. A symbol is one thing
and what it symbolizes, is another thing.
So, the question is what makes a notation
suitable for symbolizing? Now, that is a question
that we are addressing now. When we
.write algorithms or when we talk about knowledge
representation, then we are
addressing this issue as to you know, what
is this? How do you represent? How do you
create a domain model, for example; how do
you represent the world so that, you can
compute up on that, essentially. That is an
easier part. A more difficult part is what
makes a suitable notion actually, symbolizes;
which means that if it is to be meaningful
in nature, then the world of symbols or the
world of thought, should be connected in
some ways to the material world or the world
of matter. Because they cannot be
independent of each other they are not different
worlds that are, you know, operating
independently. Our world of thoughts is, sort
of, close synchrony to the world of matters.
If we raise our hands, if we think about raising
our hands; we actually, raise our hands.
So, that kind of, how does the interaction
take place between the world of thought and
the world of matter. So, the question is how
can thought and matter interact; because the
world of thought is different. Matter, of
course, behave, sort of, obeys the laws of
physics. What about the world? The world of
thought is not made of matter; it is a
different world. How can it interact with
matter; that is a question that he could never
answer; the mind body problem, essentially,
or the mind body dualism, essentially.
.
So, this brings us to what we can call as
the paradox of mechanical reason; this term
is
by John Haugeland in his book. The paradox
says that if reasoning is the manipulation
of
.meaningful symbols, according to rational
rules; remember, that we are talking about
manipulating symbols says there are well defined
ways of manipulating these ideas. It is
not like you are doing it, randomly so, according
to well defined rules. So, if reasoning is
a manipulation of symbols, according to these
rational rules; who is manipulating these
symbols? Because this question of meaningful
manipulation is coming; our thoughts are
not independent of the real world, essentially;
they have to be connected to that,
essentially. If a fast bowler is running up
and bowling, thinking of bowling and in swing
around something, he better be able to produce
the real in swing if he is worth, he solved.
How is his thoughts related to the real world,
essentially? Who is manipulating the
symbols, essentially? It is a difficult question
to answer, because what says is that it can
be either be mechanical, according to some
fix set of rules, or it can be meaningful.
How
can it be both? You cannot have a mechanical
system, being meaningful at the same
time, and by meaningful, we mean paying attention
to the mean of what is happening.
How can a mechanical manipulator pay attention
to meaning? Remember, that they are
not talking about AI or any such thing; they
are talking about human cognation; they are
talking about human minds; how human minds
operate, essentially? So, they are trying
to analyze that, essentially. Decartes said
that there is a world of the mind, which is
the
symbol processing. Then, there is a world
of the body, which is the real world, made
up
of physical matter, but they are closely tied
together. So, when I am thinking about some
real world in a meaningful fashion; if I have
got two pieces on a table, let us say, a cake
and a sandwich, and thinking about them. I
have to decide, should I pick up one of them;
I am thinking about some real things in the
world, in a meaningful fashion. My thoughts
about the cake and the sandwich are about
real things, and I making some decisions;
should I eat this, or should I not eat this
or something like that. So, this meaningfulness;
where does that come from, essentially? How
can a mechanical manipulator pay
attention to meaning; it is a question I would
ask you to ponder over a little bit, and see,
whether you know, may be like Pen Rose said,
human beings are special. There is
something special happening in our brains,
which allows us to do this, or like Grafus
said
that there are some instincts that we have,
which we cannot automate, but of course, I
will take the opposite group.
So, this led to a lot of debate in his time.
This is, we are talking about Decartes still,
Rene
.Decartes, and his mind body dualism. Some
people attribute the fact that you know, it
is
said that Decartes, who also gave us a phrase
Cogito Igo, some I think, therefore, I am.
Apparently, he is claimed to have a proof
of the God exists, essentially, and the proof
is
tied to the fact that there is this difficulty
about how do symbols get manipulated in the
meaningful fashion, but his contemporary is,
of course, did not accept any such thing.
They would, in fact, mock him about you know,
this idea. So, we can imagine a little bit
like the Chinese room, which you have not
discussed in detail. Just imagine that your
brain is a Chinese room, full of symbols.
There is somebody, manipulating those
symbols according to some rules. Who is that
somebody; that is the question that we
asking. So, people would mock at Decartes
and say that there is a little man sitting
in
your head, who is doing manipulating these
symbols, but the problem is as you can
imagine; this explanation does not work, because
the next question that you would ask is;
how does the little man operate? Little man
has his little brain in his little body, which
has little symbols inside his head, and who
is manipulating those symbols. So, there
comes an infinite review, essentially, and
people say that this is what, led to Decartes
claim that he can prove that God exists, essentially.
But in the real world, what was happening
as to this question to who people,
philosophers have tried various kinds of explanations;
something called the faculty of
will, which we cannot quite define, or transcended
ago, or as I said, the people who used
to mock him and say, there is a homunculus.
Remember, the homunculus of nearby
parcel; a little man sitting inside. So, that
is a fundamental question one has to answer.
We say that if you are in modern day world,
going to write programs, which will operate
according to the algorithms that you are putting
into those programs; how can they be
doing meaningful things? It is roughly equaling
to that, essentially, or I might say that
if
I want to implement a neural network, which
is; I know that the structure of a neuron,
and how it operates, and so on and so forth,
and I am just connecting together hundreds
of thousands of neurons. How can that evolve;
do meaningful things like character
recognition? Of course, we know that it can
be done; character recognition can be done,
but the fundamental question is that; is that
intelligent, or is it doing something that
we
have asked it to do.
In fact, he said that the computer can only,
do what is instructed to do; nothing more
than
.that, which is of course, true at a very
fundamental level. Some recent thoughts on
who is
doing this manipulation, thinking, there are
some very interesting books, and for those
of
you are interested; I would recommend them.
All of three have a common author called
Douglas Hofstadter, who is in the Indiana
University. His famous book was Godel,
Escher, Bach. He and Dennet, wrote a series,
collected a series of articles called The
Mind’s Eye. More recently, he has written
a book called I am a Strange Loop. So, he
is
trying to; Hofstadter is also trying to answer
this question; I mean, instead of saying who,
he is saying what is this notion of I that
I have, as a as a human being that I have,
essentially, or I or you, essentially. If
I talk of you as a person; what do I really
mean,
essentially? What is that you, essentially?
I say that my body, my mind, my hands, my
eyes, my feet, my whatever; what is this I,
which is saying my, essentially? That is the
question, which Hofstadter is trying to answer,
and he, sort of, uses a combination of
emergent behavior and self-essential loops,
which we do not have time to get into here,
but I would recommend one of these books;
they are quite easy to read and quite
interesting. So, let us move on from Decartes
to John Locke, known as the father of
classical liberalism.
.
His theory of mind is often cited as the origin
of modern concept of identity and the self,
essentially. It influence other philosophers
like Hume, that we will see and Kant that
we
.will see, in a moment. He postulated that
mind was a blank slate, as opposed to what
Thompskey says that we are born with an inbuilt
grammar or the universal grammar in
our heads. Locke said that the mind was a
blank slate or tabula rasa as he called it,
and
that we are born without innate ideas, and
as you can see in the last two lines; knowledge
is determined by experience derived from sense
perception. Whatever, we know in our
heads is the result of whatever we have experienced
in the world, and experience leads to
knowledge, essentially.
.
One of his elaborators or followers, David
Hume, Scottish philosopher, whom
Haugeland calls as a mental mechanic. By this,
we mean a mechanic, who is operating in
the mental domain. It was empiricism and in
his book called Treatise of Human Nature,
he strove to create what he called as the
science of man that examined the psychological
basis of human nature. He said that everything
is tied up to human nature. If you can
understand human nature, you can understand
how human beings behave and what else
is there, essentially. Science and everything,
derives from there. He follows this idea of
experience and observation as a foundation
of logical argument. He was an admirer of
Newton, and he says in a manner in which,
Newton express the movement of heavenly
bodies over planets and so on.
.He says that impressions and ideas are like
basic particles to which, mental forces and
operations are applied. Just as Newton is
giving the laws of physics, Hume is saying
that
there is a law of mental activity; law of
associations, as he called it. They were;
mental
ideas were like particles. He is not saying
that they were particles; they were like
particles to which, mental force and operations
are applied. Further, like Newton, he does
not care as to how that is happening. So,
Newton had never explained how gravity
happens, or you know why gravity happens;
there was no explanation behind there. He
just gives the laws of gravity, and says that
this is how planets are moving around the
earth, and it is explained by gravity. So,
Hume does the same thing. He does not try
to
explain how it is happening; he says that
this is what is happening, and it can be
explained by these laws; do not ask me, why
it is happening, like that, essentially. But
he
could not explain, however, what made ideas,
ideas, now. It is like that once, you say
these are particles, which are obeying these
laws, and then why are these ideas,
essentially. What makes their interaction
between different ideas count as thinking,
essentially? So, he is done away with meaning,
all together.
.
So, the last person, we will visit today,
is Immanuel Kant, German philosopher, widely
considered to be central to modern philosophy.
In fact, when I was in undergraduate, we
had a whole course, which data comparative
analysis of Kant and Mills philosophy. He
.says, and this is very interesting; they
have come a long way in this short period
of time.
From this notion that the world is out there,
and we are simply saying the world; the
correspondence theory of knowledge and then,
mind body dualism and then so; Kant has
come to the other theory. He says the mind
has a priori principles, which make things
outside conform to those principles. These
are some very consistent, with some very
modern ideas. For example, some very recent
research in computer vision; the simple
view of computer vision would be like the
correspondence theory of knowledge that you
get the image of things, and you do image
processing, pattern recognition, feature
extraction, and all these kind of stuff, and
then, you understand what is happening. It
is a
forward process from the world to the mind.
Modern theory says that we have preconceived
notions of what we are trying to see, and
what we see is already there, in our mind
to some extent; this is what Kant has said.
The
mind has a priori principles, which makes
things outside conform to those principles.
Then, he says that mind shapes and structures
experience; it is a mind which shapes
structures and experience, so that, on an
abstract level, all human experience shares
essential structural features. All our mind
operates in the same way. That is why we are
able to communicate; that is the question
that one could have asked. How one human
being can communicate ideas to another human
being? He says fundamentally, the mind
has a similar structure. Then, he of course,
goes on to explain that the concept of space
and time are integral to human experience
that you cannot operate without them, as are
the notions of cause and effect, essentially.
What causes? Causal theory is basically, a
mental theory. In the real world, I mean,
we
have these cause and effect kind of a motion
that if I turn a switch on, the light will
come
out. But the physics does not recognize any
cause or causal theory. Physics only
recognizes the equations; it goes from one
equilibrium state to another equilibrium state;
there is no causal thing, but these are fundamental
to our thinking, essentially. So, the
second last paragraph is very interesting.
He says that we do not have direct experience
of things, and we will visit this in the next
class, which we have on Wednesday. We will
come back to this question. After, as he called
is the nominal world or the real world
outside, we do not have direct experience
access to the real world, but what we do
experience is the phenomenal world, as conveyed
by our senses. So, we cannot; you
.know, this is the very philosophical question.
If you look at some Indian philosophies,
like Buddhism, they ask this same question,
again that what is there in the mind, is what
we think, essentially. That is what Kant is
saying, essentially. He says that human
concepts and categories, structure the view
of the world, as we see it, essentially.
.
So, the world is not as it is out there, but
as we see it, essentially; the world as we
know
it. So, this is known as the subject-object
problems. A longstanding philosophical issue
is
concerned with analysis of human experience.
So, the question is that the world consists
of objects and entities, which are perceived,
or otherwise, presumed to exist as entities
by
subjects; there is the subject. So, we think
that the world has this object out there,
and
how does that happen, essentially. There are
some technical terms, which we should be
familiar with. The subject-object problem
has two primary aspects; first is what is
known; what can exist out there, and this
is something that we call as ontology, which
became very popular in current day computer
science. So, the field of ontology deals
with questions concerning what exist, or what
can said to be exist, actually, and how
such entities are grouped together, essentially,
related within a hierarchy and that kind of
a theory.
Nowadays, computer scientists talk a lot about
ontology, and in the concept of the
.semantic webs. So, we have one computer,
talks to another. One computer sitting here
to
meaningfully, talk to another computer, and
we have the social of ontology and
taxonomies, which we may not have time to
go through in this course. The second
standpoint is how does one know what we know;
and this concerns epistemology;
questions as to how knowledge is acquired.
So, ontology says what can exist, and
epistemology is concerned with how do we get
the real facts of, for example, why was
Durga suspended; epistemic question. How do
we say that this is what is really,
happened out there, essentially; is the question
of knowledge acquisition or
epistemology.
.
The bounds of our own mind; he creates. Kant
says that he has done something, like a
Copernican revolution in philosophy; what
he calls as a critical philosophy. So, he
says
that two things; one is the epistemology of
transcendental idealism, which says that we
are not able to transcend the bounds of our
own mind. We can only perceive the world
through the prism of our mind, in some sense;
through the spectacles of glasses as mind,
and we cannot exceed that. So, we cannot access
the real world out there; only, what our
mind allows us to see. Already, the notion
of mind has become prominent, essentially.
The moral philosophy in those days was not
quite what we talk about it as right now,
but
something, to do with the mental world. The
moral philosophy of the autonomy of
.practical reason; he says that practical
reason can be automated.
May be, this is the last thing I will leave
you with. Conceptual unification and integration
is carried out by the mind through concepts
or the categories of understandings. So, this
is again, those terms, some ontologies are
coming up. We have concepts about things.
We know, we have categories of birds, and
flowers, and apple, and fruits; all these
kind
of categories or things, operational on the
perceptional manifold, which is build within
space and time. Space and time is something,
fundamental to our minds. Our minds think
in terms of space and time, and everything
that we think about is located within our
notions of space and time. They are not concepts,
but are forms that are a priori
necessary conditions for any possible experience.
He says that without the notion of
space and time, you would not have been able
to imagine the world, and think about the
world. Thus, the objective order of nature
and the causal necessity that operates within
it
are dependent upon the mind’s processes,
which he called by a product of rule based
activity, which he called as a synthesis.
So, the emphasis is totally, shifted to the
human
mind. It is a human mind, which shapes the
way we see the world, and we reason about
the world, and everything is dependent upon
that. So, from a notion when we did not
even have a notion of a mind, and then, gradually
we said thought and reality is different,
and then, mind body is different. Kant has
come, taken us to a point, which says that
our
interaction with the world is controlled by
our minds, essentially.
..
So, this is what we will do in the next class.
Just to remind you of the goal that
Haugeland that we had said. The goal of AI
is to build the machine with a mind of its
own. So, in the next class, we will come back
to this the cantian view of the mind, and
discuss a little bit more, and may be, wind
up with the introduction in that on next
Wednesday.
.