Today, we are going to shift focus, a little
bit to see, where we are going. Let us just
do a
quick recap of what we have done so far.
.
We started with state space search and then,
we went on to heuristic search and from
there, we went to optimization. The idea was,
that the idea of optimization came in,
because we said that instead of looking for
the goal state, we will try to optimize the
heuristic value of the evaluation function,
or the objective function, as the case maybe.
The idea of using heuristics was to find solutions
faster, because we discovered that
search spaces tend to grow exponentially.
We were looking for a function or some kind
of heuristic knowledge, which comes from the
domain, which will guide the search
towards the solution, and not go off in other
directions, in the hope that we will find
it
faster, essentially, because we do not want
to run into exponential times.
Today, we want to shift focus and look at
the other aspects. So, once you find a solution,
let us say, you are solving problems in some
domain, or let us say it is a logistics domain,
.or you are running a courier company, and
you have to send people all over the place
to
collect parcels and deliver parcels, and things
like that. The solution that you find has
to
be executed, and has an associated cost, essentially.
Today, we will look, we will shift
focus to finding solutions, which have an
optimal or least cost solutions, essentially.
That
is critical in many domains. To take an extreme
example; if 10 years from now, you start
a company in which you are setting up a colony
on Mars, then you can imagine, that the
cost of each trip is going to be significant,
and you would like to have a solution in
which, there are minimum number of trips,
essentially. So, maybe, on the way you stop
on the Moon, or something like that, or more
coming down to Earth. If you are traveling
like a traveling salesman, going through a
few cities; you may want to optimize the cost
of your tour, or if you are using some vehicle,
let say, daily in a city, because of your
job.
Unless you happen to be a politician in the
government or a bureaucrat in the
government, who get apparently unlimited fuel
supplies. You would be worried about
the cost of fuel, and you would want to find
solutions, which are optimal, essentially.
So, our focus is going to be on finding optimal
solutions, now. Of course, one might ask
as to how is this different, from the optimization
that we have been studying so far
because, for example, we said that we want
to solve the TSP, when we were looking at
example of optimization. So, it is not really
different; it is a same process; it is just
that I
want to be clear on the motivation. Earlier,
we went for this process of devising the idea
of a heuristic function, and trying to find
optimal solutions for that, or trying to find
optimum values for the heuristic function.
In the process, we, sort of wondered into
optimization, which is what we interested
in, but we never looked at solutions, which
guarantee optimality. We only looked at randomized
methods like simulated, unhealing
and genetic algorithms, and colony optimization,
which are likely to work most of the
time, but not necessarily guarantee optimal
solutions. So, what we want to do now is to
look at methods, deterministic methods, which
will guarantee optimal solutions.
So, these are the two different aspects of
problem solving; one is, how long do you take
to solve the problem. Heuristic function is
devised to speed up that process. The second
aspect is, how good a solution you find, and
that is the aspect that we are going to focus
on today. How to look at optimal, how to find
optimal solutions? So far, we have not had
a notion of cost, in the solution finding
process and whenever, we spoke about quality
of
a solution, we said the number of steps or
the length of the solution. So, now, let us
.introduce cost, which means we will introduce
a weight for every edge in the search
space and then, we want to find solutions,
which are optimal cost. So, it is like finding
the shortest path, and that is an abstraction
of all these problems that we are looking
at,
essentially; finding shortest path in a graph.
Let us start with a small example graph, just
to illustrate the algorithm set that we are
looking at.
.
So, let us say, this is a start node and then,
you go to some node called A. The cost of
going to that node is 4, or you can go to
B. The cost of going to b is 5 and the cost
of this
edge is, let us say, 3. Then, you have, let
us say, a few more nodes; C, D, E. Let us
give
some cost to these. So, let us say, this is
6 and let us say, this is 8 and let us say,
this is 4
and let us say, this is also, 4. Let us say,
this is an expensive edge, costing 15 and
this is
2. Let us say, this is goal node that you
want to reach, and the cost of going to goal
node
from here, is 2. Let us say, there are some
more edges that I am not drawing, because
we
do not want to have an exploding search space.
Let us say, this is an example, you want
to start from S, and you want to find the
path to G, which is of the shortest paths,
actually.
..
So, the general algorithm that we will follow
can be abstracted as follows; that refines
or
extends the least cost, and I must emphasize
least estimated cost, because we do not
know the actual cost. So, the main problem
solving step, which is basically, very similar
to what we were doing earlier. We have a move
gen function, which generates
successors and you have to choose one of them,
and so on. But, we can view this now, a
little bit more, abstractly, in the sense
that we are working in the space of possible
solutions. We do not have all the solutions;
we have some of them, partially defined,
essentially with every partial solution, we
have an estimated cost. When we say
estimated cost, we mean them; estimation of
the cost of the total solution, if that was
to
be completely refined. So, we will use a term;
refine, to say that if we have a partial
solution, and we had a little bit more information
about that solution.
For example, if you are solving a TSP, if
you have put in five edges, and if you had
one
more sixth edge, then that is a little bit
more refined. So, in the process of you keep
refining partial solutions, till you have
a complete solution and then, you would stop.
The
algorithm that we will use is that; extend
the least estimated cost partial solution,
till such
a solution is fully refined because, in the
end, we are interested in a solution, complete
solution. So, actually, I must clarify what
I mean by this, till such, and we will see
this is,
when the example comes out; that till the
least cost solution is fully refined. I, instead
of
writing that, I have just written; till such
as solution. But, you must read this such
as; a
least cost solution is fully refined. Just
imagine this situation where, you have some
.partial solutions and some, at least one
fully refined solution, or more than one fully
refined solution, and you have estimated cost
for them. Now, for fully refined solutions,
there is no notion of estimate; you actually,
know the actual cost, whereas, only for
partial solution you have to estimate cost.
Now, if one fully refined solution has a lowest
cost, then we will say; we can terminate.
That is going to be the basic idea. We will
discuss this as to, when is this idea sound;
or
when this is idea, guarantee to give you the
shorter solution. This is the loop that in
which we will operate, in the next few classes.
It is just that our notion of partial solution
may change, as you go along little bit. So,
let us look at this from the state space
prospective, as we have done earlier. When
I look at this algorithm, you must keep in
mind, that the similarity with Dijikistra’s
algorithm, essentially. So, I take it that
everybody is familiar with Dijikistra’s
shorter spark algorithm, which takes a single
source and finds shorter spark, to the rest
of the graph, essentially. So, we are in some
sense going to mimic that algorithm, but our
goal is not to find solutions to all the nodes;
but we will be doing something similar, essentially.
.
The algorithm that we are looking at is called
Branch and Bound. By branching, we
mean this process of refinement, or extension,
and by bounding, we mean excluding
some solutions. So, remember what I said that
at the point, which we terminate, we will
not bother about some solutions, which are
not fully refined, because we would be able
.to exclude them, or we would be, they have
gone beyond some bound, that we are
working with, and we do not need to refine
them, any further. So, this general idea is
called Branch and Bound. So, let us first
simulate this algorithm on this graph.
.
So, you start with a search node and it is
very much like the other algorithm that we
have
seen. We generate its children, in this case;
A and B. In this stimulation, we will assume
that we are not going to remove duplicates,
essentially, because it is possible that we
may
later find a shorter path, to a given node,
essentially. So, we do not want to say if
you
have seen that node, do not generate it again,
essentially. So, you can say this is
searching over paths. That instead of saying,
that we are visiting a node, for example,
D
or C, we will say, we are inspecting a path
from source to D or source to E, and we are
looking at different possible paths, and we
will. So, if there is one path S, A, D, then
this
is a different candidate from another path,
which is S, B, D, essentially. So, we will
treat
them as separate. So far, we are saying, if
you have come to D before, do not bother.
You
have already; so, do not put it into open.
That is what you use to say.
Now, the cost of s is 0. The cost of this
path is 4, and the cost of this path is 5,
so the cost
of that edges. The algorithm is simple; refine
or extend the least estimated cost partial
solution. So, instead of saying that, we are
taking the cost of the complete partial solution
and estimate of the complete partial solution.
We will work with the known cost that we
have, which is a cost up to A, essentially.
So, as far as we are concerned, we have two
.partial solutions here; one goes, say, goes
from S to A; the other, say, goes some S to
B.
This one cost 4 and this one cost 5, and we
will say that this is better than S. So, we
do
not have any sense of direction. So, this
is a simple process, we will follow. We say
that
this has been inspected. In Dijikistra’s
algorithm, you would do something, very similar.
I will just do the two algorithms in parallel.
In Dijikistra’s algorithm, you would
initialize S to cost 0, and everything else
to cost infinity, and maybe, in some versions
of
the algorithm, some description of the algorithm,
you will color them white, and you will
color this; or color everything white to start
with, which is like putting them on open,
or
something like that, and pick one node from
there. So, there is a stage of relaxation
in the
rest of the algorithm, which says that once
you relax this node, or once you inspect this
node S, you relax all edges going out of that,
which means this cost originally was
infinity, and now, it is reduced to 4. Because,
we know that you can get from S to A is 4.
So, we revise this cost to 4 and revise this
cost to 5; exactly, what we are doing here,
except that in the Dijikistra’s algorithm,
you would do it on the graph itself. Then,
you
would pick the lowest cost note. So, the Dijikistra’s
would also pick this and color it
black, for example, and then relax these three
edges, which I am also saying, that we will
generate these three edges. So, one simplifying
assumption while drawing, we will make
is, that we are not going to go back; we are
not going to allow loops, because we know
that loops are only going to increase the
cost. So, if I go back, go from S to A and
A to S,
it is not going to help me, in any way. One
assumption, that we are working with like,
the Dijikistra does, that cost are all positive
here. So, pick the least cost node S A. So,
let
us say, this also, I am coloring it black
here. The Dijikistra also would color it black,
and
there would be a pointer pointing back to
this. Then Dijikistra would color this one,
black, and try to; when you relax this edge,
you find that 4 plus 3, 7. So, it remains
like
that, whereas, this becomes 8 this, in arrow,
which comes here, this becomes 19 and an
arrow comes here.
So, there are these costs associated with
nodes, which I am not writing there; which
I am
writing here. From A, you can go to B, or
you can go to D, or you can go to E, and the
costs are, as we said, 19 for this; D is 12
and B is 5. So, very similar to what we were
doing in heuristic search, always pick the
lowest cost node, except that when you are
doing heuristic search, it used to be lowest
heuristic value, note; here, it is the lowest
known partial solution cost. So, this is,
sorry, this is not 5; this is 7. From S from
A to B,
.then if you come like this, it is 7, essentially.
Then, you pick this B and from B, you can
go to C, or you can go to A, or you can go
to D. If you go to C, then you have a cost
of 9.
If you go to A, then you have a cost of 8.
If you go to D, then you have a cost of 11.
So,
this process continues, the rest of the couple
of more rounds and then, we will stop. The
lowest node now is B. So, we do this. As I
said, we will not allow loops. So, we will
not
allow A or B to B, because A or b is in the
path here. So, the only thing you can do is,
go
to C or to D; C D. So, 7 plus 4; this is 11
and 7 plus 6 is 13. So, you can see, we have
found two paths to D; one path costing 11,
which goes from S to B to D, which is cost
11; the other is from S to A to B to D, which
cost 13.
Let us say, there is another edge, which I
have not drawn earlier; forgot to draw earlier.
This is costing 6, 7 units, let us say. Now,
this is, A is the lowest node that I can expand.
From A, I can go to; I cannot go to S; I cannot
go to B; I can go to D or to E, and the cost
of going to D is 16, here, and cost of going
to E is 23, here. I have done away with it.
Now, something interesting is happening that
I am going to expand C. C and D is
interesting, because they are the two nodes,
which lead us to the goal, essentially. So,
at
this point, this node D has become the lowest
cost node. So, this is 9, 16, 23, 11, 12,
13,
and 19. I expand this C and from C, I can
go either to D, along this path, or I can
go to G.
If I go to D from here, it is going to be
9 plus 4, 13. If I go to G from here, it is
going to
be 9 plus 7, 16.
So, I have found one path to the goal. So,
let me highlight that path. I am going from
S to
B, B to C and C to G, and that is the path
represented by this node G here; S to B, B
to C
and B to G. So, this is gone into closed.
So, should I terminate, or if you go back
to what
Dijikistra would have done. What have we done?
We have colored A, we have colored
B, we have colored C, and we have not yet,
colored D, or E. Now, if you look at this
graph, there is a path going from S to B to
D, which is 11 plus 2, 13. Now, that path
is
better than this path, which is of length
16. If I want my algorithm to find the optimal
path, I cannot stop at this stage, which is
why, we have this condition, till such a solution
is fully refined, and such, I mean, the least
cost solution is fully refined. Now, in this
case, the least cost solution is this D and
this C. So, let us say, without loss of generality,
we pick D from here. Once we pick D from here,
we will add this; we have already seen
C. So, from D, you can go to G to C and to
E. So, let us not worry about C and G. The
cost from S to B is 5 and then, another 6
and then, 2 and we have this cost of 13. Now,
.we have added, in some sense to open, if
you want to say; this path S, B, D, G to open,
and we also have another path S, B, C, G to
open, but none of them is at the head of the
queue. Remember, that we will use something
like a priority queue to increment this.
Before we come to this G, we will exhaust
this option of C, we will exhaust this option
of D, and we will exhaust; yes, only these
two options, you have to exhaust. This one,
because this is lower cost, and this is lower
cost; once we expand them or refine them,
we will get more expensive solutions, and
at that point, this G will become the least
cost
and then, we can terminate.
So, this is the idea of Branch and Bound,
essentially; that what do we mean by bound
here? That the moment, when we expand this
node with 13, we are going to bound; we
are not going to be interested in this node
with 19, or this node with 16, or this node
with
16, or this node with 23. Even though, they
are not complete solutions, we know that if
we are to refine them, there cost would be
more than 613 here, and we have found this
complete solution of paths cost 13 and the
partial solution are of higher cost. Therefore,
I
can terminate at this stage. So, at the moment,
when you pick the goal node or the path to
the goal node, you can terminate.
Let us look at another example, which is that
traveling salesman problem, which we are
so interested in, but before I do that, I
want to ask a question, a few. I used a term
estimated cost here, and when I say estimated
cost, I mean the estimated cost of the full
solution; not the partial solution. Here,
we are working only with partial solution.
So,
when you say the cost of this path is 12,
we mean that to go from S to A and A to D
is
12. It is not telling you how much it would
cost through, if you went to the goal, along
with this path. Now, I am talking about that;
that instead of using this exact known cost
of partials solutions, let us work with estimated
cost of full solutions.
Let us say, the estimated cost of any solution
is C, and the actual cost of the same
solution, and by actual cost, I mean, if I
want to refine that solution completely, let
me
use the term; C star. The question that I
want to ask is the mechanism that I used for
estimation; it can do three things. One is,
it can give me a perfect estimate, in which
case,
this would be; I would use an equality sign
C equal to C star, but that is only a wishful
hope, that you will find an estimate, which
is perfect. So, let us hope that, let us say,
that
we cannot find an estimate, which is perfect,
which leaves us two choices; either greater
than or less than. So, we have eliminated
that choice, because we have granted that
we
.will never find such an estimate. Now, if
I had a choice between an estimating function,
which underestimates a cost, and a choice
with a different estimation function, which
over estimates the cost. So, let say C 1 and
C 2 are such functions. Let us say, C 1 is
less
than C star, and C 2 is less than, is greater
than C star; always greater then C star; which
one, should I use? In other words, while devising
an estimating function, what property
should I take care to satisfy? Should I use
C 1 or should I use C 2? How many people
here, feel it is C 2, and how many feel, it
is C 1? The rest are undecided or not awake.
Anyway, just keep this in mind, I will ask
this question in a little while again, essentially.
Now, let us spend a little bit of time on
the travelling salesman problem, again. This
time, we are looking for an exact solution;
even though it is NP hard problem. We want
to look at methods, which will give us exact
solutions. Maybe, we cannot solve very big
problems, but at least, for the smaller problems,
we want that, essentially.
.
We look at something called refinement search.
By refinement search, I mean the
following; that consider the set of all possible
tours, that will be the root node of our
search three, the set of all possible tours,
and then by some operator, I will partition
the
set into smaller sets, essentially. What is
an operator? One operator could be the
choosing an edge, for example. Then, in the
process, I want to refine so, essentially.
I
also want to talk about estimated cost. So,
one thing that while I draw a small example,
you should think about is; given a problem,
which means given a set of cities, and the
cost of edges between those cities; how can
you estimate the cost of a tour? In other
.words, can you find a lower bound of a tour,
or maybe, if you are interested, can you find
a upper bound of a tour; any tour? Or in other
words, all tours are going to be greater
than some lower bound; can we find such a
lower bound? So, let me write a small
example. Let us say, we have these five cities;
Chennai, Bangalore, Hyderabad, Bombay
and Delhi and. So, Chennai, Bangalore, Hyderabad,
Mumbai; I should say, otherwise,
there is always a danger; and Delhi. So, I
need the edge cost between these cities. So,
I
am just drawing the edge matrix to capture
those costs. So, these are 0s; the diagonal
elements, because you are already in that
city. Let us take some simple values. Let
us
say, between Chennai and Bangalore, the cost
is 300 Kilometers; between Chennai and
Hyderabad, it is 600 Kilometers; Chennai and
Mumbai; it is, let us say, 1000 Kilometers,
and Delhi is 2000 Kilometers. These are not
correct figures, but there was a list. So,
given these figures, can you find an estimated
cost? I am asking you a specific question
now; can you find a lower bound on the tour
cost; which means that no tour can be
cheaper than that cost.
Let us put in some more values. Let us say,
Bangalore and Hyderabad, let us say, 500;
Bangalore and Mumbai is, let us say, 900;
and Delhi is the farthest from everything.
So,
let us say, 2100 here, and 1500 here, and
just some random, a close to random figures,
and that leaves me with, between Mumbai and
Hyderabad, let us say, that is 700. So, this
is my matrix given to me; edge cost, and I
want find the solution for the travelling
salesman. My refinement search is going to
do the following; that my root is going to
be
S; I will just call it S, and this is a set
of all tours. What I am asking you is that
for this
node S or route S, which consist of all possible
tours; what would be a cost that I would
want to associate with that, which is the
lowest possible cost that I can think of,
essentially? Now obviously, you can say 0
is a lower bound, because definitely, every
node, every tour will have cost greater than
0, but I am not interested in such a trivial
lower bound. You can even say 300 is a lower
bound, for example, but I am not
interested in that. The reason for that is
that, if I am going to do this Branch and
Bound, I
am interested in excluding candidates from
my search space, and I can only exclude
candidates, if their estimated cost is higher
than my actual cost of some known solutions.
To see an example here, if I want to expand
this known solution, is cost 13, this
estimated cost is 19. Now, this 19 is actually,
the actual cost of going from S to A to E,
but I can be overly optimistic and say, that
is actually, the estimated cost of going to
G
from this path, essentially. The rest of the
edges, I have cost 0; I can be overly optimistic
.about that. So, I can treat this actual cost
of going to E, as estimated cost of going
to G,
via this path, essentially, but even, if that
were to be the case, I know that the estimated
cost is 19, and this actual cost is 13, and
this is only going to increase as I refine
the
solution further.
So, it can never become better than 13. So,
I do not really need to refine that. I am
going
to; that is a bounding, I mean. I am just
not looking at that, this thing. So, for such
reasons, that I should be able to exclude
bad candidates, as quickly as possible, I
need
estimated costs, which are as high as possible.
So, as I said, you can always give me 0 as
an estimated cost, or 300 as an estimated
cost, but I am not interested in that, because
they will not exclude solutions from a search
space, essentially. You were saying
something.
..
. Yes. But I am not interested in higher bounds,
so much. So, let us talk about lower
bounds, essentially.
.Lower shortest four edges.
. Lower shortest four edges; why not five?
..
. Yes, but that would give me what; 300 plus
500, even assuming that I will look at
only the diagonal matrix, I mean, triangular
matrix; 300 plus 500 plus 600 plus 700. That
would, you know, something like that, essentially.
But, all my desire is to get as high an estimate
as possible. So, the general idea is that
I
want as high an estimate as possible, but
it is should be a lower bound, essentially;
these
two things, remember. So, there are, of course,
I know that there are more than one way
of doing it. So, we will just use one method
here, which is that we will take the lowest
two elements from every row, essentially.
So, I will take 300 plus 600 from here. I
will
get 900 from this row. I will take 300 plus
500; I will get 800 from this row. Then, these
two, which will give me 1100 from this row;
7 plus 9 is 1600 from this row, and 12 plus
15, which is 2700 from this row. I will sum
them up and divide the answer by 2.
.What is the rationale behind this; taking
two lowest from every row? Yes. In a tour,
every city will have two edges; one incoming
and one outgoing, if you can distinguish
between them. We are sort of being optimistic
here, and saying that the two edges are the
lowest cost to edges, because they cannot
be better than that. So, if the lowest cost
two
edges are taken from each row and we sum that
up, and divide by 2, because we do not
want 10 edges; we want only 5 edges; we will
get an estimate of the lower bound
essentially. So, we follow this similar, this
high level algorithm, we follow; refine the
cheapest cost partial solution. In this case,
we have only one at this moment. So, we will
refine that, till the solution is fully refined.
Let us say, we use some heuristic and we say,
that we will add a cheap edge to the tour,
essentially. So, the cheap edge here is, for
example; between Chennai and Bangalore.
.
So, I have now, I will just draw it a little
bit this side, because I want to write things
here.
I have two successors. This one, I will call
C B, and the other, I will call C B bar. By
this, I mean, I have portioned the whole set
into two subsets; in one subset, which I call
C B; the Chennai Bangalore segment will always
be present; and in the other subset, it
will always be absent, essentially.
Now, I want estimated cost of these two. So,
for every node, my search three, I need an
estimated cost, exactly like, what is happening
here. Now, you can see that, let me write
it here; C B here, C B bar; let me write here,
and C b here. Now, you can see that C B
.will not change, because I am going to include
this lowest cost edge, I have already done
that in my original estimate. So, whatever
was my original estimate, will continue there,
essentially. In that case, I can just copy
these figures from here, but for C B bar,
I cannot
do that; why? Because I have excluded the
edge C B from that set, essentially. So, I
have
to find revise. I cannot choose 300, because
in this, that node C, this thing; can
somebody tell me the value for this? I think
so, we can use that. Divided by 2? 3550. So,
this cost is 3550, and this cost here, it
will also be 3550. This cost is not going
to be that,
because I cannot use this 300. I have to use
the next two edges, which means 600 and
1000, which means, this will go up by 700.
So, I will write plus 700 here. I cannot use
this here. So, I have to use this. Instead
of 900, it becomes 1600, which is plus 700
here.
Instead of 800, this becomes 1400, which is
plus 600. The rest will not change, because
I
am not using that edge here, essentially.
So, that is 1300, and when I divide by 2,
I will get 650. So, this will be plus 650.
So, I
have a way of devising edges. What have I
done? I have said that; so, this is Chennai,
then, this is Bangalore; this is Hyderabad;
on some scale, this is Mumbai; this is Delhi;
I
have said I am going to add this edge, and
that is my set C B. So, all towards in which,
this segment is there, I will call C B, and
all towards in which, this segment is not
there, I
will call C B prime. Out of these, C B seems
to be better. So, I will refine that. Let
us
say, I follow this heuristic. It is not necessary
to follow this heuristic, but let us say,
we
will follow this heuristic, which means, always
pick the cheapest available edge. It is like
a DD algorithm, which tries to build cheapest
tour, essentially. So, I look around this
graph here, and the cheapest tour, I can find
next is 500, which is between Hyderabad
and Bangalore. So, what am I doing now? I
am saying, add this edge, and I am refining
this graph. So, one side will be called Hyderabad
and Bangalore, and the other side
would be called its compliment. So, the way
to interpret this node is that, this edge
H B
prime node is, that all those tours, which
contain the Bangalore Chennai segment, but
exclude the Hyderabad Bangalore segment, and
the way to interpret this node is, all
those tours, which contain both the Chennai
Bangalore, and the Hyderabad Bangalore
segment, essentially.
So, that is what I have drawn here. All tours,
which have these two edges is this. Now,
let us find an estimate for this. How do I
do this? At this point, I should mention,
before
we do this. This process of computing the
estimates is computationally, intensive
.process, in the sense, you have to spend
some computation time, looking at this matrix
and doing something. But there is also that
you can do a certain amount of reasoning;
something, that we would call constraint propagation,
in the process of doing estimates.
Let me illustrate that. Let us, first of all,
because we have chosen the cheapest edge,
then
for this nod H B, I am anyway going to include
both these. So, it is not going to affect
my cost. So, the cost for H B is not going
to change. You should just convince yourself
that is going to be 3550 also, but this cost
for H B prime; that is going to change. So,
let
us look at the changes, essentially. So, one
thing is, of course, that you cannot use this
Hyderabad Bangalore link, which is; this is
Hyderabad; this is Bangalore. So, this link,
I
cannot use, just as we did first C B prime,
for this nod also, we cannot use this link.
So,
which means now, this will become 300 plus
900, which is 1200. Originally, I had 800,
now it is 1200. So, if you compare with this
as a basis, I get plus 400 here.
Likewise, here, I cannot choose this 500.
So, it becomes 600 plus 700. Originally, it
was
1100; now, it is 1300. So, it is plus 100
here. So, I am just adding the incremental
cost.
Only these two rows will change; plus 200,
but coming back to this, how; see, we have
this desire, and we will see this in the next
class, that having an accurate estimate helps,
or if not in the next class, then, the next
class after that; that the higher the estimate,
the
better for us. Intuitively, it means that
the higher my estimate is, the more likely
it is that
it will get excluded from a search space,
essentially; if I find a cheaper solution.
Now, if
you look at the estimate for this, I have
this Chennai Hyderabad section; Chennai
Hyderabad is this one; this 600, and this
600. Now, if I do a little bit of reasoning,
how
constraint propagation, and what is the constraint
I am propagating is, that I want to find
the complete tour, which means that I cannot
have a cycle, which is smaller than length
5, in this example. I cannot have a cycle
of length C. So, if I am going to have that
set H
B, which includes, actually, it means that
this estimate is not correct, even though,
I
wrote it there. Why is it not correct? Because
I cannot include in my estimate, this
Hyderabad Chennai sector, why, because I have
already included C B in that path, and
then, in this path. So, I am talking of this
node here, and I am saying that even, the
estimate of this node will go up. The reason,
why that will go up is that having included
C B, and have having included H B, I am forced
to exclude H C from there, because
otherwise, I would have a cycle of length
C, which means I cannot use this value for
computing this; for this one; for computing
the estimate of that node, I cannot use this
value, 600. Instead, I will be forced to use
the next value, which is 300 plus 1000, which
.has become 1300, essentially, which is, of
course, more reasoning than what I did so
far.
What I did so far was, if I am including an
edge, I cannot count at, when I am using those
bar kind of node, essentially, because they
are excluded, sorry, if I am excluding an
edge,
then I cannot count them.
But now, we see that there is certain propagation,
which takes place that if I am
including this edge, and if I am including
this edge; I
cannot count this edge. So, let me
just draw a zigzag line to say, that I cannot
count that line. Why, because then, I would
have a cycle. I can go to more extent to do
more reasoning, to get better estimates, and
what do I mean by better estimates? Higher
estimates, which means, if you cannot
include something, then do not include it.
That something, in this example, is 600 here,
which is a low cost in this row, also in this
row, but I cannot use it in my estimates.
So, I
must use something else, which will give me
a higher estimate. Another edge here, that
I
cannot include, after I have included Bangalore
Chennai and Bangalore Hyderabad, there
are two more edges that I cannot add, because
I want a tour, and the tour has this
property; that every city is visited, exactly
once, which implies that every city has
exactly, two edges incident on it. I already
have Bangalore, which has two edges incident
on it in this set. So, I cannot have this
set. Neither, can I have this set.
So, you can see that problem solving is does
not necessarily, one prompt strategy, that
you just do search and only search, essentially.
Later on, we will see that it is often
useful to combine search with reasoning, essentially;
some amount of reasoning and
some amount of search, and in the process
you will try to cut down on the search space,
more and more, essentially. What do we gain
by excluding this? We get more accurate
estimates. For this tour called H B, which
is the set of all tours, which include; now,
we
can describe it more specifically, saying
that H B stands for the set of all tours,
which
include that path here, that C B H, the H
B H and which excludes, H C D B and M C,
essentially. So, already we have narrowed
down our choices and made better estimates.
So, this is the same thing that we were doing
here; refining the least cost partial solution.
We started with 3550 and then, we got two
solutions; one was 3550, and the other one
was a bit more than that. We refine this;
we get these two solutions. We have not
computed the actual cost for this, but once
we do that, we will refine them. At some
point, we will get a complete solution. For
example, in this problem, if you want to add
one more edge, let us say, this edge; Hyderabad
Mumbai. Then, actually, you have
.solved the problem, completely, because then,
after that, you do not have any more
choices left. If you are going to include
these three edges, then you have to visit
Delhi
once. Once you have to visit Delhi from Mumbai,
and once from Chennai. So, the rest
will be four, essentially.
So, after we have done the search, we have
found a complete tour. After we added this
search; below H B, if we add M H, and if this
node M H, which includes these three
edges, happens to be the lowest cost node
in my search space. Then, I can terminate.
That is the shortest path. So, you must convince
yourself, that this termination criterion
is
sound. By that, I mean that it will guarantee
an optimal solution, essentially. One of the
reasons behind that is, that I have said that
we are going to use lower bounding estimates
for estimating the cost of a solution.
You can see that there is some similarity
of Branch and Bound with best first search,
essentially. You can view best first search
as doing Branch and Bound, with the
condition that all edge cost are equal, essentially.
That will force the; if all edge cost are
equal, then you will just go down level by
level, because the first level; the cost is
1, the
second level; the cost is 2, third level;
the cost is 3, and so on and so forth. So,
depth first
search is a special case of Branch and Bound
where, all the edge cost are equal. When
the edge cost are not equal, then Branch and
Bound is a specific specialization of best
first search, sorry, it is a generalization
of Depth first search. So, you have to convince
yourself that this will give you an optimal
solution, but it does not have this. Of course,
I
said we are going to use a heuristic that
uses a minimum cost solution, but it does
not
have a sense of direction, essentially.
..
So, let me illustrate that with a very small
example, that if you are doing this city map
kind of a thing, and if this is your start
node and this is the map that you are looking
at,
and this, let us say, this is to scale, which
means a length of the edge, that I am drawing
is actually, the length of the edge. So, let
us say, you have some such place. You add
this
start node and then, of course, there is one
node here, let us say and then, some nodes
here, and let us say, this happens to be a
goal node. What will Branch and Bound do?
What is the behavior that Branch and Bound
will exhibit? It will explore all this part
of
the graph, because that is what its mandate
is; extend the cheapest partial solution.
All
the cheapest solutions are on this part of
the graph. So, it will explore this; it will
explore
this; it will explore this; and all possible
combinations, which of course, has an
intelligent view or you would see is not a
very bright thing to do, essentially.
It will guarantee eventually, it will find
me the optimal solution. For example, if there
is
another path from here, which goes like this,
which is longer; it will find me the shortest
path, but after doing a lot of unnecessary
and useless search, in this part of the map,
essentially. It does not have a sense of direction.
We are focused on this part, finding
optimal solutions, and in the process, we
have forgotten about this part; finding solutions
faster. So, in the next class, we will combine
these two together. We will see that how we
can combine Branch and Bound with, this was
best first, if you remember; best first
search.
.We will introduce a heuristic function back
again, and try to use this diastase frame
of
working on a graph to look at an algorithm,
which is a very well known algorithm called
A star algorithm. So, I will stop here and
we will take this A star algorithm, up in
the
next class.
.