Today, we want to move on to a different topic,
which is, games.
Now game playing has
fascinated computer scientist ever since,
the beginning of computing time.
Von Newman
was the first person to talk about chess playing
programs, and we have discussed in the
introduction that Alex Bernstein wrote a program
in the early 50’s, and Samuel wrote a
program to play checkers, and so on and so
forth.
Essentially why do we like games?
You can say games, we like, because they have
well defined rules.
If you solve real
problems in the real world, if you want solve
computer vision and natural language
processing, or let us say, TSP, and things
like that; some of the problems, TSP is well
defined, but some of the other problems are
not so well defined, essentially; the real
world problem if you are trying to solve.
Whereas, games have clear cut rules; it tells
you these are the moves you can make and so
on.
Essentially easy to evaluate, it is very
easy to decide; the rules tell you when a
player wins when a player loses.
So, it is easy to judge.
Incidentally, the kinds of games we are talking
about, these are not
.the games which are popular amongst students
where, you are shooting somebody or
killing somebody.
We are talking of simpler games, which are
like chess and checkers,
and so on and so forth, essentially, but the
fact is that games, because of these two
features; they were well defined and easy
to evaluate, or always the good medium for
evaluating your reasoning algorithms or search
algorithms.
Whatever is the technique
that you are using, I mean, not only for us,
but even in the real world, you can imagine
that if you look at our country, you will
find the politicians there children, are
politicians, that is their only merit.
A film star has children, who become film
stars, again, that seems be their only merit.
Whereas, if you look at world of sports, children
of sports men, do not necessarily, make
it begin the world of sports, essentially.
Look at Sunil Gavaskar, one of the greatest
batsman we had, his son Rohan Gavaskar, could
barely, make it to the Indian team,
essentially.
Whereas, is if he might be a politician, he
would have been some big shot by
now, essentially.
That is because games are easy to evaluate
that you do not have bias;
you do not have judgment.
Somebody saying, no, this is not good and
that is good; they
have no such things; either, you win or you
lose, essentially.
.
Now, game playing derives some game theory.
So, what is the name when associated
.with game theory?
Who is credited with inventing this field
of game theory?
Not Mash,
essentially.
Von Newman is the person, we credit with inventing
game theory, and what
do we mean by game theory?
We mean rational choice in a multi agent scenario.
So,
essentially, game theory is the first place
that we have stepped out of a single agent
situation.
So far, the algorithm that we have looked
at, search or whatever else; there was
a single agent, trying to solve a problem,
and you are looking at what are the approaches
solve that problem.
In game theory, we first time, introduce more
than one player, and
therefore, we have to consider the actions
of other players, essentially, and that has
to be
part of listening process that we do, essentially.
.
Now, I wonder if we have heard about this
game called Prisoner's Dilemma.
So, let me
introduce this game to you in more familiar
setting.
Let us say, there are two players as
far as this game is concerned, and I am going
to write the pay offs here.
So, there are two
players.
Let us say, some hypothetical country, obviously,
not our country; there are two
students who have been caught cheating, and
the Dean has put them into separate rooms,
and they are being asked to confess, whether
they have helped each other, cheat or not.
The payoffs are like this.
Let us say, this is you, I mean, you meaning
not personally,
you, but the player for which, you are designing
this game.
Let us say, this is him
whatever, the other person, essentially.
You have two choices; you have to confess
or
.you have to deny, likewise, the other player
has two choices; you have to confess or you
have to deny.
When the game was originally defined, it was
defined in terms of two crooks, who were
locked up in two different rooms, and the
police were trying to interrogate them.
They
had to confess or deny, but the principal
is the same, essentially.
So, what is the payoff
here?
Let us say, these are your choices; confess
or deny.
So, if you confess and if the
other person confesses, let us say, you get
a E grade.
This is symmetric for both.
So, both
people will get E grades.
If both of you deny, then let us say, the
payoff is this; you both
get D grades, because nothing is proved and
something like that.
Now, if you confess,
and the opponent, if you want to call the
person, opponent; denies, and then let us
say,
you get a B grade, and the opponent gets an
F grade, likewise, if you deny, and the
opponent confesses, then you get an F, and
the opponent gets a B grade.
So, the top right
corner is your grade.
The bottom left corner is the other person’s
grade.
These are the
four possible situations; you confess, or
you denied, opponent confesses, or opponent
denied.
You can construct that game, three out of
this; two represent this choice.
Now,
remember that this is the game, which is played
where, you have to decide sitting alone
in the room, and you have been interrogated
by somebody.
You have to either, confess or
you have to deny.
You know the payoff matrix.
Both players know the payoff matrix.
What is the correct strategy to use here?
Game theory is concerned with questions like
this; that if you know the consequences of
your actions, in the context of other people’s
actions, what are the choices that you will
make.
So, in this situation, you think it is good
to confess, or is it good to deny.
Rationally speaking, sorry, you have to speak
a bit
louder; deny is better; why is it?
See; let me explain this matrix, again.
The first, look at the first square here,
on the left
hand side.
It says that you are confessing, and the other
person is also confessing.
You do
not know what is the other person is doing,
but if the other person also confesses, then
you get an E, and other person gets an E.
This square says that if you deny, and the
other
person confesses, then you get an F; that
is your F, stands for fail, and the other
person
gets a B, essentially.
If you confess and he denies, then it is symmetrically,
opposite; you
get an B and gets an F.
If both of you deny, then you get a D each,
essentially what
should be your strategy?
..Confess.
How many people say confess, and how many
say, deny?
So, others, do not have an
opinion.
.If you confess, the other deny it should
be oppose it.
Sorry.
.If you confess and the other deny, it should
be oppose it.
If you confess and the
other deny, the other person should get a
B, because in this case, deny is paired in
both
the cases, irrespective of whatever he says.
Yes.
If you look at the other scenario, let us
say, two people have robbed a bank or something
like that.
I do not know which is the worst; the cheating
in a class, or robbing in a bank;
anyway, let us say, they have robbed the bank,
and then, the police is interrogating that
two people separately.
They say, if you confess, we will let you
off lightly, but the other
guy will get punishment.
So, it is in that sense that you help them,
establish that there
was a crime, essentially.
So, it is in that sense.
That is why, if you confess and the other
person denies, you are let off with a B, but
other person gets an F, essentially.
Otherwise,
if you use deny, and the other person confesses,
it is the other way alone, essentially.
So,
many people said confess; why is confess,
good?
We should give a rational argument.
Game theory is about rational behavior that
what is logically, the correct thing to do,
essentially.
You want to maximize your grade in this case,
or in the case of those
robbers; they want to minimum their punishment,
but the problem are equivalent,
essentially.
.Irrespective of what the other guy does,
it is better for you to confess.
Yes, but either that, let us say, your answer
is correct, but I just do not want the answer;
I
.want an explanation.
.(( )), but if you confess, you will get a
B, and which is better than F.
If other
person is denying, you will get a better grade.
if other person is confessing also.
I will encourage you to draw a small tree
out of it.
So, for example, you confess, deny,
and then, the other person, confesses and
denies, or you can construct it like the other
person confesses and denies, and then, you
confess and deny.
You can construct the three
both ways and then, explore that, essentially.
.Either case, if you take the situation where,
whatever, regardless of what the
other person does, if you say corresponding
row; your choice is between confessing and
denying, because it is between E and F, and
in the other case, it is between B and D.
So,
it is always better to take the choice of
confessing.
Let us argue.
Let us just expand up on the argument and
say, let us say, if you confess
what will happen?
That means, you are looking at this row, essentially.
You are looking
at the first column.
If this person confesses, then you get an
E. If this person denies, then
you get a B, which is, this, so, looking at
this thing is, looking at these three structure;
first, you look at your decision and then,
you look at other two decisions and then,
and
see which one is better.
You will see that in this case, this is better.
In this case, this is
better and this is bad.
If you deny, if the other person confesses,
you get an F, and the
other person denies, you get a D. So, maybe,
this is actually, may be, let us look at the
other side of the argument.
If the other person confesses, what should
you do?
If the
other person confesses; so, you looking at
row, now; we are looking at this tree.
You can
argue this tree also, but let us look at this,
may be, this is simpler.
If the other person
confesses, you are looking at this row.
If you confess, you get an E. If you deny,
you will
get an F.
If the other person confesses, it is better
for you to confess, correct.
You are
looking only at the row.
If the other person denies, and if you confess,
you will get a B.
If you deny, you will get a D.
So, even in this case, it is better for you
to confess.
So, it is better for you to confess in
both cases, essentially.
If you look at, you constructed tree like
this where, you consider
.the other person’s choice as first, then
your choice, and then, you will see that your
choices; this is better, and this is better.
In this case, these two are better, and these
two
are the worst, essentially, but this way,
it is easy to evaluate.
Yes, the actual choice is to
confess, and assuming that the other person
is also rational; other person also confess.
So, your expected grade would be an E, essentially.
This E is called the Nash equilibrium
in this game, which means that if you divide
from this, rather the other person cannot
divide from it, without spoiling the game
from him, essentially.
Such an equilibrium is
called the Nash equilibrium, but is this the
best outcome?
It is not the best outcome in
this particular matrix, because if both of
them are die hard people, I am not saying
that
students can be die hard criminals, but we
are talking about those robbers now.
If both of
them are die hard criminals, like you know,
for example, it is eulogolized in many films
essentially.
So, they are these two criminals, who were
really good guys, but you know, they will
never confess for anything.
Now, if you have two such people, and they
have trust in
each other in some sense; then, they will
both deny.
In this matrix, they will both end up
in this lower right hand corner, which is
the better situation than that situation.
So, this of
course, is called a Pareto Optimal, but it
is not a stable optimal with this problem
situation.
If I want to exchange these grades for these
two corners, this E, E and D, D;
then the Pareto Optimal coincide with the
Nash equilibrium, and then, it is really the
best
solution, essentially.
Why is it called the Nash equilibrium?
Because in some sense, if you confess, and
the opponent is forced to confess, if he does
not confess, he will go off, likewise, if
he confesses, then you are forced to confess,
essentially.
Now, obviously, you cannot get into complicate
or you try to get into
complicated, kind of pleasing that I can figure
out that it is real.
So, this is the basic idea
of game theory, puts you in a situation like
this.
It is a basic mechanism for studying
economics, when people try to evaluate things
like, what should be the pricing
mechanism; you know, how much will you advertise
and things like that; people use
game theoretical concept to reason there,
essentially.
So, rational choice, in the case of
multi agent scenario, essentially.
So, you can think of Price Wars, for example,
as the
game between two players.
So, let us first characterize the games a
little bit.
The kind of
games that we are going to be interested in,
are much simpler in nature.
..
These are called Board games, and as the name
suggests, they are played on a board, like
chess, for example.
In particular, the games that will be interested
in, have this following
characteristic; they are two player games,
which means that there are only two players
in
this game, but there can be multi player games,
may be, will give an example, Zero Sum.
So, we would be interested in games, which
satisfy these (( )); two player, zero sum,
alternate moves, deterministic games.
I might even say, discreet games, in the sense
that
you know things, like chess and so on, where,
you have to choose between the set of
discreet, set of choices, essentially.
So, two player basically, says that there
are two
players, but you can have multi player game,
essentially.
I was just talking about Price
Wars.
If you think of Price Wars as a two player
game, which means, let us say, Pepsi
and Coke are getting into a price war, about
to decreasing prices to get more market
share.
Then, you can think of it as a two player
game, and you can also think of it as a
negative sum game, which means that both the
players as going to lose out on the money
that they get, essentially.
So, a zero sum game is the game, in which,
the sum of the payoffs of different players
is
0.
So, chess for example, one person wins, and
the other person losses.
So, if 0 stands for
a draw, and minus 1 stands for a loss, and
plus 1 stands for a win, then the total sum
is
.always 0, essentially.
One person’s gain is another person’s
loss.
So, these are the game
offers where, you have opponents, essentially,
but there can be games, when there is
negative sum.
So, for example, this game is a negative sum
game, essentially, assuming
that E and D are negative things, which you
do not particularly, like.
The Price War game is a negative sum game,
because the revenue of both the companies
is going to suffer a loss, which is seen as
negative, essentially, but you can also have
positive sum games.
For example, cooperation between people, if
two people sit down
and study together for an exam, then both
of them gains from it, essentially.
So, you can
have different degrees of games.
So, Price War, as I said, can be seen as a
two player
negative sum game, but if you include the
third person, which is the consumer, then
it
becomes the three player game.
Let us say, there is one figurative consumer
and then, it
becomes the zero sum game, because whatever
the company loses, the consumer gains,
in terms of price we are talking here, essentially.
I missed out one very important
characteristic; which is complete information.
In complete information games, each player
knows; what are the moves available to the
other players.
Essentially what are the choices available
to the other players, essentially.
So, obviously, the game that we have been
talking about, like chess and checkers and
Cross and Knots, or Go; all these game called
Othello in which, you are going to do an
assignment.
These are board games on which, you can see
the board.
Both sides can see
the board, and therefore, they are complete
information games, essentially, but there
are
many incomplete information games.
So, games, like car games, for example, games
like
Poker; are incomplete information game, but
there are also games, which are
deterministic versus nondeterministic.
For example, if you have to throw a dies in
a game, game like Backgammon or Ludo, or
something like that, and that is not a deterministic
game where, you cannot predict the
outcome of the move, essentially.
Backgammon, for example, is a two player,
0 sum,
alternate move, and stochastic, incomplete
information game.
The moment the game
becomes stochastic, it becomes incomplete
information, because we do not know what
happens, when you roll a die or when the opponent
rolls a die, essentially.
Of course, in
the real world, many situations where, you
have to do rational decision making.
You are
.mostly operating in an incomplete information
world, essentially.
An extreme example is
two generals, who are fighting a war, essentially.
So, you do not really know what the
other’s army is doing; which side they were
moving.
Of course, we try to have spies on
the other side, and you try to have intelligence,
may be, you take satellite images and all
kinds of stuffs, but that is an effort to
move towards the complete information,
essentially.
But in practice, of course, you have to work
when the information is not complete,
essentially.
Alternate move games are essentially, the
simpler kind of games in which, I
make a move and then, you make a move, then,
I make a move and then, you make a
move, which are easier to model for us, essentially.
Now, the moment I talk of alternate
moves, you can see that we are moving away
from these kinds of games where, there is
only one decision to be made, and you make
one decision.
Here, typically, you have a
sequence of decisions; I make a decision,
then, you make a decision; then, I make a
decision, and things like that, essentially.
So, such games can be represented by a game
tree.
A game tree is a layered tree.
So, let me draw one, and typically, because
we talking
about two person games, there are two kinds
of nodes; one for one player, and one, the
other kind for the other player.
.
.Typically, we draw them differently.
So, this is the route node, which the first
player has
to make a move, and let us say, this is one
move that this player makes, out of the many
possible moves.
Then, the other player makes a move.
Then, the first player makes a
move, again.
Then, the other player makes a move, and so
on.
So, this is the game, which
is a, it is the actual game played, says that
one player made this move, and second player
made this move, and the first player made
this move, and so on.
So, square is one player
and circle is another player, essentially.
Of course, there are many choices that they
all
have.
So, in practice it is a tree or something
like this.
So, such a tree is called a game
tree.
It is a layered tree where, each layer represents
the choice for one player.
This is
some tree, I have drawn randomly.
Traditionally, this player is called max,
and this
player is called min, and you can see that
the tree, basically, represents a sequence
of
choices for both players.
We are assuming that max plays first.
So, max has chosen
within these three moves.
Then, depending on what max chooses, min has
to choose
within two moves, and so on, essentially.
Such a tree is called a game tree.
.
In a game tree, leaves are finished games.
So, leaves represent the end of that game,
and
it has got three kinds of labels.
So, a leaf may be labeled by one of these
three labels;
win, draw or loss; and this word is from max’s
perspective.
When you say win, it means
max has won the game, and if you say loss;
that means, max has lost the game,
.essentially.
This is for max.
Anything that we do is for max, essentially.
So, labels are for
max and so on.
So, we can complex this to W, D and L, essentially.
.
Let us label this arbitrarily.
Let us say this is L this is D.
This is D and this is W. This is
L, W, D, D, L. Every leaf must be labeled.
Every leaf has a label.
So, basically, the game
tree represents all possible games that can
be played; given the rules of that game.
When
we draw the game tree, we do not talk about
rules.
We just say this, a game tree.
You can
imagine that if you want draw a game tree
for chess and white starts first; white has
a set
of moves that white can make, which is 8 plus
8, 16 pond moves plus 4 knight moves.
So, those of you, who know chess, at the top
level, white can make 20 moves,
essentially.
You could just draw the tree and say, forget
about the rules of the game,
essentially.
So, a game tree is basically, a representation
of the rules of the game.
Once we represent
the game in the form of a game tree with,
we can just reason with the game trees,
essentially.
Now, every game has an outcome, which will
be the outcome, if both players
are playing perfectly.
We are always interested in rational choice,
remember.
We do not
want to play against an opponent, who can
make mistakes, and things like that.
We
assume the opponent is perfect, and our analysis
is based on that, essentially.
So, if both
.the players are perfect, then every game
and a game tree is a finite tree, because
it has all
these leaves, essentially; has on outcome,
which can be computed, essentially.
So, just
like, you can think this as a game tree with
only one node, essentially, and its outcome
will be determined by what choice you make,
essentially.
At the same time, this is
simultaneous; this is not alternative move,
essentially.
Both the players are making
moves simultaneously, whereas, the games you
talking about; first max makes a move;
then, min makes a move; then, max makes a
move, like chess, for example, and so on.
.
How do we listening?
The outcome is called the minimax value, is
equal to outcome of
perfect play, one more thing.
By perfect play, we mean that each player
is making the
correct choice, essentially.
Let me ask you, for example, you are familiar
with Knots and
Crosses, right.
This game which children play, or Tic Tac
also, as it is called.
You put
one cross, somebody puts a knot and you put
another cross, and so on and so forth, right;
you are familiar with this game.
So, let me ask you; what is the value of this
game?
What
is minimax value of this game?
It is wrong, right; which means that we everybody
knows
that if we played perfectly, then the game
is withdrawn.
So, how would you compute the
value, minimax value of the game?
Is that we would have a backup rule, we should
back
up value from bottom to top, and the backup
rule will basically, look at the kind of node
that it is; I will not write the rule; I will
just state it here.
So, for min, it means that if you
.can back up L, if another choice is L; then
back up L. If none other choice is L, then,
if
you have D; back up D. Otherwise, you back
up W. You have forced to back up W, in
some sense, because min; the desired outcome
for min is the leaf labeled L, because min
wants to win the game, which means that max
should lose the game.
Therefore, min is
trying to drive the game towards L. So, you
can see what is happening here.
The first
move is made by max.
So, let say max makes this move.
Then, it means, it up to min; so,
min will try to drive the game towards L.
For example, there are some Ls here, but if
min
drives the game here, unfortunately, I have
drawn both of them like this.
So, let us say,
this is L. If min drives the game here, you
can see, max can choose W, and end the game
there.
So, it is better for min to play this move.
If min plays this move, then max will not
choose that, of course, you know, and max
will choose this, and at this stage, min can
win the game.
You can see that if min makes this move, then
min can win the game,
which means, max should not really, make this
move, essentially, because perfect win
will have been here, essentially.
So, this kind of analysis is simplified by
this back up
rule, which says that you back up from leaf
to the routes, and for min, you choose.
.
So, for min, the order of preference is this.
For max, it is this.
It means, min will prefer L
to a D; if it can see L and D, it will take
L, whatever, it will always choose the right
most; max will choose the left most.
So, as we will see, it helps to think of this
as a
.supply chain kind of a thing where, max is
supplying some values to min, and min will
choose.
Min’s choice is always, prefer the L and
then, D, and then, W. Likewise, min is
making offers to max, and max will choose,
and so on, and so forth.
Before I fill up the
tree, let me also say that we can represent
this by 1 or 0, or -1 as well; just a numerical
way of representing this outcome, which of
course, gives us a clue, as to why max is
called max, and min is called min; because
max is driving it towards 1, trying to
maximize the value of the game, and min is
trying to drive it towards 0, sorry, towards
minus 1, and trying to minimize the value
of game.
So, that is why the players are called
max and min.
In terms of numerical value, it is easier
to state the backup rules.
Max
chooses the maximum of the values, available
to it, and min chooses a minimum of the
values, available to it.
What do you mean by available to it?
That, at from the next layer,
what is being supplied to it, essentially.
So, let us fill up this tree.
This is L; this is D; so,
min will choose L here.
.
This is D; this is W; min will choose a D
here.
This is L; this is D; the max will choose
a
D here.
This is, both these are Ds; so, min does not
have a choice.
Here, it is L and so,
there is only one node.
This gets backed up; L. Max will choose W
here, and we analyze
this part of the tree, earlier, right; min
will choose L here; max does not have a choice;
so, max has to choose L here; min will choose
L here; here, max will choose W between
.W and L; min will choose D from this.
So, as a top level, you can see that max has
three
choices.
One of them leads to a node, which will evaluate,
eventually, evaluate to a draw.
This move will eventually, lead to a loss,
and this move will eventually, lead to a draw.
So, max can choose one of those other two
moves, essentially.
Rationally speaking, and
the minimax value of the game is therefore,
D.
So, this is the game, which has a minimax
value of D, essentially.
In some sense, solving
a game amounts to trying to find the minimax
value of the game.
It is called minimax,
because at alternative layers, you are minimizing
and maximizing, essentially.
So, in
some sense, you are trying to distinct.
Another way to put it is that we are trying
to find a
strategy for max.
Obviously, at the first level, we have known
that max should make as
this move or this move, but on what basis,
are you saying that; that basis can be formulas
in the notion of the strategy, and a strategy;
we are talking about max at this movement,
but we can talk similarly, about min; is a
sub tree, which is constructed as follows,
that
one choice for max, and all choices for min.
So, by strategy, we mean that max is
freezing max’s choices is and saying; this
is my strategy; this is how I am going to
play
this game, essentially.
It means that every plays in the game, max
says that this is the choice I will make.
So,
that is why, the strategy is the sub tree
that we construct by making one choice for
max,
and all choices for min.
Why all choices for min, because it is max’s
strategy, and max
does not know what min will play, essentially.
So, max has to account for, or cater to all
of min choices.
So, the strategy must consider all of min's
choices.
So, we can draw a
strategy for max.
One strategy is, let us say this one.
Now, we have chosen this, but for
this, we must choose both; because all choices
for min.
Then, we can have this choice for max, and
let us say this choice for min.
So, this is, the
thick lines represent one strategy for max.
Of course, yes, max has occurs to many
different strategies, and you can say that
the task is to find the best strategy for
max,
essentially.
Let us draw another strategy for max, which
is on this left side of the tree.
So, max could have chosen this move, and then,
of course, you have to choose both these
moves.
Then, max could have chosen, let us say this
move, which is the better move and
then, min would chosen.
So, that is how, we construct the strategy.
At max level, you
.choose all, sorry, at max level, you choose
one choice for max.
At min level, you choose
all choices for max.
What the strategy gives you is the set of
leaves.
Every strategy
has a
set of leaf nodes, which tell you about this.
This is what will happen, if max chooses this
strategy.
So, the question I want to ask you is, given
a strategy; how do we evaluate a
strategy?
Let us work with this one; numerical representation.
Let us say the leaves are labeled with 1,
0 and minus 1.
Given a strategy, S, and I talk
about the value of a strategy; how can I compute
the value of a strategy?
.Worst possible one.
Worst possible one and by that, you mean the
lowest value essentially.
So, if you look at this white strategy, in
this white strategy, the leaves have W, D,
D, L;
four nodes in the leaves.
The worst of them is L or minus 1.
So, that is the value of this
strategy.
If max chooses this strategy, he will end
up losing the game.
If min is perfect,
because the choices that are left, are only
for min, essentially.
If min is a perfect player,
then if max chooses this strategy represented
by this tree, then max will end up losing
the
game, and the value of the strategy is the
lowest value of the leaf nodes, essentially.
If you look at this strategy, then you can
see that there are three leaf nodes here;
D, D,
and W. The worst of them is D, and therefore,
the value of the strategy is D or 0, in this
case.
If you looking at minus 1, 0 and 1, value
of the strategy is 0.
Now, none of them is
a winning strategy.
A winning strategy would be a strategy, whose
value was 1,
essentially.
Ideally, of course, you want to find a winning
strategy for a player, or max,
in this case, because we are writing the program
for max, let say, and somebody else is
handling min, or if you cannot find a winning
strategy, then at least, you should blue one,
essentially.
So, I will leave you with this question here.
Can we think of this as an AND OR tree, and
can we use A0 star algorithm to find an
optimum strategy?
Because you can see that this like an OR choice,
and this is like an
AND choice.
This is like an OR choice, and this is like
an AND choice.
So, can we think
of it as an AND OR tree, and can we use A0
algorithms?
So, I will stop here and in the
.next class, we will take it up from here,
essentially.
.