So, let us for the last time this in this
course look at planning and so as I said in
the mid
nineties, there were a series of approaches
to planning which produce much longer plan,
which means, they were much faster algorithms
and could the solve larger problems.
.
All these approaches were 2 stage approaches
which means you have at we have a
planning problem, you converted into something
else and solve that problem essentially.
So, one thing that was very successful was
that if you converted into a S A T problem
and we already familiar with S A T and then
you could use some solver. In fact, there
was an algorithm called S A T plan which was
very successful in the mid nineties and
early part of this century. So, how do we
know it was a good algorithm?
..
They used to be, there is every 2 years a
competition call I P C international planning
competition, in which people submit their
programs. So, just like you had this travelling
salesman problem competition, in this you
submit your planner and they try it out to
set
up problem and then the planner which was
best is does the to be the winner.
So, S A T plan was one of those planners which
did very well for the period of time, and
what they did was to convert a planning problem
into a satisfiability problem and then
solved it using it so on algorithm because,
but you could solver first, that is
Another approach was to convert a planning
problem into a C S P
problem, which as a name suggests converts
is into a C S P and, by C S P mean constant
satisfaction problem we look at a, at them
briefly in the next 2 lectures and then solve
the
C S P.
So, here posing it has a different problem
and then using some solver, to solve this
is
recurring team in many problem solving situations.
What graph plan does is to convert it
into structure called a planning graph? This
is algorithm we want to look at today and
it
is called graph plan, it was given in 1995
by two researchers called Blum who is now
as
C M U I think in first. So, failed recent
by in contrast to the other algorithm that
you
have seen all those algorithms were quite
old.
.So, as a name, as I, as I said what these
types is it construct a structure called a
planning
graph and then searches in the structure for
a plan. All these 3 algorithms have one thing
in common is that the conversion that they
do in the case of either S A T or C S P or
planning is incremental in nature. So, they
construct a structure of certain size and
then
see if there is a plan there little bit like
D F I D you might say. Keep exploring longer
and
longer plans to see when you can find the
plan and because of that all these algorithms,
end of finding the optimum solutions as well
because they incrementally search for
longer plans.
So, you can imagine that whatever the mechanism
for convert, take it into a S A T
problem, it is a relation between action and
states and new states and new action so on
and you express this as a satisfiability problem.
Things like re condition of this must be
satisfied by the action, by something you
know that kind of some and they always find
shortest answers. So, let us start where looking
at the panning graph structure, the
panning graph is a layered graph with alternate
layers of prepositions and actions
essentially.
So, there is a layer P 0 which is, which contains
all the star prepositions, then there are,
there is a layer A 1, which is a layer of
all possible actions, which can be done at
the first
time instance. But, followed by layer P 1,
which consists of all the prepositions, which
could possibly which you at the, at the end
of the first layer essentially. Now, the
difference between the other algorithms heuristic
search, we just briefly mentioned in the
passing that we know. We could have powers
express search or backward express search
with the heuristic function which was computed
by solving a relax planning problem a to
decide which successor is best.
That search heuristic search or set space
search searches in this set of states plan
space
search that we saw in the last class searches
in the space of plans. Here, we searched in
a
structure called a planning graph which is
some sense are union of all possible states
that
can happen essentially. So, if I have, for
example a start state and I can do action
A 1 to
go to sate S 1 and I can do action A 2, do
to the state S 2, that is what heuristic search
would do, powers express search would do,
it is a should, I go to S 1 or should I go
to S
2, in graph plan what you do is.
..
You have this layer start layer, then you
have first action layer which includes both
this
actions A 1 and A 2 and, then you have layer
which is basically the union or will be S,
right S 1 union S 2. We put together all the
possible predicates into one set which is
in
this next layer or the, so we have this proportion
layers and action layer essentially. So,
one thing with all these algorithms do is
to first convert this problem into a proportional
problem which means, then if I will operator
like a pick up a put down. So, on you look
at what the starting state is what the objects
in the domain are, so that let say I have
blocks A, B, C, D, E, then it will produce
all possible actions.
So, with this 5 blocks pick up a stack A 1
to B, stack A 1 to C, all possible actions
that
produce and work A goes actions. So, I want
to give you a flavor of this, so let us search
work with this, with this same example that
we are looking at the Sussman’s anomaly.
..
Which means we are starting with the state
A C is on A and B is on the table and they
are
on the table, so in the initial layer, in
layer P 0, we would have all these things,
so let say
arm empty then on table B, clear B on table
A on C, A clear C these act these. So, this
is
P 0 while layer P 0, now there are 4 kinds
of edges in the planning of the, first is
preconditions edges which go from an action
to some precondition in the previous layer.
Then effects positive edges, it takes minus
edges and one more set of edges, which is
called Mutex Ulatian.
Now, already familiar with the precondition
edges, the positive effects and the negative
effects we look at work Mutex is in the movement.
So, in the, in the initial layer, we
have this proportion, so it is a proportion
layer 0, P 0 then we have action layer 1 in
which we want to insert all actions which
are possible in this propositions.
We want to put a slight additional constant
that the preconditions of those actions must
be possibly true at the same time if they
are possibly true, at the same time we will
consider such an action. Let us, why this
notion of Mutex relations will come? So, as
he
told with, now this is an often use term some
mutual exclusion essentially, so we will
have this notion of. So, this Mutex relation
is going to be a, these edges are going to
be
inside east layers essentially, so this layer
will have it is own Mutex relations.
.This layer will have Mutex relation, they
are from one action to another, in an action
layer or from one proportion to another in
a, in a proportion layer. If they might exists
between two entities, either two actions of
the propositions it means at, though A cannot
be true at the same time. So, it if there
is a Mutex between A 1 and A 2, it means they
both cannot be done at the same time. So,
as you can see in this example, we have 2
actions unstacks A from A or pick up B and,
we can see that they cannot be done in the
same time because they both required the arm
to be empty and only one can use the arm
essentially.
So, you would have a Mutex relation between
them, likewise they are Mutex relation
between proportions which say that those things
cannot be true at the same time one
thing which happens constantly as we construct
planning. So, we construct the planning
graph from left to right, we keep inserting
actions, then proportion and actions then
proportion and actions then proportion. Till
what time do we do that? Till the time when
the goal propositions appear in a propositions
layer and they are not mutually exclusive.
So, what are the goal propositions that we
are interested in? In our case, we are interested
in on A B and on B C, if these 2 occur in
a proportion layer. In fact, the first time
they
occur in the proportion layer and they are
not Mutex, which means they are not mutually
exclusive as per the planning graph. Then
there is a possibility that we have solved
the
problem so that at that point, the first stage
of the algorithm which is a powered space
and the second stage begin. So, that says,
that this is that actually a plan which will
achieve a both those put goal conditions for
me or not essentially. So, it is a 2 states
problem, you construct a planning a search
for solution, if you cannot extend the
planning graph by more search for a solution
and you keep doing that.
Now, one action which is a uniform action
which we always insert is called a no op and
a
no op has any predicate P as an input and
the same predicate P as an output. So, as
a
name suggest, it says that no operation we
are doing on this predicate. So, we will depict
no ops by these lines like this initially,
but we will not draw them after that because
they
really take up to a space. So, as a effect
of this, in P 1 we will have the same actions
clear
B on table, B arm empty on C A clear C, this
we will do all the type in every layer, we
would always insert no op actions.
.You can see the effect of this no op actions
is going to be that the planning graph is
going to grow monotonically. The sets of propositions
in the proposition layer is going to
grow monotonically because whatever is present
in previous layer will always, we
carried forward to the next layer plus of
course new things may be added essentially.
So,
what are the new things which can be added
in our example? We have the action unstack
no, so it be write here pick up B, so that
I can add to this. Why can I, why can I add
to
this? Because it is preconditions that B is
clear, that B is on the table and arm empty
is
true
maybe I should have written this a little
bit that side we will manage then.
So, this is a first kind of links we have
been edges, we have maintained the precondition
edges then the second kind of edges are positive
effects. So, the effect of pick of B is
holding B, so I have a positive edge from
this to holding B and I have negative edges
to
it is negative effects which is on table B.
So, I have negative edge going from here,
so we
will defect to net, let say we can defect
net negative edge leg this, and for argument
sake
we will urgent that this also becomes falls
at the end of A and arm empty.
So, that is a third kind of edge, so first
kind is precondition edges which go from a
propositions to an action layer and they basically
capture the preconditions that A is
necessary, thus action to be applicable. The
second kind is the positive effects which
are
what would be true in the next layer of proposition,
if there action word to be executed
and in that sense. You can see that no op,
basically say where if the no op action word
to
be executed then on table layer would continue
to be true a. So, this we have been here
on table A was true here and if I do a no
op then on table A will be true in the next
layer
essentially.
That is one more action and one more action
we can add is unstack C from A and you
can see that the preconditions for that is
that arm must be empty, that A must be on
the
table A and C must be clear. So, all these
4 conditions of preconditions for that the
effect
of that is holding C and clear A and the negative
effect is that we have assume that we
will mark this like this. But, that C is no
longer clear C is no longer on A and arm is
no
longer empty, so when do we have Mutex solutions?
That is A. How do we define that
two entries in a layer are Mutex essentially?
So, let us talk of actions first.
..
There are 4 conditions under which action
are Mutex, so we say a 1 and a 2 are Mutex
if
one of these conditions holds. The first is
that P 1 belongs to precondition of a 1 and
p 2
belongs to precondition of a 2 and Mutex P
1, P 2, Mutex P 1, P 2, I mean there is an
edge between P 1 and P 2 which says that they
are Mutex. So, if a 1 requires P 1 as
precondition and a 2 requires P 2 as a precondition,
and the previous layer, thus to mark
as Mutex then those actions convert be done
together. Essentially, 2 effects P belongs
to
effects plus of a 1 and P belongs to effects
minus of a 2, the second condition for two
actions to be Mutex is that there is some
predicate P which is a positive effect of.
So, that is in the layer, remember that this
effect links go from the action layer to the
next
layer and we are trying to decide whether
any 2 actions in the action layer or Mutex
or
not. So, if action a 1 produces P and if action
a 2 deletes P, so that means it is a negative
effects of a 2 then a 1, a 2 are Mutex. They
can never happen the same time because the
semantics of these 2 actions happening in
parallel is not defined essentially. So, graph
line in general, will allow us to develop
parallel plan which means if we are the 2
arms
robot, for example. Then the 2 arms robot
could have simultaneously picked up C from
and picked up B from the table and then something
with them essentially.
.So, parallel actions are in general allowed,
of course we have put both is actions in our
action layer, but we know that, now familiar
with this one arm robot. How it can
operate? That only one of those actions can
happen which means that these actions must
be mark as Mutex somehow essentially. So,
we will see this is not a condition for that,
but one condition is that the one action is
producing something P and the other action
is
deleting P. So, we do not know it both were
to happen together whether P would be true
or P would be false and, if you go to linearise
them then the final effect of those
sequential actions would change depending
on the order essentially.
So, we cannot do that, one condition the third
condition is the P belongs to effects minus
of a 1 and P belongs to precondition a 2.
So, if a, if a predicate P is required by
action a 2
and predicate P is being deleted by action
a 1, then we say that a 1 and a 2 cannot be
parallel. Again, the reason for this is, that
if you got to linearise them then the 2 orders
will not produce the same effects essentially,
for example if you going to do a 1 first then
it would delete P and then it convert to a
2 after that you could do a 2 first and a
afterwards.
But, then you can see that the effect of these
2 out actions is different, we want our
parallel pans to web search that they can
always be linearise to give us a solution
plan.
So, that is one more condition and the fourth
condition is that, so it as draw it like this
is
a 1 produces P and deletes P and if a 2 also
does that, it consumes P and deletes P if
both
of them are consuming something. So, this
remember this dot stands for deleting P, it
is a
negative edge, it saying that P is a condition
for a 1 and not P is a effect of a 1, this
is
also saying that P is condition of a 2 and
not P is an effect for.
So, if both the actions, so it have something,
you have consuming I mean there only 1
cake and there are 2 people, so only one of
them eat essentially. So, both cannot be put
into the running after saying a is eating
the cake and b is eating the cake. In our
example
you can see that there is a negative edge
from to arm empty from pick up b that this
is
going to delete arm empty and this is also
going to delete arm empty both are consuming
arm empty. So, this fourth case applies to
this and we mark Mutex edge between this and
this we can also say it that this no op is
Mutex would pick up b because it no op is
producing clear b and this pick up b is deleting
clear b.
.So, the a, second clouds which say that one
of them is producing it and other one is
deleting it and these 2 actions cannot happen
in parallels. So, we have to, so as you can
imagine there would be many Mutex suggest
between a actions a, that we will have to.
So, one Mutex edge that we have is between
this and this, another Mutex edge is
between these two, and there are others, of
course that you can find, so that takes care
of
the action layer.
.
Then Mutex relation between proposition P
and P 2 are Mutex, so P 1 and P 2 are
proportions in the same layer. Obviously,
Mutex relations are always within the layer
if
there is, I will just write a wrong explanation
that we see what to write, what we want to
say is that P 1 and P 2 are Mutex. If all
ways that P 1 can be produce and all way is
Mutex with all ways that P 2 can be produce,
and by this mean any action with produces
P 2, if Mutex with every other action with
produces P 2 essentially.
If there is a no actions a 1 and a 2 in the
presiding layer such that P 1 belongs to effects
a
P 2 belongs to
of a with 2 and, in other words if we can
find 2 actions a 1 and a 2 which
are not Mutex and a 1 is producing P 1 and
a 2 producing P 2. Then we can say P 1 P 2
are not Mutex essentially, but if you cannot
find, so in there are no actions, a 1 and
a 2 is
satisfy this condition then we say that they
are Mutex essentially.
.So, let us solve, try to construct this example
from here, so the first thing you will
observe is that in this layer a 2. So, a 2
is a superset of a 1 everything which is there
in a
1 will always be there in a 2, why because
we are just no op operations which a carrying
forward everything which was here, which made
this, all these action possible. We are
being carried forward here and, therefore
there will be possible, so apart from this
pick
up b unstack c from a and so on. So, for example
it is always possible for me to say that
my first action is to do nothing, for some
strange reason that I will do a no op.
If I do a no op then I can always do a pick
up b after that essentially or I can always
do a
unstack c a, after that which means these
2 actions must come in my layer, so everything
which is there in a 1 plus something new.
What are the new things we can have? So, we
can see, so I am not going to write all these
again here ideally you should copy it here,
but now it is a bit of work. So, I will just
write this as a 1 plus the following that
you
have holding b, you can do something with
b.
.
You can stack B on to C, why because you know
all the conditions are there if you are
picked up B, then you are holding B and then
C is clear because no op, we will make it
clear in that, is that is about what you need.
.So, we can stack B on to C, or you can stack
B on to, no you can put down B these are
two extra actions that I will add to my, likewise
for this one holding see I will add stack
C on to A, stack C on to B putdown C. So,
I have the same A 1 set of actions and
remember all these no ops are always there
for every predicate in my act proposition
layer any proposition that proposition layer
there is a no op action which takes it power
to the next layer.
So, that is always part of the graph plus
anything new that I can add essentially the
only
condition, I need for adding an action is
that it is preconditions must be available
in a
non Mutex fashion essentially. So, again to
repeat you want stack, you want to see what
do I need, I need holding B, of course I need
clear C and that is what it is. So, of course
it
will have its effects, it will say arm empty
not clear C and not holding B and so on
essentially. So, in this process, I construct
the planning a layer by layer, at every layer
I
have to find what are the Mutex and put them
in.
As you can observe the planning op is going
monotonically essentially it is start with
these propositions then it expands and because
whenever a proportion gets into the
planning of a no op will take it to the next
layer, only new ones will be added. So, for
example A on a stack B on C, one thing that
gets on B C plus of course all these P, so
it
is growing monotonically, it is also. Can
we show in? It is going as a polynomial of
the
original problem size and general, the size
of the planning of grows increases polynomial
essentially.
So, that is a first space of graph land you
construct the panning graph. So, till what
stage? The stage 1, they are 2 possibilities
that either you have reach the stage in which
a
plan may exists. So, let say we have 2 arm
robot for arguments, say we can pick up C
in
and pick and pick up and pick up the unstack
C A and pick up B in as action 1, then at
the second layer we can put down C and also
no.
So, let say in the first layer, you unstack
C A and in the second layer you put down C
and
pick up A at the same time. In the third layer,
you pick up B and the fourth layer, you
stack B on to C and fifth layer you stack
A on to B. So, you can get a 5 step solution
if
you had A 2 arm robot.
.We know that for A 1 arm robot, as you on
a last class there is a 6 steps solution,
so the
stage when ends if one all goal predicates
of propositions exists in a layer non Mutex
if
you can find all the goal proposition. What
were the goal proportions to interest in on
B
on A B and on B C? If they happen be in A,
in a proposition layer and they are non
Mutex, then we stop this forward planning
graph construction exercise and we go to a
backward search.
So, typically you could do something like
depths first here remember that the problem
is
still in hard, but you could use other method,
so for example people have try to
understand satisfaction methods and so on.
What are we looking for? We are looking for,
so at some stage, so let me write that, those
things here on B A and, I can write them here
on B A and, sorry on A B and on B C, I am
looking for these propositions. So, if they
occur in some layer and they are not some
let us say P n and they are not Mutex then
I
start a backward search face and say. Can
I find all the sub goals of this, in the previous
layer in the non Mutex fact fashion?
Now, hobbies these have positive links coming
from actions and those positive links
could be in the final solution that we have
going to construct. What are these positive
links going to be? What are the two actions
will produce this stack? But, are they non
Mutex? I am looking for non Mutex actually,
so I need to do this backward search
looking for non Mutex actions with non Mutex
preconditions. So, as you can guess this
is a no op action essentially, so in a previous
layer if I have stack, and I am I am saying
that because I know where the solution is
a last action must be stack A on B.
But, essentially what they, I will go to them
in neat will lead to do is to search, so from
this goal set find an action set which assumes
goal sets which is non Mutex. So, stack A
on B and stack B on C will be Mutex because
both are them, so stack A on B makes B, A
makes B not clear and this needs or something
like that. So, something will come and
they will be Mutex essentially, I need a goal
set here and then an action set here. Then
a
goal set come, A here sub goals and then actions
and then sub goals and then actions till I
come to the initial layer and nowhere do a
encounter a Mutex solution.
.If that is a case, then found up line, imagine
as you can imagine this will be found only
in
the 6 layer, for this particular problem because
A we know by now that it need 6 actions.
But, in the sixth layer, we will find this
stack A B Mutex with nothing and its condition
will be Mutex, will be not Mutex, A envelop
them will be holding A and clear B and on
B C already the here and, so essentially will
be able to find a path back. So, this
backward space is a search space which will
try to solve every goal set with sub goal
set
with another sub goal set right up to the
start set in a non Mutex fashion.
So, do this, of course it, let it do some
it try this sub goal set another sub goal
set could
be just 2 actions, for example you can see
that that it may try. But, of course it will
not
find a solutions because for 2 no op action
to be happen in parallel this must need 7
steps, we know we need this 6 steps anywhere.
But, it could try this it could try this
combinations or it could try this combinations
or it could try com third combination we
will do some kind of the search and typically
the original graph and algorithm which in
the albumin first backward space was depth
first search.
So, in the forward space, you go all goal
proportions like this in the layer non Mutex,
you do backward search, if it fails then you
extend the graph by one more layer and do
the same thing again. Now, notice that when
you extend the graph by one more layer,
you will still get those things non Mutex
or you mean, you need to convinced about this
that once a goal set is non Mutex, it will
remain non Mutex in the next layer also. But,
it
is possible that some sub goal may not the
Mutex some sub goal may be Mutex which is
why we need to extend the planning a further
and further essentially.
So, there are 2 cases, one is that a pan exists
in which case stage 1 ends when all goal
proportions are found then the backward space
begins else. So, I will just, else meaning
we are not found the plan extend panning graph
and you keep doing this extend planning
graph search for a plan, extend the planning
graph, search for a plan. So, you can
imagine that because we are doing that, if
you find the plan it will be shortest possible
plan essentially, the other situation is no
plan exists or this is the little bit trickles
see. So,
I do not think we will have the time to go
into details to stretch out the conditions
when
the algorithm should say that no plan exists,
but the general idea is as follows.
.So, what is happening in this in this planning
graph extension stage that more
proportions a being added, so more and more
things will come in to play as non Mutex.
So, initially for example you might say pick
up B is possible, unstack C from a possible
and then because we all, we already have clear
C somewhere. You can say after B you
can stack C on stack B on to C and because
we have unstack C from we can pick up A in
the next you can and so on.
So, it might be that you might see the proportions
appear in the proportion layer, but they
may not be Mutex, at some point they will
be Mutex and then you will search for in a
backward space. You will find that at some
layer some preceding layer they become
Mutex and then you cannot complete backward
space search all way all the way to the
start set. So, you find that their Mutex for
you, if you have tried all possible
combinations and at some layer and they are
Mutex, then we extend the planning graph
to let say it was that layer T, and then extend
it to layer T plus one and then we come
back and search.
So, what Blamen first showed was this condition,
if the sub goal set that you are trying to
solve the main constant when you extend from
planning. What is the sub goal set? Sub
goal set is the set of sub goals where each
sub goal is the set that you want, so for
example for on A B on B C, they will have
the sub goals as we want to do stack on B
holding A clear B and on B C. These three
actions would be in the sub goal set, this
action will have different actions at the
sub goal set, some other actions will have
different actions in the sub goal set.
So, we have a set sub goals set of sub goal
sets, if the set of sub goal sets does not
change
as you go from layer T layer, T plus 1 as
you extend the planning graph from layer T
to
layer T plus 1 then we can terminate best
in it. There is no plan or to get some intuitive
feeling behind this, what happens is that
as we construct the planning graph first the
set
of propositions stabilize that no more propositions
added to the set. We added everything
possible essentially and then the set of Mutex
relations stabilize, it means at no more
Mutex relations are added.
But, even then you have to be a bit careful
that you can extend it by one more layer and
.you might still find and what Blamen, first
this is straightly complete condition which
says that if extend the planning graph from
layer T to T plus 1. The sub goal set at some
intermediate layer n remains constant, then
n you can be sure that you will never because
if you are not be. If B able to add a new
sub goals, at when you move from T to T plus
you can never add anymore because a set rule
set up propositions as stabilized set up set
up Mutex is stabilized.
So, there is nothing more you can do after
that it takes a bit of a time to figure this,
so
it
is summarize a graph plan algorithm works
in 2 stages. In the power stage construct
a
planning graph which contains is 4 kinds of
edges A, the precondition edges, the positive
effects negative effects and Mutex relations.
Once it finds all the goal properties, it
exists
in a non Mutex form in a layer it goes to
the backward space tries to search for a non
Mutex substructure in the planning graph where
they are no Mutex relations which
means that those actions are possible even
if they are in parallel.
If it cannot find, it goes back and extends
the planning graph by one more layer, again
goes it will the backward space and keep doing
that. So, still at some point either it finds
a solution or this criteria which we described
somewhat briefly is met where it says that
no plan can be found essentially. So, the
planning graph gives as a optimal plan in
terms
of the most the shortest times span or the
shortest number of the steps in which parallel
solutions can be found if there is a parallels
solution.
So, of course keep in mind that domain that
we are talking about has no parallel solutions
because it has single arm robot. But, many
domains may have parallel solutions and what
graph plan does give us is the shortest time
in which a parallel solution can be found
and
we can of course always linearise that by
putting all the actions in any layer can be
linearise in any. What it gives us is the
set of actions at layer 1, set of actions
in layer 2,
set of actions in layer 3 which is the parallel
shortest possible planning. So, it is an
optimal algorithm and it gives to the shortest
plan and it can solve must larger problems
than the earlier I will go to essentially.
So, I think I will stop here with planning
we do not have time to go into the other
algorithms. So, what you will do in the next
couple of lecture is get a flavor of constant
.satisfaction problems which is actually a
very big area in computer science in a that
there
are people who work, try to pose everything
as a C S P and there is a huge amount of
activity writing solve us for constraint satisfaction.
So, what we will do is, we will just
get a flavor of how to pose a problem as a
constraint satisfaction problem. What is the
constant satisfaction problem? What are the
basic ideas of? What are the algorithms at
we use for solving it?
The interesting thing about studying C S P
constraint satisfaction problems is that it
gives us a opportunity to combine search with
reasoning essentially know that you can
do some amount of search. But, you can contain
the search while doing some amount of
reasoning and constant satisfaction problems
give us a national way of doing that
essentially. We will try to get a flavor of
that in the next few lecturers essentially,
and
then we will move on to representation proper
with login essentially. We will stop here.
.