So, let us begin we continue our study of
state space search and what we have just seen
is
that the size of the state space can be significantly
large even for a small toys that we talk
about. So, in Rubik’s cube we saw where
the branching factor is eighteen if you want
to
search up to depth 20, then you have to search
about 10 based to 25 node essentially
even at smaller puzzle which is the 8 puzzle
and the 15 puzzle. If you look at the 15
puzzle where the branching factor is capped
by 4, you can only move within one of four
directions, it is about 10 raised to 13 states
and the 24 puzzle is about 10 raised to 24
states.
So, even that small puzzles that you get can
generate huge state space essentially and
we
have seen the 10 based to 24 states is not
a number that you can slip that essentially
it
will take you huge amounts of time. So, what
is happening essentially is that the
algorithm that we have seen so far is blind.
Essentially, that gives some state space given
some start state, what is what this algorithm
is doing with the goal that you want to
achieve. It is using it only to test whether
given state is goal state or not it is not
using it
.to guide at search in any manner at all depth
first search as we said goes often some
direction.
Then, it back tracks and tries other direction
irrespective of where the goal state is
breadth first search always circles around
the star states and it will gradually expand,
it
search frontier to move away essentially.
The goal step no role to play here essentially
the next step that we would like to do is
to somehow exploit what we know about the
goal state to help guide the search. So, let
us assume that this was a city map essentially
and let us say this s stands for IIT and you
have to go someplace essentially. So, let
us
say this is a goal state somewhere, so if
you are consistent with the geography of
Chennai, then this g could be may be Marina
beach or something like that somewhere in
the north east.
If you want to go of IIT to marina beach and
you of course have to follow the roads the
every junction is a node and every road segment
is an edge essentially, so in some sense
being at a junction is a state, so you are
you are at IIT. So, you are at this state
you want
to be somewhere and here is the Gandhi statue
in Marina beach that is a different state
and you can move across the road to move to
a different junction which is a different
states and so on. Now, imagine what these
two algorithms are doing they just go of in
the
predetermine manner essentially and eventually
of course if somebody tells them we
have reached Marina beach they will say I
am done.
Essentially, what you really want what we
really want is an algorithm which would
somehow head in this direction somehow you
know what do you mean by this? What we
mean by this is that given a state given a
start state and given a set of successors
instead
of choosing in a predetermine fashion, which
successors to inspect or expand as a term
we use next. Let us try to get some exploit
whatever knowledge we can of the domain to
help guide the search essentially.
..
So, that is called as heuristic search, so
the word heuristic comes from the word I mean
with their various routes that I have read
about, so Eurisko or Heuriskein and so on.
All
these are sort of Greek words of Greek origin
and you might remember a word which is
also related to Eurisko which is called eureka
you know this story of argument is running
naked through the streets saying eureka and
so on essentially. So, what is eureka
meaning it means that I have found it, I have
discovered it, essentially and this whole
idea of Eurisko heuristics is based on this
knowing something essentially, so how can
we
get heuristic?
So, let me first discus how this heuristic
knowledge would be used essentially, so we
will
assume that we have another function called
h of n which will take a node or a state and
give a value which is a measure in some sense.
How easy is it to go from that state to the
goal state, essentially so supposing we had
such a function. So, the theoretical
community would say we have an oracle, it
tells you what is the complexity of going
from this you know or it tells you which if
somebody could tell you that of these
successors.
In general, given open list which one to pick
next then it would help it would be helpful
essentially that because then they would just
tell you if you go ahead if you go ahead if
you go ahead you will reach the goal state
essentially. So, first let us get this out
of the
way this mechanism of how we are going to
exploit the heuristic function.
..
So, if you look at this algorithm that we
have the same framework, we will follow open
is initially made of this pair start. So,
it should really be list of list essentially
and then
extract the first one extract the node all
that is the same and we at some point generate
new the set that we have of new nodes that
we want to add to open, what we will do now
at least conceptually is that. So, remember
that so far we said that we can either add
new
at the head of the tail of open or the remaining
part of open or at the end of the tail of
open if it was at the head of open, it was
like stack if it was tail of open, it was
like a
queue.
Now, we are saying is that something like
this sort on happened new, so if I say append
new tail of open that part is like depth first
search essentially that new is added at the
assuming append. That is what append does
it sort of take this list and concatenate
with
this list putting them at this towards the
head it is like that this thing. Now, I am
saying
after you are appended the two list sort them
on the h value what is h value h value is
this
value of this heuristic function of the node
essentially.
This means what simply that the best h value
will come the head of the list we are still
talking about it is the list and this same
algorithm will pick it from the head of the
list
and then this thing. So, if we have such heuristic
knowledge we can exploit it by simply
modifying our algorithm to keep open as a
sorted list. So, that when we remove the head
element we always get the best element what
do we mean by best? By best we mean best
.according to what the heuristic function
believes or what the heuristic function thinks
essentially only as far as that essentially.
If we have a heuristic function then we can,
this is called a heuristic function is should
write it right, it returns a number which
is a measure of how easy or hard it is to
go solve
the state from there essentially. So, this
is the only chain we would need to make in
our
algorithm that we have to sort the open list
every time we add new elements essentially.
Now, obviously the data structure person inside
you must be rebelling against this idea
sorting this list again and again and again
because sorting is expensive. So, you could
you could do a other thing you could do for
example, merge then sort new this tail open
yeah that is a first thing one think.
So, this is not needed that because the number
of new elements is going to be small and
the rest of the tail is anyway sorted. So,
just sort the new elements again an h of course,
and then merge it with the tail open of course,
which is a little bit better in terms of
computational work, but that obviously is
not the last word on this. So, just like we
said
that to make efficient use of close you must
maintain it as table what about this open
now
how do we efficiently implement open. So,
of course, that efficiency will only be from
the computational point of view as far as
the task is concerned of choosing the next
successor.
It does not matter in what manner we manage
to sort it how much time is spend sorting
it
essentially, but if you what if you were concern
about that how should you manage open
at the risk of turning this into a data sectors
class we will spend one minute here.
Student: Sir, we have to maintain it.
So, you must maintain open as a priority queue
of course, there are many different
mechanisms to implement priority queues we
will not go into that we will just make this
observation that you must somehow implement
open efficiently. So, what is really
happening just imagine this that we have this
tail of open this, tail of open is like a
big.
Let us say it is sorted list or something
like that and then we have this new which
is a
smaller list essentially. So, this is already
sorted and we have get this we have got this
new elements and we have to sort of insert
them into in the right place inside this sorted
list. The best way to do it is by a priority
queue one way to implement the priority queue
.is use heaps, but there are other ways of
doing it. So, you must if we are implementing
heuristic search it is very important that
you pay attention to how you manage open
because that is going to affect your running
time essentially things become a little bit
more complicated.
When you remember that you also wanted to
remove from the new list those things
which are already on open essentially which
is not for which the priority queue is not
really the best we have doing things. So,
I will leave this as a small exercise for
you to as
the data structure exercise you might say
you want to do both these task you want to
check for membership in open. That is a new
node already present in open, which is
based on by a hash table you also want to
maintain open. So, always the best nodes will
be at the head of open which is what a priority
queue does.
How can you do both, can you do both in and
if yes how it will be, but it is not our
primary concern here our primary concern is
to look at how heuristic search happens.
This is basically what is happening essentially,
now let us pay attention to the heuristic
function itself how we get this heuristic
function.
.
So, one thing that one can do is which part
of operational zing is this whole process
is at
the search node which was originally a pair
which has the current node the parent node.
Now, we want to convert it into a triple,
so it will become current parent and that
is the
call it h value for that node essentially.
So, we want to also store that h value out
of node
.which means what that every time we generate
a new node we will need to compute the
h value. Let us say this is the n, n is some
node and you want every time we generate a
node n we want to compute the h value for
that node.
Now, of course, you must keep in mind that
this h value is not just the property of that
node it is also dependent upon the goal node
essentially for different goal nodes. The
same node may have a different h value, but
we are sort of losing over that here little
bit
essentially, so how do we how do we generate
these heuristic functions?
.
So, there are two approaches to this one is
domain dependent
or static, so by static we
mean that it only look as this current node
and may be it looks as a goal node in some
manner, obviously it will have to do that
and gives us a value back essentially. So,
let us
take an example or couple of examples let
us say this is a city map like we said that
is
this is IIT and that is Marina beach and so
on and so forth. How can we give heuristic
values to this node essentially, so the simplest
thing is h of n, so city in a city map
problem route finding problems. So, now, a
days of course, we have all these algorithms
which do route finding for you have to go
from one place to another you must think
about how they do this we can say h of n.
So, let us assume that the goal node is given
to us, so what can we expect in the city map
we can expect to get coordinates essentially.
So, start state is from x start and y start
in
the two dimensional map and goal state is
some x goal and y goal if the coordinates
are
.given to you and that you can that is reasonable
to expect that the coordinates may be
available in such a situation. How can we
exploit this? How can we sort of get this?
So
we say for each node or each location in the
map we compute the distance to the goal
node and that is the estimate of heuristic
that we will use.
So, one is Euclidean distance
and that is a good estimate of, so how are
you going to use
this Euclidean distance we are going to say
these are the different places that we can
go
to. So, remember that in a city map situation
we are moving from one generation to the
next that once you on a road you have to go
to the next you have to go to next junction
which has these nodes here. So, essentially
you compute this distance for each of these
n
nodes each of this successor and in general
for every node in open. To start with, this
is
only open that we have and then choose the
one which has which seems to be closes to
the goal essentially now this is the heuristic.
So, when we say heuristic we also use a term
rule of thumb and if you go to the
psychology today website they will say that
it is a mental shortcut heuristic is a mental
shortcut which we use to solve problems quickly.
So, the emphasis the word quickly we
are trying to fight this common neutral explosion
and trying to use some knowledge in
this case from the domain to guide our search.
So, when you are using a domain
dependent heuristic function we have now three
domain function one is the move gen
function that we already talked about and
one is the goal test function.
The third is now the heuristic function which
means that if you are going to now create
a
new domain you must write the program which
will compute h of n. So, that is the search
algorithm can exploit that is why the search
algorithm goes it only uses that h value to
sort or maintain a sorted list or maintain
a priority queue of the candidates essentially.
The domain must now tell us what the h value
is we will in the moment we will try to see
whether is this can be done in a domain independent
fashion at all because you see this
whole idea that we are trying to pursue is
to write this algorithms in a domain
independent fashion.
We want to write these search algorithms without
saying that I want to solve the city
route finding problem or a Rubik’s cube
or a Robert movement problem or a factory
scheduling problem. It does not care you have
to find some general purpose algorithm
and we would like to plug-in domains and just
use those algorithms essentially.
.Yesterday there was a talk about this mars
Robert yes anybody attend, so this NASA,
you know they had this mars Roberts. They
used a lot of this kind of planning algorithms
for finding paths for this and move because
it is not just the path for the Robert to
follow
also what are the movements that.
For example, a robot arm must do if you have
to pick up something from the ground, let
us say piece of rock from the ground or something
every move have to be has to be
planned carefully and there we use the lot
of these techniques. So, heuristic function
of
course, if the heuristic function is perfect
which means it is like an oracle what the
theoretical computer scientist would say.
Then, it will just tell you which is the correct
thing and then of course, you would find the
solution in linear time essentially, you just
go from along the path essentially, but in
practice of course, it is not, so easy to
find
heuristic function.
.
What is the other function that one can talk
about, so another function that we use
sometime is simply this x s minus x g, so
what is this doing instead of measuring. So,
the
Euclidean distance is telling you the distance
as we say as this is telling you a difference
between the x coordinates and the difference
between the y coordinates. What is the
name of this distance function Manhattan function
Manhattan distance
also called a city
block distance essentially if you have a nicely
laid out city like Manhattan, then you
know it is like on a grid then you can only
go along the roads on the grid.
.That distance that you cover would be basically
this that if you know if you had if a grid
on a grid you can only move along the x direction
or on the y direction and then other
distance measures that one can think of.
For example, one could take the max of this
or max of this or max of this and this only
and choose that or there are other something
called Murkowski norm which we will not
get into here. So, essentially what are we
trying to do we are trying to devise a domain
function which takes two inputs one is the
node given node and the other is the goal
node
which we assume the during the ten year of
the search is constant. So, we are not
mentioning it here, but it is there somewhere
in the background and it returns a value to
us which gives some idea of how close one
is to the goal node essentially.
So, in this context we can say a heuristic
function is an estimate of the distance to
the
goal essentially. So, we are using the term
distance explicitly here in this case essentially
in general it is an estimate of how hard it
is to solve a problem from the given state.
By
hard, we mean typically the number of moves
that you want to make and later on when
we see when we add cost to each move. So,
for example, in the road we might add the
length of a road all the conjunction on the
road as a cost or something that we will come
to that later. So far, our idea of optimal
solution is simply to have a smallest number
of
moves essentially.
.
.Let us look at another example which is this
eight or fifteen puzzle, so let us say this
is
my given state
and I have or let me choose one with three
successors, so I have three
successors from here one is that I can move
this two down. So, I will get 4, 8, 2, 6,
7, 3,
1, 5 or I can get, I can move 6 this side,
so 2, 4, 8, 6, 7, 3, 1, 5 or I can move 3
up. So, I
have these three successors which i can make
from here and I have to decide which one
of them to choose so obviously I need a goal
state. So, let me
say that we have some goal
state which looks like this and so let us
say any state can be a goal state. So, let
us say
this is a goal state and we want to somehow
arrange the tail, so we reach that state
essentially how can we talk about heuristic
functions can you think of heuristic function.
Now, what is the heuristic function or static
heuristic function, so let us say we are
talking about this state this middle state
where we have moved 6 to the left hand side
is
this move that we should make? So, that is
the question we are asking should we make
this move or this move or this move essentially.
So, we want to four each of this we want
to compute the h value as it is called are
the heuristic value which basically should
look
at this only. That gives us a number and let
us say we were adopt the convention that the
smaller the number the better for us essentially
we going with the sense of distance or
notion of distance the smaller the distance
the better can you think of a heuristic
function.
So, one function is let us calling it h 1
of n is equal to sum of the distance for each
tile
distance to goal. So, when I say distance
to goal I mean the distance to the goal position
no suggest keep in mind and what do we mean
by distance here. Let us assume that we
mean the Manhattan distance because this is
the problem where actually distance is has
to be it makes sense use manhattans because
you can only move horizontally or
vertically. So, what would be the heuristic
value of this state for this state we look
at two
is here and two is there.
So, I will add one for two then four is here
and four is there, so I need two steps to
get to
that. So, 2 plus for 8, I need 1, 2, 3 steps
for 6, I need 1, 2, 2 steps for 7, I need
1, 2, 3
steps for 3, I need to move 1, 2, 3, 4 steps
or one I need to move 1, 2, 3 steps and plus
for
5 I need to move 0 steps. So, basically the
sum of all these numbers, so let me remove
them, it is confusing here, so I have all
these numbers and basically the sum of all
these
numbers is the heuristic value for this state
essentially. So, if we added up you will get
a
heuristic value likewise, you do for this
and likewise you do for that and you would
have
.some way of making a guess which one is better.
Can you think of any other heuristic
function? It can be simpler than this, number
of misplaced tiles.
That is another, so in this case h 2 of n,
you simply count how many tiles are out of
place
essentially. So, you can say in this situation
five is in place and nothing else is in place
or
if you want to count the blank tile as well
then you can says the blank tile is in its
place,
but that will anyway add up to something essentially.
So, it is a simpler measure
essentially it is easier to compute, but is
in a notion of better here is one heuristic
function better than another
supposing I want to tell you that these are
the two heuristic
functions to use.
What does your intuition say see there are
two aspects to making this choice one is the
cost of computing the function and second
is the benefits that it gives us what is the
benefit the benefit that we are looking for
is that we should guide our search better.
In
other words, one way of counting this is that
that if you let us say run 10,000
experiments on this 8 puzzle then you could
compute something like this a measure its
we call as effective branching factor equal
to number of nodes seen divided.
So, there is a effective branching factor
it is the property of the heuristic function
and the
way it is computed is that you run an experiment
what is it mean you give some start
state some goal state. Let the heuristic function
guide search according to this algorithm
that we have just written and then count how
many nodes that the algorithms see and
divided by the total length of the solution
what is the ideal value here. Ideal value
is 1,
essentially even to heuristic function is
perfect you will only see the nodes which
take
you to this goal station, so you will not
see any other new terms.
So, the ideal value for this effective branch
effective is one the branching factor of the
problem itself is known to you which is 4.
Essentially, let us say is bounded by four
or it
has Rubik’s cube its I mean concentrating,
but in this case it is not concern, but let
us say
it is. So, the effective branching factor
will be some value between 1 and 4, the better
the
heuristic function. Of course, you will not
do it for one experiment, you will run
thousands of experiments just to even out
all statistical variations that you come by
choosing difference start states and that
kind of a thing essentially.
So, then you have a notion of one being better
than the other, but at the same time you
have the cost difference between the two in
this case these two functions. In general,
they
.may be a choice of more than two functions,
so one has to choose the heuristic function
essentially.
Now, if you just go back to this algorithm
again
it makes sense to use a heuristic function
if now remember that the heuristic function
you have to compute for every node that you
generate every time you call the move gen
function and generate the children. After
removing the duplicates ones, you have to
compute the heuristic function for that node
essentially. So, the extra cost of computing
the heuristic function must be much less than
the total time save for this algorithm which
means that how do you save time by seeing
a
fewer number of nodes.
Essentially, if the heuristic function is
good then you will not go down some paths
which
are meaningless you would only go down the
solution path essentially, so obviously it
make sense to choose a versatile use a term
inexpensive heuristic function. The simplest
or the most inexpensive ones are the static
functions which only look at given state and
tell you a value essentially it shows a state.
It will say this is a good state or a bad
state in
terms of some number which it will compute
using one of those things why do we say
that, so let us go back to this city map example
for a moment.
What can happen which the heuristic function
cannot foresee essentially, so if you know
the topology of Chennai and if you know that
you will go to the gate, you have no other
option you go to the main gate and from there
you have to decide where to go. So, this is
the starting place that is the goal location
what happens when there is a river running
across this, we have this Adyar River and
it even has water sometimes. A heuristic
function which is only looking at the start
state and the goal state will be oblivious
of the
fact that there is a river on the way.
So, in the mountainous situation it could
be a paths for example, you need a paths to
cross some mountain ridge here you need a
bridge. So, let us say the bridge is one bridge
is here and another bridge is here, but there
is no bridge along the blowflies direction
close the river. What will the heuristic function
do it will drive the search in this
direction because it will tell you this node
is better than this node and this node is
better
than this node. In actual practice these two
one of these two nodes is likely to be better
why because this might take you to this bridge
and this might take you to this bridge,
.whereas this will take you to dead end and
then you will have to go down this path and
then go like this.
We will not be able to see in the future a
heuristic function will make judgment only
based on what information it has in this case
it is a static function which means the
current location and the destination location
and based on that this appears to be the best.
So, in that sense heuristic functions are
fallible that is not necessary that they will
give
you the best thing. We will in the next class
look at another example to see how a
heuristic function can take, you can be misguided
in some sense essentially and we will
discuss that in the little bit more detail.
So, you have to devise some heuristic function
which will give you a number for every
node that you add to the open list and we
are assuming here that the smaller is the
better
because we are talking about notion of a distance.
Then, we will sort the open list
according to the heuristic function and always
choose the best node and the search will
progress essentially. So, what is the hope
the hope is that the search will go towards
the
direction of the goal, but sometimes it may
go in one direction then it may have to back
trap and try something else essentially. So,
which one might say that you start with the
search this thing go down some path and you
can fill in some values so that we will go
down this path here.
So, for example, this could be 40 this could
be 60 and this could be 50 or something like
that. So, which choose 40 and then likewise
remember that all these are closed according
to the algorithm and everything else is opened
essentially. So, it is possible that the
heuristic function will take it down this
path and suddenly it will discover that the
heuristic value has short of at this stage.
So, this becomes the next directly, so the
heuristic function is guided since its guided
by the heuristic function it does not always
explore the space in the same predetermined
pattern, but it will depend on what is the
goal that you have given to us.
If the goal of was instead of here is the
goal was here, let us say station or something
then the certain algorithm would have try
to go in this direction essentially. So, its
behavior changes with every goal that is a
basic idea that it is trying to go in the
direction
where the goal will be achieved essentially.
Likewise, for the other problem essentially
I
.will come to the dynamic functions in the
moment lets discus the properties of this
algorithm I have gotten the four criteria
that we have talked about.
Let us start with completeness, so where should
I write this I think let me here, so let us
give this algorithm and name by the way we
haven’t given it a name and this algorithm
is
called best first
best first in the sense that of all the nodes
in the open. It will pick the best
one first and what do you mean by best the
one with the lowest heuristic value, so best
first what are the properties
completeness let us assume that it is a finite
space for
simplicity, which is complete. It is complete,
but how would justify your argument
actually we did not actually give a very a
little bit more formal argument even for the
earlier search is, but you can give it now
looking at this algorithm how can you say
that it
is complete essentially.
In every cycle, it picks one node from open
inspects it and either put into close or
succeeds or whatever the state space is finite
which means open can have only all the
entire state space in the worst case it will
explore the entire state space. In every cycle,
it
will inspect one node from open, so it will
terminate either when open is empty or when
it found the goal state it will always find
the goal state if it exist because it will
at some
point enter the open. It will always pick
node some open and open is the finite list
specially given the fact that we are prove
we are moving the duplicates we are never
adding the same nodes again.
So, the open have only the finite set to start
with and in the worst case it will pick them
one by one and in a recycle and remove it
and say I cannot find the solution. When the
solution exists at some point, it will be
picked by open pick by this step here and
it will
say succeed what is the difference between
depth first and best first. The only difference
is that best first is sorting at least conceptually
it is sorting the open list every time
essentially though that is the only change,
but it is going to pick every node once before
it terminate, so completeness follows.
..
Let us talk about time and space in one breadth
here very quickly what would you say
time complexity, let us worry let us not worry
about space. So, much in this moment, let
us talk about time it really depends on how
good the heuristic function is. Now, you can
see that if the heuristic function is perfect,
then the time complexity will be linear you
will always go to the correct node linear
in what linear in depth right. So, the depth
is
this search tree, you will always choose make
the correct choice at every level and in
linear time you will reach the goals.
In the worst case, it will exponential essentially
if the heuristic function is bad the
heuristic function could be actually malicious
essentially like you know in some cities
you find ask somebody how do I go there and
then tell you the opposite direction. So,
even in the worst case you will only do an
exponential amount of search essentially,
so it
really depends upon the heuristic function
likewise for space it really depends upon
the
heuristic function. Now, in the search tree
that we were drawing like this solves the
open
list for breadth first search and the open
list for depth first was like this. Now, it
is really
difficult to give you a feel of this exponentially
going pen list of breadth first search, but
you must keep in mind that every time when
I go from one level to the next.
I am multiplying the length if you want to
call it by b essentially where b is the bunching
factor which is not really depicted in the
diagram this is just kind of a schematic diagram,
but every time it is going becoming longer
by b. So, therefore, it is going exponentially,
.whereas the for breadth depth first search
the open is basically kind of proportional
to
length and its linear that we have argued
it turns out that for best first search. Typically,
the search frontier looks like this, now this
is typical of course, which means it is not
really linear and it generally tends to be
more towards exponentially in nature in practice
essentially.
There is one thing that you should consider
if you have solved this kind of problems or
if
you have solved Rubik’s kind of problems
just try to imagine that sometimes you have
to
go against the heuristic function. We will
come to this point later in the sense that
if you
are counting for example, the number of tiles
and place or something like that then at
some point you have to disrupt something that
you have already done. So, for example,
in the Rubik’s cube you have done the top
phase and then do to do the second layer you
have to temporarily disrupt the top phase
now heuristic function would be very upset
about such things.
Now, you have made the top phase and then
you are disrupting it will not reflect nicely
in your search essentially. So, we will come
to those issues later completeness time space
and what else quality I will differ this discussion
quality later just think about is do you
think that this will give you an optimal solution
or not and we will come to this later. I
just want to spend the couple of minute on
the other side which is the domain
independent
and without going into details I will just
say this that domain independent
heuristic function solves what we call a relaxed
problem. So, it solves a relaxed problem
and. So, what is the key difference the static
function only looks at the given state and
the goal state and gives you a value.
So, relaxed problem and when we look at planning
we will see if we get time we will
look at this in a little bit more detail,
but the relaxed problem is modifying the original
problem, so that it can be solve more easily
essentially. So, to give you an example when
you look at the eight puzzle like this, now
if I have to go from two to if I if two has
to go
here or if two has to let us say seven has
to go here in place of one. We want to move
seven to one now in the real eight puzzle
you have to first move eight out of the way,
then you have to push seven up.
Then, you have to you know somehow create
the gap by pushing, so we have pushed
eight here, then you push 6 and then 5 and
then 4 and then 3 then 2 and then 1 and then
.you push seven up essentially you have to
do a lot of moves in the real world.
Essentially, imagine an eight puzzle in which
you can slide on top of other slides or sit
on top of other slides other tiles essentially
which means I have modified my problem
that I can make a move a seven can come here.
Then, it can come here essentially, it does
not have to be a blank tile to move into which
is the real problem essentially the relaxed
problem, you can move over on the tile and
sit on top of another tile.
Now, you can see that if I am working with
this relaxed problem I can easily find how
many steps it take for me to go from seven
to one this is two steps now which where we
devise the static function. Also, we gave
the same value remember that distance to the
goal step he said the difference between the
static. This dynamic domain independent
function is that the static domain function
was devise specifically for the eight puzzle
whereas, when we learn how to sort of pose
problems in the uniform manner. We can see
that we can pose problems and then we can
pose relaxed problems in a domain
independent fashion and they can be solved
typically in polynomial time that is a key
thing.
So, what is a difference between a static
function and a dynamic function or domain
independent static function we assume is solved
in constant time because it only looks at
the given state. The goal state and gives
you a value whereas, this domain independent
function actually expose the space, but under
different constraints which are relaxed
from the original problem. So, it still may
search up to the certain depth essentially,
but
problem has been relaxed to such an extent
that to solve the relaxed problem it needs
only polynomial time u that is a general idea.
We will try and come back to that later, but
it is done in a domain independent fashion
I just illustrated it with the eight puzzle
here
essentially.
So, what happens now you have a heuristic
function which is computed whenever n is
generated with a static function this is computed
in constant time. So, obviously, it likely
to be helpful the question is if I have a
polynomial time function sitting here is it
going to
help which is attractive. Then, I can do this
in a domain independent fashion I do not
have to say oh this is the city map. I can
use a Euclidean distance or that is a eight
puzzle
I can or that is a Rubik’s cube or I can
count the red tiles and the blue tiles.
.I do not have to do any of that reasoning
I will say in some well defined manner, I
will
change the problem definition to such in such
a manner that it can be solved in
polynomial time and then the length of that
solution I will use as a heuristic value here.
So, you have plugged in a polynomial function
here and the question is does it help you
have plugged in this polynomial function inside
this thing which is basically exponential
in nature and the answer is that yes in practice.
It helps and we will see that little bit later,
but to generalize the idea of using a heuristic
function is to use a function which will
given the choices you have given the open
list that you have.
It will tell you which node to inspect next
rather than do it in a blind fashion like
depth
first or breadth first or for that method
d f I d was using it is using some it is doing
search
in a more informed fashion and that is why
it is called best first search essentially.
So, we
will take a best first search again and then
we will try to improve upon this a little
bit we
will come back to this notion of quality and
completeness and revisit them. Essentially,
keep in mind that time and space complexity
on the average are still exponential in
nature they may be better exponential functions
than the original, but that they still tend
to be exponential.
Of course, in some domains, where the heuristic
function is very nice easy to build in
which case you will get lot of improvement.
For example, if you are in Manhattan, then
you can find the path quite easily I think,
so we will come back to this in the next class.
.