So, we were looking at heuristic search and
you saw this algorithm column best first
search. So, the way that this algorithm works
is that it is the heuristic function h of
n
which gives you an estimate of the distance
to the goal and what essentially best first
search does is that it sorts the open list.
So, let us say new is a set of nodes that
is
generated by Mogen and the basic difference
between best first and early algorithm if
we
saw was that open is modified as follows.
If we do not have this sort h then you would
simply have offend the new loads to the tail
of open and then it is behavior would have
been like depth first search, now what you
are
doing is that we are sorting on this heuristic
function h. So, the best nodes come to the
head of the lets see we always speak node
that strategy is does not change we always
pick the node from the head of the open. Then,
start does all the processing that we do
and eventually add the new nodes open in sort.
.Now, when I say sort we essentially mean
conceptually we have sorting it, but of course
from the computational point of you it would
be quite silly to sort open this every time
and, but we really do is that in set we maintain
open is a priority cube. This is an efficient
way of maintaining a sorted list of elements
and you can keep adding new elements to
that, now if you look at the behavior of best
first search.
.
What it does is it is starts with some node
then it puts it into closed and adds it is
successes to the open list. So, the single
circles are open and the double circles are
closed
then it picks one of them whichever has the
best h value and expands that
now
everything else everything in single circles
season open list.
It can take any one of them depending on the
h value, so let us say that it expands this
node next and I am assuming here a branching
factor 4 and the search proceeds in this
fashion may be this is the next one that it
expands. Since it always looking at the
heuristic function it not necessary that it
will expand one of these four any one of them
could suddenly turn out to be better than
that. This is because this is my gradually
become worst and worst in terms of heuristic
value and is possible that after this doing
this it suddenly goes off in the different
direction.
.So, it expands this and then may be it expands
this, so the search can, so the jump around
this entire list of nodes is essentially open
list
if you can make this out. So, the open list
is basically a list of all possible candidates
that it is generated which could be inspect
that
some later point of time. It is a global list
and best first search is a global search
algorithm. So, what are the properties of
this algorithm that we have looked at properties
from four perspective?
.
This is time space quality and completeness,
so if you look at this algorithm from this
four qualities we can say that it is complete
because the only thing it does differently
from best first search. Best first search
is there it is sorts opened this; otherwise
it will
always take one node from open and expand
it and so on. So, put at least for finite
spaces
it is complete the quality of the solution
as we saw is not necessarily an optimal path.
..
So, an example of that is if this is the start
node and it has let us say some source and
the
goal is somewhere here then it slightly that
this best of search will go along this path.
So,
maybe it will expand this next generated structure
source may be it will expand this
generated structure source and so on. So,
it will find some path to the goal which will
have some number of nodes where is this possible
in that this one had a direct link to the
goal in which case it would not have on this
path of length to.
Remember that we are not counting we are not
allocating any h cost we are viewing.
Simply counting how many states are there
in the solution first and this situation it
will
not find the shortest path, which is this
one or it will go in this direction.
We also saw in the example that if you have
if you have a city map and suddenly there
is
a river on the way. Then, the first best first
search will drive it towards the goal and
suddenly see that there is a no bridge and
it will have to take a and find the longer
path
decision. So, quality is not guarantee we
do not necessarily get an optimized path now
as
to time and space complexity. It really depends
upon h
if the heuristic function is good
then it will drive the search towards this
goal directly and you will find goal in linear
time requiring linear space it is like a algorithm.
.If it will directly goes straight towards
the goal, but in factors of course that does
not
happen in factors it is very difficult to
devise heuristic function which has so good
and in
practice it tense to be exponential. So, this
is something that we want to try and that
we
do not want algorithm which are exponential
in nature, so what can we do to devise
algorithm which will require lesser space
and lesser time complexity.
.
So, let us look at this variation of this
algorithm in which we modify as follows we
simply do this that open is the sorted version
of the new nodes that we have generated.
So, what have we done here we thrown away
all this nodes that we have generated
earlier.
..
So, in this case the open list is set of includes
this nodes it is big list nodes that we have
generated sometime in the past and nodes that
we have just generated everything is
included into the open list. So, this is like
a search there is now what we are saying is
do
not do that just maintain just look at the
latest note that what they would generated
the
new the newest note that was generated and
just pick the best amongst them.
.
.So, what is the behavior of this algorithm
you start with some search some start node
and
let us assume that we keep that of the parent
point you generate the children. You pick
one of them let us say the same heuristic
function we are using we take this node, but
we
generated children. Now, this algorithm is
saying that the set of candidates is only
these
children of this node that we have generated
and we have forgotten about those are the
nodes. So, in effect we have deleted them,
so those nodes no longer exist, so open as
we
can see is going to be a shorter list then
we generate the third load form here generated
children and we throw away this.
So, what is happened with this variation is
that the search has access only to the latest
nodes that have been generated only to the
neighbors of the current node it is infect.
Once we are going to do this, you do not your
need to sort this thing we can simply
modify the algorithm as follows that next
and next is a name of a node it is simply
the
best of current. So, essentially what we are
saying is at if you are at current node, so
for
example, if this is the current node then
you move to the next node which is this let
us
say this one. So, you have a here and then
you simply move to this one and that is the
move that you make here.
So, that is current and this is next you see
because we do not want to waste time sorting
because we are not going to use those anywhere
later you see once you decided this is
the best of the of this current. We can directly
select that and this can be done in linear
time of first and we just put this in a loop
while next is better than current, we just
keep
doing this as long as we can see a better
node move to the better node. So, one thing
that
we have done here is that we have changed
the domination criteria when we are doing
best first search the domination criteria
was either goal test or open empty.
This means that either we have found paths
to the goal or they are no more candidates
left in which case there is no path to the
goal because the algorithm is a complete
algorithm. You would terminate in the positive
piece only when the goal test function
returns true now we have these criteria while
next is better than current.
..
So, what we mean that better this that in
the case of heuristic function that we were
talking about it simply means the heuristic
value of next is better than the heuristic
value
of current in. If the heuristic value of the
goal is 0, then it should be lower than the
value
of the current node decision.
So, you have changed the termination criteria
simply and we have converted this into an
optimization problem, we are saying that optimize
the value of heuristic function. So,
instead of a state space search algorithm,
we have now converted into an optimization
problem and said find the node with a best
value rich if you see and we keep moving
forward till we find the better value of this.
..
Now, if you consider your situation, there
you are blind folded and you are standing
on
the slop of a hill side and you have been
told to go to the top of the hill then what
is the
algorithm that you would follow is, so this
is you standing blind folded. The algorithm
that you would follow is that you would pose
possibly take a step in all direction well
some income this set of direction. Then, move
forward to that direction which seems to
be going up, now this is a two dimensional
world or a one dimensional world in which
you can only move left or right.
Then, you can see that if you go right you
will be going higher if you go left you will
be
going lower, so you go right, which is exactly
what this algorithm is doing that it set of
look exploring the neighborhood of the current
state.
Then, saying that if there is a better neighbor
it moves to that state next is best of this
thing and you keep doing this still next is
better than current actually to be more precise.
You should have the check at this stage itself
that you should check whether next is
better and then only move to the next in principle
what you are doing is you are moving
along the steepest gradient. In this example,
we can say that we are doing steepest
gradient ascent
and it is not surprising that this algorithm
is actually call hill climbing.
So, if I remove this version now becomes a
little clear to watch, so this algorithm called
.hill climbing algorithm.
Essentially, it is analogous to climbing a
hill blind folded and we just move in the
direction of the speakers flow and hope to
reach the maximum. So, this means that if
you
reach here and then you terminate and then
you allowed to open your eyes and
see if we
have a local maxima then we will stopped the
local maxima exactly how will that will
ever reached the global maxima exactly. So,
that is what I would just about to illustrate
here, so this is the figure that I am trying
to draw that you have done this climbing and
you have reached the place where I all the
neighbors are not better than the current
neighbor.
So, initially of course you have a smile on
your face saying that you have reach the
maxima, but when you open your eyes then the
smile turns into a because then you will
discovered that actually this. So, precisely
the problem that you have pointing out that
this algorithm will take it to maxima or a
minima if you are minimizing because it should
be analogous. You will get start in this local
maxima and that is the problem that terms
because of the fact that this algorithm is
a local search algorithm. It only looks in
the
neighborhood of a current state to decide
where to go next unlike the best first search
algorithm which maintains a global list of
open candidates.
It could always move to a better candidate,
but never does says must to be said about
this
algorithm why because of the complexity issues
involved time space complexity
completeness as we have just observed it is
not complete. So, hill climbing cannot take
you to the global optima it is not complete,
it will get back of the local maxima quality
of
the solution.
Also, you cannot even talk of completeness,
so you cannot even talk of quality again,
but
time and space complexity. So, what is the
space complexity of this algorithm in a it
is
log n if we take a bindery tree see in that
log n. So, similarly by space complexity we
mean the size of the open disk how many nodes
does it need to keep in the memory only
those mean number of open it explore by this
heuristic function this heuristic function
is
there's the best. So, next on you go on incrementing
only one node at a time is present in
the priority queue one plus four in this case
1 plus 4. So, it is constant space complexity,
.so this is the single major advantage of
this algorithm is that it requires constant
space as
appose to best first and the entire algorithm
that we saw.
We said that is general require exponential
space off course well does not require
exponential space, but best first search does
because it could not it had no sense of
direction. It would say and hill climbing
also games on time because it only moves along
the gradient it will stop moving once the
gradient becomes negative. So, in some sense
it
will require linear time that it will take
a if it takes n steps, it just about takes
the n steps
and communicates with that essential. So,
the question is what is this surface appear
talking about this hill that we are talking
about where does this surface come from.
The answer is that this surface is defined
by the heuristic function that we are using
to
guide such thing. So, I would want to take
a couple of examples one example to illustrate
that you can have two different heuristic
functions and they will define different
surfaces. Now, if the surface of the that
you what in the space that you are searching
were to be smooth if the surface was like
this then you can see that this algorithm
would
have taken you to the global maxima that is
the global maxima. So, it really depends on
nature of the problem if the nature of the
problem is searched that the heuristic function
defines a smooth and monotonic surface then
hill climbing will work, otherwise it will
get struck to on a local maxima.
..
So, let us take an example from the blocks
world domain which is a domain which is
often used to illustrate many ideas in e i
and the domain consist of a set of children
blocks. So, for example, you may have a b
set of blocks which are arranged like this,
so
you can keep only one block on another block,
so here we have free blocks and filled up
one top of the other. Then, there is the table
and then we have two more blocks filled up
like this, so this is the start state given
to us and the goal state is let us say state
which
looks like this that you on a to sit on D
and then D to sit on B and b to sit on C and
let E
be like this.
So, this is the goal state what are the moves
available to you we have only one move
which we will say is like this move block
x let us call it commas source to destination
and source can be a top of. So, this move
can only be done if you can pick up of block,
which means it must near the top of a stack
all around the table and you can put it down
either on the top of another block or on the
table. So, the source can be only the top
of a
stack or the top most blocks in the stack
and the destination also can be only a top
most
block in this stack. So, for example, in this
situation we can do the following moves we
can say move this to top of b.
So, you would get a situation like this
that is one possible move you can then another
.move we can make is we can put a down. So,
this B and C remain like this D is here and
A is here, A third move that you can make
is we can move D. So, only A and D are the
two blocks we can move here because they are
of the only once on the top of the stack.
So, you can put D on top of a, whereas E remains
here and the fourth possible move is
that you can put D down. So, you will get
these are the four possible moves, so this
is the
neighborhood of this state and you want to
use hill climbing algorithm to decide which
state to move.
So, now, it means to design the heuristic
function, so what is what can be a heuristic
function that you can use here, so I want
to discuss two functions. They are as follows
the first function says that if a block is
sitting on a correct destination block. Then,
you
add one further block what do your destination
block A should be sitting on D should be
sitting on B and B should be sitting on C
and C should be on the table and likewise
for E
should be on the table.
.
So, let us call this h one of n it says add
one if block on i just use a term block, so
in
general we mean either block or the table
and we subtract 1 if it is on, so this gives
a
such function which only looks at a state.
So, the idea of a heuristic function in that
it
should be computationally cheap pieces just
look at the state and get a value out of it.
So,
.let us just give heuristic values for all
this functions, so let us start with a goal,
so for this
we will have plus one for this plus one for
this plus one for everything because
everything is on the correct place. So, the
heuristic value of the goal is 5 or plus 5
whatever the start state.
The start state we will have plus 1 for this
plus 1 for this minus 1 for this because a
should be on D, but it is on b plus 1 for
this minus 1 for this because d should be
on b in
the goal state, but it is sitting on e. So,
if we add this entire sub you will get a value
of
plus one
now what about the other states. So, let us
look at this value this is a, b, c this
ends to plus one here plus one for this and
minus one for this. So, just let me know if
I
making a mistake this state am plus one here
it is minus one for this minus one for this
plus one for this plus one for this. So, this
cancel, so and e, so this is also plus 1 for
this 1
plus 1 for this plus one for this minus 1
for this plus 1 for this minus 1 for this.
So, this is
also plus 1 in this case it is plus 1 for
this plus 1 for this plus 1 for this plus
1 for this.
Notice because a sitting on d and in the goal
you want to a to be sitting on d and minus
one for this. So, this value turns out to
be plus c, so these are the four states this
is one
state this is another state this is the third
state this is the fourth state that this move
gun
function generates and heuristic function
tells. So, the algorithm says look at the
neighbors if one of the neighbors is better
than if at least one neighbor is better than
the
current state then choose a best among the
neighbors, in this example three neighbors
are
equal to plus 1. So, we do not consider that
where we consider this one which is better
than, so the first move hill climbing will
make this heuristic function is this one it
will
complete, so from here what are the options?
Again, we do the move gun function, so you
can move either d or you can move a if you
move a one thing is you can go back to this
state you can take a from here and put it
on
top of b or you can take a from here put it
down here which is you will go to this state.
The other options are you can take b on top
put it on a, so you will get this state and
you
must tell me that heuristic value of this.
So, plus 1 for this minus 1 for this plus
1 for this
minus 1 for this plus 1 for this, so this
whole thing comes to plus 1 so that is one
move
from here and one more move is that you can
pick up b and put it down on the table. So,
.you would get B C and A A D E, so this minus
1 for this plus 1 for this plus 1 plus 1 and
minus 1, so this is also plus 1 is that correct.
So, here we are sitting on a state which has
the heuristic value of plus 3 and it has four
neighbors this has the value of plus 1 we
have completed earlier this has the value
of plus
1 we have completed earlier and these two
also have a value of plus 1. So, you can see
that this is the maxima and the algorithm
will terminate here without reaching the goal
state that we are interested.
.
So, let us have a different heuristic function
and this function is as follows. So, let us
call
it h two of n and this says add one for
every block in a structure. So, we are looking
at
the whole structure that the block is sitting
on
and subtract one for every block. So, the
difference between that is that you adding
O W either you adding 1 or subtracting 1.
In this case, you may an a add of many things,
so you are adding one for every block in
the correct structure. So, if it is entire
structure below the block is correct then
for every
element in the structure, you will add one
if it is a long structure, for every element
you
will subtract 1. So let us together start
with the goal, so will start with plus 1 here
plus 2
here because it is on c and c is on the table
likewise plus 3 here because d is on b and
b is
.on c and c is on table, so three things below
we factor it and plus four here and this is
plus 1. So, this is 10 plus 1, 11, let us
look at the start state you will add a plus
1 for c
plus 2 for b minus 3 for a because it is a
long structure it should have been on A D
B C,
it is on a b c a b c is not a correct structure.
So, three things below it along, so we have
two minus three for here likewise we do
minus 2 for this because it is on a wrong
structure and plus one for this. So, this
three and
three canceled out this canceled out, so this
is minus 1, the start state you can see the
same force nodes are generated by the same
move gun function which is that you can
move this thing. So, let us see valuate the
values for this four states here as before,
so in
this case as we have seen this adds to 0 plus
1 plus 2 minus 3, so this is 0 this is plus
one
and this will be minus 1. So, this will end
of 0 in this case these 3 add up to minus
0 as
before this will add another minus 4 to that
because it is in a wrong structure which is
fourth in below that.
So, minus 4 here plus 1 here, so this will
be minus 3 this 1 plus 1 plus 2 plus 3 for
this
plus 4 for this minus one for this and minus
2 for this. So, his will be plus 1 and this
last
one which is
plus 3 for these 2 plus 1 for this 4 minus
2 for this. So, this becomes 2 and
minus 3 for this, so it becomes minus 1 is
that correct, so now, let us follows and look
at
what this heuristic function is how is it
evaluating the situation, the first heuristic
function took this as plus 1 and this as plus
3 and this always plus 1. So, it is thought
this
is the good move to make and it move make
that move essentially.
Now, when you look at the problem you can
see that the optimal solution is when you
pick up a put it down somewhere, then pick
up D, put it on B then pick up a and put it
on
that is optimal solution. So, the first correct
move to make a s u pick up a and put it down
on the table and if you look at this second
heuristic function h 2 that we are looking
at.
First of all you must notice that it is moved
discriminative the first function had only
very few set of values plus 1 here plus 3
here and plus 5, there essentially. This one
has a
value of minus one here plus 1, 1 for this
0 for this minus 3 for this plus 1 for this
and
minus one for this all values is different.
So, it does not think that they are equal
in states
not only that is feel that this is the good
state then this is the next based state and
these
.two state it is comes as to be bad. Actually,
because its values are lower essential, now
using the algorithm, it has a better state
to move, it was at minus 1 you can you can
see
plus 1.
So, it will make this moves and that you will
notice is the correct move to make from
here what can we do it can either pick up
a and put it on b which is going back here.
That
you can see is the move it will not make because
it is going from plus 1 to minus 1 or it
can pick up A and put it on to D and that
is the state that we have seen here it can
make
this move and that is going from plus 1 to
minus 1 again. So, it will not make that move,
so it is not going to pick up A and do something
with it. So, A could have put on d it is
going to take it to a bad state or it could
have put it back one B this also in which
going
to take it to a back state, so what about
the other possibilities, so it can either
pick up B
or it can pick up D.
.
So, let us first take the B case, so it can
pick up D and put it on C on D sorry B, D,
E, C
A, that is one possibility or it can pick
up B from here and put it on a that is second
possibility and the third possibility is you
can it can put B down. So, these all B moves
that we are looking at this the third possible
state, so let us just look evaluate these
values. So, we have plus one for this minus
1 minus 2 and minus 3 for this, so that is
.minus 6, so this value should be minus 6
is it correct, so C is plus 1 E is plus 1
E is plus
one 1 2 D is minus 2, that cancels that.
So, minus 3 for this and minus 1 for this,
so minus 4, so obviously, it is not going
to
make this move. So, it is sitting at plus
one just keep that in mind it is not going
to move
to minus 1 here or to minus 1 here or to minus
4 here what are the states values for these
2 states. So, this is minus 3 minus 2 minus
2, so obviously, these states are worst states,
so it is not going to move from it, so that
leave just only the D moves, so let us look
at
there, so I can either pick up D and put it
on B or on A or put it down.
.
So, there are three possibilities. So, D,
B, C, E, A or it can put D on
A which is B
minus
1 and minus 2, 3 plus 2 is that correct for
this state plus 3 for this plus one 4 for
this
minus 1 for this and minus 2 or this. So,
it will be plus 1, so if remember it was sitting
on
plus 1, so it would not go to plus 1 or it
won’t go it can go to plus 2, but let us
look at this
one. So, this is plus 1 plus 2 plus 3 that
is plus 6 plus 1 plus 4 minus 1 6 plus 1 minus
1,
so plus 6, so you can see that this heuristic
function will actually derive the search hill
climbing algorithm to make these two moves,
first it will pick up d and put it. First,
it
will pick up A and put it on the table and
then it will pick up D and put it on B and
you
can see that the heuristic value is going
a plus 6.
.If you want to take this forward you can
see that this actually leads to the goal state
essentially in the next step essentially it
will pick up a and put it on top of D recheck
value of plus 1, all other moves will be worst
in that essentially. So, what we have seen
here is that given a problem to solve what
is the problem it is a block solve problem,
you
are given some initial configuration. You
have some desired configuration when you are
given a set of moves you want to use hill
climbing both these functions are static
evaluation functions.
This means, they only look at a state ant
give you a value for that when I when we
valued this plus 1 on this minus 3 or this
plus 6 or plus 1 we are not doing any search.
We are only looking at this particular state
and saying this is the value for this state
both
is static. So, both require constant time
in some sense, but one is more perceptive
then
the other one is more detailed one looks at
the entire structure the other one only looks
at
what the current block. You can see that one
search the first heuristic function takes
it to
local maxima the second one takes it to global
maxima. So, what does that mean, it
means that the surface that h one is defining
as local maxima it is like this something
like
this where is the surface at this one is defining
is smooth essentially.
So, one thing that you can do when you are
using an algorithm like hill climbing chooses
a heuristic function which will define a smooth
monotonic surface like this. Then, of
course you are done and you are done at a
very inexpensive price the space requirement
is constant. The heuristic function have takes
constant time and the time complexity is
linear because it will just keep taking one
step in positive direction and eventually
come
to a stop at the goal.
So, that is why hill climbing is such an attractive
algorithm because it allows you to do
this thing at constant space and linear time
essentially the caches can you find the
heuristic function which will define the smooth
surface for the searched. If you cannot,
then you have this problem of having getting
struck on local maxima or a local minima
as the case. Maybe then, we need to look for
algorithms which have variations of hill
climbing which can overcome this problem of
getting struck in the local maxima. So, we
will look at that in the next class, so we
stop here.
.