So, let us get back to this question on the
philosophical side of our introduction, so
what
are mines essentially.
So, if you remember the view from Aristotle,
it said that our
thoughts are our reflection of what is out
there.
If I see an apple or if I think of an apple,
it
is because there is an apple out there and
my thought is in the image of that apple that
is out
there.
The diametrically opposite view was given
to us by Canter much much later; he said
that what is out there is the reflection of
our thoughts that what we think is out there
is what
we think is out there.
Now you see there is a gap that you can never
cross, because what you think is out there
is
only what you are thinking is out there, what
is really out there.
So, you see a person you
know person sitting here.
So, I think there is a person sitting here
especially.
So, I have this
concept of people; I have concepts of you
know boys, girls, men, women, all kind of
concepts, trees, chairs.
So, that is how I think about the world and
it is out there.
So, I also
have concepts about clouds and you see an
image of something in the clouds; you see
a
dog in the clouds or you know something else.
.
.What is out there really is a question we
want to start with and then we want to we
have
seen already that the notion of the mind has
come about the people understood that there
is
something called the mind; gradually over
a period of time when they realize that what
they are thinking about is not in direct correspondence
with what is out there.
But now
what we want to discuss is that it is a necessity
that if you have to have an intelligent agent,
we have to have a mind which can represent
the world in a way that it can manage the
representation effectively.
So, that is the question I am driving at today.
So, let us start with the basic question as
that
what is reality; of course, we live in a world.
We are also part of this world, but what is
the
objective reality?
If you wanted to create a model of the world,
how would I do it?
No what
is really out there, any suggestions?
We are talking about reality.
So, you are saying that
reality is as we see a collection of situations
which we can manipulate.
No, but simpler
things like people take this young man sitting
over here; is he real or what is the young
man; what is the human being?
.
Okay, now let us take a scientific enforce
point of view, the physics point of view;
everything in the physical world is made up
of a small number of fundamental particles.
So, whereas a small number of fundamental
particles I mean there is a number of different
particles are small; it is not that the number
of particles is small.
The different type is small
actually.
So, depending on what theory you are following.
So, the simplest one could
.follow the bore atom module, for example;
you know an atom is made up of protons and
neutrons and electrons and everything else
in the world is made of these three kind of
things essentially.
So, physics is, of course, I have been struggling
to figure out what the world is made up of
but let us take it for granted at it is some
fundamental particle; it could be something
smaller that proton and neutron, but everything
is there, and these particles they obey some
laws of physics.
So, the laws of physics are sufficient to
explain what is happening in the
world out there.
So, that is a first assumption that we will
work with and it is not something
that we can dispute because then you are saying
the physics is wrong essentially.
So, like
Penrose was saying that the physics of the
brain we do not understand, then you would
be
saying that we do not understand the physics
of this world essentially.
So, the physics is believe that that you know
we do not know what the.
So, there is a sling
theory, then they are neutrinos and gluons
and that kind of stuff, but there is something
out
there.
And they all behave according to the laws
of physics which we are trying to
discover; by the way they behave according
to these laws, and, therefore, everything
can
be exchanged according to these laws.
So, that is enough to understand the world
in some
sense.
So, we are talking about people, what is the
person.
So, even adult, it is made up of
about 10 raise to 27 atoms.
I do not know whether you can visualize the
number 10 raise to
27, but you should try; it is a huge number.
So, we can think of a person or person not
in the social sense, but in the physical sense;
a
human body is made up of about 10 raise to
27 atoms.
So, this young man sitting over there
is just a collection of a 10 rise to 27 atoms
which for some reason decide to stick together,
and the reason is given by the laws of physics.
It can be explained by the laws of physics,
and of course, we may call it in different
terms.
We may talk about biology or chemistry
and so on, but deep down they obey these laws
of physical is fundamental particles obeyed
essentially.
So, we have mention earlier that there are
two views of the world.
One is
materialist view which says that there is
only matter and the other is the idealism
view
which says that there is no matter essentially.
So, which is why in the last line I had said
that if there are fundamental particles; you
know
some people believe that it is all energy
or something out there essentially, but that
let us
not get into that kind of a thing.
So, we are trying to understand the world;
we are trying to
.model the world; we are trying to why do
you want to do that?
Because an intelligent agent
and we discussed this in the early lectures
should be able to operate in a meaningful
manner in the world.
Do something useful for itself and achieve
its goals and you know
learn and that kind of stuff.
So, it needs to represent the world out there,
but what is the
world out there is the question we are asking.
.
So, human beings is about 10 raise to 27 atoms,
and these 10 raise to 27 atoms are
continuously interacting with zillions of
other atoms out there; you know we breathe,
we
eat, we have sound wave impinging upon us
which are also made up of oscillating particles
and so on and so forth essentially.
So, if we try to talk about reality in these
terms like a
physicist, can we ever make sense of this
world out there?
And when I say it makes sense
of this world as I mean in the practical sense
as an intelligent agent in some environment
trying to do useful things especially.
So, can we ever hope to write down the equations
for them and solve them even if we
know the equations and what would we get if
we solve them especially.
The trajectories of
their location how does that help us?
You know that atom number 259 is moving in
this
direction or something, does not help.
So, if you want to interact with the world,
we need
to have our own level of presentation, and
this is what I am going to be driving at today.
The world that we interact with like handset,
it is a world in our minds especially.
..
So, we have already said that the world around
us and including us operates according to
and can in principle be explained by the fundamental
laws of physics; nothing else is really
needed, but it is too big for us to work with,
because the number of amount of information
we would have to use would be too much essentially.
What we do is that we create our own
worlds in our minds, and it is only our creation
that is meaningful to us essentially.
So,
coming back to the example of a person, I
do not think of a person as an example of
raise to 27 atoms behaving in some concerted
action.
I think of it as a single entity a person
who is sitting on a single entity called a
chair or
eating a single entity which is I call a dosa
some masala dosa; for example, I think of
it as
one thing essentially.
Of course, it is not one thing; it is made
up of so many things and so
many processes and I do not want to get into
that at all.
So, we create levels of abstraction
at which we represent things and reason at
those levels of abstractions.
So, we should also
keep in mind Newell and Simon physical symbol
system hypothesis is that we can create
symbol systems and manipulate that symbol;
that is enough for us to reason about the
world in an intelligent fashion essentially.
So, Douglas Osheroff who I will talk about
again in a moment has a different notion of
a
symbol which we will not peruse very much
here.
He talks about how the mind creates
symbol, how the brain creates these same symbols
that we are talking about.
We stand for
a person and so on and so forth.
So, when I was talking about a symbol, I said
something
.which was perceptible.
So, for example, I write the name of a person;
I can read it
essentially or I can you know type it in a
word processor and things like that, but Osheroff
also talks about symbol processing in the
human brain that the human brain leads symbols
and what are the symbols?
These are kind of concerted patterns of activity
in thousands of
neurons.
So, we will not go into more detail than that,
but somehow neurons act in concert with each
other in a manner which we are inspecting
ourselves, think of a symbols that we are
reasoning with symbols.
So, this kind of an idea has been exploited
in movies; of course,
movies do not necessarily depict reality.
So, again coming back to the matrix, so if
those of
you have seen matrix would remember that its
main character called Neil Neo; in Neo’s
mind, Neo was a software engineer working
in New York city, and that is how the movie
begins, but in reality, whatever, that means,
neo is in some cell in some human battery
which the machines have constructed to extract
the energy out of him.
So, which is the complicated sequence which
we have to sought off watch the movie
carefully to understand that when eventually
that something is pulled out of his brain,
he
really finds himself in some very unknown
like place you know inside some cell where
he
is just unit of a large battery or something
like that.
The important thing that I am trying to
say is that it uses this idea that the world
we live in is actually in our minds out there
essentially which is why, of course, sometimes
people can hallucinate.
They imagine
something what is not out there, because their
minds are sought of not in sync with again
let me use the word reality out there.
But there is a big case in that you know we
do not know what is reality; we only know
what
we know essentially.
Inception is another film in which you would
not know whether you
are dreaming or whether you are in some real
world.
And this is not the physical system
hypothesis says that if you can create a level
of representation and is it not that level
that
should be enough for creating intelligence
systems.
..
We have dense slides that I have put in; we
are not going to go through this slide.
It is just
to illustrate the levels of scale at which
our concepts exist.
Remember that in the end
everything is made up of examples of this
fundamental particles, but then we talk of
people, we will talk of football field, we
talk of a planet.
All these are at different levels of
scale.
There is a very nice movie; I do not know
how many of you have seen it called,
‘powers of ten’ which is available on
the web, and there is a link I have given
here which
essentially is rooms out of a level in which
a couple is seen in a park and goes to the
very
top most level here which you can see a 10
rise to 26 meters and then zooms down back
and goes to the bottom most level which is
10 raise to minus 17 meters and things like
that.
So, at different levels you see the world
with a different perspective.
Suggest some
examples, for example, mustard seed is about
one millimeter thick whereas the distance
from Chennai to Pune is about 1100 kilometers.
So, in these powers of ten, you keep
magnifying the image all reducing the image
by powers of ten every time and then you sort
of keep diving in deeper and so on and so
forth.
So, you can see at the top most level, there
are very things that we cannot I mean our
mind bowels to talk about something like ten
billion light years.
First of all, you have to imagine what is
a light year or remember what is a light year.
It is
a distance covered by light in one year and
we do not even think of light having speed.
I
mean I just see you and you raise your hand
and I see instantaneously; where is the
.question of speed?
We do not even have a notion of speed; of
course nowadays we have
thanks to Einstein and all these people but
light travels at a finite speed.
And we do not
realize it because we know it is so fast for
all of us here that everything happens
instantaneously.
We do not suffer from these effects of relativity
and things like that.
But ten billion light
years, how much would the light travel in
ten billion years?
I mean we cannot even think
of these kinds of things especially, alright,
the very extreme end 10 raise to minus 17
meters where you have quacks and gluons and
so on and so forth.
So, the world as we think
of nowadays exists at these very different
scales of things; that are at one level.
At another
level, it is all just collections of fundamental
particles which we have already agreed that
we cannot deal with at that level; that is
why we think of these different scales especially,
okay.
.
So, our perceptible universe is a small subset
of the scales essentially.
So, the largest thing
we can see is may be about a kilometer across.
So, like the golden gate bridge and San
Fransisco or something like that, and the
smallest thing is may be a mustard seed or
may be
some people can see pollen you know there
is rays of light and you can see dust particles.
Some of them may be 0.1 millimeter across.
So, you can perhaps think about things at
this
level of scale essentially.
So, the human mind as far I am trying to get
at; the human mind
has evolved to create concepts at these scales
essentially.
.So, we tend to think of objects at these
scales; that is why we are comfortable with
this.
We
are not even comfortable talking about how
far the planet Jupiter is from here, because
we
cannot even imagine that kind of a thing.
And at least we have not evolved to imagine
that
kind of a thing, and to reasons at different
levels, we have created this different discipline.
So, we become a specialist in biology or geography
or aestrophysics or anything.
.
But each discipline operates in its own level
of scale; social science is operated some
level
where we are talking about collections of
human beings.
Remember human being, each
human being is collection of 10 raise to 27
particles.
So, social science in some sense is
talking about collections of 10 raise to 27
particles, but we do not, obviously, think
in
terms of fundamental particles any longer,
and we have these different disciplines
especially.
..
So, Hofstadter, so remember this mind-body
problem which Decant was blipping with that
if there is this world of the mind which is
reasoning about the real physical world out
there
the body; how do the two things interact essentially?
Nor the physics we say we have laws
of physics of the fundamental particle level,
and if you know that, you will know how the
rest of the system is having essentially.
But Hofstadter says that we have to introduce
a
notion of what he calls as downward causality
which means the causality is from a higher
level to a lower level.
Even though the laws of physics can explain
going from particle level to ensemble particle
level, he says that is not useful for us,
we have to think about how.
So, for example, if I
want to drink a cup of tea, then I am thinking
at a level about cup of tea and so on and
so
forth.
And this level of thinking which is happening
with its concepts at this level of
abstraction is eventually driving at one level;
you might say my muscles or my nerve cells
or something at even lower level you might
say the very fundamental particles which make
up my hand, for example; in such a manner
that my hand eventually reaches out for that
cup of tea and pick it up and you know take
a sip from it essentially.
So, the causality is from our level of reasoning
to the lower level where things are actually
happening.
Now physics, of course, does not have a notion
of causality; that is why
Canter’s even when he was talking about
human categories, he was saying that is face
and
causality are given to us that we accept we
have to start working with those things
.essentially.
.
So, these things are calling epiphenomenon.
So, things like pressure, for example, in
a
balloon, we talk of pressure, but what is
really happening that lower level activities
you
know molecules of different kinds of molecules
in air, nitrogen, hydrogen, carbon dioxide,
everything; they are moving around randomly
and you know impinging upon the inner
surface of the balloon.
And this cumulative activity or the epiphenomenon
phenomenal of
pressure is dealt essentially.
Likewise, in our human brains, there are these
billions of
neurons which are firing away in some fashion.
We do not tend to think of our brain in that
fashion.
I tend to think of my brain and say, oh,
I want to have this cup of tea which is operating
at a very higher level essentially.
So, can
a machine operate at epiphenomenon level like
this, and that we feel is necessary for
machines to be intelligent.
So, we have run through this.
So, computers are manmade
objects; we know how they operate.
So, it is easy for us to explain; for example,
if you type
something in a word processor, in principle
somebody can say that at the lowest level,
these are the kind of micro level operations
which were taking place.
But we do not do
that, of course; we as human beings tend to
think of machines as doing higher level things.
So, how do we see a machine computer?
As a music player or a web browser or a game
or
any of these many things that a machine can
do; so the important thing is that many people
have called starting with tuning is there
is a universal machine.
The computer just like us is
.a universal machine.
So, if you want to call yourself as a universal
machine and the
universal machine is a machine which not only,
of course, a simple machine can do only
what it is designed to do, but a universal
machine can imitate other machines and do
what
they were doing.
So, they are flexible in that nature.
Scans as a machine be intelligent; Hofstadter,
so I come
back to Hofstadter.
He says that if this machine can introspect
and examine its own
behavior, then it is possible for it to become
intelligent essentially.
So, he is going one
more step from Newell and Simon.
Simon and Newell they said that if you can
create
symbolic representations and create algorithm,
you still work on this representation; that
is
sufficient and necessary to create intelligent
behavior.
Now we can see that that is at one
level of.
So, there have been layers and layers that
one has to talk about.
In computers, we have bit
level representation; they have machine code,
assembly language, higher level languages,
higher level data structures, representations,
objects, all kinds of things and you keep
going higher, likewise in the real world out
there.
So, Newell and Simon said that one level
of representation which he calls as the symbol
level is enough, but now Hofstadter is going
one step further.
He is saying that in addition to that, you
need this capability to introspect
essentially.
So, if you read his book, it is quite an interesting
book to read; I must change
the loop.
He sought of goes through a long detailed
argument of how Godel discovered this idea
of
self reference in Rusell and Whitehead Principia
Mathematica, and this in spite of the fact
that Rusell and Whitehead went out to formalize
everything, and they wanted to keep
away self referential structure.
So, they had layered logical representation
or typed logical
representation where self reference would
not be possible.
The same type of an argument
element could not be an argument to a sentence
in that same language essentially, but
Godel constructed this very elaborate; he
gave us very elaborate mechanism of how to
construct a sentence.
So, there is this two levels at which things
are operating upon.
One is this level of number
theory which is principle of mathematics is
all about, but there is also this level of
encoding things into this number theory and
then encoding sentences like I am lying or
something like that essentially or this sentence
is not true and things like that.
So,
.Hofstadter is saying that if a machine can
have this capacity to introspect and reason
about
its own actions which means also reason about
other people’s actions, then it can in
principle be intelligent.
So, let us talk about intelligence agents
for a moment; it is a very popular term nowadays.
So, these are programs; we will talk of intelligence
recent programs which are persistent
which means like the operating systems, for
example; if we leave a machine on that is
exist
all the times essentially.
They are autonomous which means that nobody
is saying that run
this program, run this routine or call this
subroutine or something like that; they are
proactive.
If the see an opportunity in the environment,
they sense an environment; they
will go after it essentially.
And they are goal directed which means that
you know they have goals; of course, these
goals may not be self generated; they could
be given by the creator essentially.
It is just
like we have that secret agents and the governments
are supposed to have who have all
these properties they are persistent, autonomous
and proactive, but they carry out the
billing of the government essentially.
.
This is a rough diagram of what an intelligent
agent should be like.
So, that white figure at
it is supposed to be the agent, and the thing
inside that is what is in the head of the
agent.
And what is in the head of the agent is the
module of the world out there, and the module
of
the world should contain itself which means
it can introspect on itself.
And, obviously, you
.might ask the question as to it that if the
model of the agent has a world in which the
agent
is there, then in that agents head also I
should create the model of the world.
So, there is an
infinite level of next thing which is possible
in principle.
So, they are these kinds of very
curious loops which can form, okay.
.
So, we are slowly coming towards moving away
from history and coming to what we want
to do.
If you want to build an intelligent agent
which interacts with the real world, then
you
have to have at least these layers of different
kinds of reasoning.
One is the outermost layer
is what we can call a signal processing.
It means you are receiving signals, sound
waves,
light waves or whatever from the world, and
the innermost layer is symbolic reasoning
which is what is classically AI is what all
about that you can create symbol systems and
reason with them.
And you may have and this is my interpretation
of this whole thing that an intermediate
layer of neuro-fuzzy systems which serve the
purpose of converting signals into symbols
essentially.
So, for example, if I am speaking and what
I am creating is a signal which is
you know sound waves of a particular pattern,
but your brain is converting these sound
waves into linguistic entities essentially.
So, you are recognizing words out of this
sound
wave; from these signals you are extracting
symbols essentially.
So, if I say the word apple, it may be certain
sound wave which is meaningless in itself
just
like neural activity in our head is meaningless
in itself, but you can process it to understand
.at a higher level to stand for a symbol apple,
and neural networks are particularly good
at
doing this kind of things.
So, you must have heard about fact that character
recognition if I
were to draw the letter a on a hand written
characters.
.
So, if I write A like this, if I write A like
this, if I write A like this; we have no difficulty
in
recognizing that these are A and neural network
is also very good at this sort of a thing.
But
at some point, you may start getting a doubt
about whether I am writing an A or whether
I
am writing an H. And it is very difficult
to describe rules to say that this sequence
of
segment forms A, this sequence of segments
forms H and so on.
Whether the learning
system which will learn these characters in
context of other letters around them will
eventually learn to recognize the character
A for example,
So, neural networks are very good at this
sort of a thing, but if you want to do give
an
explanation of let us say the Pythagoras theorem,
what is the Pythagoras theorem and how
do we prove it.
Then neural networks are not really very good
at that kind of a thing; for
that we need this symbol manipulation ability
which everybody is from Simon Hostettler
is saying it is necessary for intelligent
behaviors essentially.
..
So, these are the topics that one can identify
if you look at AI in general.
This is not the
topics of this course.
If you look at the enterprise of AI, then
we have all kinds of topics
here, knowledge representations, semantics,
anthology, models, search, memory, machine
running, problem solving, planning, adversarial
reasoning, qualitative reasoning, natural
language understanding and all kinds of topics.
So, on the left what I have drawn in this
figure are the sensing kind of activities.
Signal to symbol kind of activities, speech
processing, image processing, video processing,
computer vision, neural networks, pattern
recognition, studs sensors and that kind of
thing.
On the right hand side, it is the opposite
from symbol to signal.
So, you have motor control
of.
If you want to build robots, you have to eventually
make the robot do what the robot is
thinking about doing.
If the robot is thinking about going from
place A to place B, it must
do something to make their physical movement
possible.
So, we need activators and things
like that at that time essentially.
So, these are the topics of AI.
In the circle, basically this
figure is taken from my book the circle roughly
it is a kind of describe what is there in
the
book.
So, of course, we are doing this course on
AI which we are doing here, but in our
department, there are a whole lot of courses
which cover these areas.
And I just want to
give you some idea of the kind of courses
that we offer.
The first four courses that will
come are courses which I am personally involved
with, but the rest of the courses you
.know mostly my colleagues are handling.
.
We will start with this course which is Ai
which kind of covers some of this stuff inside
this thing here, then planning and constraint
satisfaction.
These are names of courses.
So,
this will be offered next semester; for example,
both these courses will be offered next
semester knowledge representation reasoning
as well.
Then there are other courses which
my colleagues teach machine learning which
is being offered now.
Pattern recognition is
also being offered now I think.
Natural language processing as well is being
offered at this
moment.
Probabilistic reasoning is not being offered
at this moment; very often I think Dr.
Ravindran offers it as a self study course.
Then we have computer vision; I am not quite
sure which semester, may be this semester
it is being offered.
Speech technology, Kernel
methods, this is I think next semester, visual
video processing, computer graphics.
We do
not have so much on the output side.
So, you can see our department is not very
strong in
things like robotics.
So, we do not really offer courses in that.
Imagine mechanical
department may be offering some courses.
So, in terms of assignment, I might have
mentioned this earlier; one assignment is
going to be on game playing.
So, I will try to do game playing not in this
order but a little bit earlier than this order;
may
be after heuristic search or something like
that.
So, that you can get going, and we will
decide which game and we have to implement
an algorithm for it.
And your programs will
.play against each other that kind of stuff.
And another assignment would be
implementation of some of these algorithms.
.
So, we will sort of assign some algorithm
and you should implement in that way; we will
go into the details as we go along course,
okay.
.
The text books as I said it is a text book
which I have just written and everything that
I am
teaching is from there and vice versa in the
sense what is there is what I teach.
So, we will
use that as a text book, and then there is
a host of others reference books that I will
point to
.as and when needed essentially.
So, already from these reference books, we
have in some
sense finished with two of them which is Pamela
McCorduck machines who think and
John Haugeland AI the very idea artificial
intelligence is the very idea, but some of
the
other books we will refer to as and when the
time comes essentially.
So, we will stop here and next on Friday when
we meet, we will have quality type shift and
start devising algorithms for simple search
that just we mentioned essentially.
.