So, we are looking at FOL and in particularly
we are looking at reasoning aspect. We
shall not have the time to look in to the
knowledge representation aspect too much here.
So, we will assume some simple representation
schema which means the choice of the
functions at we are talking about a set of
predicates a set of functions and the set
up
business.
Now, we saw 2 rules of infants; 1 was a universal
in sensation we said that a from for all
x and this is an instance of that. You can
p of a and then we saw generalization it says
that from p of a you can reduce the x p x.
So, in case you have a query of this kind
we
saw an example of that earlier. Now, in addition
to this there are also some rules of
substitution. So, for example, you can replace
for all x p x with there exist x naught p
x
and likewise it exist naught exist x p x equivalent
to for all x naught p x. So, these are
kind of commonsense rules. So, if you see
what we are saying here we are saying that
if
.it is naught the case that for every x from
property p or some predicate p is to it means
there must be some x for which p x is naught
true essentially.
So, if you move the naught across a quantifier
it changes the nature of the quantifier. If
you move a naught a across a universal quantifier
it becomes an existential quantifier.
The rest of the expression does naught change
it is like you are moving a naught inside,
but changing this likewise if you change the
move are naught across the existential
quantifier it becomes a universal quantifier.
So, again if you look at this; this is like
saying that for example, if p x stood for
something which is both even and odd. So,
this
left side is saying that there does naught
exist an x which is both even and odd which
is
equivalent to saying that for all x which
the case at they are naught even and odd.
So,
you can move them across on both sides. So,
these are rules of substitutions which I
quite useful in some situations we will see
some of them. And you might be familiar with
them they are known as de Morgan’s laws.
Also something which are use some times
that is that for example, if you have for
all x for all by p x y there p some predicate
this is
equivalent to for all y for all x p x y.
So, the quantifier of the same kind you can
change without changing the meaning of the
sentence. Likewise for there exist there exists
y there exist y; there exist x they would
be
similar, but if the quantifier of different
kind then you cannot do that. So, if you say
for
all x there exists the y p x y this is not
equivalent to saying that there exist a y
thus that
for all x p x y. So, you can try and think
of a counter example to show that this is
not the
case. So, for example, for every number x
there exist a number y which is bigger than
x.
So, p stands for bigger than or greater than
then this statement is true whereas this
statement say that there exist a y which is
greater than every number. So, which is
obviously not true essentially So, you cannot
switch 2 quantifies of different kind if you
do switched and the meaning change as the
truth value also will change. And you are
talking about something totally different
here and something totally different here.
Whereas, here there is no difference if they
have the same kind then you can switch the
quantifiers and it does not change the meaning.
Here we are saying that if you if you have
a negation sign you can move it inside
inwards towards the expression and what it
does? It changes the sign of the quantifier
.changes the nature of the quantifier. Universal
quantifier becomes existential and
existential becomes universal, which is why
I had mention in the last class at it is not
very easy to identify what is really the nature
of the quantifier. So, for example, if I make
a statement a it does not
let say we are talking about people and this
statement is saying
that they does not exist a x who is divine.
What is the nature of this variable x? Is
it a
existential variable or is it a universal
variable? And this becomes important, because
if
you remember the implicit quantifier for that
we discussed in the last class you can
replace a universally quantified variable
with a question mark and then it become
simplistic.
So, is this a universally quantified variable
or existentially quantified variable? So,
the
way to look your answer is right your way
the way to understand that is to push the
negation sign as much is possible. And then
look at what is outer most quantifier
essentially if you push a negation sign inside
it would become equivalent to saying that
for all x naught divine x. So, we are saying
that everyone is naught divine which is like
saying that no 1 is divine essentially. So,
this is the universally quantified variable.
So,
we can replace at he want to put at in implicit
quantifier form by saying naught divine x
I
putting a question mark that is a cementation
we are adopting between our sense. So, that
we do not have to write the quantifier we
do not have to process the quantifier when
we
are liking a program to do that we can just
keep those kind of variables as universal
variables. So, just a word about what you
do with existentially quantified variables
when
you are talking about implicit quantifier
from.
..
Let us forget a sentence like this there exist
x even x. So, it is saying that there exit
some
number which is an even number essentially.
The way to convert is into implicit
quantifier form and the process is called
skolemization after legation called skolem.
So,
well solemn who for us introduce these ideas
by replacing it with a constant even s k 12.
So, conventionally we may say we use a name
s k this is us again between us it does
naught impact the meaning of what we are writing
it is a constant. So, we so what are we
done? We have remove the quantifier and replace
it we replace x by something called s k
12. So, s k again is the sin honors or skolem
you could have use any constant as you as
far as you remember that it is a constant
which is been introduce in this process and
it
must naught be a constant which is being use
anywhere else. So, you cannot say a for
example, 0 if it is a constant or something
like that you must use some unnamed some
new name and treated as a constant after that.
Because if you look at the meaning of the
there is some number which is even and all
you have do saying is here that there some
numbers which I am calling s k 12. And that
is even essentially, because you may naught
really know what that number is, but you
can do that. If you have something like this
or statement like this for all x there exists
y p
x y they if you look at the what is the sentences
saying the sentences saying you should
always read the quantifier from left to right
that for every x there exist a y. So that
p x y
.is true essentially. So, for example, for
every x there exist search y which is greater
than
x essentially. So, that is an example that
we mentioned in the last class we can this
into
an implicit quantifier form by writing it
as p x s k eleven x. So, what are we saying
here
when we have a existentially quantified variable
inside scope of a universally quantified
variable then we are replacing that variable
with the function of the other variable and
the function is the skolem function.
So, this is the this is the skolem constant
of x So, what is this function we do not know
what that function is it is some function
and what we intent by the usage of the word
function here is that the value that the variable
can take is dependent upon the value that
x can take. So, again if p stands for greater
than
and the implication and the meaning of
this is at y is greater than x because the
meaning is always determine by us. It depends
upon the relation that you are talking about
essentially then what we are saying is that
for
every x you can choose a y. So, is that y
is greater than x so that y that it choose
depends
upon x and therefore, we can think of it as
a function of x. We do not know what that
function is, but it some function as for as
reasoning in concerned will treated as a
function and translate this into this statement.
So, this so in general off course if you have
for all x 1 for all x 2 for all x n p x 1
x 2 y
then you will translated to p of x 1. So,
I should put a question mark here because
x is the
universally quantified variable x 1 so this
y which is in the scope. So, there exist the
y
here is in the scope of all these universal
quantifier for x 1 to x n. So, this y become
to
skolem function of x 1 to x n. So, in general
you just look at what are the quantifiers
on
the on this side universal quantifiers on
this side and make that variable of function
of
that. If I had something like this there exists
x for all for all y p y p x y then I would
replace it with p s k 5 y. So, this entire
process of converting a sentence into implicit
quantifier from now it is we call it as skolemization
after this suggestions skolem
essentially.
..
So, in the last class, we had started looking
at forward chaining we had looked at the role
of modified modus ponens mindset that if you
have alpha prime and alpha implies beta
then you can produce beta prime from there.
And if you move from alpha prime to beta
prime the process is called forward chaining.
So, in forward chaining you have alpha
prime and then you can add beta prime in backward
chaining
you would not to show beta
prime. So, we use it is connection show beta
prime so we have sub goal now show alpha
prime. So, backward chaining we just started
looking at in the last class it works with
goals by goals. We mean something that we
want to show to be true a formula that we
want to show to be through. And looks for
implications of this kind alpha implies beta
so
basically it is using mod modus ponens in
a slightly different form. Or if you think
a
little bit about this you can see that what
backward chaining is the doing is this kind
of
modus may be that will become clearer as we
move forward that is a different rule of
infonants.
So, if we have our original Socratic argument
which said that man x implies mortal x and
in our database. So, this is there in the
database and this is there in the database
which is
man Socrates. And off course, you may have
as a date of birth less ignores that for the
movement and you want it to show that mortal
Socrates is true. Then forward chaining
would apply this modus modified modus ponens
rules and in this form and this form this
.thing. Whereas, backward chaining we are
not written the it in this form, but it says
that
which show beta prime man with alpha implies
beta you can reduce it to show alpha
prime essentially. So, show mortal Socrates
how does it is works if you recall we match
this with this with a unifier x is equal to
Socrates we will look at unification a little
later.
So, we apply this unifier to this and according
to this backward chaining process we
reduce this to show
man Socrates. So, let us put wholes inside
boxes so that we can
distinguish between goels and fact. So, this
is a fact this is a fact this is a goel; this
is a
goel and so on. So, what this off course,
it severe way to simplify to solve the goal
and
so see with that is present in the data base.
So, in this example, when you have this goal
of show that that man Socrates is true then
you simply look up the database.
And you will find that it true essentially
will in the movement we will look at how the
language prolog is basically doing this which
is it is doing backward chaining. And if it
if a fact is present in the database or in
your program prolog program it is really true
essentially. But the nice thing about reasoning
with logic is that we can ask a question
like is this formula true that it does there
exist the y such that mortal y is true this
is what
is given to us this is a database. And this
is a database even this database is that satement
true that there exist the y so that mortal
y is true. So, I intentionally use a different
variable here y and here an x here it is naught
really necessary forming to do that.
Because when you look at this statement then
it is saying that for there exist some y such
that pus that y is mortal. I could have Jolivel
said there exist some x such that x is mortal,
but because we want to set off keep above
formally spleen and a part and is a practice
that is necessary as we will see.
We use a different variable name which is
a is a goal noise know if I if this is my
goel
that show that this is a case. Then we invert
that is skolemization convention when you
are doing forward chaining a formula like
this a a universally a formula which has a
universally quantify variable is put with
a question mark here. Whereas, in backward
chaining an existential variable is denoted
by a question mark that is specifically in
backward chaining when you are talking about
show when you are talking about goels
sorry for goels the convention is reverse.
So, I will this as mortal y so again let be
that
when I write show mortal y in this form this
notation denotes and existentially contified
variable that is true only for variables which
occur inside goels. So, inside goels a
.convention is reverse essentially and the
next class we will see why that makes sense
but
you can try and guess.
So, I can ask a query existentially query
so this is now becoming like little bit like
a
database essentially activity. So, you have
some set of acts available to you and you
are
asking a query is there some entity with satisfy
certain properties. So, if you are saying
somebody like something like is there in employee
he wants more than 10000 rupees and
something and you get some results out of
that essentially. The difference between
something like RDBA BMS and using login is
that logic can make inferences on the way
essentially to retrieve answers for you. So,
when you asking a question that is there
somebody whose mortal in the knowledge base
or data base whatever you want to call it.
The knowledge base has only 2 statements in
our small knowledge base that Socrates is
the man and that all women are mortal a knowledge
base does not say that any one is
mortal any specific individual is mortal.
But backward chaining in particular and reasoning
in login in general allow you to ask
existential queries like this. And answer
those queries after a process of doing some
inferences making some direction. So, what
do we do? We match this show mortal x
with the right hand side of our statement
implication mortal x. So, we say x equal to
y is
the substitution you want so this becomes
mortal y. So, this case translated to show
man
y so our query is about. So, it is still an
existential query it is a easier someone whose
mortal gets translated into a sub query or
a subgoel which is easier some whose the man
essentially now that can be answer by the
database yes Socrates is the man. So, we can
communicate the query written the answer to
this query by saying yes y equal to Socrates
is the answer to your question. So, in the
last class, we had briefly mentioned that
you
could define. So, let say you want to define
grandfather or let say you want to define
grand pa grandparent.
..
So, you might want a statement like this a
for all x for all y grand. So, let say g m
stands
for grand ma x y and let say this means that
x is the grandmother of y implies. Let say
g
p stands for grandparent let say for some
reason we want to we want to this put this
rule
into our knowledge base or database, what
you want to call it? So, what you are saying
here is a grandmothers are grandparents then
you could have a role like for all x for all
y
g f and the same thing. Then you could have
a role which says a for all x for all y and
for
all z mother x y and father z x implies grandfather
z y. I could have a role of this kind
which says that for all x for all y for all
z if x is the mother of y and z is the father
of x
then z is the grandfather of y. So, you could
imagine that you have billing a database of
relationships where you are defining how what
is relationship means what is grandfather
abouts a grandmother abouts a grandparent
and so on and so forth. And then you should
be able to ask a query you should give us
database of acts. So, let say the basic database
only contents a mother child or let say parent
child and the gender of each person. So, I
could say a Jane is a parent of tom and Jane
is female and Tom is male.
So, I could have this kind of database. So,
there is only 1 relation parent child
relationship and general relationship then
you can define a mother at saying that x is
the
mother of y if x is the parent of y and x
is female. So, you could do all that kind
of staff
we will naught get into the details, but you
could have a knowledge base of this kind.
.And then you could ask a question how is
Peter related to Jane? For example, you know
then the system should find whether what is
the relation between them? Off course, you
cannot ask this very generic question is to
how it is related you can ask something like
whose Janes paternal uncle. For example, you
could ask such questions essentially let
say we in talking about grandparents whose
grandparent. And that is about to basic query
about then you can see that grandparent x
y can be solve in 2 is that either you are
a
grand pa x is the grandfather of y how x is
the grandmother of y? Then you could say x
is the grandfather of y if you could use this
as 1 rule which says that now you have to
a
bit careful here a father x z. So, I am just
using different name such to be consistent
here
and mother z y. And you can imagine that there
is a another rule which uses father and
father in both the places so that 2 possibilities
here.
So, you can see what is happening here that
is the space in which backward chaining
operates if you ask a query about something
is Jane the grandfather of Peter then this
system will apply. So, in backward chaining
you match with right hand side of an
implication and c is the left hand side can
become a subgoel or you can match either with
grandparent So, you can match either with
this rule or with this rule in both cases
grandparent will match. So, you could either
use r 1 or 2 if you called 1 rule will take
you here another rule will take you to grandmother.
So, either x is a grandfather of y or x
is a grandmother of y then grandfather if
x is a grandfather of y. It could be that
x is the
father of z who is the mother of y or it could
be that x is the father of z who is the father
of y both are possible. So, you have all these
question possibilities and the space that
backward chaining we have to search is that
is an ando trees essentially and what prolog
dose is backward it does depth first search
on that tree. So, let we rewrite this you
know I
am skipping in the step of skolemization which
in this cases simple because we are only
universally quantified variables. So, you
can just replace everything with a question
mark before that if you were to write this
in prolog you would write it as something
like
this g p.
..
So, prolog is this the different convention
pro see we are using a convention that
question mark stands for the variable and
something without a question mark stands for
a
constant. It should be a constant or existentially
quantified variable which is the skolem
constant or something like that it does not
matter. But that is a convention way using
prolog is this the different convention prolog
uses the case that when you have x and y
uppercase letters then it is a variable. So,
those of you why use prolog would know this
so let us stick to our convention which is
to use a question mark. So, we write the
consequent first and then we write the antecedent.
So, this same rule let us write it like
this
so what is happened I have taken this rule
and rewritten it like this are you I have
away the quantifiers I have convert it to
an implicit quantifier form. And I have the
order
in which you are writing in the normal rule
you write there antecedents on the left hand
side and the consequent on the right hand
side in this notation. I am write in the
consequent on the left hand side and the antecedent
on the right hand side and I have
change the direction of that.
So, have use an arrow instead of that sign
here. So, again those of you use prolog would
know that prolog this is something like this
instead of the arrow sign, but it means a
same thing that is only a matter of convention.
This is the easier for us to understand that
ther direction of implication is from right
to left. Then I would write the second
.statement as g p x y g m x y then g f x y
then somewhere I would write a statement for
g
m then g f which is what I have written here
which is that g m x y if a mother x y prolog
is it is a coma instead of. And so we will
also use a comma here the keep in mind that
this coma basically stands for in and so the
same set of statement to either writing in
a
different. We are not changing anything we
have into implicit quantifier from and we
are
writing it consequent on the left hand side
and antecedent on the right hand side.
And we are replacing ands by comas and this
kind of staff, but the statements are still
the
same they are still the same universally quantified
statements in logic. Somewhere down
there I would have let us say a mother Jane
Peter sorry oh ya a
x is the grandfather of y.
So, y is the mother of no sorry z is the mother
of y and x is the grandfather of x is the
father of z thanks. Somewhere I would have
a statement saying a mother Jane Peter for
example, and father Peter Jane and may be
other fact also, you recognize this as a prolog
programme. I hope prolog programme a statement
of these kinds now this is a restricted
form of logic, but we do not go into that
the restriction here is that the consequent
can
only be one predicate. You cannot have more
than you cannot have alls inside here and
so and so forth, but you can recognizes as
the prolog programme what does prolog do?
.
If I ask a query like is there or show grandparent
x. So, a let us say Peter z or something
.like that. The reason for writing things
in this invited form is, because it makes
a task of
matching simpler you always match with what
is on the left hand side in you have a
programme and the right hand side is the step
of making that inference. So, if I ask a
query like that is there someone whose peters
grandson or is there someone to be more
precise whose grandfather is Peter. Then prolog
starts looking from top to down trying to
match this with the things on the left hand
side in this example very conveniently. It
matches the first element it is in so when
it matches this it poses this as the goel.
So, at last whether Peter is a grandmother
of some z essentially So, it will translate
that
gole into the subgoel. So, backward chaining
we said was moving from right to left in
this notation. So, in this notation it is
moving from left to right. So, it basically
goes from
goels to subgoel ask that as a new query and
as you can imagine I should have something
like I have a I could use parent here parent
here. And then a female Jane and so on and
so
both I mean that is a data that I originally
said we have the Jane is female Peter is male
and Jane is male and that kind of staff. This
will get translated to g m grandmother Peter
z which intern will so essentially here going
down. So, because I written this rule first
this grandmother rule first it is like having
this rule on this side. So, it is going down
that
path so you can visualize what prolog is doing
as backward chaining and with a
particular strategy which is depth first.
And the way it is implemented here is that
the
first rule matches the that.
So, it will it is it tried this so just imagine
that that tree was lift from left to right.
So, it
would be going down the left side first. And
then it would eventually with naught be able
to show that Peter is a grandmother of z it
would back track. And then try this second
rule essentially which saying we go all the
way down and then try the other branch.
Exactly as we had when we looked at goel trees
with that first search first essentially.
So,
let us look at another a example that we have
considered earlier which is that of planning
and outing. So, if you recall when you are
looking at a goel trees the we had this task
of
planning and outing with a friend and outing
consisted of some 3 things that 1 evening
out 1 a entertainment and followed by dinner.
So, eventually you know you have to finds
values for these which your friend would be
happy with.
..
So, if you are remember it was something like
this that let say a let say let us call with
a
birthday plan I do not remember what we had
said that time. So, you have a birthday
plan made up of x y and z if you have an outing
plane of called x and entertainment plan
called y in a dinner plan for z. And then
you could say an outing plan is a valid plan
if it
is an outing and likes that is a f stands
for friend x likewise a other 2 plans entertainment
plan and a dinner pans. So, you could write
it as a prolog programme you could say that
this is how. So, you could add f as a parameters
so x comma f here comma f here comma
f here. So, let say f is f if stands for your
friend and let say your query is a essentially
that. So, let me write the query here a what
is the good birthday plan x y z and let say
your friends name is Peter and this is my
query.
So, that question mark after this what backward
chaining will do is exactly the same
thing that we did here earlier it would. So,
this is birthday plan then it tries to find
an
outing and entertainment and dinner or may
be this is have entertainment. We are said
movie in the last class it does naught matter
and below this would be ando tree outing let
say beach or moll and things like that. And
entertainment could be some in movie a or
movie b or movie c and restaurant could be
some restaurant d or e or f and below that.
off course, you have the facts like whether
your friend f likes going to the beach some
statement like
beach Peter it must be present in your in
your knowledge base. Because
.that is how will instead of asking in a friend
you are saying that is there a statement like
that in my database already.
So, that attention that I want to draw to
you here is to the same problem that we
encounter. Now, you must recall what does
happening there you are searching this ando
tree and well initially we had pouse it as
a simple odd tree. But what were saying is
that
let say that you decide that you want to go
to a go to the beach you ask your friend shell
we go to the beach and then you are doing
a depth first search. So, you try all these
options 1 by 1 you say shell we go to this
movie a or shell we go to this movie b or
shell
we go to this movie c and then try all combinations
of this. So, for example, a beach and
a and b then beach and a and e then beach
and a and f and let say all fail. So, what
is
happening here in backward chaining is that
you are doing this subgoel promulgation.
And
so the way prolog does is there it goes from
top to down and left to right so given
trees of goel outing and entertainment and
dinner. It will first try outing try to find
a
value for that that say beach then entertainment.
And then try to find a value for that let
say a and then dinner and try to find a value
for
that d and at that point let us say it fails
and say that no this is naught a good birthday
plan. So, it will back track and try e here
so it is still be in this goal, but it would
try a
different value. So, whenever back tracking
happens it happens in these same directions.
So, when it is back tracking here it goes
up 1 step when it is back tracking here it
goes
up. Well, where is back tracking here goes
down 1 step and it is back tracking here it
comes f 1 step. So, it tries the first option
for dinner and the second option for dinner
and
the third option for dinner. And everything
fails you do naught want to do repeat this
same search again for a different option of
b if you can figure out somehow that beach
is
the. So, we had mention the term dependency
directed back tracking there. So, in some
systems like in satisfaction system that is
kind of done automatically the system keeps
track of what is the dependency? But in a
system like this in logic or the implementation
of logic call prolog the language gives the
user ability to control back tracking.
So, instead of writing a statement like this
what you can do in prolog is to instead of
this
you write the statement as follows that a
birthday plan. So, let me just use this b
x y z f if
outing plan then you use a special symbol
cut then and entertainment plan any user
.special symbol and then a dinner plan. So,
instead of 3 subgoels you have added 2 extra
subgoels these are which special subgoels
is prolog allows you. And so those you have
use it could know the this is the cut operator
as it is called. And what it does is there
is
basically a device given to the user or the
programmer. If you want to say to control
back
tracking and what it basically saying is that
if you are going to back track from this to
this side. Then do not try a new value for
this really jump back to the original goel.
And
you have without going to the details I just
want to point out that the cut feature of
prolog is basically use to control this huge
amount of back tracking that one doing in
an
unconstraint search.
So, what prolog does forward backward chaining
is allows you to do is to allows it to ask
existential queries you can ask some query
about is Peter the grandfather of somebody
or
who is Janes grandfather or you could defined.
And maybe that is a good exercise for
you to define the ancestor of so when is an
x in ancestor of y. Then you could ask a
query whether you know Jane is an ancestor
of someone or things like that and the
system will search in your database. It may
it will make inferences by jumping across
such implication signs and eventually dig
out an answer for you. This process is often
called as which is more than what a database
system give you database system gives you
retrieval in an efficient faction. But it
does not do deductions on the way prolog allows
it
you deductive retrieval and in that sense
it is more powerful than the RDBMS system.
And in fact prolog is the complete programming
language anything you can do in java.
For example, you can do in prolog essentially
and logic programming in general is also a
complete programming paradigm essentially
it had it is limitations. So, I had hinted
about that when I said that there is only
a limitation in the format in which you can
write
prolog program it works with only a subset
of logical statements which are known as a
which a which basically say that there can
be only 1 consequent in any implication
statement. So, it is not complete I refer
you back to this problem of 3 blocks that
we had
mentioned in the last class, we are said that
a is on b and b is on c and a is green and
c is
naught green. And we are said that is it true
or does there exist 2 blocks x and y such
that
x is on y and x is green and y is not green
in we cannot solve that problem using in the
forward chaining or backward chaining.
.So, in that sense forward and backward chaining
are naught complete and remember that
when you talk about logical systems we are
interested in sound and complete system. So,
everything that we are doing here is sound,
because it is based on sound rules of
inference it is only the queue completeness
which is the question. So, in the next class
which is the last class of our course, we
will look at this use of resolution method
which
we saw for proportional logic and apply to
in ((Refer Time.) logic. And see that
that particular problem which I will discuss
again in the next class can be solved using
resolution method essentially. So, on the
way we will need to just have a quick look
at
the unification algorithm which is this algorithm
which is used for matching a to terms
like this which is necessary in the implicit
quantifier form that we are using here. So,
I
will stop here and will meet in the next class
for the last time in this course.
.