So, let us continue with the study
of FOL. In the class, we defined the language,
essentially
the syntax and symmetries. Now, let us look
at how you can do reasoning or inferences
with
possible logic, but before we do that let
us just recap that, a language is defined
by the sets of
RFC. So, let us say that r is
a symbol called g and very small language,
F is a symbol a 2
symbols, let us say one is called s and one
is called c and c contains of one symbol,
let us s
say is called e. So, we said that we defined
a mapping I to define the meaning of these
3 sets
these things essentially.
.
So, this mapping is called interpretation
mapping, but we also call an interpretation
that is use
the symbol I is defined as a domain and an
interpretation mapping. So, an interpretation
of a
set of sentences or a language is in terms
of the domain about which, the language is
making
statements and a mapping which tells you what
does is predicate symbol mean, what does
each function symbol mean and what does each
constant symbol mean essentially.
So, whenever a sentences alpha is true under
an interpretation and we defined the symmetric
in the last class. We say that is interpretation
entails alpha. So, it is a notation that we
use and
.we talked about the motion of valid sentences.
So, a valid sentence is something which is
true
in all interpretations, which means you can
choose any domain and any mapping function
and
the sentence will be true. So, basically the
set of tautologies that we can talk about.
So, for
example, the system that we discussed earlier.
Satisfiable sentences are those which are
true under some interpretations and unsatisfiable
sentences are those which are never true.
So, an example of unsatisfiable sentences
would be
for example, x not equal to x. So, such a
atomic formula can never be true essentially.
I think
which we can also read as write as x which
is the same thing.
.
It is just a short form that we have used
to write in. So, given a set of sentences
s we say that
a interpretation which means a domain an interpretation
is a model for s. If every s belongs to
s interpretation imply this sentence s. So,
if you write a set of formulas or sentences
in a
given language and then you get find the domain
and an interpretation which makes all those
sentences true. Then we say that we have found
a model for those set of sentences. Logics
are
always tried to say this is the logic system
and does it have a model essentially.
You means can you is it true in some domain
and some interpretation it is just to for
the sake
of complete lesson. We not really go into
too much detail there. So, let us look at
this small
example of a small language which is got one
relation symbol which, we have called g and
two function symbols we have called s and
c and one constant symbol, which we have called
e essentially. Now, we can have one interpretation
I 1, which does the following.
..
Let us say domain is equal to national numbers
and I can say my constant. So, this is the
mapping I maps to 0, the number 0. This maps
to successor plus 1, this let us say this
is of I i
t 2 and this is of ii t 1, this maps to plus
or multiplication it does not matter some
binary
operation on this. This map to greater than
let us say. Then I can write statements for
example, I can say
successor of e greater than successor of successor
of e. I would use this as
the prefix and then said the arguments are,
but I used so this variations.
.
So, this is the predicate symbol and these
are 2 arguments, which are terms and the terms
are
.used constructed using the function symbols
and the constant symbols here. They are no
variables in my sentence, but I can add variables
1 of them could be. So, I could write for
all
x greater than x e. I am not talking about
the truth value of these sentences. I am not
claiming
that this sentences is true or this sentence
is true. Always saying is that we can interpret
what
does the sentence mean and the meaning is
given by a choosing a domain and choosing
an
interpretation mapping.
Then any sentence in my language here which
I have define the syntax, the sentence like
this
is essentially saying as we all know that
the successor of 0 is greater than the successor
of
successor of 0. Of course, it is not a clue
set will, but that is what it saying. So,
we can
understand the meaning of the sentence and
this is saying that every x is greater than
0, which
may or may not be true or which is not true,
but that that is not the point. The point
is not we
are not talking about the truth value here,
we are talking about the meaning of the semantics
of the syntax.
.
As the same time I can choose a different
interpretation which is let us say streams
over
alphabet a and b and then I can say that this
now this is i 2 maps to empty string, let
us say
lambda. This maps to concatenation, this maps
to successor in lexicographic order and this
let
us say maps to longer than.
So, the point I want to really emphasis here
is that a language is one thing and what it
means
or what is the semantics of those sentences
in that language is totally another thing.
It is
.depended upon the interpretation. So, a same
expression like this which is defined in my
language would mean one thing if I am talking
about numbers. It would mean a different
thing if I am talking about strings, it could
mean a totally different thing if I am talking
about
people. For example, I could map these things
to some relation between people. So, that
is
one point which, I really want to emphasis
that and this is something which is very central
to
in fact writing programs as well as the study
of logic.
.
So, we cannot stop emphasizing the fact that
everything that we do in logical reasoning
is
based on forms essentially. It is not ma based
on meaning essentially any proof procedure
that I have, if you remember it says I have
a rule set of rules of inference, I gave a
set of
premise sand I keep adding new formulas. It
is purely based on form it does not matter
what
we are talking about numbers or they are talking
about strings or they are talking about
something else.
..
So, the logical system is formal and the logic
is basically captures valid forms of reasoning.
So, this we have talked about earlier as well,
so it is it says that when is an inference
or sound
inference, which we call as deduction essentially.
How do we define deduction? Logic is
basically concerned with making sound inferences
and we have seen as to when can a rule of
inference we sound. For example, it is based
on tautological implications or tautological
equivalences and so on. If you build logic
around sound rules you will get a sound logic
it,
but everything is formal essentially.
.
.So, what is the reasoning mechanism that
we can use in first set of logic. We already
have a
set of rules that we have spoken about. So,
for example, still applies it still says the
same
thing that if we have alpha, if we have alpha
implies beta, then you can derive beta. Thus,
same rule we can carry forward to first set
of logic because it is only talking about,
how to
interpret this implication sign essentially
even that we have essentially. It not really
worried
about things like variables and so on.
So, it does not matter what alpha beta is.
As long as they are sentences this rule applies
essentially, but we also need some new rules
of inference to take care of the fact that
we have
talking about quantifiers. The most important
rule is call universal instantiation
and what it
says is that if you have. So, I will write
it as top and bottom if you have a formula
of the kind
for all x and anything else inside this, but
which contains an x essentially.
.
So, let us say an alpha with some x somewhere
essentially, it could have other terms also.
If
you have a formula of this kind, you can have
a formula of this kind alpha which the term
replaced by a where a belongs to a set of
constants. So, what we are saying is that
you can
always instantiate a universally quantified
sentence to a sentence, which uses the constant
essentially. So, let us see an example of
this. So, if you go back to the argument that
we were
talking about.
The argument was all men are mortal, Socratic
is the man
and you want to show that Socratic
is mortal. We had made an observation that
we cannot do this in propagation logic and
we
.need something more expressive almost stronger
to talk about this essentially. Now, we have
the machinery for doing that. So, let us first
translate these sentences into first logic
and this
is an exercise which you must have done i
am sure at some point of time, but if you
not done
you must practice a little bit, but you can
translate this into a language as follows.
.
For all x, man x implies mortal x where, man
and mortal predicates. Since unary predicates
they basically define a subset of the universal
discourse of the domain. What this statement
is
saying that, if any x belongs to this or any
x satisfies the predicate man, it must satisfy
the
predicate mortal x essentially. In other words
if x belongs to man interpretation, then x
belongs to predicate man. So, what is this
man interpretation?
Basically, it is a set in my domain subset
in my domain which defines unary relation
of man
essentially. So, when you say man x we say
that x belongs to the set of thing, which
is call
men. So, recall that unary relation is basically
a subset relation essentially of the of the
u
universe of discourse essentially. You can
see the same thing as saying that man is the
subset
of mortal i. So, this statement is essentially
saying that the set of men and here off course
we
mean set of human beings is the subset of
the set of things which have mortal essentially.
That is just set in English language we say
that all men are mortal in FOL we will write
it like
this, but the semantics of that is that the
set which corresponds to the set man. The
mapping
of this is a unary relation this is a subset
you see call man I and essentially we are
saying this.
This sentence we can map to man Socratic and
we want to show that mortal Socratic. Now,
.with this rule of universal in sensation
which we often abbreviate to UI. We can produce
the
formula which is very useful for us which
is that I can instantiate this formula by
substituting
x equal to this. So, off course I should have
clarify here the belongs to set constants.
So, that
is a
inference step of UI and then off course this
is the inference step of mortals followings.
.
Now, having used universal instantiation I
have a formula which is very nice because
it is
saying alpha implies beta and then I have
alpha and I can use which is this essentially.
Again
to emphasis the fact that it has nothing do
with the factor it is man or it is mortal,
it could be
all students have bright or all leafs are
green or all birds are small anything.
Any such statement if you have, if you accept
the first statement, if you accept the second
statement, we must accept the third statement
that is all logic is telling us. It is form
of
reasoning this form of reasoning is valid
essentially. If this is true and this is true
this must
necessarily will be true that is a lotion
of ((Refer Time.). What motion of proof is?
This gives us a way of producing the sentence
syntactically without looking at the meanings
of things essentially.
As you can see if you want to talk about mechanizing
this process, then there is a little bit of
guess work involved there. What is this value
of that? I should substitute essentially.
Off
course we look at this whole picture and we
can see that a must be Socratic in that case
of
that x must be Socratic. Off course I will
have this useful thing, but never the less
if you are
doing the forward search can of a process
and you are saying I have all these universally
.formulas, how do I proof something which
means you have to keep.
So, remember that the basic mechanism is pick
a rule pick a piece of data for which the
rule
is applicable and apply the rule essentially.
So, this universally statement could be applied
to
100s of people. Every element in my database
I could say Socratic is mortal, Ram is mortal
whoever essentially, anybody you give me a
name and I will say he is mortal that is why
I
could prove that thing. So, this off course
should trigger this thoughts about forward
reasoning versus backward reasoning for you
and we will look at that little bit, if not
today
then we will tomorrow.
The same kind of strategy is come into play.
When you do forward reasoning you have a
choice of applying so many rules of inference
so much data that we have whereas, if you
are
doing backward reasoning, then you know what
you want to show true, but the thing is that
we need a role of inference which allows us
to. We need to be able to use backward
reasoning here.
So, if you remember as you saw during planning,
backward reasoning, backward state space
search for planning and into some kind of
problems essentially. So, are they similar
problems
here, we will have to see. Now, for a sake
of completeness there another rule which is
called
generalization. What this rule says that,
if you have a formula of this fine alpha a,
you can
replace it by a formula of the kind there
exist x, x.
.
.So, if I have the statement in my database,
which says is Ramesh is bright, then I can
generalized to say that their exist someone
who is bright essentially. Why do we need
this
because sometimes the goal may be to show
that there exist something, something, something
essentially. So, an example which is given
in one of the text book is as follows. It
says that
you are given the following facts on a b on
b c green a, not green c. So, this is what
is given
to you the set of premises, the set s of sentences
that a is on b, b is on c, a is green and
c is not
green.
.
Your goal is to show in exist
on x then exist on y that on x y. So, the
goal is we asking
whether this formula is true. So, this is
given to us, a is on b, b is on c and you
can off course
do any interpretation of the set of formulas.
The most natural interpretation which comes
to
main is the blocks follow interpretation and
where green stands for a color. So, let us
accept
that, but the thing is to show that this formula
is true, we are not going to rely on the meaning
of those sentences essentially.
You want to show that this formula which is
there exist x exist y such that on x y and
green x
and not green y these true. So, what does
this formula true or not true? First of all
what is the
intuition whether it is true or not true and
secondly, off course the question that we
will ask is
can we prove it. Remember the motions of soundness
and completeness that does a logical
system prove every true formula essentially.
So, first let us let me ask is this formula
true or not true. You people have done the
career
.course should not answer what is the intuition
says? So, let us look at the meaning it saying
that there is a block on another block and
the block above is green and the block below
is not
green. Given to us is three blocks the top
most block is green, the bottom most block
is not
green nothing is said about the block in between.
So, I will leave it as a small exercise for
you to work out, but this is the kind of thing
you may
want to prove which is while sometimes you
may need a rule which say something like that
essentially. So, this is the process of forward
chaining we are looking at. So, forward
chaining says basically stringing together
a set of facts by moving from the left inside
of a
rule where, we are using more exponents. So,
the right end side given alpha, you are chaining
into beta then given beta there is beta implies
gamma then you chaining into gamma.
So, you moving in the forward direction essentially
what is given to you and what can be
derived. You move in the forward direction
and this what we have doing here essentially.
Even this formula we can derive this formula,
given this you can derive this. So, you have
moving in the forward direction. The first
thing you want to do is avoid this guess work.
You
do not want to use this rule of universal
because if you go to use it directly, then
you would
end up during lot of guess work as to what
should I instantiate the values of the variable
tool
essentially.
It is clear if you look at this formula is
that, you know here we are talking about x
here we are
talking about. So, it make sense to somehow
say that I am instantiate x to because while
looking at both this formulas. So, the difference
is the universal instantiation rule only looks
at this formula then says I must produce this
whereas, if you also look that is then you
would
know the you have to produce this essentially.
So, let us define a new role which combines
these 2 steps into 1 step, but to that let
us first
modify our representation little bit to make
it simpler for us. To do that we define something
in what is called an implicit quantifier form.
So, we want to express our formulas without
actually lighting down the quantifies because
remember that if you going to write programs
to process these sentences, then you have
to in worry about how to interpret the quantifies
and so on. So, you will have to parse them
in you know construct quantifies and then
take
them as a stuff.
..
So, instead what is normally done is to express
the quantifies implicitly and for today’s
class
we will only look at the universal quantify
because that is all we have here. We are not
worry
about the existential quantify in the next
class for a universal quantifier. So, if x
is universally
quantified.
.
So, for the moment let us assume that we know
the nature of a variable. So, in our logic
that
we have defined there only 2 kinds of quantifiers
and in the sentences there are no free
variables. So, start with there are only bound
variables and variables are bound either by
a
.universal quantifier or by a existential
quantifier. So, let us assume that we know
the nature
of the quantifier and we can somehow say that
is a universally quantified variable, which
is
easy in sentences like this, but in more complex
sentences we will see later it is not.
So, let us assume that we can do that than
in the implicit quantifier form, we simply
place it
with x souse the same symbol x. So, this is
just a convention which says that I am going
to
use the question mark to stands for a variable,
which is universally quantified, which means
I
will now rewrite this whole thing as follows
that man x implies mortal x.
.
So, instead of writing is like that I am writing
like this, but it does not mean that i have
changed the sentence, the sentence is still
the same except that the universal quantifiers
implicit. I have indicated it in my sentence
by putting a question mark before the variable,
which tells we that this variable all these
occurrences of this variable has one occurrence
of a
universal quantifier before the sentence is
implicit. It is their like in that, but it
is implicit
essentially.
You can see that this is basically motivated
to simplify the processing that you do when
you
write a program to do forward chaining essentially.
So, given this and given this
you can see
that it is becoming a little bit simpler to
do this processing. Somehow if I could have
a
version of more exponents, which did not require
an exact match, but which allowed us to
substitute anything for a universally quantified
variable, then life would become simpler.
I
would say I am trying to match this with this,
how can I do this?
..
If you can simply say x equal to you can do
it and then this will become like the step
of
universal instantiation. Again I would like
to emphasis, I am not doing it independently
first I
am now looking at a modified version, which
will have this built into it essentially.
So, in
some sense I know the target to which I want
to instantiate because I have this fact here
essentially.
So, this rule is call in that calling modified
and the rule is as follows. It says that let
us say m,
m p and it says that from alpha prime
and alpha implies beta, beta prime where,
a
substitution
let us say theta applied to alpha gives alpha
prime. So, we are saying the substitution
is a
function which when you applied to any formula,
then it replaces some occurrences of
variables in that formula with other occurrences
essentially. So in fact, when applied alpha
implies beta, it gives you alpha prime implies
beta prime or it gives you alpha implies beta
whole prime.
What is the substitution? A substitution is
basically a set of variable value pairs and
in our
case, the variable is x and the value that
is Socratic that is the substitution we are
interested
in. What does it do? It says that when I apply
theta to alpha implies beta I am looking at
this
specific example. In general if you apply
theta to any formula this is just one kind
of a
formula which we have interested in. It gives
you alpha prime implies beta prime and how
does it give you that it substitutes.
So, what is the substitution telling we it
saying that you substitute every occurrence
of x with
.Socratic essentially. So, if I apply the
substitution to this if this is my alpha implies
beta, then
my alpha prime implies beta prime is this.
So, this is alpha implies beta and this becomes
alpha prime implies beta prime under the substitution
theta is equal to x.
.
So, how we are saying is that the substitution
tells you what to substitute for the set of
variables named in the substitution. In this
substitution only one variable is named which
is x
and a very simple substitution is given which
is, but it could be anything else. I could
substitute any for example, arbitrary term
for it I could say the grandfather of which
means
let us say the father of mother of Socratic.
That is a term remember
that is also a term I could
have substituted this in my formula, then
I would have formula which says if grandfather
is
the man, then grandfather is mortal.
I would have got that statement instead the
substitution that I am doing here is which
for x.
So, I am getting this statement that if is
a man then is mortal that is alpha prime implies
beta
prime. I already have alpha prime here which
has got inside. So, now I can apply more
directly essentially. So, this whole 2 step
process is collapse into one step process
in this
modified exponents rules where, thus instantiation
is taking place somewhere inside by
means of a substitution.
It is saying that if you given a formula alpha
prime and a formula alpha implies beta, if
you
can somehow found find the substitution which
will make these two equal. So, the technical
term you uses the unifier, which we will study
in the next class, but for the moment just
let us
.think of it does a substitution, which will
make this formula equal to this formula which
is
what the universal instantiation step is doing.
So, the technical way of saying that is if
you can unify alpha prime with alpha and you
can
always unify by means of a substitution, which
means you make them look the same. Then
you can imply beta prime directly, which means
apply the same substitution to beta. What
is
beta here, mortal x man x implies mortal x.
So, this is alpha and this is beta and this
is alpha
prime. I can make alpha prime and alpha the
same by saying applying the substitution x
equal
to this. This rule says apply the same substitution
to the right hand side of the expression and
directly infra mortal.
.
So, this step is, this is the modified rule
that says that I can substitute directly here
jump to
this conclusion in some sense without having
into go through that step of instantiation
explicitly, but this is a simple example.
It has unary predicate with only one argument
and so
it is easy to understand. In general modifies
says that given any alpha prime and anything
of
alpha implies beta.
In fact, I do not need have to call it alpha
I could call it gamma. I can unify gamma with
alpha, but it traditionally we see alpha prime
in alpha. If you can somehow make them the
same, then go higher and make the inference
and apply the same way of making them the
same to the conclusion as well essentially.
So, apply the same substitution to beta to
get beta
prime.
.So, if I have a simple database and by simple
I mean, I have only statements of this kind
something x implies something x. So, b b x
implies 2 x which one let us say there is
only 1
variable could have more than 1 variable essentially.
So, you could have a statement which
says friend x y implies friend y x essentially,
then I could say Suresh is the friend of Ramesh.
I could infer that Ramesh is the friend of
Suresh essentially by applying this rule.
So, if I have
a simple database of the kind where, I can
apply modest exponents rule then I have a
simple
mechanism for keep applying rule repeatedly
till i generated formula that
I have essentially.
Let us assume we are using only modified modest
exponents because our data is of that
nature, but still the question of which facts
to apply to is still open. You still do not
know
there is no sense of direction saying that
this is an inference I should make. So, the
same
problem of huge branching factor in the forward
direction exist in forward chaining
essentially. So, can we do backward chaining.
So, what would backward chaining be like.
So,
let me just give you a hint here and we will
take it up the next class.
So, backward chaining needs to distinguish
between statements which are there in the
database. Let us call them facts and statements
which you want to show to be true essentially.
So, forward chaining is simple you have a
set of facts given to you which includes no
rules
and statements like all these kind of statements.
You can keep adding new statements and you
can terminate when the required statement
is produced essentially.
If I want to do backward chaining what is
the mechanism that I have been used to do
backward chaining. So, let me take the same
rules, but I want to express something like
this.
To show what I am trying to highlight here
is that you need to distinguish between what
you
have and what you do not have.
..
What you have is the set of facts, what you
do not have is something you want to show
to be
true. So, we could use a marker this is only
for programming purposes. It is not part of
the
language. It says that if you have a goal
beta prime and if you have a rule of the kind
alpha
implies beta. So, we call this a rule left
hand side, right hand side, then you can replace
the
goal of showing beta prime with the goal of
showing alpha prime essentially.
If you implementing this we will need to keep
the facts that we have in one set of formulas,
which are separated from the goals that we
are trying to show. So, we can do that simply
here
on the board by putting a marker called show.
So, when you have marker called show it
means, it is a goal it is not something which
is true. It is something you want to show
to be
true and this is saying that to show that
beta prime is true, if you have a rule of
a kind alpha
implies beta and you can do this unification
process.
So, you can find the substitution then you
can reduce it to a sub goal of saying show
that
alpha prime is true or does a translate to
our problem here. It says that if you want
to show
that Socratic is mortal and if you have a
rule which says all men are mortal, then substitute
or
replace the goal of showing that Socratic
is mortal with the goal of showing that Socratic
is a
man. This is the process of backward chaining.
So, from goals you are moving to sub goals
essentially. Now, you can see that this process
is
going to become a little bit complicated.
If my left inside had more than one statements.
So
for example, you can define a grandfather
by saying that x is a grandfather of y, if
x is a
.father of z and z is the parent of y, you
could define it like this. Now to show that
x is a
grandfather of y, you would have to show both
those things that show that there exist a
z
whose father is x and there exist I mean that
same z is a father of y essentially.
So, grandfather x y if father x z and p stands
for parent z y. In the forward direction I
would
have this fact somewhere that says Peter is
the father of marry and marry is a mother
of John,
then I can show that Peter is a grandfather
of john by going in a forward direction. In
a
backward direction I have to put and here.
So, you can reduce the sub goal to these 2
sub
goals, but there is and here essentially.
May be there is another rule which says that
grandfather of x y. So, let me say instead
of
parent I have mother here father x z father
z y I have 2 separate rules. This rule says
that x is
a father of father of y, this rule says that
x is a father of mother of y essentially.
For some
reasons I have these 2 separate rule, then
you can see that to show that Peter is a grandfather
of John I could either use this rule or I
could use this rule. So, you can see that
it is becoming
an AND-OR tree essentially.
You could either use one rule or you could
use another rule essentially. So, backward
chaining has this complication. You know that
how do you get that to think like this. So,
essentially it maps to AND-OR tree and we
will look at that in the next class essentially.
Essentially, what backward chaining is saying
is that from a goal you can move to a sub
goal
essentially.
So, I will stop here and in the next class
we will look at this process of finding the
substitution here and there is a very nice
algorithm call unification algorithm which
some of
you must have studied for doing so. We will
see how this kind of AND-OR trees is a tackled.
We will also briefly mention as to this kind
of backward chaining process is what really
this
language prolonged does. Just to complete
the course may be we will look at the resolution
method in first set of logic and the motivation
for that method can be this problem that we
have here.
..
So, let me reveal to you that this sentence
is indeed true, but it cannot be proven either
by a
forward chaining or backward chaining. Those
methods are not complete, but resolution
method we showed this or at least we talked
about it. In proportional logic case also
it is a
complete method essentially which is why it
is so attractive essentially. So, we will
end the
course with resolution method for first set
of logic, which is in the next two classes
I think.
.