So far in this course, we have looked at mostly
search base methods and 1 form of the
other. But if you look at human beings; human
beings are essentially knowledge base
creature by this I mean that we do not we
very rarely do search all we well rare rarely
do
tried and other unless off course you are
doing research or something which is the
different matter. But by enlarge in everyday
activity we look at a problem or we look at
a
situation and we instinctively do something.
And when say instinctively what I really mean
is that we already have lots of experiences
toward in our heads and we also have lot of
rules that we have acquired over a period
of
time. We know exactly what to do. For example,
if you it is raining and if you happen
caring and a umbrella you instinctively open
it. You do not plan and say that if you open
in umbrella and keep it over your head then
you will not get wet. In fact, you do not
even
reason about a goal saying that you have a
goal of not being wet. So, lot of time we
simply use knowledge. So, we want to now spend
the rest of the semester looking at
knowledge based approaches. In particular
we will look only at a specific kind of
knowledge representation which is logic base,
but let us start off with the more general
representation.
..
So, essentially you can associate the word
knowledge bit to know that you know you
know facts you know how to solve problems;
you know how to play tic tac to you know
how to ride a bicycle. All kinds of things
are known to you essentially. And if a agent
is
to interact in a with it is world or with
it is surroundings in an intelligent way.
Then an
agent needs to represent its surroundings
create a model of its surroundings if you
all and
reason with that model. Not necessarily a
model which reflects how the world is around
us but some form of representation which helps
us solve problems. So, if we remember
that we had said that when these philosopher
2 three hundred years ago they were
.wondering about what is mind? What is thinking?
They said Hume and deccart 10 hobs
they said thinking is meaningful; meaningful
manipulation of symbols. So, if you recall
this we are sought coming to this approach
of what we mean by thinking.
Off course, when we did search we also did
meaningful manipulation of symbols in the
sense that we created a represent representation
of the state space. We created the
representation of the move and we move sought
did some manipulation which would
take us from the start state to the goal state.
But now, we are talking in the more general
sense so manipulation of symbols also we call
the physical symbol system hypothesis
which we had talked about in the very beginning
saimon and newel. They said the ability
to manipulate physical symbol systems is sufficiency
to create intelligent behavior and
what we meant by physical symbol systems?
So, symbol systems of first we understand
these are structures of symbols by physical
what they meant was that they obey some
kind of laws of reasoning. So, which is also
serve ties of a this idea of manipulation
of
symbols know only question that remains is
about meaningful.
We will try and get some insides into this
as we progress not necessarily today, but
may
be in the next week. But let us focus on the
fact that what we mean by thinking is
representation of our situation or the world
or the surroundings and the goals and the
desires and anything. And thinking basically
means manipulation of those
representations if you sought of bring it
down to simple computer science term. It
basically means we want to do some kind of
representation data structures we want to
device and wherever we have data structures
we need to have algorithms. So,
manipulation of symbols would be done by algorithms
and in that sense the word
physical fits in there is that is that we
have well defined ways of manipulating symbols
which obey some laws. Essentially what is
the kind of knowledge that we carry in our
heads? So, simplest is natural language; natural
language is a medium for representing
knowledge and even exchanging knowledge essentially.
Of course, it is started off as a media of
a exchanging, but as people device means of
writing and printing books. It also became
a means of representing knowledge so that
somebody else could read it as a different
point of time. Why do not we use natural
language as a representation mechanism for
knowledge? The main reason has we
.probably have discussed earlier is that it
is ambiguous it is not straightforward to
understand what 1 is saying in an ambiguous
un ambiguous passion essentially. Because
languages is so first of all we can so say
the same thing in many different ways. And
secondly if you express something if you utter
something for example, if I say she
walked over towards a terminal. It is not
clear entirely what I mean by this sentence
or if
I say he went towards the bank again it is
not clear what I mean.
Because the words bank and words terminal
have more than 1 sense is more than 1
meaning essentially a terminal could be terminal
in a lab a computer terminal. It could
also mean a terminal in a airport essentially
so we do not know what we are talking
about. Likewise bank could mean a river bank
or it could mean a financial institution
this, only word which have different senses,
but other things like verbs also have
different sense. We saw an example time fly’s
like an arrow I think we had discuss it the
beginning of the course is a sentence which
for us seem some ambiguous. But if you
what to look at it this passionately without
the background context at we always carry
in
a our head it has more than 1 pass essentially.
And we discussed may be 1 or 2 of them
may be I would encourage you to look at them
again. But for various reasons natural
language is not attest yet a medium of knowledge
representation though even eventually
we hope that we will acquire our machines
with enough language processing facility.
Capability is to talk us in our languages
in English, Hindi, Tamil whatever and represent
knowledge also in those language is essentially.
Then we do not need to program in C
plus plus python ogg in our any such thing
you could simply talk to them in English that
is way in the future we saw other mechanisms
for representation. So, I am talking about
representation here it could be an natural
language, we a seen rules already essentially
when we studied rule base systems we said
that you know you could capture heuristic
knowledge in the form of rules. And then use
that in fact it turned out at rule base
systems has become like a programming language
in itself essentially. We also saw
something similar to rules when we were talking
about planning. The planning operators
had the similar flavor about rules at there
was a well defined language in which you
could describe the preconditions. And then
an action basically linked preconditions to
post conditions essentially there was a well
defined language.
.So, we were moving towards move systematic
base of representing things they could be
other mechanism for representing things. We
could be have tables for example, log
tables I do not know how many of you have
used log tables. But when I was a student
that was the primary means of which you needed
to carry to your exams know if you
wanted to do some sophisticated computation
you needed a log table and something
called a slide rule. I do not know whether
you have heard about it but these are
representation of knowledge in some sense
essentially then he tells you that for this
number the logarithm is this for this number
the logarithm is this and so on essentially.
Then we have knowledge embedded in procedure
at typically and imperative program
contains a lot knowledge which is not explicit
essentially. You may have written a
program to create the, I to compute the Eigen
values or Eigen vectors or to find routs of
an equation.
All these programs contain knowledge which
is your knowledge which has been put into
the program. And hence for when the program
runs basically it is executing your
instructions knowledge is not explicit essentially.
And I do not know whether we had
discussed is sometime but the view that was
performed by Kowalski Robert. Kowalski;
he use to teach in imperial college London
1970s, he was the invent of 1 of the inventors
of the programming language. The idea of logic
program he said that a program is equal
to logic plus control
that the program compute a program has 2 components.
1 is what
you might call as business logic or the domain
logic or the problem solving strategy. And
the other is control essentially what statements
to execute in a program essentially and
the view in an logic programming community
is that control should be left to a system
in
our case and inference engine.
So, prolog will basically as you will see
rather basically does depth first search over
a
representation, but we have seen a variation
which is system which is the forward
chaining system where you write rules and
everything that you want to says express in
the form of rules. So, we can associate logic
with rules and control with an inference
engine. So, we this we study the rate algorithm
for representing representation of rules
and then we saw the match resolve execute
cycle which forward chaining the essentially.
So, that is separating out the so the control
is left to the inference engine you only
provide the logic essentially. But very often
in our imperative program C programs
.specially whatever you do is embedded inside
procedure that is another form knowledge
representation when you talk about knowing
how to swim or knowing how to ride a
bicycle. It is almost impossible for you to
articulate that knowledge how do you ride
a
bicycle you cannot explain, explain it so
easily so it is sought of embedded into some
procedure which you have learned over a period
of time essentially.
So, we also carries us knowledge off course
then there are things like neural networks
which basically encode knowledge in form of
weights. And we had already observed that
these are sub symbolic they are representation
they are explicit representations, but a
symbol does not stand for something in a neural
networks a symbol meaning. A weight
basically everything in a neural networks
is we called it in terms of weight essentially.
A
weight basically tells you what is a connection
between 1 neuron and the, we will spend
our time in
the
next in the remain the part of this course
looking at logic as a mechanism
for representation as well as vehicle for
reasoning essentially. So, whenever we do
representation what is the use? Representation
if we cannot do something with it so
along with representation you must have reasoning’s
essentially and logic provides a
very nice vehicle for doing both essentially.
So, logic is associated with on the 1 hand
with language and on the other hand with
inference, inference procedure of the capability
to doing essentially. So, before I get into
logic I want to sought of try to create a
outline of what are the different kind of
logics at
people talk about essentially. 1 thing common
amongst all is that or the language of logic
talks about sentences a thief race in logic
is a sentence a basic entity in when you are
talking about using logic as a language representation
is sentence. So, essentially logics
are devised to express instances in 1 form
of the other. And what is the sentences some
sentences something which in principle is
true or false or can be true or false anything
which in principle can be true or false is
a sentence and logic. Various logics are device
to represent various categories of sentences
and then of course,, reason with them
essentially.
So, what do you mean by something which can
be true or false. If I say can you please
lend me a book now that is not a sentence
in the sense of sense of logic, because it
is not
something which is true or false is basically
a request or imperative statement in saying.
.Can you do something for me essentially or
it could be question mark. So question marks
are not sentences if I say what is your name,
it is not something which is true or false.
So, it not logically a sentence it cannot
be assign a truth or false value or if I say
please
give me a glass of water, it is not a sentence
it is a request or an imperative statement.
Those things are not sentences anything which
in principle can be assigned a truth or
false value is a sentence if I say why it
wins in chess or why it always wins in chess.
And
by this I mean when both sides play perfectly
it is a sentence I do not know whether this
sentences true or false, because as we discussed
when we talking about playing the chess
game tree so huge that we have no hope of
solving it at least not in the very near future.
So, we can make such sentences whose value
we cannot determine, but never thus they
had they qualify a sentence if I say the moon
is made of green cheese that is also
sentence. But in this case you sought of fairly
confidently say that it is a sentence which
is false so sentences as those things which
can be true or false essentially. Now, there
are
different kind of languages essentially so
the simplest kind of language treats a sentence
as 1 unit. So, if I say the earth is flat
then that is 1 unit essentially and the simplest
kind
of logic or logic language which we called
as propositional logic treats a sentence as
a
unit unbreak unbreakable indivisible unit
you cannot look inside a sentence. You cannot
say that this 1 is talking about something
called the earth. And is talking about the
property call being flat nothing of the sought
it simply says this is some sentence and
typically we use.
And you must we familiar with this something
like a symbol to say p stands for this p
stands for the earth is flat essentially or
I can say Socrates is a man. This is a sentence
in
propositional logic I cannot look inside it
I just it is something and there off course
I
would want to assign a truth value essentially.
I can say all men are mortal this is also
in
propositional logic it just some sentence
I can simply call it q and I can simply call
this r
or p 1 p 2 and so on and so far that the we
cannot look inside sentences. So, a logic
in
which you cannot look inside the sentence
or were a sentence is the atomic unit is called
propositional logic. And then off course,
we have logical connectives so we can say
the
earth is flat or Socrates is a man or the
earth is flat implies that Socrates is a man
you can
do all these kind of things. You can combined
sentences to form compound sentences we
will see the syntax and I am sure you are
familiar with it such logics are called
.propositional logic essentially.
Now, these 2 statements are well known for
anybody who have studied logic, because
they together represents some of the oldest
examples that people have been using in logic
in fact from Greek times that is why we have
the term Aristotle. Socrates and the logic
and the reasoning part says that if you know
this or if this is true. And if you know this
and or in other words this is true we will
use the term interchangeably then you can
infer
that Socrates is mortal. So, this is the reasoning
party and this is what we mean by
reasoning in logic is that if you know certain
set of statements to true or you assume that
to be true or that given to be true. Then
you can infer that there are other statement
which
are true somebody tells with that Socrates
is a man and somebody tells you that all men
are mortal. Then what Aristotle should was
that you should be able to infer that Socrates
is mortal essentially.
And this particular form of reasoning or this
particular loll is called a syllogism we will
not go too much into history of logic here,
because there is plenty to look at they, but
we
just keep in mind that this was there in Greek
times as well essentially. In fact, reasoning
is the motivation for which logics by maintained
in the first place essentially. Because
people wanted to say that we do not want to
argue about truth value of statement
essentially. If you know something is true
and something else in true and something else
is true we should be able to infer that something
else is true essentially. So, in that sense
logic is associated with the particular form
of reasoning which is called deduction. And
we will come to this again, but just to get
started by deduction we mean making
inferences which are necessarily true essentially.
So, that if the premises or the given or
the axioms are true then the conclusion man
net must necessarily be true logic is
concerned with forms of reasoning which take
you from true statement to more true
statements.
And they take you and it is a reliable robust
mechanism if logic if a logic machine and
we will talk about that says that this sentence
is true. Then you should be able to believe
it without any reason, but there are forms
of reason that we often do which are not
necessarily always true. So, in a experience
for example, is always captured in patterns
and conclusions. So, you see that clouds and
you say it is likely to rain essentially now
.off course that conclusion you can make,
but it is not necessarily true. Because you
do
not know what is going to happen in a that
is not a logical that is not something that
you
can did use essentially or to take a more
topical example if I say this students signature
is
there on my sheet. Then he is present in the
class know that is not a reliable conclusion
to
make essentially these are forms of reasoning
which are not deductive essentially. And
we do deduction we though other forms of reasoning
all the kind we do for example,
generalization the whole machine learning
community is occupied with generalization
you look at examples from that.
You generalize essentially you look at one
leaf you look at another leaf you look at
the
third leaf. And then you a come to a conclusion
that all leaves are green it is a form of
inference which is not necessarily deduction
essentially or you look at a crow. And you
see that the crow can fly and you see that
the sparrow and you can see that sparrow can
fly. You see a parrot; parrot can fly and
you come to a conclusion that all birds can
fly
this is a form of generalization is a form
of learning you might say, but it is not infallible.
For example, there are birds which cannot
fly penguin is cannot fly so there are other
forms of reasoning which we do all the time
or look at the process of diagnosis. We saw
recently an example of doing diagnosis by
a process of consistency checking essentially..
But we can not necessarily say that we have
concluded is the real fault, because in the
real world in the real world a fault causes
a symptom in the real world something has
gone wrong. And therefore, we can see the
symptoms of, it has it having gone wrong,
but
in diagnosis we move in this other direction.
We look at a symptom and we jump to a
conclusion or we way can inference that this
is a fault essentially and these are not
necessarily correct. So, if you go back to
example that we looked of multiply as an
adders we could have concluded that the 1
adder was wrong or you could have
concluded that 1 multiple had gone wrong.
Any of them could have been true in fact,
we
could have even said a combination of things
could have gone wrong any of them could
have been true and without further investigation
we are not able to make a more
definitive statement.
Medicine is full of this kind of reasoning
you look at symptoms and you make inference
has to what has happen to you; you have fever
you have shivering in the evenings. And
.you jump to a conclusion that you have malaria
essentially now this is not deduction it is
not necessarily true. We are interested in
logic for deduction that statements that we
derive or produce using this logic machinery
should necessarily be true and logic is built
around that motivation essentially. Now, in
propositional logic I cannot take these 2
statements and I cannot device a mechanism
for arriving a that conclusion, because it
is
not so straightforward to to make the connection
for that. We will have to go to a higher
logic or a more descriptive logic which is
called as first order logic. And we will infects
spend most of our time in first order logic;
in first order logic we break up a sentence
into parts.
We keep the word all separately; we keep the
word men separately; we keep the word
mortal separately and the connection between
them separately. We break down the
sentence and represented with consequent which
we can then reason about essentially.
So, essentially what will say is that men
is men is a class of entities mortal is another
class of entities and if anything happens
to be a man then that was also be mortal.
And
there from that we will reason the, because
Socrate is happens to be a man then Socrates
is these reason, but to this to do this we
need this machinery of first order logic which
is
little bit more expressive in nature. Now,
this is a fact of logic is that the more expressive
a language you device the more complex is
the computational required to reason with
that essentially so computational complexity
increases with expressiveness.
So, some of you would have heard about good
else incompleteness theorem and what
that theorem says and may be will come back
to that bit later. If we get time is that
if
languages are expressive enough then there
are conclusions which the logical machinery
cannot make in that sense it is incomplete
essentially. So, we talk about completeness
when we have talking about search there is
a similar notion of completeness in logic
is
that given the fact that there true statement
out. There is my machinery able to reach the
true statement or not is the notion of completeness
and what good else showed in 1931
that reach enough languages will never allowed
completeness in. So, there is a trade of
the more reached the language the more difficult
it is do computation. And most of the
computations that we do include including
the program that we write C program will
following to the category of first order logic
essentially.
.And it is characterized by having variables
and being able to write lops with use
variables and things like that essentially
we will formalize that a little bit later
but there
are other kind of sentences we can talk about.
So, we have seen 2 forms logic
propositional logic first order logic there
is also, mething of called second order logic
which is what apply to we will see if we come
to that, but what about sequence like this
if I say Nisha is tall. Now, that is the statement
in principle off course, I can give a truth
value to this by saying that this is true
this could I could say this is a true sentence
or this
is a false sentence. But the question arises
as to when can I say that this sentence is
true
so logic will also we concern that semantics
associate that when is this sentence true
essentially. Now, the trouble with this kind
of sentences is that if I want to device a
rule
with says if you have more than 6 feet. Then
you are tall if you have less than 6 feet
you
are not tall then I have this problem that
you know what is somebody's 5 feet 11 inches
or 11 and half inches would is that person
not tall.
And somebody who is just 6 feet is tall it
leads to problems when you are trying to model
real world domains. And reason with them that
if you want to talk about properties like
tall warm. Know cool what you really mean
somebody say this room is to warm
somebody else is feel is not to warm apart
from the part the fact that there is subjective
difference. There is also the notion of we
do not really know what temperature does
warm begin with. And what temperature it is
known on the so do we say that if it is more
than 30 degree centigrade it is warm or some.
Or it is more than 35 degrees can have a
crisp boundary that is the real question essentially.
Can we divide things into warm not
warm, tall not tall by drawing a crisp boundary
and many people felt that that is not the
case that that is not what you do should do.
And one of them was lofty zeza zadeh you
must have heard about in who device this thing
call fuzzy logic
so the where fuzzy logic
is difference from what we is use here.
So, these 2 are what we call as classical
logic and by classical logics we, but more
less
mean 2 valued logics sentence can take 1 of
2 value in our case we call them true and
false. But that is only for our own convenience,
but people have thought about multi
valued logics somebody says may be you should
have 3 values true false. And may be or
something like that or true false and do not
know maybe that is a third value people have
try to device logics like that essentially
what fuzzy logic. So in 2 valued logics a
.sentences either true or it is false essentially.
And that is as we will the semantic of
sentence like this says that if you have a
mortal you either belong to the set of things
which are mortal. Or you do not belong to
the set of things which are mortal if you
belong to the set of which are mortal then
you are mortal otherwise you are not mortal.
So, that is a crisp set as we say as oppose
to that what is Zadeh said was at why do you
want to work with crisp set know you have
a notion of a set membership or the
characteristics function that you must have
defined a some point why is it mapping only
to 0 or 1 why cannot it map to 0.7 0.8 or
something like that. And zadeh said that for
example, if I want to define tallness and
this is height then I should be able to define
something like this.
Whereas, some point it becomes 1, but there
are regions where you have different
amount of commitment to this belonging to
this set. So, set membership of fuzzy sets
so
fuzzy logic comes from fuzzy sets and classical
logic comes from crisp sets that which
either have membership is 0 1 here membership
is a continuing between 0 to 1. So, you
can if you have this height this is a membership
to the set of tall people if you have this
side this is a membership to the set of tall
people and it varies essentially. There are
other
kind of logic which deal with uncertainty
so for example, if I say tweedy is a bird
can I
infer that tweedy can a fly to make these
kind of inferences. And we call these inferences
defeasible inference meaning that the inference
can be defeated that you may say yes
tweety can fly, but somebody will give you
some evidence to show that tweety cannot
fly essentially. Somebody tells you tweety
is a bird and you say tweety can fly and then
somebody tell you the tweety is a penguin
then you realize that penguins cannot fly..
Then you inference defeated essentially, but
most of the time we do make inference
which can be defeated. So, we go to the canteen
and assume that I will get tea there or
canteen will be open or my bicycle will have
here all kinds of things. We believe in
which can be defeated essentially so the ability
to make defeasible inferences very
important to us, because otherwise we would
never be able to make inferences if I say
if
I use a statement that all students have bright.
Then somebody comes and shows me 1
student in some corner of the country whose
not bright then may statement becomes
false essentially. Because when I say all
students are bright it means that each and
every
students that each and every person whose
the student must be bright. Now, if somebody
.shows me 1 person not in Chennai off course,
who is not bright. Then my statement goes
is no longer to which means any in any inference
that I would have use making that
statement as a premise and know can no longer
may, because the statement is no longer
too.
So, if I say students in IIT go and take a
jobs in gold man sacs where in bright or
something like that the ability to make to
ability to reason with statements in which
you
do not have complete belief of which there
is uncertainty. And then reason with them
is
very important for us we use it all the time
and we must develop mechanisms to that.
And some of the things that off course we
will not studied in this course a things like
default logics and default reasoning essentially.
Then we make other kind of statements
which so we may want to make a statement this
kind that may be let say we are sitting in
this room. And we here some sounds and then
we make an inference we make a
statements that it is raining essentially.
Off course do not know whether it is raining
or
not.
But we can make a statement that it is possibly
raining
what is a what you mean by truth
values of sub sentences, how would you valuated
truth value of such a sentence. If I say
it is raining you can go out and look at outside
window and say that the statement is true
or statement is false. But what about statement
like it is possibly raining essentially or
if
you say that may be he is sleeping in his
room essentially. So, off course, you can
in this
particular case you can go and check with
the person is sleeping in his room. And then
you can have new statement which says he is
sleeping in his room, but what can you say
about the statement may be he is sleeping
in his room is that the true statement or
a false
statement. Now, people have tried to device
logics well I do not know what you mean
when you say true statement so you have to
be a bit careful essentially when you say
it is
a true statement.
Then what one should say is that there a possible
world, so if you assuming that
everything that you do not know you we have
only a about the knowledge about the
world essentially. Then if there is a possible
world or a feasible world or a consistent
world in which that statement were to be true
then we can accept such a statement to be
true essentially. So, it is a little bit not
easy to discuss right now, but we have this
that it
.is possibly true or it is necessarily true.
So, in fact there is a whole logic which is
devised
to talk about statements of necessity and
possibility essentially. So, for example,
you
might say in that diagnosis that it is possible
that he has malaria essentially and these
logics which are called modal logics allow
1 to talk about statements like this essentially.
So, we have something called modal operators
and there are in particular 2 operators,
one is called diamond operator this is standard
usage in modal logic community. And the
other is called a box operator and if you
write a statement in diamond p it basically
means that p is some statement like this.
For example, the earth is flat if I say diamond
p
it means is possible that the earth is flat
essentially. So, I have a language for expressing
this essentially and then they have mechanism
of reasoning which such statement
essentially. One particular kind of modal
logics is temporal logics where the temporal
off
course deals with time and when you deal with
time and you are talking about the future.
Now, you know that not all the time we can
make definitive statement. So, if the world
is
if the sky cloudy then you can say it will
possible easy in essentially in the future.
But
temporal logics are even more tied to time
you we can make statements like if you leave
a block of ice on you table.
You can make a statement that it will eventually
meat essentially that there will be
sometime in the future when the block of ice
will no longer be there and till meal
essentially. So, we can reason about time
essentially or time in change and things like
that essentially so you can say that if you
keep within proxy then eventually you will
get
a w grade essentially. Of course, not today
now another kind of log temporal logics deal
with statements like the following that John
knows something so John knows that the
earth is round. Now, look at this statement
this sentence contains a sentence so that
is the
first thing you should observed that there
is a sentence inside this the earth is round
and
well I had p here. So, let us call this P
1 now what I am saying in this sentence is
that
John knows p 1 essentially. So, such logics
are called epistemic logics
and I would
basically represent this statement in a simple
epistemic logic as saying that k j were k
j is
the modal operator which says the John knows
something.
And then that sentence p 1 so when can now
talk about someone knowing something’s,
but one can also talk about statements like
this that
this is another sentence in this
.epistemic logics. And let say m stands for
marry what this sentence is saying is that
Mary
knows that John knows that the earth is round.
And off course, you can I have all kinds
of thing you can say Mary knows that John
does not know that peter has gone home or
all kind of statement. So, you can combine
logical operators which I am not seen so far,
but we will see them in due course. So, what
modal operators at modal logics are doing
is that they are taking some standard logic
and in our case is propositional logic that
we
are talking about then applying modal operators.
So, these are modal operators which
talk about necessity and possibilities possible
that Mary loves John if I want to say then
I
could use a diamond operator essentially.
And or I could use a know this operator temporal
logics use modal operators which talk
about time epistemic logics use modal operators
which augment a language by talking
about what people know essentially. Now, almost
similar to knows is the notion of belief
so people have built logics which talk about
belief essentially what is the difference
between knowing and believing? Well, we would
like to say that if you know something
it is necessarily true if you believe something
it may not necessarily be true. So, I can
say
peter believes at the earth is flat essentially
that is the perfectly valid true statement,
because that is what peter believes essentially.
The earth may not be flat, but the
statement is the true statement essentially
so belief so knowledge and belief.
Off course, it is quite an interesting thing
to work with specially when you are talking
about multi agent scenario essentially. In
fact, epistemic logics were created to handle
multi agent situations if we have know many
agents if you have networks of agents and
they are doing certain things. Then how can
we reason about it how can we show form
example that given a certain protocol. A group
people will always elect a leader or not
elect a leader a would be unable to elect
a leader. How can you prove such thing
essentially this what people with epistemic
logics have been associated with possibility
and necessity is a mathematical foundation
called rough sets. So, just like fuzzy sets
form a basis for fuzzy logic and fuzzy sets
are sets in which membership can vary to
degrees rough sets are sets which have basically
2 boundaries essentially.
..
So, for example, if I say I am talking about
the set of tall people then I could draw 1
boundary here. And another boundary here and
the meaning of this is that anybody
inside anything inside the any circle is definitely
tall necessarily tall. And anything inside
the outer circle, but outside the inner circle
is possibly tall but not necessarily tall
and
anything outside both the circle is not tall
essentially. So, rough set is a mechanism
which has been device to deal with this kind
of a uncertainty essentially now the last
form of reasoning that it not so much like
logic. But we have probabilistic reasoning
so
probabilistic reasoning is one way of handling
uncertainty essentially. So, for example,
when you are doing diagnosis for example,
you might device a system with says if
somebody has some symptoms. And somebody has
yellow eyes then its lightly that the
person has jaundice how do you express his
lightly look us one thing is this possibility,
but if you want to now talk about gathering
evidence and increasing your belief in
something.
So, you believe that that this is the really
the case you may be you do one more test and
you belief increases probabilistic reasoning
is 1 mechanism for handling uncertain logic
knowledge essentially. Now, you must distinguish
between fuzzy logic which also is
talking about numbers which are less than
1 and probabilistic reasoning which says my
conclusion. I am 70 percent sure of my conclusion
or something like that there is a
.difference between this and fuzzy reasoning
in fuzzy reasoning. It is a question of it
is a
linguistic problem really as what do you mean
by the world tall? Word tall essentially,
because it is not defined clearly whereas,
in probabilistic reasoning if you say that
the
chances that he has jaundices 0.7 or the probability
is 0.7. Then you are saying that this
is way of talking about my lack of knowledge
about the real situation. So, off course you
know that you know when you throughout diceyou
say the chance of it falling 1 or 2 is 1
by 3 is simply says that.
Because I cannot say what it what is going
to fall I just use probability as mechanism
for
expressing my lack knowledge about what is
what really is the cases essentially. If you
had perfect knowledge about physics and all
the information that is needed to do the
calculations of what is really going to happen
when you through a dice then between the
moment when you through it. And the moment
when it really falls you should be able to
compute in principle whether it will fall
with 1 or 2 or 3 or 4 or 5. But off course,
we do
not have that knowledge we do not have the
computation ability. So, we say talk about
probabilities it is likely that it that it
will fall like this certain likely it will
fall like this
essentially if you get time we will look at
a variation of probabilistic reasoning in
the
context of diagnosis and see that when you
get multiple pieces of evidence. How do you
combined those evidence to maintain a different
amount of belief in all kind of things
that will be towards a end if we get time.
In the next class, we will look at propositional
logic more formally in fact, when we talk
of logic we always use the term formal logic,
because logic is concerned with form and
not with content essentially. Logic is concerned
with valid forms of reasoning and it does
it is not concerned with what you are talking
about. So, I can say that Socrates is a man
and all men are mortal the syllogism allowed
be to complete to conclude. Socrates is
mortal if I say Ramesh is a student all students
are bright then the same form of
reasoning will allow me to infer that Ramesh
is bright essentially. And why is that a form
why is that a valid conclusion, because the
form of reasoning that I am using which
called as a syllogism he showed to be valid
form of reasoning. So, we will look at valid
forms of reason that we will use in propositional
logic and try to show why they are valid
also in the. So, will start off with the language
and then we look at the mechanism for
reasoning and this whole thing we will called
as a machinery of logic. So, we will in the
.next class try an build a small machinery
for propositional logic essentially. And then
the
rest of the course will spend on first order
logic essentially, because that is really
interest
more interesting essentially. So, I will stop
here I think.
.