So, we meet for the last time semester and
we want to look at the resolution method
for F
O L essentially. So, as my might have mentioned
earlier it was the method which was
introduced by Alan Robinson in 1965 and since
then it has been used extensively in
theorem proving. So, things like for example,
the proof for last theorem had extensive
support from programs which would based on
resolution method eventually. And it is a
complete method for a proving the theorem
or proving something which uses only one
rule of inference which is the resolution
rule and it does not mean any other essentially.
Now, talking about generally about logic as
we said that logic is basically a system in
which you define a language. And then define
some rules of inference in that language
define a meaning of sentence in that language
and then talk about soundness and
completeness and as you define more and more
expressive languages. So, we have seen
only one step we have moved from professional
logic to personal logic in which we said
that we can talk about variables and quantifies.
Our variables it was shown by godel in
.his theorem which was called Godel’s completeness
theorem that first of the logic is
sound and complete essentially which means
you can always device of a certain logic
system which is sound and which is complete.
And by complete we mean anything which is
entailed by a set of statements can be
derived using that machinery that we have
building essentially. It terms out that that
F O
L is sound complete, but it is only semi decidable.
And what this means is that in
particular it the way it applies to F O L
is as follows that if you gave a true statement
or
statement which is entailed to the system.
And ask the system to prove it then there
exists
a proof for that statement in that system
essentially. And you can always devise a
strategy and you can imagine the strategy
something like breath first search that always
you know find the nearest inference first
and eventually. You will go further and further
away and eventually you will find the proof.
So, you can always devise a strategy to for
finding a proof, but if you give a statement
which is not true then the system in your
halt.
Because there is no proof and the system my
never come out saying that there is no proof
now in the case of proportional logic, because
we have only dealing with a countably,
countable set of propositions when usually
it is finite.
We can always say that at least for finites
set of propositions we can always say that
there is no proof, because we try all combinations
and eventually say that there is no way
that this can this statement can be true.
So, even if it is false you can come out and
say
false in the case of first of logic we cannot
come out and say that yes statement is false.
You can only keep trying essentially which
falls down to saying that you are program
can get in to an infinite loop essentially.
And which is not of course, surprising that
we
have written all of us have written programs
which get into infinite loop. Of course, most
of our programs get it be infinite loop imperative
languages, because we have written it a
long a long loop or long exist criteria in
logic programming or prolog. We do not control
the flow of execution we simply stay it what
is to be done. Of course, we do control it
in
the order in which we write statements, because
there we observed prolog does depth
first search essentially. Top to down and
and left to right which means if you write
statements in a wrong order it is possible
we could get it into a infinite loop. But
even if
you write statements in the correct order
if the statement that you trying to prove
is not
true it can still get into an infinite loop
essentially.
..
So, today, we will we will go back to this
example that we saw and so on a b
on b c. And
let us on table c and being a supposing given
to you this is a set of facts given to you.
And you want to show that there exists an
x there exists a y such that on x y and being
x
and not green y. This is a goal that you want
to show to be true and that is the facts given
to you now you can see that forward chaining
backward chaining does not make sense
here. Because in your in your data base or
knowledge base there are no implication
statements both forward chaining and backward
chaining move set of allow you to move
across simplification statement. So, if you
have alpha implies beta then if you have alpha
then you can say yes beta is there. Or if
you have the goal beta you can say the goal
alpha can be a goal, but they are no implication
statements here given the set of facts and
we are also show this here. So, you can imagine
that forward chaining and backward
chaining does not work at all essentially.
So, you was of course, convenience your self
is that this statement is true and as human
beings. We might use one technique which is
call looking at different cases of proof by
cases we could say take the case when x is
a and y is b
or look at b. So, there are 2 cases
that either b is green or b is not green if
b is green then x is equal to b and y is equal
to c
and b is on c and b is green and y is not
b. If b is not green then you can say x is
equal to
a and y is equal to b and a is green and b
is not green. So, whether b is green whether
b is
.not green you can show that in either or
the 2 cases this statement is true. And if
you
further say that this is the only possibility
that one of them is true then you can argue
that
yes this statement must be true essentially.
So, this sequence which has slipped in
between if you argue that one only one of
them is true is essentially a part of classical
logic in classical logic every statement is
either true or false and there is nothing
in
between.
So, it is called law of excluded middle essentially
which some people object to, because
of statements like this, but I can say that
p or not p is true or q or not q is true.
So, this is
a true statement why because of the law of
excluded middle either p must true or not
p
must be true. So, in which case this this
and this true and true and both are true
essentially I can shuffle this and write it
as not p or q or not q or p. And then which
I can
write as p implies q or q implies p. So, this
is true for any 2 statements p and q whether
had any language personal or professional
or high order language. It does not matter
and
if you treat implication as implies in the
causal sense then people have difficulty with
such statement. Because just imagine that
p stands for the earth is flat and q stands
for
the moon green then you are saying that there
is casual connection between these 2
things that the earth is flat. And the moon
is green that either the earth is flat implies
that
the moon is green or the fact that moon is
green implies that the earth is flat essentially.
Now, obviously there is no casual connection
between these 2 statements you take any 2
statements p and q. And this statements is
always true essentially so which is I
sometimes logicians tend to distinguish between
logics with capture cause and
relationship. And we will not go in to that
but rather they would see that instead reading
an implication here. You must read it like
this when you say p implies q it is easier
to
read it as this without getting worked up
about it says that either p is false or q
is true.
That is all you are saying essentially, but
when we read this an implication we have the
sense of being a causal relationship, which
is not really the case essentially. Now, let
us
get back to the resolution method.
..
And before we do that we want to look at this
algorithm called unification algorithm
which is a very famous algorithm. What unification
algorithm does is that it takes 2
patterns while use a more generic term then
formulas and tries to unify them which
means tries to find the substitution which
should make them same essentially. This
patterns are made up of 2 kinds things; one
are one is constant and one is variable. And
variable is something that you can substitute
something for the other and constants are
or
atoms as some people call it cannot be substituted
cannot be changed they have. So, for
the sake of simplicity we will adopt slightly
different notation.
..
Supposing I have this statement man x or,
so let us say not man x or mortal x. Now,
this
statement which is in the mathematical language
of logic has this particular notation that
you have the predicate name. Or it could be
the function name in some situations
followed by brackets followed by the arguments
and then predicates connected using
logical connectives essentially. So, you have
to distinguish between different kinds of
things for the sake this unification algorithm
that is assume that we have a uniform
notation. And the in that notation what this
will look like is a that I will use or here
and
the notation uses the question mark as a thing
for variable. This just for the sake of
understanding this algorithm easily you can
always adopt the algorithm to this notation,
but this is simply easier to use. Because
it is a very uniform list like notation which
those
of you who are use list put be happier to
look at essentially. So, I have moved a or
sign
outside. So, the outer most connective is
first and then the inner connective which
is not
here so not man is written like this so not.
So, this whole thing from this bracket to
this bracket is one expression or term if
you we
just call it a term or a list. So, from here
to here is a list which is so the first one
is always
a connective the first element in the list
is always a connective or a predicate name.
In
this case so here predicate name is differentiated
and you know connective. So, the first
thing is in the case it is a predicate name
man here it is a connective here it is a
.connective. So, this has got this 2 arguments
this whole thing is one thing and this whole
thing. So, it is a list of 3 elements so everything
is a list of some number of elements and
the only thing we need worry about is let
either something is a constant or an atom
as the
list people say or it is a variable essentially
So, and the only the point up out that is
an
atom can only match an atom. So, if I am this
with a if I want to match this with man, so
what I am trying to do I am trying to do something
like resolution. If you recall I have
this clause and I have this clause. And I
have something here I have and I have the
negation of that thing here resolution's rule
if you remember always first of all it works
in the clause form that that you must express
things in c n f like form. And then you have
to look for something verses and it is negation
of a positive literal and negation negative
literal. And in some sense cancel it out essentially
and from there you can derive mortal
x essentially.
So, which means of course, I will have to
match this man x with mortal x with man
sonatas which is work the unification algorithm
will allow it do it will tell me what
values for x will make this true expressions.
The same in one case we have just called it
as list here essentially. So, to match this
with this of course, the predicate name must
be
the same. So, we are just treating it as a
atom here which means it can only match a
another atom which is same a man not can only
match not or can only match or it is only
the variables which can match something else.
So, let us assume that we have an
arbitrary nested pattern which is express
as a list of this kind. And we want to write
a
general algorithm which will find a unifier
for any 2 patterns or a substitution was those
2 patterns which should make it a same this
substitution is called a unifier. And that
is
algorithm that we are looking for unification
algorithm. So, the algorithm is called let
us
say it is called unify I will just sketch
it here and you get fill in the details.
So, let us say x y and what is does is it.
So, will write in a prolog like fusion this
part that
is sub unify x y. So, like we do in very very
often we write a program; we add a third
parameter to make like simpler for us we added
an empty list and call it sub unify sub
unify what this is going to be is the substitution.
So, obviously when we call it when we
call we so x y are any search list arbitrary
list we start of by supplying an empty
substitution. And now we, so x y theta where
theta is the substitution we are trying to
build what is a substitution? Substitution
is a collection variable value essentially
it says
.x equal to x should be substituted by this
y should be substituted by this and so on.
We
should make the 2 patterns same essentially
and this algorithm goes to a series of cases.
I
will just list out the salient once here;
obviously x and y are the same whether they
have
atom or whether they have a list then you
do not need to do anything they already unified
essentially. So, some of main cases are follows.
So, these are cases so I just write it as
f So, let us understand this to mean that
x is a
variable then call another function called
unify x y theta. So, if one of them is a variable
then it is a candidate for being substituted
by something else and that this function unify
will do likewise if y is a variable you can
also call var unify with y x theta somewhere.
So, this order will not be the perfect order
I am writing here if atom x then
if x equal to
why return theta else. So, if x is an atom
if the argument that we are trying to unify.
So,
this going to be a program, so this x and
y initially will be such bigger patterns but
eventually when we build on into list at some
point they will either a variable or an atom.
So, if it is a variable then we just I call
it call var unify with others argument if
it is an
atom we check whether it is matching or not
essentially. So, if it is not a variable then
if
it is not an atom it must be a list then we
say if length x not equal to length it is
a list.
So, we can compute it is length return fail
if the 2 list are of unequal length then you
can
never make them match else make recursive
cause. So, make I just write it like this
appropriate recursive calls what does it mean
that? For example, if this is one of my
argument this is x and this x has a list of
3 elements the first element is constant.
Or the
second element is this list which is this
whole thing and the third element is this
other
list. So, if I have another list of 3 elements
I can try to match that and then I will make
recursive calls once this with this then another
with this and another with this. So, I
implemental build a substitution that leads
with ask with the task of writing the var
unify
which is really building the substitution
I might have skipped one of the small details
does not matter x. So, when we make a call
to var unify we know that x is a variable.
The
other thing would be a list could be a something
else. So, let us say this is a variable and
y and theta we know that the first thing is
a variable essentially we have to do a few
checks. So, essentially what we really want
do is to say add var egual to y to my theta.
Add one more substitution, but before doing
that I want to do. So, what I what I want
do?
.I want say return bete union var equal to
y. I want to basically add one more substitution
which is the call I am making, but is I may
allowed to do that I have do a couple of
checks first first is if var is already equal
to y. Then you can just return theta you do
not
have to do anything else it could be the case.
For example, I am comparing well these are
not variables does not matter it could that
they are same variables then you just return
theta then if variable occurs return fail.
So, if the variable happens to occur in y
then you
return fail. So, let me use an example to
illustrate by this is needed and this example
is
from book by I can make them what which disturbs
it in this notation.
.
So, the example is as follows naught c’s
x. So, let us say c is stands for the predicate
and
the meaning of sees is that the first argument
can see the second argument. So, for
example, I see you or things like that, and
this is a universally quantified statement.
It is
saying there for all x let us assume that
x is people x cannot see x which means one
cannot see oneself essentially. So, let us
assume that that is a true statement and I
have a
rule which I am let us say I am doing forward
chaining. And the rule is as follows again
I
am writing it in this new notation where instead
of writing the implication sign I will
write an if here then the antecedent and then
the consequent. So, instead of saying this
implies the consequent I am writing it in
this list like notation which may them what
the
use which is quite nice notation to use easy
to process so this rule says.
.So, it always worry about the number of brackets
in this set of thing. So, what does this
tool say? It is a universally quantified statement
how would read it in English. So, feet is
a function remember that in first of the logic
the argument to predicate can only be terms.
And terms are either variables or art or constant
or functions feet of z is function. So, let
us say feet was stands for z's feet. So, this
is saying that is anyone cannot see their
feet
they should diet essentially this may be a
true statement. Of course, know the question
is
shall should this rule and this these 2 rules
can we apply forward chaining here to that
everyone should diet
not given these facts right. So, let us say
how that particular
statement that we are talking about if variable
occurs y then return failure comes to our.
So, we are trying to unify this with this
remember the antecedent should match.
Now, we will make recursive cause first you
see that this is a list of 2 arguments then
we
will make 2 recursive cause one with the first
argument. Then one with the second
argument then the first call this is an atom
and this matches this. So, that is fine so
the
first recursive call will work and it will
not change theta at all the second recursive
call
has list of 3 elements and this also as a
list of 3 elements. So, that is fine first
we will
make a call with sees and sees here in the
first call this case will come if if this
is an atom
this is same atom then do nothing in the second
call we will do this. So, our algorithm
will say x is a variable. So, I will call
var unify with x and x and z and then in the
last
statement which I will reached there I will
say add x is equal to z I am not writing the
question mark here to theta. So, this will
go into theta so this is if you want to may
these
2 patterns same substitute for x the value
z. And you will have theta now you have x
is
already been put as z here. So, let so whether
you do this here or whether you do this
theta both ways it works in fact the others
other situation is if var as the value in
theta
while you let us call it z in theta.
Then
if variable already has the value in theta
then call sub unify with that value
essentially.So, in this example we already
have a value z in theta x equal to z. So,
if we
are not change this x that clause will and
we will call with x n. So, we so that recursive
call that sub unify call in this line here
would be with the value of z with z and feet
of z
essentially. So, let us assume that we have
already made this z which is this case where
this is happening now you are trying to unify
this x which is a variable with feet of. So,
this is become z now, so let me put an arrow
here and show that this is become z.
.Because we have substituted x with z now,
we have making a call of a variable z with
a
list which is feet of z which is the y.
So, this x in this statement here sorry this
is well in this statement and this is y and
this
statement says that if var occurs in y then
return fail essentially. So, in this example
z
occurs in this pattern or list. So, the algorithm
should return failure in that we cannot
unify this essentially which is good for us
because otherwise all of us would have have
to
diet. So, this does not apply and this particular
clause here is meant to catch exactly these
kind of a things essentially. So, you can
never unify z with feet of z you know if you
substitute feet of z for z then you will have
to substitute feet of z for this z also then
the z
inside then the z inside then the z inside.
So, it know does not make sense. So, this
unification algorithm.
.
And what it returns is the theta which is
the most general unifier which can may the
patterns same. So, for example, if I have
a statement p x z and another statement p
x let
us say constant a. Then you can see that I
can have one unifier which is x is equal to
b
and z equal to a that is a unifier I am not
saying that this algorithm will find this
that a
unifier. So, that is one unifier and there
is another unifier which is simply z equal
to a
this unifier more general then this unifier,
Because it does less amount of substitution
I
.mean anything that this does this also does,
but there is something which this does which
this does not do. So, this is called more
general then this go in to details we will
accept
that there is a partial order of unifiers.
And there is something called the most general
unifier which is called m g u and this algorithm
essentially returns the most general
unifier. So, again without going into details
we just accept the fact that it is desirable
to
find the most general unifier. And the reason
for that is that you can make the most
general inferences from which you can always
derive most specific inferences using the
universal rule essentially. So, I am we do
not have to go in to details over that, but
it
basically the it is son ate algorithm which
is really popular and theorem proving and
we
use it all the time. So, let us address this
problem let us see an how the resolution method
solve this problem.
.
So, to convert to solve a problem with resolution
method you have to convert it in to
clause form. And a clause form is a form which
looks like follow as follows at there is
some number of universal quantifiers x 1 all
x 2 all x n. Then there is a set of clauses
c
one and c 2 and c k such a form such a form
of a formula is clause form when each c I
is
d one or d 2 or d r and each d I is equal
to l I or negation of l I. So, of course,
they inside
part you will recognize as a conjunctive normal
form a set of clauses which are joined by
an and each clause is basically some something.
And each of those things is either a
.literal which means an atomic statement or
the negation of an atomic statement. So, you
have push the negation side all the way inside
and you have removed or thrown way
existential quantifiers likely in our example
we do not really have existential quantifiers.
Or at least we will see in a moment that we
do not have, but we discussed earlier how
to
handle existential quantifiers by using the
solemn functions. And the solemn constants
that can be done and then re arranging any
formula into c n f is something that I am
sure
you have studied how to do that.
And then you move the universal quantifiers
outside one they are together outside you
can just threw it away use quantifier form
which is what we had doing here essentially.
So, what is it, so if you recall the deduction
theorem that we had talked about earlier it
said that to show this follows on this you
are equivalently showing that this and this
entails this. And if you want use the resolution
method you will recall that to use the
resolution method you must take the conclusion
and take it is negation and add it as a
clause to your system essentially. So, this
is already in clause form all we need do is
to
convert this into take it is negation. So,
what it is negation of that? The negation
of that
put on negation sign outside here I will have
to push the negation sign inside, because
I
have to convert it into this clause form.
So, this will become for all x for all y not
one x y
or not green x or green y. So, once this negation
go inside then it go inside the and sign
convert it to an or remember that we have
to push to the inner most place. So, this
will
become not on this will become not green this
negation negation cancel then this will
become green y.
So, let me write this here on x y or green
x or not green y. So, this is one clause express
it
in the implicit quantifier from and those
are other things given to us which is on a
b and
on b c. So, let us forget on table c that
is not useful for us I mean we can write it,
but it
does not help us green a and that is say it
is on table c there any way we do not really
need that. So, we has this clauses and we
want to what is it we want to show that can
we
derive the null clause from this. And we are
going to use the unification algorithm along
the way our example is so simple. That we
do not have to really use a very complicated,
because it is very simple you can match it.
So, let us just try this form this and this
I
substitute x equal to a and y is equal to
b I get green a or not green b. So, I am not
stated
the resolution step or the rule for first
of the logic, but you can see that it is very
similar
.to modified you do you apply the substitution
and in the resolving you have substitution
already applied essentially.
So, because I am saying x equal to a and y
is equal to b then this becomes a this becomes
b and I get this essentially then from this.
And this I can get similarly green b or not
green c is that correct this should be negation
here right and these should not be negation
and this should be negation y. So, all 3 are
long way so negation on x y negation green
x
yes seen that thing there and green y essentially
what we get here is not green a and
green b and not green b or green c. So, is
that correct know and then from this and this
I
can get not green b and from this one and
this one if you can keep track of arrows I
can
get green b and from this and this. So, just
I repeat from on a b and that negated goals.
So, remember this is a negated goal that we
have added we get not green a or green b
then from on b c and the negated goal we get
not green b or green c, but here we have
side not green c.
So, when we resolve this with this we get
not green b only this remains when we resolve
this with this this is green a and this not
green a. So, you get green b and then we not
green b or green b and from that we get the
null clause essentially. So, you can see that
there is simple proof using the resolution
method and if look at a proof carefully you
can
see that it is trying to in some sense say
at the same time that if this formula is to
be
unsatisfiable. If this whole set of formulas
which means only this formula, because this
is
accepted to be true; this is the premises
given to us. If this is to be false then it
entails
same time b must green and b must not be green
and of course, is a contradiction. So, as
we discussed earlier the resolution method
is like a proof for contradiction. So, if
you
remember when we talked about forward chaining
or backward chaining. There is no
way you can move from this set of data to
this conclusion essentially the conclusion
holds that one the exists a block on another
block.
So, that the block top is green that the block
below is not green it is it is not even initially
clear, but it is true. But we cannot derive
it using first forward chaining or back ward
chaining, but in resolution method there is
a very simple small proof for doing that.
So,
in fact, this procedure by Alan Robinson was
a big in logical reasoning automatic
theorem proving. And nowadays, automatic theorem
proving is an, in many different
.place for many different applications essentially.
And the heart of this is resolution
method essentially which is a sound and complete
method for first of the logic
essentially. So, I think we should stop here
with this we will end this course I must say
I
enjoyed teaching the class. And I hope some
of you at least enjoyed the course I think
so.
.