So, in the last class we looked at goal stack
planning and one of the observations we
made was that, it essentially does backward
listening, and it takes a set of goals to
solve,
serializes them and tries to solve them one
by one essentially. And then we saw that like
suspense showed that there are certain problems
where you cannot serialize the sub goals
and solve them independently and arrive at
the final solution; you may have to do extra
work to, finally, come to this thing.
.
So, today we want to look at an approach which
is called nonlinear planning
and it is
named and it is known by many other names.
So, lot of people have looked at it also
known as partial order planning which kind
of stands for the fact that the plan may be
a
partial order of actions not necessarily a
sequence of actions. So, far we have said
in the
simplified world that a plan is a sequence
of actions; we do action a 1, then we do action
a 2 and then we do action a 3 and so on. But
this allows us to have actions, plans or
.recognized plans as a structure which is
a partial order, which means that you are
not
committing to the order of actions essentially.
So, to take an example, supposing you have
to wear shoes for going out or something,
then you have four actions to be done which
is, for example, wear left sock, wear right
sock, wear left shoe and wear right shoe essentially.
Now it is not necessary that you
choose a particular sequence of these four
actions. The only thing that you have to do
is
to wear the left sock before you wear the
left shoe and wear the right sock before you
wear the right shoes. So, as long as you satisfy
this constraint of this order, then the rest
can be done in any order. So, in that sense,
this kind of planning is also known as least
commitment planning.
And by this we mean that in the process of
planning, you do not commit too much
essentially; you only commit and we will see
what are the kind of commitments you
have to make as little as possible as little
as necessary to solve the current whatever
subproblem that you are solving. This is also
known as plan space planning, and again we
are familiar with this notion. We have talked
about solution space planning; we saw, for
example, that when you want to solve SAT like
problems or TSP like problems, you
construct candidate solutions and do some
perturbation in them or we also saw that when
we are doing branch and bound with TSP that
you work with partial solutions.
That you initially start with a set of all
possible to us and then gradually partition
them
into subsets eventually homing on to towards
you are looking at. So, this is in that flavor;
it is in the space of possible solutions essentially.
So, plan space planning basically
works with partially specified plans, and
there is a refinement operator step. And there
is
a refinement step which refines plans in the
sense that you specify them more and more
essentially. Now a partially specified plan
or the partial plan is denoted as a four topple
which is a set of actions or operators A which
are part of the plan.
So, we are not saying anything about where
they lie in the plan; all you are saying is
that
these are actions as part of the plan. And
these actions may be partially instantiated
which means instead of saying, for example,
unstake a from b, you might say something
like unstake x from b which means that you
basically want to achieve clear b, for
.example, and if there is something on b,
then you want to unstake it essentially or
you
might also say unstake a on x, for example.
So, partially specified actions may be
allowed essentially, then there is an ordering
relation which basically says that action
a
happen before action b.
So, we will specify order explicitly as supposed
to implicitly in the planning that we
have been doing so far. So, the planning that
we have been doing so far can be seen as a
state space planning. And so if you remember
states space planning, so you combined
selection and placement of actions; of course,
this is more true of power state space
planning and backward state space planning
and little bit lets true for goal stack
planning. But in forward state space planning
and in backward state space planning, a
forward state space planning you says this
is s; this is by a 1. I go to some explain
and
then I choose a 2 and I will go to s double
prime and so on.
In forward state space planning, the twin
task of choosing actions and placing actions
in
the plan are done simultaneously. They are
sort of so closely coupled that you cannot
distinguish between the fact of choosing and
scheduling them, because the process of
looking for action says that I am looking
for the first action, then I am looking for
the
second action, then I am looking for the third
action. So, both the things go together.
Likewise in backward state space planning
essentially; you are choosing the last action,
then the second last action then the third
last action and so on essentially.
In nonlinear planning or partial order planning,
we do these two things separately. We
sort of distinguish between the fact that
an action is necessary for
necessary part of the
plan, but we do not necessarily say where
the action should be, okay. So, for example,
if
you are planning a trip from here to Mandy,
then you might say, okay, our necessary part
of the plan is to somehow get from let us
say Chennai station to Delhi station; let
us say
you are going by train. So, you have decided
what the action is, but you have not stated
when that action will take place in your plan
in a sequence of actions that.
You will say that somewhere in my plan, there
must be this action of catching a train
from Chennai to Delhi. So, this is the flavor
of partial order planning or plan space
planning or least commitment planning is that
you have said that, okay, I need to take a
.train from Chennai to Delhi, but I have not
said at which point if because eventually
my
actions will be sequences of actions at which
point will I actually be taking this train
essentially. Likewise, another action might
be booking a train ticket essentially. Now
I
could do it at any time before the journey;
assuming, of course, that we get tickets,
but
this is not always the case but still.
So, this thing about combining the selection
and the placement of action is forced in state
space planning. Because you are working with
states in plan space planning, we are
working with the notion of these partial plans.
And we can say that these two things are
dependent of each other. Of course, eventually
we will have to impose certain order on
the actions, but when we are talking about
plans, we say these are the actions in the
plan
and some actions may have certain ordering
which you will state in the ordering relation.
And this basically says that a happen before
b and so on and so forth.
Then we have a casual relation; let me just
use the terms c here which I will come to
in a
moment and then we have a set of binding constraints.
So, what do I mean by this? I
might say at some point that an action stack
a on to x. So, I will use this lower case
for a
variable just for a moment is part of my plan.
I might even say that this action comes
before something and happens after something
and so on and so forth which I will say
here, but at some point I might say that x
equal to b here. If I add this extra bit of
information, then I have added something more
to the plan which says that this action
must put a on to b essentially or I could
even say x not equal to b.
I could add any kind of a constraint binding
constraint to variable essentially or I could
say that x belongs to some domain of let us
say block set I have; let say blue block set
or
something like that. I could do all this sort
of things; I could add extra constraints which
tell you how the variables are bound essentially.
Here we are talking about casual links,
and the general idea is that this is a triple
where you have an action a; you have a
predicate p, and you have an action b. And
what you are saying here is that a produces
a
predicate p and b consumes a predicate b predicate
p essentially.
So, for example, p could be holding a, and
what is there action which might do that?
It
could be something like unstack a from y,
and there might be another action like put
.down a. This forms a triple and we see this
as a causal link between two actions a and
b;
in this case unstack a from something and
put down a. And we say that unstack a from
something is providing a predicate or producing
a predicate holding a because that is a
effect. So, p is a P belongs to effects of
a and p belongs to the pre conditions of b.
So,
there is a predicate like this if you have
expressed the predicate like this as such.
So, all these are sets, sets of actions, sets
of ordering links, set of causal links and
sets of
binding constraints, and this partial plan
is represented by a portable like this. And
if you
have asserted a triple here which says that
a p b, we are saying that in our plan a
produces a predicate p and that p is consumed
by b essentially. So, obviously, the
moment I add such a causal link, I must also
add an action that a happen before b and
you can say that this either happens implicitly
or you must do it explicitly. So, this is
a
structure of a partial plan; as you can see
in this partial plan structure, I may specify
something; I may not specify other things.
So, I may have let us say six actions and
I may have ordering relations only between
a
few of them and causal links between a few
of them and binding constraints for some of
them essentially. This is in keeping with
this notion of least commitment planning,
and
what we are saying here is that we will add
only as much to the plan as it is necessary
for
solving the sub problem we are trying to solve.
So, if you go back to suspense anomaly,
in goal stack planning, you are committing
to solving one sub goal first and then the
second sub goal. And then you are committing
to ordering them in the particular way
that you are doing; we do not want to do that.
We will try to do add constraints only
when necessary. So, in that sense its least
commitment.
A word about plan space planning; so we are
not working in the space of states anymore.
We will start with some initial plan and we
will apply the refinement step to get new
plans out of that. The search space contains
only plans or partial plans and partial plans
are described by this portable essentially.
So, eventually what we want to do is look
at a
partial plan, choose a refinement step and
there may be more than one refinement step.
So, some of you have to select one; come up
with a new partial plan and do this
repeatedly. Choose the refinement step; come
up with the new plan and so on. So, one
question that one might ask is when will one
terminate this.
.Now one thing that I would like it to sort
of ponder over and think about is the following
that even if I have a small state space; let
us say I have these three blocks like in
suspense anomaly a b and c. There is only
a finite number of ways in which you can
arrange this c blocks. So, the set of states
is finite essentially, but even for such a
domain,
the set of possible plans is infinite; maybe
we will come to that, but I want you to think
about this a little bit, okay. So, what is
the initial plan? The initial plan this we
will call
as pie zero; we will always have an initial
plan. And the initial plan has two actions
a 0
and a infinity.
It has one ordering constraint which says
that a 0 happens before a infinity, and it
has
nothing else. This will always be our initial
plan. Remember, keep in mind that states do
not exist as far as this planning algorithm
is considered; we are only looking at
plans or
partial plans essentially. So, now the objects
that we are manipulating are only plans
essentially. So, of course, one question will
arise us to when do we terminate because we
can no longer say that apply a goal test function
to a state, because we do not have state
anymore in our this thing. We will have only
plans essentially.
Now what are these actions? A 0 has no preconditions
and its effects is equal to I just use
this notation to start it. So, of course,
every planning problem will have a different
a 0
action and a 0 action simply produces the
start state essentially its effect. When I
say
this, it is basically a set of predicates,
okay.
..
For example, in the suspense anomaly, we said
this is C A B; this is the start stage. So,
we have an action; let me draw it here, whose
preconditions is the empty set and whose
effects are these things on C A on table A
on table B, clear B, clear C and A. So, this
is a
0 action. As you can see every time you define
the planning problem. So, what is the
planning problem? A planning problem is a
given set of actions. If you are looking at
the
state space project then the set of states
in a start state and a goal state and a set
of action
that you can use to generate the moves essentially.
So, now, we have said that we are doing away
with the notion of states at all. So, instead
of the start state, we have a start action
and what the start action says is there is
an action
whose effects are these precondition this
start space predicates essentially that somehow
produces that.
..
And if our goal is to have A on B on C, then
my a infinity is an action which has no
effects but whose preconditions are what I
want to achieve. So, on AB and BC; this is
a
infinity. So, this is my starting node in
the search space of partial plans, and this
is a
partial plan which has two actions. One action
which produces the start state, other
action which consumes the goal state and I
have specified anything else except that the
start stage happens before the goal stage
which we have said here. The start action
happens before the goal action or a 0 happens
before a infinity.
So, if you now try to remember, when we are
talking of TSP and we say that we partially
specify we say that we have only one edge
specified which will go from Chennai to
Bangalore. Then we say that everything else
could be anything. So, it was a set of
solutions. Likewise, this partial plan pi
0 can be seen to stand for a set of plans
in which
this is the first action and that are the
last action. Now intuitively we can see that
we will
have to somehow make the connections between
these and the kind of connections that
we will need to make is that how do we generate
the. So, I must have some action.
So, a little bit like backward state space
search; some action I must have stack a on
b
which will have an effect on a b which I will
link to this essentially. So, this is like
saying that I have specified now one more
action in my plan that I must have the stack
a
.b action, and along with specifying this,
I am going to specify the few more things.
For
example, I would say that there is a causal
link between stack a b and a infinity and
stack
a b is producing this predicate on a b which
is being consumed by infinity. So, I must
establish a causal link.
And one of the things that we would want to
do in partial order planning is to somehow
add causal links and see that they are not
disturbed later essentially and various people
have tried various approaches to that essentially.
So, this is the causal links which is
doing that essentially. So, let me say this.
.
So, let say you unstack a from let us call
this b here in the different planning problem
and
then you want to generate this holding a and
you want to link it to put down b put down
a
essentially or instead of putdown a, let me
choose a different action which is to stack;
let
us say a on c. I want to illustrate what I
mean by this disruption of causal links
essentially. So, what am I doing here? I am
saying that I have an action unstack a; it
produces holding a which is consumed by stack
a onto c or instead of c, you can use a
variable x or something like that, it does
not matter.
And let us say this arrow stands for a causal
link essentially and implicitly we assume
.that wherever causal link goes and other
link follows that this much happen before
this.
So, it implicitly captures it essentially.
Now I have said that my plan is a partial
plan.
Now supposing I have some other action floating
around in my plan which says that
stack let us say d 1 to y. So, let me change
my example a little bit. Let us say this is
producing it is producing holding a, but it
is also producing clear b and then I am saying
unstack stack x on to b.
So, this also illustrates a fact that when
I am considering two actions, they do not
necessarily have to be continuous essentially.
So, I am not saying that this action
happens immediately after this. I am saying
this happens after this sometimes, but this
action unstack a b; one of the things it produces
is clear b and for the stack action x on b,
I need to consume this clear b action. Because
I can only put something on into b if b is
clear. So, I want to emphasize the fact that
that they are not contiguous; this could
happen at supposing it is eventually you produce
a linear plan because it is a one arm
robot and it can only do things in a linear
fashion.
So, let us say this is the fifth action, and
this is the twelfth action. So, I am not saying
anything about that; all I am saying is that
there is a causal link from this action to
this
action which means it is producing something
which this is consuming. And there is an
ordering link which says that this was happened
and sometime only later this must have
happened. And now somewhere in my partial
plan, there is a action floating around
called stack d onto y which says that you
stack this object d onto some variable y.
Now
we can see as I say that let us assume this
is the fifth action and this is the twelfth
action.
What if this was the seventh action sometime
in between and what time this y became
equal to b; remember we can do these binding
constraints. So, some point I might say
stack for some reason that stack d onto b.
So, there is a danger that this causal link
that I
am interested in is going to get disrupted
by this action. And my planning process must
somehow take this into cognizance and try
to do something about it; we will come to
that
in a moment. So, some of the older planning
algorithms, there was an algorithm called
tweak one of the first nonlinear planning
algorithms. This was written by a guy called
Ariston Tate.
.So, if you look of Tate and tweak, you will
find get some information on the web. They
use the term clobbering which modern planning
people do not use, and they also use the
term declobbering. And I was told that Ariston
Tate has one of these online courses on
planning which one of my acquaintances was
telling me about. So, I am sure if you
search for this online course, you will hear
lot about tweak and this process essentially.
So, what do I mean by clobbering? I mean I
am clobbering the casual link. This action
threatens to clobber this causal link.
And if it clobbers it, another action might
declobber it essentially which means that
even
if I let say stack d on to b at some later
point I might say unstack d from y because
eventually I want to stack b on to y. So,
I am just trying to give you a flavor of the
nature
of partial order planning that you keep throwing
actions into your partial plan, because
you somehow discover that those actions are
necessary. Like, for example, deciding that
you have to take a train from Chennai to Delhi
and then you keep adding more actions.
When you add more actions you have to be careful
about things like this essentially.
That casual links are not disrupted essentially,
then when we talk of links like ordering
links; one is to talk about consistency. The
ordering links should be consistent, and what
do I mean by this? You cannot say that a happen
before b and b happens before c and c
happens before a, then you have a cycle and
then that is not consistent essentially. So,
another thing that the planning algorithm
will have to do is to know what is the planning
algorithm we are talking about.
..
We are talking about a set of refinement steps
and the refinement steps are of four kind,
add an action to the set a, add ordering link
to this set of ordering links, add the casual
link to see. Anyway it says whenever you add
this, you have to also add one here or add
a constraint. So, what we are saying is that
we will start with a partial plan; we will
start
with this partial plan always an action a
0 which produces the start state as it is
showed
here and an action a infinity which consumes
the goal state as we have shown there. And
then we want to fill in more and more stuff;
how do we fill in? We have a series of
refinements steps.
What do refinement steps do? They may add
an action; for example, I said here that you
must add this action stack a and b, then I
must add a causal link between this and a
infinity and an ordering link between this
and a infinity. So, I could choose any one
of
these refinement operators, and that is where
the search will come into play. And
eventually, I need to refine the plan more
and more which means specify the plan more
and more. Initially, when I have only a 0
and a infinity, I could have an infinite number
of plans which would fit into this and which
would still be a solution.
..
So, what is a solution? When do we terminate?
One way to say it is that, okay, if you
want to decide whether a partial plan is a
solution, then you could at look at it from
the
state space perspective, which means you completely
specify it. Complete; that means a
slight b here; they do not any variables in
the plan. Insensate all variables to something,
produce a linear order or in other words do
a topological sort, because given a partial
order, you can always convert it to a consistent
linear order. And that process as I am
sure you know is called topological sorting
and this topological sort of pie will give
me
some pie prime.
And then I will just use the old mechanism
of progressing from the start state, applying
the actions one by one, because now I have
sequence of actions. I will apply the first
action, then the second action, then the third
action and so on and check whether the last
state that I get is the goal state or not.
Of course, I could do that; the travel is
the
topological sorts could be many. So, do I
check for one sort or do I do for all. So,
if you
go back to this shoe wearing problem which
no doubt you have encountered at some
point.
You could first wear both the socks and then
the two shoes, then both the sox could wear
in any order and then the two socks two shoes
in any order or you could first wear the
.left socks, then the left shoe, then the
right socks, then the right shoe; all these
minimizations of the partial plan that we
talked about but we did not draw are valid
plans. They are valid ways of wearing a pair
of shoes; do I need to look at all those socks
and then do that? That would be too painful.
Instead the partial planning community has
come up with a different test for a solution
plan and we say that as well plan has no
flaws. Of course, we need to clarify what
do we mean by this essentially.
So, what are we interested in? We are interested
in a way of looking at a partial plan
and
saying whether it is a solution plan or not,
it is a solution or not. And implicitly, what
we
mean is this that if this was a solution,
then I could take any ordering of the actions
and
that would any consistent ordering by which
you mean that if there is an ordering
relation in the partial plan, it must be respected
in the solution plan in the linear plan, and
that is called topological sort. I can do
with any topological sort and that will be
a valid
plan.
But I do not want to actually do this process
of making linear orders and testing,
applying that, check for validity function.
I want to look at the partial plan itself
and
make it this observation essentially, okay.
So, it should have no flaws. So, what do we
mean by flaws? There are two kinds of flaws;
one is called open goals. By open goals,
you mean no casual links. So, if you look
at my partial plan of three objects which
you
have to somehow figure out from this stuff
on the board, I have one action a 0. I am
trying to solve those Sussman anomaly problems;
I have one action.
So, this is my starting position and a 0 essentially
produce this starting position. I have
one action a infinity which has these two
preconditions; one of them has a causal link
which is stack a on b, but this instead intern
has more casual links or more preconditions.
So, you must be holding a. Then b must be
clear; I think that is all, right. So, if
I look at
this partial plan of three objects a 0 stack
a b and a infinity, I have three open goals
or
three unsatisfied goals; one is clear b, one
is holding a and one is on b c. And I say
if I
have an open goal in my partial plan which
means I have a unsatisfied goal or I have
a
goal which does not have a causal link, then
that is a flaw in my plan essentially.
So, a solution plan must not have open goals.
If it has no open goals, then it could be
a
.solution plan. The other kind of flaw is
called a threat, and what we saw here was
a
threat essentially. What is that threat? A
threat and action threatens a causal link.
So,
causal links can have threats from actions
essentially. When is this situation a threatening
situation? It must satisfy three conditions.
So, I will just mention them today and in
the
next class we will take it up from there.
First thing is that it must be somehow undoing
this predicate that the casual link is
supporting. Remember that every causal link
has a predicate produced by one consumed
by the other. If it can somehow produce lot
of clear b; so if this action has an effect
not
clear b, then it could be a threat, why? Because
this action stack something onto b; it
requires b to be clear, and this action is
producing that or clobbering that predicate.
So,
how do we express this view? We say this that
we cannot unify this tear by and by unify
for the moment, we will just assume that we
cannot assign this value to this variable
which means, if y becomes equal to b, then
this action could be a threat, but that is
only
one condition.
There are two more conditions. The other two
conditions are that this action happens
after this action and before this action.
If all these three conditions were to be true
which
means that I can put y equal to b in my plan?
I can add an ordering link between unstack
a b and this like this which means it is consistent
to add this ordering link. And I can add
an ordering link like this which means this
action happens before this action. If all
these
three things happen, then we say that the
theta is materialized essentially, and in
effect, it
will no longer be a valid plan, because once
you have put d on to b, you cannot put this
x
on to b essentially.
So, something has gone wrong with the plan
essentially, but this is only a potential
threat. It is a potential threat, because
my plan is a partial plan; I do not know what
this
value for y is. I can force it to be not equal
to b; for example, I said you can do
something like this. I can say do not stack
it on to b, then of course, I have removed
the
threat or I can say force it to happen before
this action. Then also I have sort of evaded
the threat or I can say force this action
to happen after this action essentially; that
we will
see the algorithms for resolving flaws.
.But we have this idea of a threat now and
action a or let us say an action c threatens
a
causal link a p b; if it is consistent that
it can produce lot of p if it is consistent
that it can
happen after a and before b, then it is a
potential threat essentially. And of course,
you
resolve that threat we will have to see that
one of those three conditions does not happen
essentially. So, we say that partial plan
is a solution plan if it has no flaws and
by this we
mean, it has no open goals like for example,
here we have three open goals this one this
one and this one. And it must have any threat
essentially.
In this example, I have only three open goals.
So, may be my step would be to put in the
action which will produce this or put in the
action which will produce this. And this is
the general flavor that once I have flaws
in
my plan and the flaw should be either open
goal or a threat, I must produce a solution
for
the flaw which is to say somehow takes care
of that flaw essentially. So, the high level
algorithm for partial order planning or plan
space planning or least commitment planning
or nonlinear planning is to start with a empty
plan a 0 n p t, which basically is telling
you
what the start state is and what the goal
state is. Keep refining it till there are
no flaws
left essentially.
Once you have no flaws, you must still have
a partial order; you may not have specified
a complete order. Like for example, in this
shoe wearing example, but that would still
be
a plan. And by this we mean we take any consistent
linearization of those actions, and
that action will be a plan in the sense of
those plans being a valid plan in the state
space
perspective that we have seen earlier. So,
today we have just specified what do we mean
by a partial plan. So, this is four topple
made up of a set of actions which may be
partially instantiated the set of ordering
links which may not be complete, a set of
casual
links which may just link some actions with
other actions and set of binding constraints
which says that some variables can takes some
values or cannot take some values and so
on.
And we have defined what does it mean for
it to be a solution plan that it should have
no
flaws, no open goals and no threats, and task
is to keep refining a partial plan till it
has
no flaws essentially. So, we look at this
algorithm in the next class when we meet which
is on next Friday.
.