So, we are looking at plan space planning
and its known as we discuss in the last class
by
various names partial out of planning, lease
commitment planning. And the different
between plan spaces planning, state space
planning is plan space planning purchase in
the space of all possible plans.
.
And a plan in represented as a 4 topple where
the first one is actions as they could be
operators with variables inside them then
ordering links
the causal links and then binding
constants. So, a plan is basically made of
this 4 topple and we have observed that pi
0 is
always with a 2 actions A 0 and A infinity.
And it as 1 ordering links if says that A
happens before A infinity it as know binding
constants no causal links. And that is
always the starting position for such in plans
space planning where A 0 if remember is an
action whose pre conditions are nil and post
condition are others started. Whatever the
dedicates in the start state of everything
is a effect of the A 0 actions. And A infinity
you
.in the action which consumes the goal predicates
and has no effect. So the starting node
in such space is this pare of 2 actions and
the ordinary constrain between them. So, let
us
first write down on the algorithms and then
will discuss for those constants. So, high
level algorithms for plan space planning so
begins with pi 0 which is a initial plan.
And
we will use pi to stands of plans in general
we initialize pi to pi 0 and then while we
discuss flaws that will pi them again and
a moment.
So, the basic strategy in plan space planning
is to inspect the plan for flaws and try to
resolve those flaws one by one essentially.
And you have using here what we will call
as
nondeterministic operator which we choose
some flaw from the set of flaw that in the
plan is will define flaw the again in moment.
And it looks for resolvers as will assume
that we have mechanism for fine in of what
are the resolvers for those flaws? They may
be more than 1 and then again we say choose.
If the set of resolvers empty then you
cannot you find of plan else choose resolver
R belong to set. Again we assume that
nondeterministic will make the right choice
which is by at this stage we can return empty
in practice. Off course, I am sure your know
conversion with this idea now, that we talk
about nondetermisum algorithms like this.
It basically implies at the background the
deter mist calculation there search happening
essentially. So, you would try 1 flaw from
this set try to resolve it and then if will
each at then you will back track and try the
next
flaw and resolve it.
Likewise you would choose one resolver to
use of flaw and carry forward. And if you
each at then your backtrack and try the next
resolver. So, essentially in currently there
is
a search embedded behind this nondetermisum
choose operators which we and a familiar
with that here we will assume that somehow
a choosing the collect clause of this
algorithms is nondeterministic in nature.
Then let us a pi 1 or pi gets lets in a apply
is a
choose is applies operator to pi essentially.
So, this so here we have looking for the set
of
is the dissolvers the flaw then we are picking
1 resolver and applying that 2 pi which
means little do something to the plan remove
that flaw in some way. And then update the
plan essentially and will keep doing that
is longest the plan has a flaw essentially.
Only
place we will exist which failure so of after
we exist from this off course we just return
on pi. But the other place so exist is when
we cannot find the resolver for flaw between
is
exploding all possible resolver in missing.
And then we are discussing that they are 2
.kinds of flaws one is open goal and the other
is threat. So, let us discuss this suspense
that we at seen earlier remember that we a
shown that a algorithms like goals type
planning, which does linier planning in the
sense at it breaks of the goals one by one
trails all the first goal and then trails
all the second goal.
.
And we are shown that with the problem like
this with the goal like on A B and on B C.
If this is the goal set which in our system
would be represented by A infinity having
goals on just you short forms on B C if it
is nothing. So if you remember this was the
suspense annually the start the goals state
was at a s on B and B s on C and the starting
state was that C is on A.
..
And B is on the table A is on the table which
again you will recall you can represent by
A 0 with no input and anything that is here
which is let us say norms empty global be
we
a having a dealing with A 1 norms. So, what
on take this for this ants for A 1 table B
clear B on table A on C A clear A that. So
start action an that is end action that is
so
suspense monopoly problem way wave we have
way simple problem of 3 blocks. And
what we so earlier was that if you try to
say that of the 2 goals that I have on A B
on B C
I will try to solve them 1 by 1. The first
I will completely solve on A B then I will
completely solve on B C or in the other order
that you cannot do essentially when you do
the second goal it enviably disc rubs the
first goal that you had achieve earlier. So,
these
goals are what we set was nonsingular lisable.
And what you want see the plans space
planning offers the possibility of solving
such problems and finding optimal solution.
So, if you work out the solution in your mind
for this problem where this is the start state
an that is a goal state. The optimal solution
is the 6 step solution was you first untaxed
from A put it on the table then put B on to
C that is 2 more action. Then put A on to
C
that is 2 more action goals at planning would
never find this 6 step plan and plan space
planning can find influence that why interest
in that. Now, they are 2 kind in flaws as
you set in a plan, one is opens of goal or
open goals we will use a 2 terms synthetic
ignobly. Another is a threat so as of now,
this partial plan which as only 2 actions
A 0
.and A infinity as 2 flaws. And they are 2
open goals which say that there is nothing
supplying this predicate what we need is some
action which will supply this predicate.
While in other words every open goal must
have a supporting causal link which means
we must have some action here which produces
this predicate which is consumed were
this actually
so threats. So, let us what is the look looked
at threats.
.
So, let us say some point us on to pick up.
Let say pickup M is a block. So I am drawing
in this top to down as is open a practice
is many books M city some way here. And I
have on ordering from top to down which have
will not draw. Because we have only few
actions with discuss here. And then some way
we have the action let say stack n on to y
so I will you this question mark to distinguish
constants from variables as you also open
practice. So, n is a constants with means
the block name is n and this question mark
y
means it is a variable. So, we do not know
which block you n stack n 1 to some for some
reason you have got this action have an this
happy this is the ordering an this is the
order.
And let us say one of the B condition for
this is clear M of course there other B
condition. It will remember the strict action
that A must B M T and M must b on the
table and 1 of this clear M. So, let us so
let say this is opens goal that is flaws b
addressing so how do you how do you address
how do you resolve this open goal flaw?
They are 2 possibilities, one is that an existing
action in the plan can supply the predicate
.which means as already action some way and
you can just establish causal link from that
action to this action provide it.
It is consistent and by this we mean the ordering
links a consistent by and by that we
mean that there are no cycles in that essentially.
The other option the other way of is
ordering open goal list to add an new action.
So, for example, in this situation there is
no
action which can supply on A B or on B C so
we are comparing to add a new action. So,
for example, we might say stacks A B as on
action and this provide this causal link to
on
A B. That the second way of in solving the
open goal which is to add an new action to
the plan how do we add an action to the plan?
We add the action to this set of actions
then we add a causal link from this new action
to the predicate that we a try to support.
And means certain ordering link here and if
there any constant and we for example, you
make want to say add stack x y an x equal
to A and Y full B. But will skip that part
essentially likewise you could say this is
achieved by stack B C. So, because of the
stack
that one other things we are doing in plans
space planning is resolve open goals. It still
as
a flavor of backward is in, because open goals
are only in the goals state and the new
keep building.
But it split possible that you end of first
satisfying some open goals then jump here.
So,
there is no fixed order of such essentially.
The other in case in thing about plans space
planning with here observed was that in state
place planning both the selection of the
action and position in the action was them
simultaneously in 1 move. So, for example,
forward space place would say this is the
next action. So which means the select the
action an also set the next position is the
next in the plan. Because they are plan is
a
sequence actions likewise in the backward
stage space search you sack construct in the
plan from n steps. In plan space planning
we are selected this action stack A on B and
stack Bon C, but we are not say anything about
what is you pending the relating already
in between them essentially. So, we separate
the task of selecting in action and infusing
an ordering on the action essentially so that
is then independently. So, in principle off
course this allows to first select some action
in between. For example, if they have
something with as very practical to the plan
and we knew it was practical then we could
select it in between. And we a choose in select
of example of going from place a to place
b.
.So, if at to go from here to there on for
example, I would to say I need to flight to
Delhi
first and I put that action in between. So
plans space planning allows you to do that
but,
this kind of listing which is more up stack
requires still more structure in the plan.
And
structure is difficultly hypothetical in nature.
So your to top of high level actions and the
define in to low lower actions which you are
not going to considered. Here so we a
working as the at the action level which the
at 1 plat level essentially which is the I
this
as the flavor of backward search to some extent.
So, we have this clear M here and let us
say do make clear M B say up stack something
let say it do not give. Now, what that is
from x from m and that will produce this.
So I will use the dotted line to represented
causal link which means this is producing
this and this consumedly that essentially.
So,
this was off course happen before this essentially.
So the moment in set this action in to
my plan. So, what we that do in this? Already
they in my plan this 4 actions the 2 start
actions and the this 2 actions at for they
in plan.
And then I have added this action up stack
something from M and added that. Because I
want to resolve this goal of clear M, but
the moment I have this plan structure. It
has a
flaw which is of the type threat essentially
and what is the threat? In the threat is that
here on the casual link so basically threat
is to a casual link. Always that something
is
trying to disturb to casual link what is the
casual link doing? Casual link says this action
is producing clear m which is consumed by
this pickup M action. So, I which established
casual link in my plan essentially. Now, because
there are variables involved here,
because of fact that we do not know what is
ordering of these 3 actions. Off course, we
not this once come before this, but we do
not my anything about how this is place
between take to these to. Then the put essential
rate what is the put essential rate that this
action will come in between these 2 actions.
And this y will be in to M which would
mean
that for pickup M I needed clear M to be true,
but if this stack n on to M happens
before that which means it happen between
these 2 actions.
So, let us a this is the threat data an considering
that this happens first this happens next
in this happens third. So, this action happens
after this action an before this action and
there is the possibility that this y I can
we made equal to M or bond to M then you can
see the details destroying this casual link.
Because for pickup m needed clear m by
putting n on to M that clears M is been lost.
So, this action is the threat to this casual
link
.so as we I think discuss in the last class.
And action is threat and when you say threat
it
algorithms potential threat to a casual link.
If it can produce so what can it produce?
It
can produce not clear y as an effect so effects
are below and the p condition are that it
can produce an effect. Lets us call it not
p which can the infinite with a condition
p
needed by the this action which means is pointed
destroyed this condition. If can so in
other wards is y can be infinite with M and
many say infinite we mean by could M is
possible and this action happens after this
action and this action happens before this
action. So this 3 conditions were to become
too at that y equal to M and there as on
wonderingly between this and this and on wonderingly
between this and this then the
threat would materialize.
And my plan with a longer is a valid plan,
because is would know this would come on
open goal which on a longer be satisfied.
Because a casual link was satisfying this,
but in
certain this action in between destroyed at
casual link. So, threat is the other kind
of flaw
in the plan 1 of 1 is A simply kind that open
goal as those support the other kind is that
there is a threat to how to be resolve the
threat? So, there are 3 west of resolver threat
1 is
separation which in this example. So, basically
say add of binding constants. And make
sure that this cannot unify with is which
means add this to might set up binding constants
essentially. One side does that they can know
that I am not going to stack this n on to
M.
I will stack known to something else which
means M is free for whatever that x is to
be
stack known to that. That is one way of resolving
a threat another way is to demote is
called demotion So, let us say in general
terms let us say action A is a threat to a
link call
A one some predicate p in action A 2. So,
this is A 1 this is A 2 and this is action
A one
way so say that p is different which is separation
the other 1 is demotion which says that
that action A happen after this pickup M which
means add the link A 2 happening before
A.
So, when I say add added to the relevant place
when I binding ordering link I must added
to this set when I binding constants I must
added to that is set an so on. So, I can pushes
action down and so we say it is been demoted
it happens later. That were also resolve the
threat, because then nothing is disputing
this clear M. Because they all this happens
some
were later another third is as we can a imagine
promotion which is you add A 1 to
happen before A again to the set of ordering
links. So, we have basically 5 resolvers for
.open goal we have 2 resolver’s goal I just
say old action. By this I mean an existing
action so may be just right existing actions
order new action. To resolver open goal
either fines some existing action which can
supply the predicate all if you cannot then
add a new action. Because taking an old action
existing action may actually violated the
constant that the should be no cycle in the
action. So, this is all the open goal and
this for
the threat essentially and algorithm essentially
goals. So, this cycle of choosing of flaw
how a initial plan as 2 flaws those 2 open
goals choosing a resolver. So, both of those
flaws we are chosen to resolver who is to
add the new action. And a keep doing that
till
there are no more flaws left in the action.
So, this is the less a this is the flaw an
underline 1 and if have cycle it then it is
been resolved. But off course, these actions
have their own requirements.
So, stack B C requires holding B it requires
clear c it requires on no in that is all and
it
produces a from on b c produces a empty an
produces clear B. So, let us assume that
clear B is an effect of stack in B on to C
which means 1 unstack something of where if
you are to under stack of B from something
then B would be your longer clear. So, when
you are holding it B is not clear only when
it predict down it is clear essentially.
Likewise this needs clear B holding A and
it produces arm empty and its produces clear
A. So, everything A
is an open goal every time we added new action
all is B conditions
are open goal essentially then we look for
of flaw and resolve it is essentially. So,
let us
say we look for this flaw clear B and you
say this action is producing clear B. So,
I have
an existing action which is supplying clear
B so I had an ordering link which so I say
that
that this action or this clear B is consumed
by this. So, I anode ordering link which is
at
their link is between the actions that this
action was happen. So, first an must stack
B on
C which will produce this clear B and then
I will consume clear we when I stack A on
to
B known A B C.
So, you can see that slow logical in some
sense that you know you can see that you must
first stack B on to c and then A on to B an
at least 6 doing in this part correctly
essentially. Now, let us at this 1 it to this
is an action so an action that we can fine
is
unstack no holding A. So, action that we can
kind is pick up A and the action for this
also we can fine is so this here picking care
of pickup B. Lets a we are doing this in this
order so pickup we will also produce other
things likes no arm empty. In that is sense
A
.little delete A empty it needs arm empty
as a predicate A empty is predicate will
producing not A empty it needs on table A
this needs on table B. So, let us right it
here
on table B on table A it needs clear A it
needs clear B
observe that we have and open
goal clear B here which could I will supplied
by that action stack B on to C. But we
cannot choose that, because then we would
have to say that that happens before this
and
you already setup this happen before that.
So, something which is a kind of goal with
is
that the moment you added a causal link this
a causal link we are added. Pickup B
produces holding B which is consumed by stack
B on to C. The moment we add this link
we also added ordering link essentially.
So, once you have added an ordering link is
this selection we cannot add on ordering link
in this selection. So, we cannot choose this
that for this essentially. So, let us say
that we
choose this as an open goal and we say unstack
something x from A and that will make it
clear. So, become an effect of this action
and it also produce holding x and another
things and unstack x on A needs x to be on
A. So, we can produce it like this that this
start action has an effect call on C A and
we can say if you say that x equal to C then
we
can establish this casual link here. So, this
is taken care of the which am not drawn here
the C condition for this is on C A that is
taken care of, because it is will produce
by A 0
another C condition is arm empty which is
also produce by this. And the third a
condition is clear C which must be there somebody
should of point is these are this we
clear C and that is solving. So, the c conditions
need for unshackling c from we which is
clear C is true in the initial state, on C
A true in the initial state. And arm empty
is true in
the initial state and they are produce for
this so we establish this 3 casual links which
will
do that essentially.
Now, we can see there if will look at this
casual link here that A 0 is producing A empty
which is being consume by unstack C from A
is being threat arm by this action here
pickup B. Because if pickup B we have not
set when pickup B is always set is that A
happens then we some stack C from A happens.
Then pick up A happens notice also that
this cannot happen immediately afterwards
and once you unstacks C from A we are
holding C and it would produce something call
mark arm empty and holding C. So,
which means we obviously cannot do unstack
C from A followed by pick up A, because
pick up A also needs arm to be empty. But
our plan an as only set that this must happen
.before that an nothing else we are not set
that no action can be in certain between an
as
way will see that can be done essentially.
So, the only thing set is 1 line is at you
unstack
C from A and there at some point you pick
up A an stack an to B. But before you stack
an to B some time you stack B on to C and
before you stack B on to C you must pick up
B essentially so that is all we have so of
essentially. But now, we have a threat this
is
being is a threat in this is threat in to
disturb this casual link here.
So, we have these 3 option available separation
is not possible, because there no
variables safe. Promotion is not possible,
because A 0 is the first action which always
the
first action an nothing can happen before
A 0. The only thing remains is demotion which
means we say the this must happen after this.
It means we in introduce the casual an
ordering link between this and that. Then
let us say that so let us say that we address
one
of these issues they lets a we looking at
this arm empty. And we are pushed it be on
this
so we cannot connect it to the start in action.
So, we must produce some action calls
pickup our put on something. This put on by
will need holding y and this open goal can
be might by this goal holding C by seen y
could to C essentially. So, what are the actions
we have so far? We have what is action unstack
C from a pickup A put down so this will
become C here put down c is someway so 1 2
3 4 5 6 if got all the 6 actions that we need.
And I will set up leave this is the small
exercise so you to see that now, you can resolve
all the flaws in this by either introducing
in ordering constant to remove a threat. All
connecting so for example, we can connect
this to this which means this must happen
after that.
So, the first action that we can C is unstacking
C from A and sometime after that you
must have pick up A. And sometime after that
you must have put down C we do not
know we just know that this happens after
that. Then we know that after putdown C we
must have pick up B from A. After pickup B
we have stack B C an sometime after stack
B C we have stack A B off course it is not
at proper plan, because as you can C you can
a
do this to action stack B C and stack A B
immediately afterwards. It needs A pre
condition which is destroyed by this which
is should be holding A. So, you can see that
this needs holding A and that is provided
by this. So, this is a pre condition an some
we
out to figure out that the sequence of fraction
is that you unstack C from A when you
putdown C when you pick up B stack B on to
C and then this needs to be added. That
.this pickup we must be happen after stack
B C so why it happens? I will owe it as a
small, because it happens. Because some flaw
is to be resolved and the flaw could be for
example, that arm empty you are something
like that is needed for pickup A and stack
B
on the c producing arm empty so we with that
will right the stack.
So, in the end will have one order go from
here to here on here to here sorry go from
here to here when go from here to here? And
we expect earlier plan in this particular
example, because of the fact that we a dealing
with a one arm brought. And you can do
only one thing at the time as oppose to other
kind of domains. For example, this shoe tie
domain that we discuss earlier to were lefts
out were life rights of were left shoe were
right shoe there the final plan may not have
a leave your order essentially. It will have
a
parlor order that you first were the 2 socks
and then you were the 2 shoes and then you
are done essentially. And then you could do
between them in any order essentially. So,
any linearization of a partial order or any
to topological out of a partial order should
be a
valid plan. That is a original condition is
started with, but in set of having to check
all
linearization we have change this too is condition
that which should have known flaws.
And the flaw as define is they must be known
open goals. It means every open goal or
every goal every sub goal must have a supporting
casual link.
And they must be no threats that no action
must be threat in to dispute casual link
essentially. And as on is that condition is
satisfied the plan that we produce is going
to be
a valued plan. In this case it terms out to
be linear plan which you are also the optimal
plan essentially. The off course we would
possibly observe that they little bit of a
right of
a hand here that as some of chosen the right
actions and the right things. In a put some
away chosen the right things for this choose
a flaw on choose in action. So, notice at
this
a symmetric situation we want to pick up B
on we want to pick up A. And I choose pick
up A which let us to the plan if have chosen
pickup B then you can see that there know
way you could have produce the optimal plan
we the produce longer plan. Because if
you are going to do pickup B as a action which
is the after this then you will have to put
it down again. And then pickup C put it down
and then pick up A so although extraction
would keep in a essentially. So, this is the
basic idea of plans space planning this is
the
algorithms there are variation would be algorithms
which people have essentially.
.Some people only maintain and is in the,
of to be solve and the keep is ordering threat
along the way is in the open goals to be solve.
This is the more generate algorithms an
you can off course right variations this you
can put in some heuristic and so on
essentially. So I will just like to end with
((refer tim.) about something which and
mention on the way which is this notion of
so if you have observe what was happening
here? We started such resolving open goals
from the end essentially. Because x y the
open goals for an this produce more open goals
and we had this flavor of backward
reasoning happening essentially. And that,
because we are working as the ground level
we are only considering action which are applicable
in the do mine but, if you at high
level actions like know go from here to Delhi.
Now, that is not an which is the ground
level action the ground level action would
have many other steps that you go from here
to the station you go the tree in an all this.
If you have this notion of hypothetical actions
which means action which can decomposition
in to smaller actions then we can talk
about high level plan and then refining it
in to lower level plan.
And then this strategy that we at spoken about
earlier means ends analysis. If it member
Simon a Newell the means an analysis strategy
problem solving was the another first
strategy proposed by in a in the 60’s in
the last century. It was based on the way
thought
human beings solve problem. And the basic
idea behind means an analysis is that just
like we have flaws and we have resolvers of
flaws. A more general think is that you have
different is and you have resolvers for defenses
so what you mean by differences? So, in
this travel do mine I would say there are
many different is my plan to go from here
to
deradun. One is at the highest difference
is that I am here I am not in deradun so in
that is
in sense it is like of flaw. But then decompose
it in lower level actions the, and then I
decide that you know I need these steps I
need go from here to station all. Let us say
even lower level there I to go from here to
the gate and then gate to the station and
then
getting to a train and then go to Delhi. And
so I if realize that and if a can recognize
the,
these are the difference is that I and it
to resolves.
So difference one difference is that I am
in Chennai not in Dehradun. And so the largest
difference I me have a difference operator
table which would say if distance is more
than
500 kilometer you must take a train or of
flight. If distance is less than between 100
and
500 you can take up bus or something like
that we have a operator difference stable
like
.that. And then the key thing about means
and analysis is at if you have difference
is and
if you a operators you must choose a largest
differences first. The largest differences
would be that I am in Chennai I am not in
Delhi and once says say that I have to resolve
that differences first I would first selection
action or the plan for doing that. And that
let
us say that action is taking a train from
Chennai central to Delhi. And then I have
smaller
difference is left am here not in the station
that is 1 difference then I will Delhi station.
But I am not in lets I am taking to a bus
there as soon I am not the bus station on
anything likes that essentially. So, you address
higher difference is first and the lower
difference is later. So differences are the
ends and operators are the means to a cheap
bus
ends essentially. And means at the analysis
says that you must analyze the do mine. And
look at the larger more important things for
first an less them and then look at the less
important things essentially.
So, 1 interesting example of this is this
tours of ((refer time.) which we must be
familiar with. So, if you want lets a move
5 dist from location A to location C then
there
are 5 differences. In that smallest this see
that a not at C second smallest dist this
at A not
in C you are 5. And if we can now, order this
difference say the larger the dist the more
the difference then the here means. And analysis
strategy says that first whatever moving
the biggest disk to the definition then many
about moving the other this essentially. And
then off course, you know the familiar ((refer
tim.) algorithms will come
automatically out of this that you move n
minus those to B then move this largest this
to
C and so on essentially. So, all those can
be seen as specific case is of means analysis
and that was propose fight long time in their
book for human problem solving. So, all
this algorithms that we are have seen of planning
so far. These are in some sense ancient
they are all developed in the last century
sometime. It terms out that whatever however
tries to right this algorithms. The problem
is hard member we said that even the split
domain the simplest planning domain is piece
space complete essentially.
So, we terms of that even in simple domains
the only kind of plans we can find were of
lengths something like 5 to 10 essentially.
So, if you are the problem in which the
solutions of 5 steps longer 10 steps long
then we could use is algorithms for solving
them. Then in 1995 of pare of researches care
of with a new idea and with an algorithms
which look at this whole thing in very different
way. In algorithms call graph plan an
.there was the variation which came long along
that time which increase the length of the
plans could be found by an order of magnet
to essentially. It means it we could find
plans
of lengths 10 we these algorithms goes stack
planning or any of these algorithms we
could find plans of lengths of 100 using these
new algorithms essentially. Off course, we
would not have time to study those algorithms
in details in this course, but in the next
class I will just give a games of this algorithms
Graph plan which is kind of a land mark
algorithms in the world of planning essentially.
And will end with planning in this course
with that essentially so I will stop here.
Student: This shows A 2 should happen before
this shows that A 1 happens before A.
Promotion here promoting so A should happen
before A 1 that is right holding is not part
of length. Sorry.
Student: Here holding is not part of length
here this is we are going to pick up A to
after
stacking B on C we are pick up in A.
Then you have this holding A not an action
it is a predicate that is a I drawn a circle
on
that for an action. After that after pick
in up a stack A on to B in that is a last
step in the
plan essentially. So, we will stop here.
.