So, we continue looking at optimization and
we are looking at methods which we called
as population based. So, basically when we
say population based methods and we will
spend some time on this today. We mean that
instead of working with a single candidate
solution for example, as we do in hill climbing
or in simulated annealing we work with a
population of candidates. Now, the benefits
that we get by working with populations I
have not just speed up, because it is not
as if you are running the same algorithm k
times
or n times if n is the size of population.
You also get benefit from the fact that different
candidates can contribute jointly to exploring
new solutions. So, essentially we are
exploring the solutions space which for real
problems may not be a smooth surface. And
we are looking for methods which would be
robust which even when the terrain is jagged
we will do reasonably well essentially
So, in population based methods the first
method that we are looking at this moment
we
have called it is genetic algorithms
some people also call them as evolutionary
algorithms. And they have a flavor of bottom
up problem solving we we also called as
.emergent. So, by emergent systems we mean
that we put together a collection of simple
elements and more complex behavior emerges
out of that. And as we might have said
before the human brain is a perfect example
of that every neuron in our brain is
computationally a simple device, but it just
that we have billions of them in our head.
And they are it is a connections it is the
way that they are connected to each other
that
really give raise to our individual brains
essentially. So, the idea in genetic algorithms
is
that we have candidate solutions rather a
population of candidate solutions and each
candidate is made up of components.
So, you can think of this some kind of a breakup
of every component now in the simple
case that we saw about solving sat every component
is the value of one variable or one
bit. And a sats can sat solution candidate
is a bit vector, but in general problems may
be
more complex. And components may themselves
very more complex in nature
essentially in which case of course; we have
to be very careful. Because the general
strategy in solution space search or perturbation
search that we are exploring is that we
perturb candidates to produce new candidates.
So, if we had this as a candidate then
simulated annealing may try to generate a
neighborhood around this by changing one or
2 components as we saw in the case of sat
and do that. So, one has to do the little
more
carefully essentially.
So, when we talk about genetic algorithms
we have to talk about encoding candidate
solution as a string in terms of genetic algorithm.
We would call this as a chromosome
borrowing from the biological world. And essentially
there is an interplay between
chromosomes of different parents essentially
which basically modifies the design of the
candidate or design of the solution essentially.
So, we had mentioned in the last class that
there are these 2 things; one is the genotype
which is made up of the genes. And that in
that influences or they decides the behavior
of the phenotype which is the individual or
the creature or whatever is participating
in the real world essentially. So, in genotype
we
look at recombination’s and the phenotype
basically competes and its participates in
selection. So, these are the main 2 components
of the problem solving strategy that you
might say nature employ employs which is the
trial and error with its designs.
And the design is expressed as a chromosome
essentially which is some kind of a string
that we are going to work with and we said
the use a word recombination’s. So, for
idea
in genetic algorithms is that you draw some
components, some one parent some
.components on another parent and in the hope
that you will inherit the good components
of both parents. So, if you going back to
the rabbit and foxes example, let us say there
are 2 desirable properties amongst rabbits.
One is that they can run fast and other is
that
they are smart so whatever that means you
know. So, for example, you must have as a
child heard a story about the rabbit who has
to go to the lion in the jungle as food. And
then he is a smart rabbit and he tells a lion
of another lion and that kind of stuff. So,
either they are fast or they are smart essentially
which is contribute today’s survival.
So, the whole idea of evolution is that in
a population of candidates, the phenotypes,
the
fitter ones are the ones who survive the competition.
Competition is for resources it
could be for food, it could be for mates,
it could be for shelter which is you know
safety
from the predator essentially. So, if you
are good at doing these things then you are
likely to survive which means you are likely
to pass on your genes to the next generation
and so on and so forth. Now, imagine 2 parents
of a rabbit; one of them is smart and the
other one is fast essentially. The hope in
genetic algorithm is that if these 2 parents
have
let say 2 children that is module that we
are following here at least one of them will
inherit. Both these properties of being smart
and being fast at the same time which means
it will be like a super rabbit essentially
right and super rabbits will give rise to
more
super rabbits so on.
So, in general the rabbit population will
become smarter and faster essentially. So,
that is
the whole idea behind genetic algorithms like
we said one makes up the combinations.
So, there is one processor one force which
makes up the combinations jumps the genetic
pool and the other which is the process of
selection which is that they compete for
survival essentially. So, survival of the
fittest and when we say survival of the fittest
at
least in the case of genetic algorithms we
are going to impose a fitness function on
top of
the algorithm. Because it is based on the
fitness function that we will the candidate
will
survive, but in the real world its other way
round it is basically whoever survive this
is
the one whose fit essentially. So, I want
to do one example of to illustrate genetic
algorithms today, but before that I want to
sort of spend few minutes on this idea of
emergent systems essentially. Because it is
an idea which is has a lot of follows
essentially.
..
So, you must have heard about this conveys
game of life convey something called game
of life. Have you heard about the game of
life? It is like a screen saver sometimes
and the
world is a grid in cellular voltammeter. So,
you know we have rows and columns and so
on
and in the simplest form of this game in every
cell. So, every square is a cell inside
there can be one creature and creature is
a very simple creature it survives. So, it
has
some rules for survival there are rules for
surviving there are rules for being born even
in
this very simple world there rules for dying
essentially. So, the simple rules in this
conveys game of life are that if you are surrounded
by more than three living cells or
creatures in living in cells. Then you are
sort of overcrowded and you die essentially
which means that each cell is in 1 or 0 1
means its alive and 0 means its dead or the
creature inside is dead.
So, if there is a one surrounded by more than
three ones then it dies it becomes 0 if a
0 is
surrounded by exactly three ones then it comes
alive. And if a 1 is surrounded by less
than three ones and it stays alive essentially
or something I may have a small error there
but anyway something of that nature. So, you
have this, very simple rules which control
how a cell evolves over time. So, it is an
automate which goes through a sequence of
time steps. So, at every time step every cell
decides whether in the next time step it will
be alive or dead or whatever essentially.
Now, it turns out that this very simple rules
of
life if you want to call it life give rise
to patterns in this world which is a grid
world and
.which have a tendency to survive. And some
patterns survives some patters oscillate
between 2 3 patterns and some patterns even
move forward.
So, if I remember correctly there is a pattern
which looks like this that if this is one
and
this is one and this is one. So, these five
patterns if they are one and maybe you should
try the rules that I just mention on this,
these cells. Then this pattern essentially
in the
next cycle we will move little bit to the
right may be it will rotate by a little bit
and it will
keep doing that. So, as the time progresses
this pattern will appear to be moving in this
direction. Now, this as sort of takes me back
a little bit to the introduction that when
you
were looking at you know what is reality?
What is really out there? And that kind of
stuff
we were discussing in this simple world. What
is really out there is that these are the
cells which become 1 or 0 essentially. And
that is about it this whole world is full
of cells
and each cell can be 1 or 0. And they follow
certain rules whether to remain 1 or 0 in
the
next time cycle.
But in this world certainly we see patterns
like this; this is called the glider gun and
this
is the very old game, game of life was invented
in 60’s or something like that essentially
or may be 70’s. So, if you just search game
of life or glider gun on the web you will
probably get to see on animation of this.
So, this looks like a creature norm you know
of
this shape which is moving around essentially.
Of course, we are also like that in some
sense made up of how many 10 rise to something
I had mentioned 28 or something
simple cells moving around in a unison pretending
to be a creature. But that is a whole
idea of emergent system essentially that you
put together simple cells or simple
components and put which obey certain local
rules each cell only looks at it only
neighborhood. It does not see anything beyond
its immediate neighborhood and that it its
fate is decided base based on that essentially
you put in such local rules and build a
world like this.
And you will find that patterns I mean because
we tend to think of them is pattern
emerge essentially. So, basically combinations
of simple things tend to behave in a more
complex way essentially. So, more recently
there has been a lot of interest and now
imagine that instead of being this very simple
creatures that these cells are which only
look at the neighborhood. And decide whether
to die or not to die they were slightly
more complex creatures. For example, they
could have a little bit of a memory of their
own and they could have a little bit of listening
something. Then we sort of call them as
.populations of agents or some people call
them as multi-agent and you are talking about
simulations here. So, a lot of people for
example, social scientist are looking at these
multi-agent worlds in which they put together
this simple agents and they study the
behavior of those. Of course, they put together
the rules and so on so forth for example,
work ordering rules or things like that and
sort of look at more sophisticated
implementations of this.
So, I would there is a language called net
logo so you must have heard about logo of
course, devise by paper long time ago to teach
programming to children. So, there is a
total which you can say move north or move
west and so on so many step certain by so
many steps in that kind of thing its net logo
is the more sophisticated language. It has
been in implemented by some people in the
north western university in the US and its
available freely online and many. And I have
some friends who are sort of working with
this and trying to implement these agent based
simulations. And so this whole idea of
exploration is to put together simple elements
impose rules upon them and then study the
behavior. So, people have studied for example,
crowd behaviors and one of my friends
who works in TCS in Pune. He is been doing
this sort of a thing and he is sort of
simulated this behavior of this crowd.
So, there was this fire in some restaurant
in Brazil or some are in the crowd behavior
he
could replicate that crowd behavior by imposing
very simple rules on the agents
essentially. So, what do you do if you are
in a restaurant or a bar and there is a fire
in one
corner of the room? What would you do essentially
you know, so impose simple rules
upon then and then you can actually study
the behavior of crowd essentially. And
nowadays of course, crowd behavior is of great
interest specially in situations like you
know this Uttarakhand tragedy or any tragedy
that befalls upon this. You want to see
how to how the crowd would behave essentially.
So, the so there is one direction to this
population based system is to is this agent
based simulation you create simple agents
put
them together in a world. And then simulate
or run the world to see how what kind of
behavior would emerge essentially.
..
But we will come back to our genetic algorithms
which is also little bit like that except
that there is no spatial connotation here
we have a space which is made up of grids
and
cells in which the people live but in g a’s
we just have a population. And we do not
really talk about space essentially though
there have been people who have also started
speaking about spatial distribution of populations
essentially. So, just as human
populations are sort of distributed in different
continents and different countries and so
on and so forth. They have try to see whether
you know the whole population can be
partitioned into some sub populations and
evolution basically interaction mating. For
example, happens only within that population
and not outside this population. And then
they try to impose rules like migration when
is the agent allow to migrate to a new
country. If I am use the word under what conditions
will this migration be successful
under what condition will it fail and that
kind of thing essentially. For, so those of
you
have been following Australian news and elections
are coming up they have been taking
a very strict stand against emigration.
So, they have said that anybody who arise
by boat will never be given Australian’s
this is
in ship essentially you will also rules like
this. And you can see how it will affect the
population one can think that but we work
with simpler notions which is that we just
have a collection of populations and what
is the algorithm that we had talked about
the
first step is selection. So, we have this
population of some elements and they are allowed
to reproduce themselves based on some fitness
value something like this that is the first
.step which is selection. And we had said
that we will implement the rule wheel kind
of a
mechanism of course, you have to work out
how to do that which will tell which element
gets to reproduce. So, if there are n elements
we will spin the we will n times and
whichever elements comes in front of let us
say the pointer we will get to reproduce
essentially then crossover which basically
means that we randomly pair the new
population that we have. So, let me draw this
by squares we randomly pair them. So, for
example, we could say we pair this one with
this one, this one with this one, this one
with this one maybe I should have an even
number.
But still we do random pairings and allow
the cross over operator which is basically
mixing up the genes of the 2 parents and producing
2 new children. So, you can
centerline sort of see this as a paddle search
in the same space solution space except that
we start with a move is made up by somehow
selecting 2 parents. And then generating 2
new children out of it instead of one parent
giving rise to one child like for example,
hill
climbing or simulated annealing here 2 parents
give rise to 2 children in this example
essentially. And then we had said mutation
which is kind of a rare event once in a while
you change some gene randomly essentially.
This is meant to take care of the fact that
some genes may get lost in so on and so forth
essentially. So, let me take an example to
sort of illustrate how genetic algorithms
work and then we will come back to discussing
what are the issues that you have to decide
upon when you are using genetic algorithms
for optimization So, this is an example which
I am taking from this book by Goldberg.
.
.So, remember I had told you
that the genetic algorithms are device by
somebody called
Holland John Holland and his student called
David Goldberg has written this very
popular book on genetic algorithms. And this
is basically from the first chapter which
is
the introduction chapter of his book. And
it is a nice example and I like it, because
it
illustrate the whole idea of g a quite nicely.
So, it is a very it is called very small
population of size 4 so we have this 4 elements.
So, remember that the first thing we
want to do is to encode this. So, when we
want to use the g a to solve some optimization
problem we have to first encode the candidate
solution. Then we have to devise an
evaluation function which will look a candidate
and give us a number. And ideally the
evaluation function should be in sync with
what we really want to do which means that
for the optimal solution the evaluation function
must have the highest value essentially.
So, let us assume that we will do that and
then with the genetic algorithm thing comes
into play. Now, in this very simple world
I have a 5 bit vector and so the 4 elements
that
I have in this example. So, I have a small
population of size 4 and these are the 4
candidates represented as bit strings. And
let us say that we implement in we interpret
them as binary numbers which means that the
numbers that we are talking about are this
is 13 this is 24; this is 8 and this is 19.
So, essentially these are the candidates but
this is
the representation. So, we have this 4 numbers
13 24 8 and 19 and we want to know our
optimization task is to find the largest number
that you can represent with 5 bits. It may
sound like trigger to you, but we want to
see how genetic algorithms work essentially
and that is our goal and it is a problem that
we understand quite clearly essentially.
And, so we have to have this evaluation function
right. So, let us say we decide so this f
is a fitness function which will take any
candidate and give us a value. And just simply
let us assume it is a x square essentially
a simple fitness function essentially. So,
if you
want to evaluate this 4 candidates the values
that we will get 169 596 64 361. Now, what
is the role of fitness in our algorithm? Our
fitness influences the selection process the
chances of a candidate reproducing itself
our proportional to fitness. So, in our rule
wheel we will have this 4 sector with areas
proportional to these numbers essentially.
So,
this second candidate will have the largest
area the fourth candidate will have the next
largest area and so on and so forth.
So, we will have a rule wheel like which looks
like this
something like this. So, this is 2;
this is 1; this is 3 and this is 4. So, we
just rotate it and whichever thing comes here
we
.select that essentially. So, the probability
of it reproducing is proportional to the fraction
that this is of the sum of this whole thing.
So, this probability value is 0.14 for this.
So,
how did I get this values basically you sum
of this 4 numbers and then this divided by
the sum is 0.14 this divided by the sum is
0.49. So, that is how you get the probability
values which means that every time you spin
this rule wheel the second candidate has
above 50 percent chance of being reproduce
this candidate has about 30 percent chance.
And these 2 candidates have little less chances
essentially that is how the areas are
divided essentially.
So, the expected values let us call them e
are basically these values multiplied by 4,
because we are going to spin the wheel 4 times
in our case. So, the number of incenses of
these candidates that we expect to see is
basically 4 times this. So, this turns out
to be
0.58 1.97. So, what are these numbers? These
numbers are saying that after I have done
this selection space. And what is the selection
space I will spin this wheel 4 times and
whichever candidate this arrow points 2 I
will make a copy of that candidate. So, after
I
spend 4 times I expect to see about 2 candidates
of this about half candidate of this about
one fifth of this and 1.25 of this roughly
is essentially. But of course, in the real
world
these fraction do not mean anything I in the
end I will end up seeing 4 candidates. And
let us assume that when we actually carryout
this experiment the values that we get are
2 0 and 1 its quite feasible, it is quite
possible that if I will spin the wheel 4 times.
I will get 2 copies of the second candidate
one copy of the first one copy of the fourth
and none of the third one essentially. So,
let us say this is what happens this is where
the
random process is this is the first place
where this random process is showing its effect
in
the process of producing the next population.
So, this population is actually this the one
that we have said after we have done the selection
space we started with this and we end
up with this essentially. So, let us redraw
that population so 0 1 1 1 copy of this 2
copies
of this and one copy of this. So, this is
my new population so selection space is over
now
begins a crossover space. So, how so let us
say we pair these 2 and then we pair these
and we put some random crossover point. And
we are doing this single point crossover
which means at some point we will break this
chromosome into half and the same point
will break the next one into half and then
we will exchange the 2 essentially.
So, let us say that our crossover points are
like this one is here and the other one is
here.
So, this will give us a new population So,
this 0 1 1 0 will come here followed by a
0,
.because this 0 comes from the other side
likewise this 1 1 0 0 will come here followed
by
this one which comes from the other side.
And similar thing will happen here 1 1 0 1
and 1 0 0 0 0. So, just to emphasize I take
this part and I take this part and I get this
this
one here and likewise for the other 4 essentially.
So, this is my new population at the end
of one round one cycle of this let us see
whether we have a better population to start
with. Now, if you look at this average fitness
for this it happens to be 293. And the
people who work with genetic algorithm tend
to talk about average fitness of this thing
that in general the population is becoming
fitter. But of course, we are interested in
the
most fit element that is the different point
essentially.
So, let us see how is the new population.
So this numbers corresponds to 12 25 27 and
and there are f of x which is equal to x square
corresponds to 144 625 729 256. So, the
first thing is that average for this new population
is 439. So, starting with this average of
293 we have gone through one cycle of reproduction
and mating or in crossover and we
have got a new population which is this. So,
we started with this whose average fitness
was 293 and we ended up with this whose average
fitness is 439 essentially. So, this is
the kind of thing which g a’s are looking
for that can we get fitter populations and
so on
essentially. So, the whole idea is that if
you have some function in which you are trying
to optimize. Then initially you are population
may be decrease sort of spread over this
whole domain where this is the let us say
one dimensional domain. But after you have
done the g a’s sufficient number of times
you will find that the population is kind
of
concentrated towards the peaks.
And one of them hopefully is the solution
that you are looking for essentially. So,
that is
the general idea behind genetic algorithms.
So, let us look at this next population and
what would happen in the second cycle? We
will not repeat it but we will just start
thinking about it essentially. So, we look
at the probability again if you remember the
probability is obtained by taking the sum
of all these 4 numbers. And if I 144 divided
by
the sum would give me the probability of this
one showing up in this rule wheel the rule
wheel has change now. So, this happens to
be 0.08 this happens to be 0.35 this happens
to be 0.26. So, these are the 4 probabilities
value and corresponding to them the expected
value which is basically 4 times this number
is 0.32 1 1.4. So, these are the values so
want you to now inspect this new population.
So, we started with the one population
whose characteristics are given here average
fitness is 293. And this as the expected
.number of cloning’s allowed here also we
can see the expected number would be I mean
these are the expected number sorry 1.97 0.22
1.23 and so on. And those are the
expected numbers here 0.32 1.4 1.66 0.58.
So I wanted to look at this new population
and its fitness values and make some observations
well, average fitness has gone as you
can see is become 439. The maximum fitness
here goes 576 and there it is 729. So, that
is also gone so is there any problem? What
will happen if I continue this cycle? Will
I
get what is the solution that I am looking
for?
.One solution.
Five ones; so if I run this algorithm let
us say for hundred cycles what is the what
are the
intuition say? Will I get that or not?
.Probably little bit is 0.
Exactly now, if you look at the expected values
of these 4 elements, these are the 4
elements I have and the expected values are
0.32 for the first one 1.4, for the second
one
1.66, for the third one and 0.58 for the second
one. So, it is very likely that when I do
this
random spinning of the rule wheel and produce
4 new candidates out of 4 copies of sum
4 of these it is very likely that this first
candidate is going to be left out. Why because
expected values its probabilities only 0.08
and if I spin it 4 times my expected value
is
0.32 essentially.
Notice that if I want to spin it 100 times
its value would expected value would go up,
but
that what amount to saying that these 4 candidates
are being clone 100 times. We are not
doing that we are assuming here that the population
remains constant that we start with
this 4 candidates and clone 4 new candidates
out of it. And if I do that based on their
fitness values its very likely that the first
candidate will get left out and as he pointed
out
this is the only candidate of these three
which has the one in the middle place essentially
on the third bit essentially. So, if I want
to remove this, so let us say I want to take
copies of this, one copy of this and one copy
of this then no matter what future churning
that I do with this, I will never be able
to get the middle bit as one. So, I like this
example, because it illustrates exactly this
point. Now, what is the ruminative this? Why
is this happening? How can we try to see that
this does not happen, go back to nature if
you want to essentially
..The writing in the genetic the writing (refer
time.
When will they become more and more uniform?
What you are saying has the point that
yes it is possible that for a given species.
So, let us call it as species since you are
talking
about nature as well. So, if you take for
example, the cheetah now the cheetah if biologist
want to look at it is. And if you want to
call it a machine is a perfectly design machine
for hunting its it can in fact, you know you
get to see car adds which kind of try to
portrait them as cheetahs and stuff like that.
And the reason for that is that they can
escalate very fast and they can attain very
high speeds which is good for hunting
essentially. Now, the cheetah was such a good
predator such a good hunting machine
that they all became similar in a sense this
capacity to learn very fast and catch free
came
in all. So, the genetic the diversity in the
cheetah population became less and less and
less essentially. And if the diversity becomes
less it means your tendency to explore the
space decreases essentially. This is what
is happening with this here if we have getting
one candidate without the middle gene. Then
you can never look at solutions which have
the middle gene essentially.
So, likewise if you lose something’s then
you become rigid in your generic makeup
which is happen to the cheetah. And which
is one of the reasons that since human kind
change the world so much that cheetahs do
not have this open spaces. And which they
can go and catch their pray they are on the
danger of becoming extinct essentially.
Simply just like this particular creature
or the gene which this creature is carrying
which
likely to become extinct in the next round
essentially. But the question that we want
to
ask is what lesson should we learn when we
device g a’s. So, when we devise genetic
algorithms what are the parameters that we
have to select the first? Of course, is how
do
we encode the solution? Encoding the solution
should be done. So, encoding followed by
evaluation these are the first 2 steps; how
do you encode your candidate solution? And
secondly how do you what is the fitness function
that you devise for essentially?
Now, remember there is this fitness function
will have to be computed for the entire
population. So, one of the places where I
was reading about genetic algorithms they
said
that imagine that you are trying to devise
a neural network for pattern recognition.
So,
you want to recognize some patterns let us
say hand written characters or something like
that essentially. And if you have a training
set of 1000 patterns given to you based on
which you are training the neural network.
And you are task is to identify the parameters
.of neural network which basically means the
number of nodes and the edge grids and
that kind of stuff. What is the fitness function?
You could use one fitness function; you
could use is that you could test the candidate.
And the candidate in this case is the design
of a neural network or a neural network on
the thousand training candidates that you
are
that are given to you. And the fitness value
is the number of candidates this network
correctly classifies.
Now, if you want to devise such a training
such a fitness function you can imagine the
amount of work the generic algorithm has to
do. Simply to evaluate the fitness value of
a
candidate our example is very simple we just
compute f is equal to x square. It is easy
to
do it on the board, but it not a problem that
is hard to solve anyway essentially. If you
want to look at more difficult problems then
you have to be very careful in how do you
encode the candidates worst. And in the next
class, we will come back to TSP, how to
solve TSP’s using genetic algorithms. Then
how to devise a good fitness functions? The
fitness functions reflect what you want to
achieve, because in the way that we have built
our algorithm. It is a fitness function which
dominates this selection process that this
process of cloning one population into the
next. And the number of copies you make are
dependent directly upon the fitness functions.
So, the fitness function if it is good it
will
do a good job for you essentially, but there
is still one more parameter to be decided
and
that is.
.Randomization.
No no randomization is a built in process
randomization takes place here in the selection
in the spinning of rule wheel and the other
place. It take place is in deciding this
crossover point here where do we do a crossover?
May be it can be done in some more
informed fashion and people have tried out
all kinds of things, but we want to look at
general purpose algorithm at this one.
.Sir
The third thing.
.how do you decide crossover I mean.
.Sure, so I will take your question to mean
how do you decide what is the crossover
operator essentially? So, in this case now,
if you think about a simple situation like
this
where the solution is the bit string. Then
crossover essentially will mix up bit strings
essentially and without loss of generality
a single point crossover will do like any
other
crossover might have done. Though as I said
in the last class goal bug has investigated
as
the, what if there is a sequences of characters
which somehow provide a good feature.
How can we try to see whether they stay together,
but you will not get into that So, we
will assume that a simple single point crossover
does a job for us and this point is
decided randomly at run time whether it is
done here or whether it is done here this
is
decided randomly at run time. So, that is
the second aspects of random random behavior
that is happening here one is in the rule
wheel spinning and the second is in deciding
where the crossover happens. But looking at
this example there is a third thing which
would come to mind which is crucial for the
success of genetic algorithm
.We should take care of extinction
We should take care of extinction. So, how
do you do that? Somebody had said diversity
how do you increase diversity?
.Keep the best.
No you are look at it from a wrong perspective.
.All the feature if we maintained to the external.
No no listen we are trying to design a genetic
algorithm; we are not trying to design the
selection or the mating process right. Now,
what is the third parameter in designing
genetic algorithm which is going to play critical
role here?
.Size of the population
The size of the population genetic algorithms
will work if the population size is large
if
the population is large. Then they will have
all kinds of characters inside their population
with carrying all kinds of genes. And they
will all have a chance to reproduce in some
sense essentially. Now, which is one of the
reasons why we have this third space which
is mutation for the sake of completeness.
There is hope that this mutation process will
sometime toggle the middle bit here and we
will get going essentially.. But in general
.you have to choose the large population size
for these 2 work essentially. One more
aspect that we discussed in the last class
we have not mentioned it now is has to so.
.
So, some people have done it has follows that
you have a population of some size then
you take the most fit members let us say k
most fit members. So, this is k this is n
so if
you have n members you take the most k fit
members only allow those k fit members to
reproduce and mix up the genes both the process
selection and crossover. So, you get a
new populations of k elements. Now, take this
whole population here., so whatever
saying that that this k elements get to reproduce
which means they die in some sense in
the process of reproduction that we have these
2 parents vanish from the scene and inside
this new children come in essentially. So,
we get this new children here k new children
plus we take all these. So, this is k and
this is n. So, we have k plus n elements and
then
you mix them up and take the best k out of
them best n out of this. What we have done
here is that we are not keeping the original
population at all here we have said we just
replace the new one.
So, you started with this population and you
ended up with this population in the process
we lost the no sorry this population after
crossover. So, we started with this one and
we
ended up with this and none of them are reproduce
there essentially. So, we ended up
with the new population which means we replace
the entire whole population with this
new population. But I had said earlier also
that it is not necessary that you replace
the
.entire whole population you may want to keep
some of the best ones from whole
population into the new one. And this is the
one approach that people take just say only
allow the best people to reproduce. Then take
the new children plus the old population
and from that choose the best ten and that
is the new population which gives a chance
for
good solutions to survive in this case essentially.
So, I will stop here and in the next
class, we want to come back to genetic algorithms
and look at how to solve the traveling
salesman problem. How to devise crossover
operations for the travelling salesman
problems and what is the representation that
you can choose for representing the TSP
candidate essentially? So, we will stop here.
.