Today, we take a slightly different approach
to problem solving. So far, our approach has
been that we are in some given state, and
we want to find a path to the goal state or
something like that, or we are given a description
of the goal state and we want to search
for a state, which satisfies that description.
So, today, we want look at a slightly different
approach, which is kind of, has a flavor of
backward reasoning, in the sense, you reason
from the goal that you want to achieve, and
try to break down the problem into smaller
problems and so on, essentially.
.
So, the idea that you want to explore is called
problem decomposition. To motivate, why
we should use this approach, let me try and
take up a problem and solve it in the
approaches that we have seen so far, and let
us say that you have a friend, whose
birthday it is. You have all decided to go
out and let us say, give a treat to your friend.
I
know that is not the normal thing, but let
us say that is what you are doing, essentially.
Anyhow, decided that you will go in sometime,
somewhere, in the evening. Then,
.maybe, you will go to a movie or a music
show or something, and then, you will have
dinner somewhere, essentially. So, that is
the idea of planning in evening, and let us
say,
it is friend, whose birthday it is, who is
yet, to decide what is acceptable. So, you
start
querying, essentially.
.
So, let us try to visualize this as a search,
in a simple search space where, you give
different options to your friend. Let us call
this problem as designing an outing, and the
goal state is, when you have decided upon
the three things, that you will do; what will
you do first; what will you do next; and what
will you do after that. So, let us say that
you start up, by saying that you will go to
a mall; very popular thing, nowadays. Then,
maybe, you will go and see a movie. Let us
say, I will use HP for Harry Potter, one of
the Harry Potter films. Then, you will go
and eat somewhere. Let us say, pizza hut.
So, I
will use PH for pizza hut. So, you present
this option to your friend, and he or she
says,
no. That is not acceptable. So, let us say
that you are working in a depth first fashion,
essentially, or something similar to depth
first where, this may be, heuristically guided
or
something, like that. So, you try something
else, and let us say, you give another dinner
option.
Let us say this well known restaurant in Chennai;
Saravana Bhavan, and your friend
.again, says no, essentially. Can you think
of another restaurant name? Let us say Coffee
Cafe Day; you can go and eat there, which
I will use CC here. Your friend says no,
again, essentially. Let us say you are run
out of your budget and your restaurants and
so
on. So, you go back and say, let us try another
option. So, just to clarify, this is the
evening level, so, to speak. This is a movie
or entertainment, and this is a eating out.
So,
there are three decisions, you have to make.
Let us say, you offer to Bhuvan’s Home,
which is a very nice movie, as most of you
might know, but and then, of course you
cannot ask at this level, yes. So, in the
approach that we have followed so far, we
will
consider every node and ask, whether this
node is a goal node or not, essentially. This
cannot be a goal node, because it has only
two things; the third thing is not there,
essentially, but there are other approaches.
For example, when you do constrain
satisfaction, then at each stage of the partial
solution, you can inspect the partial solution
and say, is this consistent with what I am
looking for or not; but we will not get into
that
at this moment. So, again, you give these
offers. So, pizza hut; answer is no, Saravanaa
Bhavan; the answer is no, Cafe Coffee Day;
the answer is no, essentially; then, you try
one more movie. Let us say, A I, the movie.
So, you must be knowing, there was a film
called A I, the movie. Then, you try these
three options, again. I will not write them,
but
these are the same three options; what you
are trying, and your friend again, says, no,
essentially.
Let us say at this stage, you have run out
of movie options as well. So, you back track
from here, and you say, shall we go to the
beach. Then, you try all these same things
again. This entire tree that is below mall;
you are going to explore below beach, again,
essentially. So, let us say, go to the beach
and then, go and see harry porter; and then,
go
to pizza hut; then, go to Saravana Bhavan;
then, go to Cafe Coffee Day; then, go to
Bhuvan’s Home; then go to let us say, pizza
hut; and suddenly, your friend says, yes.
You have found the solution; your friend is
agreeable to the idea of going to the beach;
then, going and watching Bhuvan’s Home,
and then, going to the pizza hut for dinner,
essentially. Now, if you look at this search
tree, I want you to look at this, and make
some observations; is it a good way of searching,
or what is happening in this tree?
.Many nodes are replicated, or let me ask
a more specific question; what is wrong in
the
left side of the tree? What is it that is
not working in the left side of the tree?
Where is
.the fault in the solution that you constructing,
or what is wrong with the solution that the
left side of the tree is trying to construct?
What is, or which part of the solution is
not
working? Can you look, inspect the tree?
Because you explored the entire tree below
mall, and I have drawn three movies and
three restaurants; they could have been many
more, essentially. There could be a greater
depth, because we have explored the entire
tree below mall, and it did not work. If mall
was the problem, then you can see that if
in the first solution that you considered,
which
is mall, Harry Potter and Pizza hut; if somehow,
you could figure out that mall is the
problem, then you would not do all these wasteful
work, here; trying to see if not pizza
hut; then, Saravanaa Bhavan, if not Saravanaa
Bhavan, of course, then, Cafe Coffee Day;
and if not Harry Potter; then, Bhuvan’s
Home, if not Bhuvan’s Home; then, A I, the
movie; all these work is wasted work, essentially,
and the reason is, because the culprit is
here, and keeping that choice fixed, and search
it below the tree, is not going to help, any
longer. Anything you try below this is not
going to work. If you figure out that mall
is
creating a problem, essentially. It turns
out that you go this side, and then, you get
a
solution, essentially. So, how does one solve
this problem of doing, what is the issue that
we want to address is that; you tried one
thing and then, you are doing this useless
work,
exploring this part of the tree, which will
loss and not going to work. Only, when you
change this, it is going to work, essentially.
So, there are basically two approaches to
addressing this difficulty. One is called
Dependency Directed Back Tracking.
Now, the backtracking that we are doing here,
in most of the algorithm that we have
seen, is chronological in nature; that you
undo the last choice that you make. So, you
tried this solution. It did not work so, you
undo this last choice, which is pizza hut
and
try the next one, at this level, which is
Saravanaa Bhavan; undo this and try this.
When
all these three fail, then you undo this and
try this. This form of backtracking is called
chronological, which mean that you undoing
the last choice that you are making. What
we try to do is dependency directed backtracking,
is to identify the culprit of what is
wrong with the solution, or in other words,
without changing that attribute, you are not
going to get the solution. If you can identify,
after coming here, or after coming
somewhere that the culprit is the choice of
evening twist, went in the mall. Then, the
algorithm should actually, directly jump back
to this, and try the next choice, essentially.
.So, we will not really, explore this option,
here, unless we get time later on, but it
is
something that we study, when you look at
constrain satisfaction method, essentially.
But
we are not going to do too much of constraint
processing, here. Constrain processing is
just a different formulation of solving such
problems in which, you formulate the entire
problem in terms of variables, and values,
that variable can take, essentially. The other
approach that you want to consider, today,
is to construct what I call AND OR graphs
or
trees. We could have converted this into a
graph by, instead of generating these three,
I
could have connected them to these three,
and then, it would have been a graph. So,
there
is not really, too much of difference, whether
it is a graph or tree; just a way of looking
at
it. These are also known as goal trees.
.
We all want to look at problem decomposition
with goal trees. The idea of problem
decomposition is something, like using a mechanism
to break up a problem into smaller
parts. In this example, it is a little bit,
like using a context free grammar, to say,
that an
outing is made up of an evening out, and the
movie and dinner, and then, so on and so
forth; but it does not have to be context
free. In this case, it could be context dependent.
So, how do we do this? This approach is to
view the problem differently, which is to
say
that you have outing as a; this is the goal
that you trying to solve. Now, you are going
to
break it up into three separate sub goals.
So, one is evening out, or evening plan. Then,
.movie, and then, eating on dinner. So, this
is the different representation. To distinguish
between this sort of tree and that sort of
a tree, we put an arc here, for our benefit.
Such an arc is called as AND arc, and such
a node is called an AND node. So, an AND
node is a node from which, the choices, all
the nodes that it points to; it is a directive
graph. Every one of them has to be solved,
as opposed to such a node; this is called
an
OR arc. This view is called an OR arc, or
this, would be called as an OR node. So, an
OR
node has all OR arcs below it. The meaning
of an OR node and OR arc is that you have
to do one of the things below that. For example,
you have to either, go to the mall or you
have to go to the beach, or if you had decided
upon the mall, then you have to either,
choose Harry Potter or Bhuvan’s Home or
A I, the movie, essentially. That is the node.
So, we have those all choices here, as well.
So, let us say, mall and beech, and may be,
some other choices; does not matter. Then,
we have the three choices for the movie,
Harry Potter, Bhuvan’s Home and A I, the
movie. Then, we have the three choices for
the restaurant. So, such a tree is called
an AND OR tree, because it has AND nodes as
well as OR nodes in that. The AND node is
at top level. OR node is below that, and a
solution in the OR graph like this, the kind
that we have been studying so far, is the
path.
The solution in an AND OR tree is a sub tree.
So, a solution will have, for example, this
and this and
this and this. So, the solution for this same
problem is a sub tree here. The
solution in that combination was a path. The
important thing is that you have broken the
problem down into three smaller problems,
and solve them independently, of each other.
This means that when you know that you have
to choose between mall and beach, you do
this independent of the other things. Whereas
here, one should choose the mall, then you
are saying, even the mall; what else should
I search for?
Now, that does not really make sense, because
mall is independent of what you are going
to do after that, and this formulation of
AND OR tree, allows you to break up the
problems into smaller parts, and solve it,
essentially. So, we want to study approaches
to
solving algorithms that we will work on such
formulations, and solve problems, like that,
essentially, but first I want to give some
motivation about, where it has been used and
so
on. Now, obviously, there would be cost, if
you going to do some kind of optimal
solution, finding there, would be some kind
of cost associated with it. In this example,
cost could be, for example, mall may have
some cost associated with it; may be, the
.distant you have to travel, or sometimes,
some malls now; they charge some fees to some
people, but I do not know. Obviously, movies
also will have charges; eating out will
have some costs, and you may have some criteria;
you want to those, find the solution
within this cost, or within this budget, or
of optimal budget and things like that. So,
we
will worry about cost as we see this later.
.
Let me take another example. Suppose, you
want to construct a house, you can see this
also, you can pose this problem also, as an
AND OR problem. So, just to take some
simple variations, you might say something,
like single storey or a duplex; these might
be choices. In a single storey house, may
say that you have to make a kitchen, followed
by, let us say, room one. So, I will just
say, R1 followed by, let us say R2 and so
on, and
let us say, balcony. Now, this, of course,
would be an AND node here, and I could have
edges coming from here. For example, duplex
house also will have a kitchen and so on,
which I can always, draw it as a graph or
I can draw it as a tree; it does not really
matter.
Then, may be, room 1, would say, wall 1, up
to, let say, we have 4 rooms; we have
rectangular rooms. So, from wall 1 to wall
4 and then, may be door; let say, we have
only 1 door in this, and let say, we have
a window.
This would be an AND node, and if you look
at a wall, for example, you may have
.choices, like stone or brick or mud. In this
manner, the choices that available to you
to
construct a house, can be organized into an
AND OR tree where, the top level, you have
the high level goal, which is to construct
a house. Then these, at lower levels; this
is just
as choices here. At lower levels, these are
sub goals. Then, you keep breaking down. Till
what extent you break down a problem? You
break it down, till the problem is so simple
that you have a solution, already available,
essentially. So, I will illustrate that with
the
next example that we see, which is from one
of the first systems that were to use AND
OR graphs, essentially.
Now, keep in mind that they are two kinds
of cost that are going to be involved. One
is
cost of transforming a problem. Let say, we
assumed, there is a cost of doing that into
sub problems. The second is the cost of solving
the sub problems and so on. So, at the
end of this, these nodes are called leaf nodes,
I mean, the leaf nodes are actually, called
solved nodes. So, the leaf nodes in the tree
would be solved nodes. Solved nodes, of
course, would have an associated cost with
it. Depending on the domain, we will see a
domain; we will start with looking at symbolic
integration, for example, which was one
of the first applications, which used AND
OR graphs. The solved nodes may not have
any cost associated with it. For example,
you know that integral of XDX is something
that you can just pick up the solution, or
X square DX, you can just pick up the solution
and things like that, but if you look at the
problem, like building a house, then if you
going to build 4 walls, then each of those
four walls, when you build it; it will have
an
associated cost, and then, you will have to
aggregate all that cost into the cost of building
that house, essentially. So, solved nodes
may or may not have cost, depending on what
is
the nature of the problem, but transformations
will always, have some costs associated
with it. That is the way we will look at the
problem, essentially, because you want to
control the amount of search that you do.
(Refer Slid Time.
.One of the first programs to look at that
AND OR trees, was the program called SAINT,
which was implemented by a guy called Slagle
in 1961. When you are looking at the
introductory lectures and we are saying, what
are the achievements that A I has done
over the years; we had mentioned symbolic
integration, at that time, in 1961. I think
in
MIT, he wrote this. This was his PHD thesis
on how to do symbolic integration. So, what
do you mean by symbolic integration? That
you are given some expression, and you
want to integrate that expression, in definite
integral and you want to convert, you want
to produce a expression, which is the integral
of this expression, essentially. So, my
mathematics is a bit week. So, let me, yes,
use this break up, which, as strong as thesis.
So, let us say that you want to integrate
X raise to 4 divided by 1 minus X square raise
to
5 by 2 d x. I am sure that you people are
more familiar with integration than I am.
You know how to solve such problems is that
basically, you apply some transformations
and may be, you break up the problem into
smaller parts, something that would fit very
nicely into the AND OR situations, because
you have a choice of transformations to
make. So, first let us look at what the solution,
look like. So, this is the node, when you
can transform it into sin raise to 4 Y Y;
do not ask me how, but think for it, which
we
can. So, the transformation is X equal to
sin Y. So, eventually, when you break it down
into something, which is simple, which is
accessible to you; you will have a sort of,
invert this transformation as you construct
the solution for this, essentially, I am in
a risk
of converting this into a Maths class; let
me try one or two more steps.
.You do not have to really write this. Notice
that here, we have replaced something like
Z
equal to tan W, let me write it here, and
transformed into this, and likewise, this
can get
transformed into d w. So, now, we are assuming
that this node is a solved node, in the
sense, that you can do this without any difficulty.
This node is a solved node, and this
node is a solved node. So, you have the solution
now. So, this is an AND node, of
course, and this so. The solution to this
integration problem is a series of transformations
that you do, followed by, breaking up the
problem into smaller parts, because we have
this addition here; these smaller parts, and
then, we can solve this integral DW integral
Z
square and integral DW, very trivially. So,
we will treat those nodes as solve nodes.
So,
that is what I mean by saying that the cost
of finding such nodes, the cost of this solution
is; you can consider it to be small, but that
cost of transformation can be counted
essentially.
Of course, this is not the only way of doing
this, essentially, and there could have been
other choices. So, for example, you could
have said that transform this to cost minus
YDY, and transform this into something else,
DX, and may be, it does not look so
promising or something of even, worst you
could try something like this. So, to solve
a
problem like this, there are many options.
Those of you, who remember doing your
Maths or some entrance exam or the other,
you would remember that you have to break
your head; try to remember, what are those
transformations and so on. That is why, this
needs a lot of practice, but what this program
SAINT; SAINT stands for Symbolic
Automatic Integration.
Later, a guy called Moses developed a program,
which he called as SIN, because this
was called SAINT; which stands for Symbolic
Integration. This SIN was eventually,
transformed into a product called MACSYMA.
Nowadays, of course, you must be
familiar that we have these mathematical packages,
which can do symbolic mathematics
for you. These are all the descendants of
this SIN and SAINT, essentially. Some
MATLAB, for example, will also allow you to
do symbolic mathematics. So, what you
want to show here, is that symbolic integration
can be seen, as solving a problem in this
manner where, you reason from your large level,
higher level problem to break it down
into sub goals, till sub goals are simple
enough, to be solved trivially, and then,
you have
a solution for solving this problem. Of course,
actual answer to this, you have to undo all
.the transformations that you have done, which
I have not written here. So, let me give
another example where, this idea was used
effectively. We had mentioned that in the
70s,
was the area of what we call as expert systems.
.
One of the first expert systems
was this program called DENDRAL. This DENDRAL,
basically, also can be, some people say you
can extend it to a dentritec tree X algorithm
or something like that, because it generated
also, an AND OR graph, which look like
that, but the idea of DENDRAL was that it
was the assistant; it was originally developed
or programmed it as an assistant to a chemist,
and the task that the chemist was doing
was to determining the structural formula
of an compound, essentially. Now, you know
that again, I presume your chemistry is better
than mine. So, you know that if you are
given a molecular formula for a compound,
for example, C6 H6; how was it C6 H12;
whatever, benzene; what is the formula for
benzene? C 6 H 6, and you must have heard
the story of Kekule, and you know how people
were trying to figure out, what is the
structure of benzene.
So, at a molecular level, of course, it has
6 carbon atoms and 6 hydrogen atoms, but the
question to ask is; how are these atoms arranged,
in a structure? That is a very important
question, because the physical and chemical
properties of the substance, depends on the
.structural formula, that it is behind, essentially,
and to find the structural formula, is not
such a straight forward task, and apparently,
Kekule was dreaming, or day dreaming or
sleeping, or something, and he saw this snake,
which was biting his own tail, and then, it
is benzene ring and so on, essentially. So,
the idea behind DENDRAL was to help a
chemist, find structural formulas and apparently,
people who have done PHD in
chemistry, spend their considerable amount
of time, trying to find the structural formulas
of this thing. The problem is not so simple,
because a given molecular formula may have
millions of different structural formula,
associated with it, essentially, for larger
compounds, obviously.
At a must lower level, you know, the structure
plays an important role in materials,
because whether you are holding a diamond
in your hand, or a lump of coal; is just a
matter of structure. You, basically, holding
carbon in your hand, but it is really the
structure of it, which gives it the properties
that you looking for.
.
So, the way that is DENDRAL was implemented,
the idea was, it will explore the space
of possible structures, and this can be done
by breaking down a molecular formula into
smaller parts, and exploring the structure
of the smaller parts. We will see a small
sample
example, but this was aided by a process of
generating a synthetic spectrogram. So, there
.was an algorithm that given a structural
formula, what will be the spectrogram of that
material look like, essentially.
Once you can do that, you can compare it with
a real spectrogram of the material, and if
the spectrogram matches, then you can say
that you have found the structural formula
for
that material. That is the approach with chemist
for doing it laboriously. DENDRAL was
a program; it was developed by Stanford in
1971 or something like that, came a bit after
SAINT. It was touted as the first expert system,
which was built, and 70s and 80s was
the era of expert systems where, people said
that we will build expert systems, and by
this, they meant that they will elicit the
knowledge of experts, put it into a program,
and
the program will then, perform at the level
of an expert. So, apart from DENDRAL, in
the introduction, we might have mentioned
things like prospector, which was an expert
system to find a prospect for oils or minerals,
and so on.
There was a program called R 1, which was
also at Stanford I think, which was used to
configure wax systems. In those years, of
course, buying a machine, a computer was not
such a straight forward task as saying that
I want Apple, Mac book or something like
that. You had to actually configure various
components together, and R 1 was an expert
system, which helped people, configure computer
systems. We will look at this; how this
R 1 and things like this; such programs have
built, a little bit later in the course, but
today, we want to focus on this A 0 star,
kind of an algorithm, or AND OR tree
algorithms, and which basically, search over
AND OR trees. So, where did the expertise
come in?
Expertise came in that there was first a program
called CONGEN. So, DENDRAL was
made up of a program called CONGEN, and this
stands for Constraint Generator. This
had expert knowledge inside it. So, of the
many possible ways that you could conjure
a
structure for a given molecular formula, CONGEN
was guided by knowledge gleamed
from chemist, as to what structures are feasible
and what are not feasible, essentially. For
example, given a simple thing like C 2 H 12
NO 2, this CONGEN would produce a
structure like this, or it would produce another
structure. So, this is one, and this is
another one, and there are more examples,
which I am not drawing here.
.Essentially, again since, you are better
at chemistry than I am. You know that this
is
double bond and this is single bond, and so
on; we have not drawn the hydrogen atoms
and you can fill in the hydrogen atoms, based
on the valance here, remaining. So, 3 here,
for example, and 2 here, in that, but these
are different structures that CONGEN
generates and what was interesting about CONGEN
was, it generated only feasible
structures. That is why, expert knowledge
came into that.
So, after CONGEN, you produce a synthetic
spectrogram, compared with real and then,
you can decide, whether you have found the
structure of the material or not. What
DENDRAL would do is that it would expose this
huge space of all possible structures,
generates this synthetic spectrograms, and
compare it with the one of the original
material, and eventually, do the job for the
chemist, and it turns out that this was
working, of course, much faster than real
chemist, as you can imagine; and doing
equally, well or almost, equally well and
when you say real chemist means people, who
have PHDs essentially. So, let me just end
with a small example of the kind of space
that
DENDRAL generated, and in the next class,
we will see the algorithms, which I used to
explore this space.
.
Let us say that we are looking at C5 H12.
This is a molecular formula, and any box,
.which has a molecular formula, is an unsolved
node or which, may be partially solved, as
we will see. A solved node is where; this
structure is entirely given to you, essentially.
So, for example, it could be like this; C,
C, C, C, C; and then, the hydrogen items.
So,
this would be a solved node. A simple way
of organizing this 5 carbon atoms and 12
hydrogen atoms, but there could be other options,
essentially. For example, these are
directed graphs. You could say that it is
C. So, a partially elicited structure where,
part of
the structure is known, and part is not known.
So, 3 carbon atoms are here; 2, I buy it
inside here. This is another partially elicited
structure, and this itself, would have now,
three children, which this part, this part
and this part. So, you solved for C2 H5 with
a
bond. Then, you have another C2 H5; it is
a bond and then, you have C, H, H, H, H, H,
with two bonds, and this is solved; and this
can be solved by, and this also, can be solved
by this, and this will have, for example,
two components. One of them will be the C2
H5
with a bond, which will be solved by this;
and the remaining will be that; whatever
remains here; C, C, C, and so on.
So, in this very quick chemistry lesson, you
can see that three possible structures for
C2
H5; one is this structure; one is a structure
where, you have the middle part where, you
have C and 2 hydrogen atoms, and the two edges
contain this structure like this, and
likewise, this is another structure where,
the middle part has the C2 H5 component. Here,
the two edges have the C2 H5 components; obviously,
that matters. So, you have either,
one solution is this one. This is an AND node.
Another solution is here, and the third
solution is that side, essentially. Now, what
DENDRAL did is that it navigates this space
intelligently, in the sense, that this CONGEN,
component of DENDRAL, only generates
those nodes, which are feasible in practice.
How does it do that? It has got a lot of expert
knowledge built into it, and that is why,
this system is called the first expert system
that
was built, essentially.
Then, of course, it generates the synthetic
spectrogram of the, for example, you take
this
generate the spectrogram and compare it with
your real material spectrogram, and if this
matches, then you know that it is the structural
formula and so on, essentially. Today, we
have just introduced the idea of AND OR trees
or AND OR graphs. So, we will not
distinguish too much between them. We have
just very briefly, talked about the cost
associated with solved nodes and which, have
to be aggregated into the root node. So, in
.the next class we will look at an algorithm,
which explores an AND OR tree or a goal
tree, to find an optimal solution, essentially.
So, we will stop here, now.
.