We have been looking at algorithm A star,
which is a very well known algorithm for
finding optimal solutions in a state space.
.
And at this movement, we are trying to look
at variations of A star which are space
savings. So, before I start the algorithms,
let means ask you one small or status small
problem.
..
Let say you are in a . like city and there
are a set of so, it is a grade
like this. And you have to come to this last
city here. Let us say, this cities are numbered
0, 1, 2 up to m and 0, 1, 2 up to n. So, it
is on m by n grade and by this I mean m adjusts
in this direction and n adjust in this direction.
There are m plus 1 cities in horizontally
and n plus 1 cities vertically essentially.
It is a complete grid, I am not drawn the
complete grid. The question I want to ask
is how many paths are there, if you want to
go
from this city 0, 0 to the city m, n there.
And we are assuming that you can only travel
either to the right or down essentially. So,
it is not, it is a directed graph, you can
only move either to the right or down. But,
the
question is how many paths are there, m and
n you have to use two parameters m and n
essentially, whether I m adjust here and n
adjust in this direction. So, if you if there
only
one city, there is only one path. If there
are four cities then you can see there are
two
paths. As the number of cities increased,
the number of paths increases quite
dramatically. Thus, anyone know of the korf
how many.
.x plus y c x.
x plus y…
..C x, I mean total number of either we can
go in as an if one direction is fix than
the other direction could be fixed, suppose
from all the paths you choose after fixing
one
direction on to the limited numbers left.
Well, you can think of this as a sequence
of right moves, we have to always make m
right moves and you have to put in n down
moves, soumiya.
.n plus n factorial . divided by n factorial.
Divided by n factorial, that is a correct
answer, you can think of it has saying that
you
have to make m right moves and somewhere along
those m right moves, you have to put
those n down moves and the number of ways
we can do that is given by this essentially.
So, I will come back to this problem; let
me increase the complexity of this problem,
what if I allowed diagonal moves as well.
Now, that is a little bit harder, it does
not have
a nice closed form solution, it is the summation
of many things, but I would like it to
think about that.
So, you can think of this new problem as follows
that one diagonal move replaces one
horizontal move and one vertical move. And
out of the m plus n horizontal and vertical
moves that you are making, whichever is smaller
m or n, you can replace it with that
many diagonal moves optionally, you do not
have to, but you can replace it with that
many diagonals moves. So, that many horizontal
and vertical moves become less and
diagonal moves will become more essentially.
So, this a little bit more difficult to
analyze, but it is a good exercise.
..
So, let us first continue with our variations
that we were looking at. In the last class
we
saw I D A star and if you recall, what I D
A star does is that, essentially from the
start
node, it creates a boundary, this is the goal.
And this boundary is the heuristic value of
the start node or in other words how far it
things, the algorithm thinks the goal is from
the start node. And it draws at boundary and
does that depth first search on this. It rate
a
. comes on the fact that after it is fail
to find a goal here. It would
have some nodes open just around the boundary,
which it has not expanded.
It looks at those nodes and fix the minimum
f value from there, and extends a boundary
by that much amount essentially. And it keeps
doing that, till it has found the goal node
essentially. So, I think we are started discussing
the properties of this algorithm, but let
us recap. So, maybe I will ask you to tell
me, what do you think of the I D A star
algorithm. It was formed by Korf, Richard
Korf 1980’s something, I do not remember
exact date. So, what is good about this algorithm
and what is not good about this
algorithm. So, the first question we want
to ask is does it survive the substitute for
A star,
which means does it guarantee and optimal
path or not. So, what is the argument you
would give?
..
.Why, how can you say the .
.If I do not the optimal path at a certain
value of that then what I am doing is I
am finding the node with the value of f just
higher than that. So, I would not miss out
anymore. So, the movement I the value of f,
which is the . goal I
will find ..
So, that is one criteria it satisfies for
us, it is that it finds the optimal path,
why is it better
than A star, why would you prefer it to A
star or when would be prefer it to A star.
.Open lays does not go too large.
Open lays does not go too large in fact, it
goes linearly only and especially, if you
are
looking at problems, in which thus search
space is very huge. You can imagine if you
are
generating something like hundred thousand
nodes a second in the search space. Then
how quickly well I am will get fill up with,
you remember that each state, each node is
a
representation of a state which means that,
whatever you have described about the state
would be there. And then you have applied
a move gen function and you generate a new
state and you put all those things into some
kind of a data structure essentially.
So, the advantages of I D A star is that it
needs less space and this is the theme that
we
are going to follow today, how can we look
at space saving algorithms, but what is a
disadvantage that you can think of.
.. time complexities.
So, what do you mean by saying better pass
may be left unexplored. We have already
argued and he said that, we guarantee that
it will give you the optimal solution. So,
that
is what we want essentially. Time complexity
is like it was in the case of D F I D time
complexity is an issue, but unlike D F I D.
In D F I D we assume that the cost was
uniform of each edge which meant that, as
you get went deeper, the number of nodes in
the next layer was increasing exponentially
or it was multiplied by the branching factor
.b.
And therefore, every time we increase the
depths by one, you encountered many more
new nodes in fact, more you nodes then the
old nodes that you had seen so far.
Unfortunately for ideas are that is not the
case, because now we have edge cause involve
and as we discuss, we increase the bound only
to the next lowest f value, which means
that it may do a significantly large number
of searches before it actually converges to
this, which is why we observed in the last,
towards the end of the last class that instead
of incrementing it to the next lowest step
value. You increment it by some amount, we
determined amount delta, which is a loss of
optimality or willing to bare essentially.
So, if you increase further by a value delta,
this is delta. Then the next time it searches,
it
may find a node somewhere here, which is a
goal node. So, I have drawn only one goal
node, but in practice, search problems may
have more than one goal node essentially.
So,
for example, if you are looking for a Chinese
restaurant in a city, they may be many
Chinese restaurants, if you are looking for
a particular film, which is showing in some
theater, you may have more than one solution
essentially. So, depends on what your
search algorithm finds.
So, it might find a goal node here, as oppose
to a goal node here, this is close to the
previous bound that we had, but this is far
there from the previous one. So, it has an
error
of our delta. So, if you are willing to tolerate
an error of delta, then you can increment
this delta and you can control how much you
have willing to tolerate by essentially. So,
that is one problem with ideas are that it
may do too many iterations essentially. Another
problem with I d A star is that, it is sort
of does not cater to our ascetic sense if
you want
to call it, in the sense that, it does not
have a sense of direction.
We started search with line search algorithm
and then say, then we said we are
introducing heuristic functions to guide search
towards the goal. The only role the
heuristic function is playing is in defining
this boundary here. Of course, the boundary
as
you can see is . sided, it is towards the
goal by that is about all it
does essentially. So, the next algorithm that
we want to look at, which is also by Richard
Korf is called recursive best first search,
popularly known as RBFS.
.So, R B F S is a little different from I
D A star and no doubt korf devises algorithm,
because he saw the drawbacks of I D A star,
which is that, it was doing too many
iterations. In particular, if you do not maintain
a close list and you just let, D F S in some
sense run wild is that was good idea or bad
idea to do. Let us say, D F I D or I D S are
without maintaining a close list. With it
get, the question is one of the things at
closed,
thus for us is there it is stops as from going
to an infinite loop essentially.
So, if you have for example, search after
this is, this I told you was a directed graph,
but
if this one not a directed graph, then you
could have gone into a loop keep going in
a
loop like this essentially. And close allows
us to avoid such a possibility, but given
the
fact that we have working with bounds on the
distance from the source that you have
willing to go, can I work without closed?
In other words, if you go back to the D F
I D
algorithm, which is basically a simpler version
of I D A star that it does not have edge
cause will D F I D work, if I do not, if I
implement the D F S without a close list.
So, I will leave that the small topic experiments
for you to do. Let us forget this
algorithm RBFS. So, what R B F S does is that,
it maintains a linear amount of memory
exactly like I D A star, but it does not.
So, what I D A star is doing, it is doing
blind
search, wherever the goal is it will go of
in one direction, back track, try something
else,
back track, try something else, back track,
try something else and so on. So, it is will
basically a depth first traversal of the space
with no sense of direction. Now, let us try
to
stimulate, what R B F S could do.
So, let us say we start with this node start,
and let us say we have these four children,
and
their heuristic values for the sake of argument,
let us say, this is 40 and 70 and 71. So,
initially recursive best first search behaves
like best first search, that it fix the one
with
the lowest f value and expands that, which
means in this example this know. But, what
it
also does is that, it keeps a pointer to the
next best node that is in the open list. So,
in this
example, this is an express node and then
it does the search essentially.
So, this is second best node and that is it
node .. So, let us say it
generates this and if you remember the monotone
criteria are consistency conditions that
we said, that they in generally you expect
the heuristic values to become more accurate.
.As you go closer to the goal and a consequence
of monotone criteria was that f values
increase as you go forward, as you go towards
the goal essentially. So, he would
generally expect f values to increase in a
search space, which is consistent. So, let
us say,
this is become 45, this becomes 50 and this
become 61 for arguments sake.
So, what immediately R B F S will do is, it
first removes this pointer from here, and
put
it to this. Because, now that is a, to this,
this is the best node and this is the next
best
node in the open list, and it keeps a pointer
to the next best nodes essentially. Then it
goes like this and let us says this is what
is happening, let say this becomes 48 and
this
becomes 70 just for arguments 60. Then, it
expands this one, remains 48 let us say and
just for argument sake, let say these are
all 70 and it expands this. So, it is diving
into the
search space, using the heuristic function
as a guiding whose.
Let us say some point, these nodes start looking
and little bit worst than that node. So,
this becomes 55, this becomes 53 and this
becomes 57 or something like that. So, so
far
it is behavior and the best for search behavior
is identical. But, at this point well, it
has to
what best first search would have done is
simply, it would have pick this node as the
next
one from the open list and started exploring
the tree from there essentially, what
recursive best first search, which is trying
to save one space, thus is that it rolls back
this
search all the way. So, that it can move to
the next siblings essentially.
So, it is basically deletes all these nodes
from open, close whatever it is maintaining.
So,
it rolls back you know, there is to say about
the Indian government at one point, it is
a
roll back government. So, they would increase
the petrol prices and after two days roll
it
back or something, little bit like that. But,
it has a rule which it follows and which is
called as a backup rule, which determines
the f value of a node, f of n is equal to
all let us
call it some other value. Let us call it f
prime value is equal to f of n, if n is a
leaf which
means n is on open is equal to max no min
f prime, I just use this short form.
So, either it is a f value or it is a minimum
of the f values of it is children essentially.
So,
what really it does is that it maintains this
f prime value. So, for all these nodes 70,
70,
70, 60, 57, 53, 55, the f prime value is the
same as the f value, because it is a leaf
node.
But, when I it rolls back, it applies back
up rule to back up the values. So, for example,
.from these three nodes it will back up the
value 53 here.
.
So, let we use a different chalk to illustrate
that. So, it backs up this value 53 to this
node.
So, now this becomes 53 and there it deletes
this essentially everything. So, this is 53,
70, 70, so again it backs up 53 here; this
is 53, 70, 60. So, it backs up this thing
here,
changes this to 53, which is the backed up
value and then to seats along this direction.
So, you can see that, once it has devises
value to 53, if you just look at the snap
shot of
the search at that point, all these nodes
are not there, all these has been deleted,
only that
much of the tree remains. And this is on open,
this is put back on to open with a new
value of 53, this is 50, this is 61, this
is 70.
So, it basically naturally goes off on that
direction. So, you can see that at any given
point, recursive best first search maintains
only one paths down the search tree, which
means it is space requirement is going to
be linear, because that is what the depth
first
search also does. And yet, it mimics the behavior
of A star algorithm, in the sense that it
is best first, it always goes down the best
looking path. It just that on the way, it
has
revise the value of this node, the heuristic
value has measure by the heuristic function
was 45, but after is done this search, it
realizes that it is not 45, it is 53.
.So, it leaves it to the open value of 53
and goes down this path essentially. So, it
will
generate these children now, and depending
on whether they are. So, when this is 50,
this
will become the next best node essentially.
So, if I going down this path, there is no
node
better than 53 in this path, it will roll
back from here, and go down this path again.
So,
you can sense a similar problem as
in that it may do this many time, it may go
down this
path, it may go down this path, it may come
back here, eventually it may finish this and
it may go down this path.
And then maybe, this will become worst and
then it will go down this path. So, R B F
S
is a danger that it opposes it, depicts the
behavior of what we call is thrashing, that
is a
danger with R B F S, you read that it may
thrash something like this. So, I do not know
whether we discuss thrashing, when we were
looking at hill climbing, but if you imagine
a hill, which is like a ridge.
.
So, which looks a bit like this cross section
if you can visualize this, like this? So,
it is
like a ridge essentially, which is slowly
increasing in one direction. Then hill climbing
would have a tendency to go in this direction
which is, because that is a steepest gradient
direction essentially. And if you are search
problems is the granularity of your move gen
function is search, that once it makes a step
in this direction, it may over shoot at some
.point then it make, it may come back that
may go like. So, hill climbing can also behave
a similar fashion behavior essentially.
So, this is the one problem with search algorithms,
which are local in some sense
essentially. This is local in the sense, it
is always going down one path, but it is not
completely local in the sense are it is keeping
updated values, backed up values, for
known essentially. So, R B F S is came around
1990 also was an improvement on I D A
star, because it had a sense of direction,
but it has this problem there, it could do
((Refer
Time.). And actually we have students, we
have implemented these algorithms
for the course here, I have observed this
behavior that you know these algorithms just
keep spends, what they say as infinite amount
of time, you will just touching between a
few loads essentially.
So, what you would be really interested in
is space saving algorithms, which behave
more like A star in terms of the nodes that
they are picking for expansion as well.
Whereas, these two algorithms behave like
A star in terms of the solutions they produce,
the way they pick nodes is different. And
consequently both this algorithms have a of
course, much larger time complexity in A star,
because they will explore the same space
again and again many times essentially.
Now, so let me now ask a question has to,
if you were designing on a search algorithm
and you are add to look at different options
of whether you can save on the close list
or
whether you can save on the open list, what
would be your choice. If somebody says that
you can, I will give an algorithm in which,
the open list sizes is minimize, made constant
or something like that or made linear like,
I D A star or it somebody says that, I will
give
you an algorithm, in which the close list
side is . reduced, which
one would you choose. Would you rather proven
the open list or would you rather
proven the close list?
.. size of depends on the size of the grid
the number of
nodes.
Well, I take your answer to mean it depends
on the topology of the problem essentially.
.But, if you look at a general case, were
every node has b successors, you know branching
factor is b, every node as b successors. So,
very often the community tends to even if
you
have a graphs from which you are searching,
then you know, if you remember the branch
and bound, we started off with, in which the
duplicates were not remove and the same
node would appear and different parts of the
tree. Many people tends to think of that is
space, as a space of searching over paths,
because each node in a different part of the
tree
depict the different path, because you know
from route it as a different path. Then of
course, it tends to go very highly.
So, when we studied D F I D, we had argued
that the number of nodes in the last layer
of
breadth first search by itself was must larger
than all the internal nodes seen. And then
we argued that, because if that is only the
extra work it we are doing and you are getting
linear space in D F I D are oppose to exponential
space of breadth first search. Then you
are saving on the open list largely, that
is what D F I D was doing saving on the open
list
essentially. But, there are problem sometimes,
when you want to save on the close list,
when the close list can become a greater problem
than an open list.
.
And this problem that we are looking at, this
city route finding problem is such a
problem essentially. Now, if you visualize,
how search will progress in this space. This
.will be the start node, it has three successes,
it would generate those three successors;
it
will take one of them, generate its three
successors and so on and so forth, that is
how
search will progress. How will the search
frontier look like or the boundary of the
search
look like? It would be some of which look
like this. At some level, the search frontier
would look like; it would have gone some steps
to this thing and some steps down at
different parts of the space and search frontier
look like.
So, for such a problem how in terms of m and
n, how is this open list, search frontier
is
equal to the open list. So, this is the open
list, how the open going in terms of m and
n,
the father you go away from the… So, the
distance from the source is m plus n or i
plus j
if you want to say, if you have a gone i steps
down and j steps to the right, it is a i plus
j.
The open list is only growing linearly, as
you go further and further away. In the worst
case, when you are just about to pick the
last node, open list would be m nodes there,
and
n nodes here essentially, m plus n essentially.
Whereas, the close list, which is all the
nodes that we have traverse inside this area
is growing quadratically essentially.
Because, it is kind of is like an area is
suppose through line that you are drawing
like
that. So here, is one problem with the close
list is growing faster than the open list,
the
difficulty in solving this problem comes when
the combinations which you have, there if
you want to go from this node to some node
here, there are you can go like this; or you
can go like this; or you can go like this;
or you can go like this. So, there are many
different combinations and that is what gives
rise to the exploding search spaces. So,
there is some . trying to save on the close
list essentially.
..
So, let me introduce to a problem which has
in the last 10 or years or maybe 15, 20 years
has become very important, and that is a problem
of sequence alignment. And it is a
problem, which has spade work in search, search
had become a kind of dormant area in a
research, but because of this new problems,
which are coming out. People were set of
motivated into devising better algorithms
essentially. So, if you look at for example,
D N
A sequence alignment, and that is a problem
with in bio informatics, for example, you
want to do very often essentially.
So you do, if you want to do for example,
genome sequencing and thinks like that, the
way the sequence genome is that they get bits
and pieces of the sequence from different
parts. And then they have to assemble the
whole genome sequence by aligning, you
know, if there are two sequences which have
a partial overlap. Then if they can align
that, then they can reconstruct .. So, will
take a simpler version of
this problem, so the alphabet of this is let
us see C A G T, which are this four chemicals,
which make a pure D N A, and you have sequences
of these characters.
So, let us say, there is one sequence which
is like this, A C G T C
some arbitrary
sequence I have written here. And let us say
there is another sequence, if you look at
it
carefully, they are not identical, I made
some small changes in the two sequences, if
they
.were identical then the problem of alignment
is straight forward, you just put once, you
can against the other sequence. If they are
not identical, the two sequences and that
includes the possibility that they are of
different lens also, I may you this sequence,
I
may give you some another sequence like, T
A C G then if I say, can you align this
sequence with this sequence, you might say
that yes, I can take this part here, and
alignment this part here and have an alignment
essentially.
But, what about sequences like this, you can
see that, I can match A with A; C with C;
G
with G; but now I have T here and a C here
essentially, what do I do essentially. So,
in
sequence alignment, you are allowed to insert
gaps, if inserting the gap improves, the rest
of the sequence alignment, then you allowed
to insert the gap. So, you can see that, that
once I align A C G with A C G here, then if
I insert the gap here, which means, I will
align this T with a gap. So, let us say this
transfers that then I can again align C A
G
here, with C A G here, T C G, T C G everything
is getting aligned, up to this T A.
And then suddenly, I have to insert another
gap, so I insert one gap here, and then I
can
.. So, if you can make out this diagram, I
am inserting a gap here, in
this sequence and I am inserting a gap here
in this sequence and by doing so, I am
improving the alignment essentially. So, the
problem of sequence alignment is to find,
some alignment, which is optimal according
to some criteria will define that in the
moment, which is the best essentially. Observe
that, I could have simplify said like this,
that take this whole sequence, and the place
it with gaps all the way, and then start this
sequence.
So, I could have then something like this,
A C G T C A up to C G here, and then started
the next sequence from here, A C G C A and
so on, and these are all gaps. That is of
course, a simple algorithm, take the first
sequence, align it with gaps, then take the
second sequence and insert gaps in the first
sequence in that place; obviously, that is
not
a good alignment essentially. So, how do we
differentiate between good and bad, we
give some cost to every operation, and let
us say we do the following in practice, people
follow probably more discriminative cost function,
but will follow simple cost function,
which says that matching.
.So, if there is a match, then cost is 0,
so if I am aligning in A with an A, I am paying
a 0
cost, mismatch cost 1. So, if I am aligning
a T with a C for example here, then I am
paying a cost of 1 and a gap, I have to pay
a cost of 2. So, let us say that, for example
if
there is only one character, which is different,
if let us say only this T and this, instead
of
this C there was a... let us say another C
here or something like that or a A or a G,
which
is not T, and the rest was the same. Then
I could get away by paying a cost of mismatch,
which is 1, rather than insert two gaps to
you know, take care of those things essentially.
But, in a situation like this, where you can
see that, inserting one gap here produces
a
match for so many more characters, simply
by inserting one gap here. So, I am the cost
I
am paying by inserting this gap, I am regaining
by getting 0 costs for all the rest
essentially. So, obviously there is a notion
of optimality here and we want to find a
sequence alignment, which has optimal cost
based on these three, this. In practice of
course, you may have a cost matrices which
would say that, aligning a C with A has a
certain cost, aligning a C with a G has a
certain cost and so on and so forth or
mismatches may have you know different cost.
We are just assuming that all mismatches have
1 cost and gap filling has 2 costs. So, how
does one solve this problem, what would be
a good algorithm to do sequence alignment?
.dynamic program
Dynamic programming. So, they say they if
to use the animal programming, till this bio
informatics people came in and then suddenly,
we have sequences of hundreds of
thousands of characters and those algorithms,
so good is essentially failed essentially.
So,
if you do some kind of an analogy, if you
would see the dynamic programming is like
branch and bound that we would, that we were
studying essentially in some sense
essentially. So, you are looking at this graph
.you can use the word as the rows and column
and if cost will diagonal ((Refer
Time.) so if you move long diagonal . and
machining it.
..
So, let us try that, this is by first sequence
here A C G T C. So, I will just use the few
characters A C G T C. So, I will draw this
here, and I will draw this here. And let me
take five characters from here, A C G C A,
A C G C A or maybe I should, I have started
labeling from the second listing, any way
let us assume that, we are working here. So,
now you can see that a diagonal move in this.
So, if this I look at this alignment,
matching A with A, C with C, G with G and
T with C.
So, let us forget the first ones, I should
have really drawn this like that, but this
move
amounts to saying that I am matching C with
this C, then I am matching this G with this
G, but then I run with T with ... So, I want
to insert a gap here, in the second this,
which
means I am not going to traverse a character,
which means I am not going to traverse
down .. So, the next move would be like this
and then I would be in
this node, and then I would continue like
this.
So, can you see that, the first move aligns
C with C this move, the second move aligns
G,
it going from here; I am going from C to G
and C to G here, so it aligns that. The third
move I am going from G to C, I am not going
from G to C, I am staying in G, but I am
going from G to T here, which is like inserting
a gap in this essentially. Of course, I am
not shown mismatches here, but you can see
that the cause of diagonals would be either
.0 or 1, depending on whether the two characters
that you are moving on are same or
different.
So, if I move with A to A cost is 0, if I
move with C to C cost is 0, from move with
G
with G, the cost is 0, if I would align T
with C and moved diagonally, then the cost
would be if 1. But, instead I am saying, I
am going to insert a blank here, which is
the
horizontal move here and the cost is 2. So,
essentially you can actually forget about
alignment at this point and remember that
the cost of every horizontal, a vertical move
is
2. And the cost of a diagonal move is either
0 or 1, depending on whether a moving on a
same character.
So, remember that moving down means, moving
in this string; moving horizontally
means moving in the other string and moving
diagonally means moving on both strings
and if you are moving on the same character
then cost is 0, if you are moving on a
different character, cost is 1. So, we are
transforming this problem of sequence alignment
into a graph search problem, where you have
to go from this corner of the graph to the
other corner of the graph with a optimal solution
cost essentially. So, any question about
this.
So, this has been, this has been a motivating
problem for A I search community to look
for newer and better problem, better ways
of solving search problems. And why do we
need, what do we mean by newer and better
ways? We should be able to handle such
graphs which have, let us say hundred thousand
nodes in this direction and hundred
thousand nodes in the vertical direction.
And then you can imagine that and A star like
algorithm will quickly run out of space essentially.
So, the motivation here is to say one
space essentially.
And here, I have just shown two strings, you
can extend this to multiple strings
assignments, alignments and you can imagine
a third dimension coming here and then a
four dimension and then a fifth dimension
, you can align multiple strings. So, the
graph
would become multidimensional in nature and
then you would have to find from one
corner to the opposite corner essentially.
So, the problem is have been transformed into
a
graph search problem and the goal is to save
one space essentially.
.So, we will begin with talking about saving
on close list and again, the motivation is
the
same graph. Because, as you can imagine, if
this was to be my search frontier which
means, this is on open, this is on open, this
is on open, this is on open or whatever, this
is
on open, this is on open, this is on open.
If this was the nodes which are an open then
the
size of search can be utmost m plus n. So,
it is going to grow linearly, at least it
will be
the smaller of m and n, as it goes down.
Initially of course, it will be very small,
but the size of closed is going quadractically,
because that is would like the area, which
is enclosed in this korf, which is m into
n in
the worst case at that point, when you reach
there. If you have see explode the entire
graph and we want to see. So, this is the
motivating problem where, we would be happy
to say one closely essentially. So, let us
just ask the question, what is close doing
for us
in search, before we move on to the algorithms
which. So, this question, no closed,
supposing, I am did not have closed, what
would happen to my problem.
.
So, what is the purpose, what is the function
that a functionality of close list in a search
algorithm one is avoid looping. Now, this
motivating example may not allow for
looping, because we have said the edges are
directed, but in general of course, looping
is
possible. So, we will take a more general
view, two is find better path. So, for example,
.in . star algorithm or in A star algorithm,
you keep the nodes in the
closed and you may find a better path them
in which case, you update that path and that
kind of a thing.
And the third thing, one more things closed
as for us. In general, if you look at search
in
a planning problem, what do you do, if goal
test is true?
..
Closed has all the information about parent
pointers, which allows us to reconstruct the
path essentially. So, the third thing it does
is, it allows us to reconstruct the path.
So, if
we are going to think of having an algorithm
without closed, then we would have to
worry about, these three issues or these three
things that closes doing for us essentially.
So, let me first begin with the second one,
how can we get around this problem that, I
do
not need to maintain close with one path and
then find a better path later and I do not
want to do all this.
. star algorithm maintains a value, but in
the closed or in the colored
node as they call it, but it may find a better
path, no it may not find a better path. In
. star algorithm, when once it colors a path
or once it puts it in close
either always found the best path essentially.
But, in A star also we can do that and the
we had discussed that, when in A star can
you say, that if you have put a node in closed,
you have already found the best path to the
node.
And you would not find a better path later,
when does that happen, come on we just did
it. I mean not just now, but in the recent
past, when the monotone condition, when the
heuristic function satisfies the monotone
condition, we proved that, whenever node is
picked for inspection, which means it is put
in to close. A star has already find, found
the
optimal cost of that node essentially. So,
this updating of past we do not have to worry
about that, what we do have to worry about
is avoid looping and reconstruct path.
.So, we will do that in the next class, we
will look at some algorithms for which
drastically proven the close list. After that,
we will look at some algorithms, which
proven the open list of course, we have seen
I D A star is one such a example, which
proves a open list, but we will look at a
other variations. And then we will try to
see
whether, we can have an algorithm which proven
both the list essentially. We shall take
us to the state of art till about 2005, when
that last paper was published I think. So,
I will
stop here and then we will take those algorithms
of in the next class essentially.
.