.Let us begin; we are looking at rule based
systems.
As we discussed earlier, in rule
based system, the program part, if you want
to call it, is written as a set of rules.
Now,
these rules can do all kind of things.
They can do what you would do in normal
programming, for example, sort an array, and
things like that, but they are also, by
instrumental, in capturing what we would say
as expert knowledge, essentially.
So, we
catch a domain expert and try to get knowledge
out of expert, and put it in the form of
rules.
So, you could mix up rules of different kinds
into one system.
That is why, in the
70s and 80s, this was known as the domain
of expert systems.
It was quite in exercise to
get to experts and elicit their knowledge
from them.
There was a whole exercise of what
they use to call as knowledge acquisition
where, they have protocols of how to talk
to
expert, and how to extract knowledge from
them, and then put it in the form of rules,
essentially.
Eventually, as I said in my last class, this
technology, all this has stabilized
into something, which is more popular among
business users, because users in banks and
other such organizations; they are able to
express what they call as business rules in
a
very simple language, and the rest of the
programs takes care of everything else,
essentially.
..
If you remember that a rule based system,
consists of set of rules
what we call as a
working memory, which basically, holds the
data and an inference engine.
Inference
engine is a program, whose job is to select
rules, and apply them to data, and repeatedly
do that, essentially.
So, we saw that what this does is that it
is a process, three stage
process.
We have match; what match does?
It takes inputs.
So, this is the most important
part of a rule based system; what it does
is it takes a working memory as an input,
and it
takes the set of rules as input, and produces
what we call as a conflict set.
So, what is this
doing?
If you remember that each rule is of the form
pattern 1, pattern 2, pattern n, and
some actions on the other side.
The actions were, as we discussed earlier;
either, making
new data elements or deleting some.
So, if you look at these patterns, this is
what is used
for matching the data.
If you collect together, all the patterns
from all the rules, then you
would have pattern 11, pattern 12, pattern,
let us say, 31, pattern 32.
So, we will have a
whole list of patterns, and this working memory
is an ordered set; ordered, in the sense
of time stamp.
So, all these are working memory elements.
In the match phase, because we want to be
complete; every pattern must be compared
with every working memory element, because
you want to produce all instances of rules
which are matching; not just one instance.
So, every pattern has to be compared with
every working memory element, and that is
to be done for this.
So, it is a human less
amount of task to be done.
What this produces is a conflict set.
The conflict set is a list of
rules or instances of rules, along with a
time stamp, like this 1, 2, 3 and so on; time
.stamps of the data.
Then, the task is to select which of those
matching rules, we have to
fire.
We discussed a few conflict resolution strategies,
like specificity, and recency, and
mean sense analysis, and so on.
So, this is given to an section called resolve,
which
selects one rule from the conflict set, along
with its data and then, this is given to rule
plus data, and by data, we mean the working
memory elements; execute.
If you remember, the effect of execute is
either, to make, which means to create new
data
elements, or to delete, or remove.
These are the two principle effects we are
interested in.
Others, like read, print and halt, are immaterial
at this point of view, and then, this is
repeated into a cycle, again and again.
So, we have observed that this brute force
match
has two deficiencies; one there is possible
that different rules may be looking at the
some
of the patterns, they are using, may be shared,
essentially.
So, for the upper, this pattern 1
may be there in many rules; pattern 2 may
be there in many rules, and so on, but here,
we
have listed them as, you know; patterns of
rule 1; patterns of rule 2; patterns of rule
3;
and so on.
So, they are matched multiple number of times.
They may be even shared
partially, as we will see in an example today.
That even, if they are shared partially, we
should be able to minimize the number of matches
that we do.
Remember that these
patterns are made up of class names and attribute
value pairs.
For every attribute, there is
a test condition, which could be equality
that it must match the data, or it must be
something, like greater than a value, or not
equal to a value and things like that.
So, that is one thing that we would like to
do.
The other thing that you would like to do
is
that, because when we, let us say this, some
rule 3 is selected in the resolve phase, and
let us say this rule 3 matches these pieces
of data; let us say 3 pieces of data.
It is
possible that when this rule 3 executes, it
may say, delete this data.
So, let me put a cross
here; delete this data and may be, it might
say, add a new data, or let me use a term;
make here.
So, let us just take this simple example.
We are deleting two elements.
Let us
call these elements, A and B, and you are
adding a third element, which let us call
as C,
essentially.
That is the only change you are making into
a working memory.
Two
elements have been removed and one has been
added.
So, what we expect in such a
situation is that most of the other rules,
which are matching with some data, earlier
in the
last cycle, will continue to match in the
next cycle.
We would like to avoid the trouble of
matching them all over, again.
..
So, these two properties of this particular
match algorithm are done away with by the
algorithm that we are looking at today, and
it is called the Rete algorithm.
It was, as I
mentioned earlier, given by Charles Forgy
in 1979 as a part of his PHD work.
Based on
this, he divides the language called OPS5
which, some people say, stands for Official
Production System Language.
Remember that, we also called rules as productions,
and
all this was happening in CMU at that time.
Today, we want to look at the details of this
algorithm; the Rete algorithm and its structure.
So, let me also rewrite the rules that I
wrote in the last class.
So, remember this card playing rules, we have
said.
.
.This is an OPS5 syntax; something like this.
If you remember, the first element in this
list is the class name of the data structure;
the second element which, with this symbol
is
the attribute name; the third element is the
value of the attribute name, this attribute;
and
you can have multiple attributes and their
values.
When we enclose something in angular
brackets like this that represents a variable,
essentially, which means, it will match
anything.
There are no data types involved here.
Let us say, we also have a working
memory element, which says, who has to play.
So, this one says, it is a turn of some
player P, of course, this is a variable.
So, it could be applied to any player, and
card suit s
name X, and we are saying, in this third pattern
that there is a card, which is also;
whenever, we have same variable name in two
different patterns in the same left hand
side of the rule, they must match identically,
to the same value, essentially.
They cannot
match different values.
So, if there is a card of this group is played,
whose name is X and
is held by player P, then this player can
play this card.
I will not write at the right hand side, because
today, we are only interested in the match
part of the algorithm.
Then, we had written another rule, P highest
card.
So, instead of
playing any card, now, I have a different
rule, which says that you know, in that suit,
play the highest card.
So, this 1 and 2 will be the same; I will
not repeat that here, but
this is 1 and this is 2; it is just for our
sake, but not part of the language syntax.
So,
anyway, let me rub it off from here.
The first was same, the third one is similar
card; it
must be of this suit, s; it must have some
name, because you want to use that name in
the
output, say, play this card, and must be held
by this player, whose turn it is to play,
and
this card has a rank, let us say R. Now, we
are interested in playing the highest card.
So,
we have this extra bit of information in this
particular pattern.
Obviously, notice that
patterns can select any subset of the class
information.
I put this in bracket, just to make it show;
this is the condition that we are looking
at; yes,
and this is the negation sign.
This should be right as saying, the first
two conditions are
the same that the suit being played is s;
it is a turn of player P. Player P has a card
in this
suit s whose, rank is R, and there is no card
held by player P, in this suit s whose, rank
is
smaller than R, which means higher than R;
we assume that.
Then, we will say, play this
card.
So, in both instances, we will play this card
name s of this suit; play this jack of
spade, something like that.
So, let me just give you a third rule.
Those of you are literate,
will recognize as playing a trump card in
a, when you do not have a card like this.
So, the
.first condition is the same; the second condition
is the same; we have a third condition,
which is saying that from trump suit t.
So, those of you have played cards, would
know
that there is something called a trump suit,
and essentially, the effect of calling a suit,
a
trump suit is that its cards are always, higher
than other suit cards.
But they can only be
played, when you do not have the other suit
cards.
Again, we are talking about a card
here.
So, I will not write this name and all, but
what I will write here is that the suit is
trump.
Everything else will be the same that there
is a card, held by player P, whose
name is X, and blank; we are not bothered
about here, but this suit that I am selecting
is
this trump suit T, and not the suit s, which
I have said here.
I can even, to be explicit, I can even say,
instead of writing just T, I can write t not
equal
to s, but it turns out that in this particular
example, that does not really matter; so,
I have
not written it like that, but those are the
kind of things you can write as condition
checks,
essentially, and no card.
So, this is the another root, which says that
if the suit in place s;
if the turn of the player is P, is there;
the trump suit is T, and this player P has
a card of
the trump suit, and he does not have any card
in the suit, which is in play; then we can
play the trump suit.
So, just three different left hand sides that
we are interested in, and
we will see how Rete net handled it.
So, Rete net is the structure, which is maintained
by
the Rete algorithm or Rete algorithm, as some
people call it.
Rete is the latin word,
which actually, means net, essentially.
.
.The Rete net is made up of two layers.
You might think of it as on the network.
On the
top, is a discrimination network, and we will
see what the structure is.
Below, is an
assimilative network.
So, the top part of the network is what some
people called as a
mainly sorted, decision key or discriminative
network.
The bottom part collects together;
this is updated.
So, what do you mean by assimilative; that
for every rule, I need a set of
patterns to match, and the bottom parts will
see that it gets those three patterns matched,
essentially.
How does this work?
This basically, works by inserting at the
top, these three
tokens.
So, when you say you want to delete this working
memory element, we generate
a token; let us say we call it minus a; minus
stands for the factor we want to deleting
it,
and one for this token b, which is minus b,
and one for this token c, which is plus c.
So, as the algorithm is progressing, every
time it fires the rule, it will generate some
positive tokens and some negative tokens.
Those tokens would be inserted here, at the
top of the network, which is, as I said in
the last class, changes in the working memory.
These tokens capture what has changed in the
working memory; which things have been
removed from the working memory; what things
have been added to the working
memory.
What the Rete algorithm does is that takes
changes into working memory and
produces changes in a complete set.
So, here, are the different rules R1, R2,
Rk; so, the
network, which you will see in a little bit
more detailed in a moment, is a compilation
of
the rules, essentially.
This network is defined by the rules that
we have in the system, and
it is basically, a different representation
of the same rules in a network form.
The
working memory, this part, sits in locations,
which are nodes in this network, as we will
see in detail.
So, the working memories, kind of, distributed
over this network, and you
can imagine that tokens are flowing from top
to down, just like you would do, for
example, in the very simple case of binary
search key; you want to find out, whether
there is a record whose, key value is 17.
You will put it at the top, and you will check,
whether that root node is greater than 17
or less than 17, and it will send it down
one
branch.
You will keep doing that.
Eventually, it will filter down to the node,
whose value
is 17.
In our case, also we are looking for tokens
with, of a specific kind, but what we are
looking for, tokens with match our rules,
essentially.
So, our tokens will follow down this path,
and for example, in the first two, we need
three tokens.
So, three different tokens, if they come there,
this part is only to make the
search efficient, just like in a search tree.
This part is to collect together, the different
.pattern set or rule need.
So, if you can somehow, collect three tokens
for this tool one,
and the three tokens arrive here, then we
will say rule one is matching.
Once it is
matching, and as long as these tokens are
sitting there, it will continue to match,
essentially.
Only, when we make these changes, if something
happens, then it may go
out of the conflict set or something like
that.
So, these rules, this gives us the conflict
set, here somewhere.
Remember, conflict set is
a collection of instances of these rules.
Each rule may have more than one instance
with
different pieces of data.
Collection of instance of this rule, along
with the identifiers of
the data elements; they are matching, which
is the time stamps that we use here.
So,
these are the identifiers.
They basically, tell you when this token meet
was.
So, to start
with, you can imagine that whatever the data
that you have, you just put the whole thing
into the net.
Instead of just having a few changes, the
whole working that is a starting
point, and it will go and figure out different
set of rules; you will get the conflict set.
Then, the resolve face will select one of
those rules in the conflict set; execute that;
generate a few tokens like this.
Those few tokens would be put in here, and
they will
again, tickle down this network, and make
some changes on the way, but otherwise, the
rest of the match is, sort of, static in these
networks.
So, let us see what this network
looks like.
As I said, the top part is discriminative
in nature, which tries to separate
tokens of different kinds.
So, that you do not have to do a sequential
match.
That is a
basic idea in many of these search algorithms.
The first thing, we test for, is a class
name.
So, we have one class name here, suit.
..
So, let us say this
is the root and there is a node; first nodes
are called alpha nodes.
Just
some nomenclature; nothing to do with the
game playing algorithm that we have been
looking at.
And what alpha nodes do is that they have
exactly, one parent and they do a
certain test, and the test is what we are
writing in the box, and in the first level,
it is a
class name; that the class name is suit here.
They may have more than one child,
depending on what the rules are saying.
For example, here, we have for the card, some
different rules.
So, you may have more children, essentially.
So, the second one is for
some attribute from the class name.
Now, in our case, the attribute is played
and our
value is only a variable.
So, we do not really have much, but you can
imagine that if we
had one rule for spades, and another rule
for hearts, then you would have one branch
for
spades here, and another branch for hearts
here, and this test would be more specific.
You could say if the suit being played is
spades or the suit being played is hearts,
then
the rest of the network would be different.
In our example we have only a variable.
So, it does not matter.
We have only one.
Then,
let us finish up the easier path first, which
is the second last name, which is turn, and
it
has also, only one value; see, in all the
rules, we have only one value; turn of P;
turn of
P. Again, you can imagine if we discriminated
between the different players, if we said
turn of south, or turn of north, or turn of
east; where, north, east, south, west are
the
names of the place, then we would have different
branches coming out of here.
So, again,
we have only one branch, because there is
only one pattern of this kind.
Every path in
.this represents a pattern.
If we have different patterns, which are slightly
different, then
they will diverge, you know; one pattern will
go this way, and another pattern will go
that way.
So, it is like a structure, which is similar
to the Trie structure; I do not know if
you have studied the Trie structure.
It is a little bit like that, essentially.
So, all these are alpha nodes.
Alpha nodes have one
parent, and every node has a memory, associated
with it in which, tokens can sit,
essentially.
So, let us assume that memories, behind it,
and we cannot see properly.
Then, other kinds of nodes are beta nodes.
I will draw the beta notes with the circle,
and
what they do is; pull together, tokens from
different patterns; tokens, which are of
different patterns, essentially.
In our example, there is no test to be done.
These are kind
of independent and all we are saying is that
we should have one token of this kind, and
one token of this kind.
Then, we have these two patterns, at least.
Our first tool needs
three patterns; we have collected two.
So, these are beta nodes.
Beta nodes may have or
in the implementation that we have described
here, have exactly two parents.
We can
have more than two, but let us assume that
this is like a joint of two structures.
We are
only joining two patterns at a time, essentially.
So, if we have three patterns, then we will
first join two, and then, the third one, and
so on.
Beta node also, may do a test as you will
see in the moment.
So, let me do this rough rule first, at this
end.
Obviously, one thing
we need is card, because that is one of our
class names, and the last one that we need
is
trump.
It has one attribute called suit, and it has
the value called t.
So, this last rule needs
five patterns; one and two, which we have
here.
Then, one pattern will come down this
path, which is that trump path, and then,
two patterns will go down this path.
So, two
patterns are talking about cards, essentially.
So, one of them says that player; I have not
written that there, but it is a part of that
pattern, and this P must match this P, as
you will see.
So, card player P suit t.
So, all we
are saying now is that if this player has
a card of this suit t, then he is allowed
to play.
So, we joined together, these two patterns
by a beta node, and we put a condition that
this t, which is coming from this side, and
this t, which is coming from this side, equal
to.
So, we are using the equality condition, because
we are just identifying that; see the
variable names I have used the same, but they
do not have be the same.
There could have
been different variable names, but this test
is saying that in this case, it is the same.
So,
let us see.
.Let us say I use this variable s here, and
then, I will have to say this s equal to t,
or let me
just keep to simple thing; see, this is t.
We will look at the other one in a moment.
So, it
has got four, but four these things, but it
still needs one pattern, which says that it
does
not have a card of this suit s.
Now, we want to do a match, which says that
he does not
have, or such a data element, does not exist.
Now, that can be done in a various number
of ways.
Remember that we said that every node is associated
with a memory,
essentially.
Now, I will just use some symbol, which I
will claim is a symbol for
negation.
The way to read this is that the token will
flow down this path, only if the
count; now, this is a bit weird; only the
count of the number of tokens, passing down
this
path, with this value P and with this value
S, is 0, essentially.
So, you must have; I am
just trying to use the simple way of talking
about it, essentially.
What you want to really
say is that if a token of this kind want to
actually, come here, then its effect on the
rule
will be that it will not match, essentially.
You can think of it like that.
You can think of it
as saying that the count of the number of
tokens.
What are these tokens?
This is the
pattern, which says that is the card held
by player P of suit S. Now, if the player
had
three cards of this suit; let us say we are
talking about spades.
If the player had three cards of spades, then
three tokens would come down here,
essentially, because that should be in the
working memory.
What this test is doing is
counting, how many tokens are coming here,
and if the tokens is greater than 0, then
it
will say, no, this rule cannot fire.
The other way to look at is that if a token
wants to
come here, then it will immediately, disable
the rule to which, it is pointing to.
So, in any
case, we need a joint here, and the joint
should say that this S is the same as this
S; so, S
equal to S. I will just write, and this P
is the same as this P. So, by this moment,
we have
looked at three patterns.
There are two positive patterns and one negative
pattern.
In that
branch, we have looked at two patterns; both
of them are positive patterns.
If all the five
patterns match, which means, the appropriate
tokens come down here, then we can join
them together, and we have to be careful here.
So, P is equal to P, for example, and that
is the only thing, you have to worry about,
and here is a rule called ruff.
So far, we have drawn the network for only
one rule, which is the third rule.
The third
rule has five patterns; this one and two are
same as this; that the suit will play is that
the
turn of player P. The third one says that
the trump suit is t.
The fourth one says that
player has a card of t, and the fifth one
says that the player has no cards of the suit,
which
.is being played S, essentially.
So, this snow card is captured here, because
of this
symbol.
This captures the first two patterns, and
this is the third pattern, which is the trump
suit,
which defines a trump suit.
This is the fourth pattern, which says that
the player has a
card of this trump suit, because T equal to
T, and here, all the five patterns will come
and
sit here, and we will say, this rule is now,
gone to the conflict set.
Let us take the first
tool, which is the simple rule.
All it says is there is a card of suit S,
name X, player P. So,
I could simply say it here.
I could say here, I need one more thing which
is named.
So, if
a pattern wants to come down this path, it
would say that it is the card held by player
P
variable P, some suit, which is a variable
S, and some name, which is variable X, and
I
can join it with this, and put all the conditions;
that S equal to S, which means S coming
from this side, is the same as the S coming
from this side, likewise, for the P coming
from this side, P equal to P and I would have
that any card.
Now, you can observe that the only thing I
did at this moment, for the rule number one
was to add this box here, and this beta node
here.
This is the alpha node and this is the
beta node, and nothing else, I have to do.
The rest of the match, it is the first pattern;
the
suit being played is S; the second pattern,
the turn of player P is already there, in
the
network.
I have to just take a lead from there, and
I have already joined them together.
Then, take this third token from here, and
at this point, I have three tokens coming
together, which is what I need from a first
rule, essentially.
So, this intra cycle savings,
so to speak, that in the same cycle, I am
matching this rule and this rule, but I am
sharing
in this network; the matching work, which
is required for those rules.
Only, some things
are different, which I do separately, essentially.
You can take the middle rule, as you can
see, it always takes something from here,
and it needs a card of suit S name X player
P
rank Y.
So, we can take this from here.
Let me use a different color.
So, we can take this
from here, and add another alpha node of rank
R. I can take still, one more from here,
and add another alpha node, which you will
say, rank less than R. Remember, R is still
a
variable at this point of time.
Then, I can combine them by saying this R
equal to R. So,
what is happening in, if you can see this
purple part?
We are talking about two tokens
flowing down this path up to here.
Actually, we do not need this name, sorry.
So, this
should actually, come from here.
.The card held by player of suit S, whose
name is X, and whose name is R, and somebody
should have pointed this out.
I need this negation node here.
So, in this rule, the third
pattern is flowing from here; card held by
player P suit S name X rank R, and its coming
here.
The fourth pattern is coming from here; card
held by player P suit X, then it is
coming here, whose rank is less than R, but
then, there is a negation here, which means
the player does not have a card of higher
rank, and this I can combine with this.
With all that P equal to P, and S equal to
S, and I will get the second rule, which is
highest card.
In this network, see, we started off by creating
network for the third rule.
Then, we added few more edges and nodes for
the first rule, and then, a few more edges,
missing for the third rule.
So, notice that there is only one branch going
down for the
cards being held by players, which means that
every card that every player holds, a token
will go down this branch.
The same token, if you look at this structure
here, all you are
saying is that it is of suit S, and this is
of suit T where, S and T are variables.
So,
obviously, every card, let us say it is spades.
So, if there is a spade card held by this
player P, the token will come here, as well
as, it will also go here, but only if it matches
this, it will match this rule number four;
otherwise, it will not match this rule number
four, and only if this matches this suit,
which is in play, will the player played this
card,
essentially
The Rete network is a network, which is a
compilation of the rules.
So, if you have this
network, then you do not need the rules, essentially,
because it is just a different way of
writing these rules.
The task of the software engineer here, is
to be able to view the set of
rules, and construct a latter network corresponding
to this, essentially.
That is the first
part, building the network or compiling the
program, as you might say, and then, you put
in all the data from the top.
This act like a discrimination network, if
the token working
on the element is of class name, card; it
will follow this path.
If it is of class name,
trump; it will follow that path, and that
each stage, it is a test; that it has to satisfy;
call it
to move on.
This one says that the effect is opposite,
that if such a token exist, and this
rule will not fire.
If there is no such token coming here, then
this rule will fire,
essentially.
So, obviously, you can see that this needs
four tokens; four positive tokens, and one
negative pattern, which stands for the fact
that they must be no such token.
So, if a token
comes down this path, that rule will get disabled.
Now, we can also understand what is
.going to happen in this cycle here.
Whenever, we execute a rule, we add these
new
tokens, and put them down the network; sort
of, we push them from here, and they will
travel some down.
.
So, it is possible that we have created, only
these three; let us say these two tokens,
and
this tokens come in later, or let us say we
have these four tokens, and in the last; and
let
us say that the suit being played is spades,
and in the last round, if the program played
a
spade, then we will have a negative token
of saying that that card has been played by
the
suit, and if that player had only one card
of the suit, there is the negative token,
will
come here.
It will cancel the positive token, which was
sitting earlier, and then, this rule
will certainly, come into the conflict set.
Essentially, the effect of throwing these
tokens
down, this network is to either, activate
some new rules or to deactivate some existing
rules, essentially.
Any questions at this point?
So, I will expect that if I give you a set
of rules of some
domain like I define, you can look at some
past papers, for example, you should be able
to construct the network, and show, where
the tokens are.
Of course, here, we have not
created the tokens.
So, we do not know where the tokens will sit,
and here, every test is a
very variable kind of a test.
So, it will not stop tokens here, but supposing,
this was
played spades; let us say this rule was only
for spades.
So, if I had spades here, then if a
token with hearts or diamonds or clubs come,
it will just sit here.
It will never be able to
.reach this place, because there is no rule
to tackle those kinds of processes, essentially.
So, we should able to say where the tokens
are sitting, essentially.
So, as the last bit, we
started off by saying that this whole idea
of rule based systems was motivated by a
cognitive approach to problem solving.
.
We are also said that the rules, for example,
are the long term memory of the problem
solver, because that is the knowledge, which
is acquired over a period of time, whereas,
this working memory elements are the short
term memory of the problem solver, because
that is the data that the problem solver is
interacting with.
There are cognitive models of
the brain, which says that this is where,
you store short term data, and this is where,
you
store long term data.
So, in some sense, this is the model for doing
this kind of reasoning.
There are variations of this, we can think
of.
For example, you can think of a language in
which, you can create rules on the fly, essentially.
That would be difficult to handle in
this, because here, the network that we have
described is a static network, and we have
said it is a compilation of the rule that
we have; how do we handle a situation where,
the
rules can be themselves, added or deleted
from a knowledge base?
..
Finally, I should add that you should look
up system called Soar, which is a successor
of
this language, which amongst, apart from this
whole idea of using a Rete network; the
Rete network has become like a fixture in
all these business, I said, last time we have
mentioned that.
You know this Rule Business Management System
or Business Rule
Management System; BRMS.
So, there is lots of software, which is commercially
available for managing business.
Rete networks or its improvements; I also
said that 4G
created a newer version of Rete network, which
is called Rete NT, which is 500 times
faster than this network that we have just
described, but unfortunately, we do not have
descriptions of that network, because it is
a trade secret, and it has not been revealed,
but
they have been several improvements, in terms
of speed, that have been made to the Rete
network.
It is a big part of business rule, in general,
essentially.
This Soar, on the other
hand, was continued in the university environment,
again CMU, by a guy called John
Laird.
So, if you look up John Laird or if you look
up Soar, you would get more information
out of it.
John Laird also made an observation about
four or five years ago.
He said that
we all know that the computing industry is
virtually driven by games, essentially.
I mean,
most of the faster processors, for example,
are developed, because people want faster
games; you should be able to do things faster.
But what John Laird observed was that
games, or at least, the graphic capabilities
of games, you know the ability to render
scenes, which are realistic, and ability to
have characters moving around, which look
like
.realistic characters, has kind of saturated;
that there is not much improvement you can
do
on that front, essentially.
What he says is that the next level of improvement
in games
will be in giving a quote unquote; intelligence
to the characters.
So, whatever, avatar or
whatever, characters we have in game; if they
are intelligent, which means if they have
some knowledge of some kind, and they can
do some useful, what you may call,
thinking; then, that is going to be the next
level of interesting list in game, essentially.
He
is the same guy, who is maintaining this Soar
architecture.
So, those of you are interested in games;
I am sure, most of you are; I would encourage
you to look at Soar, and if you want to build
a game, which has intelligent characters
inside it, then this is a mechanism; this
is a language, which allows you to; which
is a
kind of decedent of OPS5, which allows you
to express what kind of knowledge that you
want put into to an agent, inside a game.
So, we will stop here with this.
In the next class, I want to move to a different
topic,
which is that of planning.
We have talked of planning on and off, but
we will look at a
closer look in a little while.
So, we stop here.
.