So let us get back to state space search and
valuation that we are looking at, we are call
uninformed. Valuations which we are looking
at today, I mean from in the sense, they do
not exploit any knowledge of any kind from
the domain. On the next class when you
meet on a Wednesday, we will try to see how
to get around this, how to exploit some
knowledge from the domain essentially.
..
So, the last algorithm that we saw was this,
simple search to in which we had two sets
open and close, open contains a set of candidates
set we want to inspect, and closed
contains, the set of candidate that we have
already inspected. And the idea is to keep
generating new candidates, and adding them
to open, and how do we can generate new
candidates by, removing from move the output
of more than anything which is already
on open or which is in closed essentially.
So, we will only get new candidates, and in
this
ways, we will only had new candidate to inspect.
And if the state species finite, you can see
that eventually, whatever states are reachable
from the start state, they will be explode
at some point or the other, and it will come
out
of this loop only, it open becomes empty.
So, there should be a check here, if open
not
equal to empty then do this, open him to empty
report failure essentially. But, let us
assume that there is a solution to the problem,
which means the goal said that we are
talking about, is reachable from the starts
state, in which case we would find the solution
that some point or the other.
So, let us take the main missionaries in animals
problem or the man, goat and lion
problem that we have been talking about. It
is possible for the man to take the goat,
and
lion and the cabbage on the other side, what
will our algorithm do, this algorithm that
we
.have said, what are the incase dent and what
is the algorithm giving us. So, what are the
interested in it start with that, what are
the, what should the man do right, man should
first take the goat, then keep the goat on
that side, comeback with the empty boat, then
take the lion and all these kind of step,
what is the algorithm giving us? It is only
giving
us to state end with satisfy the goal test
that does not help us in any way, to solve
the
problem.
.
So, that is the second problem with this solution,
and we have to address that, but before
we do that, let me also clarify the there
are two kinds of problems, one is call the
configuration problem, and the other kind
is planning problems. In planning problems,
the solution is a path; in configuration problems,
solution is a state. So, we can actually
distinguish between these two different kinds
of problems. So, the river crossing problem
is the planning problem, we want to know,
what are the sequence of moves the man must
do, to solve the problem.
But, there are problems which are configuration
kind of problems, so for example, the N
queens, so you must be familiar with the N
queens problem, I presume. The task is that
given a end by end chess board, you have to
place N queens on the board, in such a
manner that no queen attacks, any other queens
essentially. So, that is a well known, very
.commonly studied N queens problem, there
are variations with this, which say for
example, every queen must say attack exactly
to other queens. So, that is another
configuration problem.
So, in such a problem, the N queens problems
for example, the solution is only the final
state that we . if you can show that such
a state exists, then we have
solve the problem, it does not matter they.
In fact, there is no notion of a path there,
I
mean unless, you say this is the first queen
to plays on the board, and this is second
queen to plays on the board, that does not
make sense. We are interested, then some
configuration and such problems are called
configuration problem, for which this
algorithm is fine because, it will return
to us a state with satisfies the goal constraints.
Whereas, for such problems, we does not work,
because is only telling us what is the
final status, how do we solve this problem.
So, for planning problems, how do we have
to modify the search node? So, there we said
the search node was the state essentially.
For planning problems, we have to modify the
search node. So, what do I mean by the
search node, the node generated by this algorithm,
what we put into open, what we take
out from open, and you know things like that
essentially. And we have to modify it in
such a way, that it contains the paths information
essentially.
Now, one simple way of doing that, is to store
the entire path as the search nodes
essentially. So, let me use a small example,
supposing this is the start state, and this
is the
successors state. So, let us a some small
states piece we have, some random graph I
drawn, this is the start state, and let say
this is the goal state, and we have to find
the path
from the start state to the goal state essentially.
So, you say, so you will go, you will a
algorithm some will begin with start, then
the move gen function will return it is
neighbors, which is A and B.
And then the algorithm will inspect a whether
a is a goal or not and that kind of things,
so it will do all that stuffs. But, I want
to know the path that the algorithm finds,
from
start state to goal state. So, I modify this
search node, to store the entire path. So,
what
does that mean, I start with this node itself
then my successors; I call them as B S and
A
S. So, I keep a list of nodes as a, so a search
node is a list of states or list of state
nodes.
.So, this list is the list of two nodes B
S essentially, with basically says, I came
to B from
S, this says that I came to A from S essentially.
Then if I about to expand A, then I could
the let us assume that we are not going to
add S
to successors of A, only C and E. So, I will
write that as C A S and E A S. So, this is
one
approach, that I am modify I am search node,
to store the entire path. Of course, now I
have to modify my algorithm little bit, which
I am not doing, but I am leaving does not
exercise for you to do, when you pick a node
from the search node. So, this is, so these
are the search node, so this is the original
node.
And then, in the new scheme of things, double
circle stands for node gen closed, instead
of deleting nodes, because they not deleting
nodes anymore, pulling them in closed. So,
we put this in closed, I do not know I hope
it not to confusing, put this in closed and
so
on essentially. So, these are the two nodes
are in open and this three, let say we have
inspected already, when I pick a node from.
So, this is I mean, this is my search node,
it is a list of states, I have to extract
the first
element from this, which is C or E depending
on which node I pick. So, I extract seat,
apply the goal test to C, same goal test function
I can apply to C, and if it is fails. So,
let
say C any C does not have any children, so
let say I pick E, I apply the goal test to
E, and
goal test fails, so what do I do I generate
the successors of E, again the same move gen
function, I can use to generate successors
of E, but I must append that.
..
So, what are the successors of E returns to
me in this graph F and G, so I must take this
F, I must take this G, and append and put
it at the head of this list. So, I must generate
F
E A S and G E A S. So, I have to modified
the algorithm is little bit, but notice that
I can
still use the same move gen function, and
I am only going to applying to a state. And
I
can use the same goal test function, because
I will extract the first state from this,
and
apply the goal test to that, and then apply
the move gen function that is essentially.
So, I will leave this as a small exercise
for you to do, we will inset use another approach.
So, this is one approach, to convert everything
into a path, the second approach is to only
store the parents essentially. So, search
node is the pair, we will call it a node pair,
and
the pair is current and parent, and let say
it is a list of two nodes, in which we store
the
current node. So, we will always be interested
in the current node, we will apply the goal
test to current node, will apply the move
gen function to current node and so on
essentially.
But, we will only stores, so here we are storing
the entire path, up to the start node from
that, which of course, makes the task of returning
the path must simpler, I have to just
take this and reverse it and return it as
output S. So, for example, when I generate
this,
and this is the, this the satisfy the goal
test function, then I have to just take this
and say
.the path is go from S to A, A to E and E
to G and that is solution. So, I have just
reversed
this list, and return it as a path. Now I
am saying, that instead of stoling this entire
path
as a search node, uniformly store a search
node as a pair, made up of the current node
and the parent node.
And my route will look like S comma nil, a
nil stands for no parent, and then this will
be
again B S, this would be A S as before, but
this would be now only C A and E A, and
when I generate successors of A, I will get
F E and G E. So, all this is gone into closed,
and let say whether does not matter, whether
we have seen this or not, and when we pick
up this node. So, let me say this stands for
the fact that we have found the goal node,
we
have to still return the path, but now you
have to do a little bit of extra work, to
reconstruct the path.
.
So, we need than algorithm, which you will
call as reconstruct path, and to this algorithm
we will give a node pair as input, and which
node pair the one whose first elements
satisfy the goal test. So, this for example,
G E will give this as input to G E, so what
do
we want to G do with the G E. So in general,
I will have a goal node and parent node, I
will call it P 1. So, this is I am describing
this algorithm reconstruct path algorithm.
So,
the input to that is a goal node and it is
parent node. So, it is a node pair and the
.particular node pair is a goal node and it
is parent node. And so I start constructing
the
path, I say I had.
So, initially as a path gets an empty list,
and then at this point as a path get cons
G path.
So, I am using the list cons functions, because
it is a convenient mechanism to add
something to the head of a list, so I have
a list called path, and I am adding this node
G at
the head of the path, then what do I do, how
do I go to the parent, parents parent, I want
to go to the grandparent . parent. Of course,
I can find from here,
but from the parent, I will have go to the
grandparent, they will a find the grandparent
corresponding.
.
But where do I find the corresponding parent.
. if we store the parent .
But, how do I I am looking for a node pair
of the kind P 1 P 2 correct. So, I know that
P
1, I came to G from P 1, I am trying to find
out, where did I come to P 1 from, and that
that is call it P 2, where will I find this
P 1 P 2.
.
I will find it in the closed list why, because
I am putting all these things into closed.
So,
for example, G E is what I have, and I am
looking for something like E followed by
something, which is E A in this case, and
will find it in the clues. And likewise the
parent
of A, I will find in the clues and so on.
So, search in closed, so I search in the closed
to
find this node pair, everything is a node
pair, opened with consists of node pairs,
and
search consists of node pairs, and close consists
of node pairs essentially. I find this, then
again like this, I find P 2 P 3, and I keep
doing that, till when will I stop doing this
search.
.. .
Till I find the route node which is, characterized
by some P n, followed by nil, and at
each stage, I will do this, cons P 1 path;
here cons P 2 path and so on and so forth,
I will
keep doing that by the time I am come here,
and found this, come out of this loop. So,
all
this is happening inside one loop, going from
parent to grandparent, till I find that there
are no more grandparents, at which point,
my path for the win constructed, because I
would cons this P n to path. So, I would know
that, I start with P n go to P n minus 1and
so on and so forth.
So, I need this extra bit of work to be done,
to return the path, but what do I get in that
advantage is that I have a uniform representation
that everything is a node pair, open
content consists of node pairs, close consists
of node pairs and so on and so forth. So,
this part for example, searching in the closed,
I will leave it as a small exercise to for
you
to work on. And write this whole algorithm
in fact, for reconstruct path. So, we have
this
algorithm call reconstruct, a supporting call
reconstruct path, we have also this
supporting in that is call it, remove seen,
which removes nodes
already in open or closed.
So, let us say that we have now move completely
to a list based representation, where
our path is a list, node pair is a list, everything
is a list essentially, open is a list, close
is
also a list. So remove seen, when we are generating
the new nodes for open, the remove
seen function should remove things which are
either in the open list or in the closed list.
Now, we must be careful here, our open and
closed has been modify the little bit, they
have become pairs. So, you have to take care
of the fact that you are looking at the
correct element there, so I will lead that
exercise for you to do.
And, we will assume that, we have something
like a, suppose those of you who are
studied list or something similar, something
like a map car function, which does the
following that. So, this removes in will represent,
will give as a list of successors, so we
will apply the move gen function, which will
gave us all the neighbors, there removes in
will remove from those neighbors things, which
are already in closed or which are
already in open in it will give us new list.
From this new list, we will apply this map
car
function to, say that take each of the successors,
and construct node pairs with the parent
.essentially, so whatever it doing.
.
Let me draw it here, so there is some node
N, we will call move gen, it will give us
some
successors. Let us call them, let say A, B,
C, D, E, F then remove seen will remove some
of them, let say this one and this one. So,
we are left with B D and F; then I want to
call
some function, which will essentially give
me this list of
B N, D N, F N. So, it should
give me a list of three elements, in this
example, of the three successors, already
converted into node pair form. So, I can just
take this and upend it too, open list
essentially.
So, my algorithm is still very similar, open
is a list, I extract some element, from the
list,
which is a node pair, from the node pair I
extract the first element, which is the current
node I am interested. Apply the goal test
to that, if it works or if it returns to then
I call
the reconstruct path function, with that node
pair and it will give me the path. If he does
not work, I generate successors of that element
N, node N to move anything that I have
seen or I have put on open already.
And construct node pairs from so the successors
of N or B D and F, so I want B N, D N
and F N. So, these are the B D and F are the
successors, but I want to construct the I
will
.want to remember that N is a parental B;
N is a parental D; N is a parental F. And
I will
add this to open, and the same cycle will
continue. So, that is a algorithm that we
have
written, so the only thing that is remains
is, when he said pick some node from open,
let
us pin that down as well.
.
And we will do the following node pair, I
call it node pair as a variable name, I will
always pick the first node from open, open
is the lists now, and the simplest thing to
do
with the list is to remove the head element.
So, I will just say I will remove the head
element. And so, what will this give it, this
give me a node pair, I will extract the first
element from that, and do all this goal tests
and everything is to that. So, one thing I
have
pin down is, that we will always take the
first element from the open list.
Open is now a list essentially, what should
be the first element of the list that is the
next
question, that will really now determine the
behavior of our search algorithm. So, there
are two possibilities, so somewhere down this
line, I will have open
as the following
thing append. So, I want to append two lists,
what are the two lists, one is the old open
minus the note pad that we have removed. And
the second is, the new elements that we
have generated by this process, this list
that we have, I have to append this two lists
to
found the new open.
.Again I can append them in one order or the
other order, and that is really going to this
side matter. So, let us choose one order first,
which says that append new. So, this list,
number this is the list of node pairs, I am
calling new, and this I went to a generate
this
new, when I have inspecting the state, found
that it is not the goal state generated it
is
successors calling the move gen function,
moved duplicates from there, made pairs and
call this a new, so this is new. So, it is
in the form which can be added to open, so
that is
new, and I will just use rest, all you can
use, tail assuming a not removed in that step
from open, because this only which return
the head, here I will take the tail of open.
So now, I have a completely deterministic
algorithm, there is no .
statements about pick some node or add this
node to open and so on. We have specified
everything completely; we have said that the
new nodes will come at the head of the
open list, which means they will be inspected
first. And I will always pick the head of
the
open list. So, we want to now, look at these
two options that we had, what is the other
option? Other option was the opposite, was
to change the order. So, I have to choose
between this, either this or this, which option
is better. Now, what do we get from what
rather how to be analyses choice, so this
is the choice that we have to make in our
algorithm, should be up should be put new
at the head of the list.
And keep the old elements behind or should
we keep the whole elements first, and put
this in the . So, you would have recognize
this two data structures,
that we have kind of simulating here, this
is the queue and this is a stake, this like
a
stake. So, we can maintain open is there as
a queue or as a stake, what is the repucation
of these two choices, is what we want to,
inspect next. So, let us take this option
first,
where we are looking at the new nodes first,
so newest nodes first, what does that
meaning in terms of the search trees that
we were talking about.
..
Let us draw the search tree. So, when I draw
the search tree, I will not draw the node
pairs and everything, all let us any you can
draw it does not matter. So, let say S nil
and
A S, B S, C S in some graph now this is an
ordered, this I am depending on the order
and
which may move gen function gives me this
A B and C, they will go in some particular
order that is not worry about that. So, I
always choose the left most first, so I think
this
and add let us call it D A, so the next one
will be this one and so on.
You can see what is happening, this algorithm
in which open is treated like a stake, as
this greedy like behavior, in the sense that,
the latest nodes that have been generated
are
explode first. So, these are old, so these
are the latest, out of them one we have chosen
randomly, and officially without loss of generality
we always chosen the left one, it does
not matter really. Because they were generated
where move gen function, and we have
not specified them order there essentially.
So, we officially a chosen the left most,
these
are the newest; these are little older; these
are the oldest.
The algorithm always picks the newest node
first. In terms of the search space the states
space, what is this algorithm doing? It will
take go from the start node, it will generate
some successors, it will choose one, it will
generate the successors, it will go there
and so
on. It will dive into the states space, you
know headlong without looking left or right.
.Till of course, it heads a dead end, what
do you mean by dead end here? When there are
no new successors along this path essentially.
In which case, for example here, if this
was to be a dead end, that they were no successors
of this G.
Then automatically this would be inspected
next, because that is that would be next in
line and open, if this was also a dead end,
then automatically this would be inspecting
next essentially. And if this for a dead end
then automatically this would be ((Refer
Time.). So, the you can see the path going
like this, and like this, and like this,
and like this, it dives into the search piece,
there is a danger of course, that if the state
space is infinite. If I say you know, find
me two numbers or three numbers, whose
powered to three A is to three plus B is to
three is equal to C is to three.
You will just try generating newer and newer
combinations, and you will keep diving
into thus search pairs. So, if the states,
search space is infinite, there is the danger
that
this algorithm will get lost essentially.
If we look at this search tree, we can also
called it
as the deepest
node first, going down this direction of all
the open list, who was the
candidates in open all these single circle
nodes, this is in open; this is in open; this
is in
open; this is in open, these two I will open.
It always picks that deepest node first
essentially.
.
.So, you should not be surprised at this algorithm
is called depth first search, this
algorithm .
as oppose to that. The other choice we had,
was to
maintain open as a queue, and as you can imagine,
what will happen with a queue is that.
.
I will write the order here, this is one first
node to be inspected; always the start node
is
the first node to be inspected. This will
be the second one, they will be generated,
but
now it is a queue, which means these two will
go behind these two. So, this should be the
third node; this should be the forth node;
then this would be the fifth node; and this
would be the sixth node; then this would be
the seventh node; the eighth from would be
this child here; then nineth . child and so
on.
It has a exactly the opposite effect, depth
first search dives into the state space, this
algorithm chooses the shallowest nodes first.
Even a choice of nodes, in this search tree,
it always pick the one which is closest to
the start node essentially. And you know the
name for this algorithm, breadth first search,
breadth first in the sense, first this layer
completely; then the second layer completely;
then the third layer completely and so on
and so forth. In terms of the states space,
what is this algorithm is doing, it will come
here; then it will go here; then it will go
here and here and here, in this particular
order, it
will clever the states space.
.Now, notice that both these algorithms are
totally oblivious of the goal state, goal
state is
somewhere here, they do not cares, only place
where the goals set plays a role, is in a
goal test function. If you have reach the
goal state, we has the algorithm can consume
whether you reached or not, but given the
set of choices, it has no sense of direction
that.
I should go in this direction or I should
choose this successors, that will come to,
when
you look at heuristic searches, but these
two algorithms are blind. So, we call them
blind
search algorithms or uninformed search algorithms.
One of the . to stick as close to the sources
possible, the other has
opposite tendency a going as far away as possible
is essentially. So, let us do a
comparison of these two algorithms, that depth
first search and breadth first search. So,
I
can remove this, what are the parameters on
which we should compare? We will look at
four criteria, what is the most common criteria
for comparing algorithms.
.
So, D F S verses B F S, the most commonly
use criteria is time complexity. So, let us
assume the simple search piece. So, let us
take the N queens problem, in the N queens
problem, let say that the way that you will
proceed is, you will place the first queen,
let
say in the first row, then the second queen
in the second row and so on, up to the n th
queen essentially. So, the search space would
be, end steps the solution will always be
.end steps along.
And the branching factor is constant. So,
if we have a search tree like this, why do
I
provide like this, because the number of nodes
are going to increase exponentially. So, if
I branching factor is five let us say, I will
have 1 node at this first level; 5 nodes at
the
second level; 25 nodes at the third; they
will for second level whatever you want to
. 125 in this level and so on. It is going
to multiply by the factor of
branching factor every time, and any and in
such situations where you multiply at a
every stage the think tense to go exponentially.
So, this is how search space nodes the search
trees looks like, so let us forget about that
five thing. So in general, we have given a
branching factor of b, and let say the solution
is a depth d. So, it is let us say is a d
queens problem, you place d queens and then
you
are done essentially. Let say for argument
sake that there is only one goal node, in
practice of course, for example, to the N
queens problem, there are many solutions.
So,
they would be many nodes which are the goal
states, let us assume that there is only one
goal node, in some problem which is similar
to N queens, what would be the time
complexity of depth first search.
So, before we do that, in the last layer,
there are b is should be d nodes, and all
the
internal layers nodes, how many are inside,
up to one layer less, up to one layer less,
how
many are the total internal nodes b is to
d minus 1 these are the internal nodes. Now,
the
first into observe, there is if we ignore
that minus 1, for large b and large d you
can
ignore that minus 1 on the top of site. So,
you can say this is roughly b is to d divided
by
b minus 1, even this minus 1 you can ignore
for large b, but let us we are not bother
about that. The first thing to observe, is
that is d th layer contains more nodes then
all the
previous layers combined.
So, this is the nature of exponential growth
that every time you go one level, further
away. The amount of work which do a that level,
and by amount of work will mean
inspecting that many number of nodes, is greater
than all the work that I have done
before that essentially, that is a feature
we will use. I think it will have to be in
the next
class, but we will see that. Now, what is
the time complexity of this, so will next
some
.simplifying assumptions that the goal not
can be anywhere from here to here. So, in
the
case of depth first search, if it is here,
it will just inspected after d plus 1 inspections.
So, let us say d plus 1, plus seeing the entire
list, which is the entire tree, the ((Refer
Time.) it and let say divided by 2 search
some . proximation
essentially, which if you work out, will turn
out to be roughly b is to d essentially, of
the
order of b is to d, of b is to d by 2 essentially.
For this one, either it has to inspect the
entire sub tree, up to this point, see noticed
that depth first search, were it finds a left
most goal, it just only inspect these nodes,
just goals on this path and finds a goal node.
So, it only inspects a d number of nodes on
the way, but when breadth first search comes
to this, it has to go through like this, and
like this and plot through this whole thing
one
slowly, slowly. It has to inspect the entire
sub internal sub tree, internal tree before
it
comes to this node, and for the right most
of course, both of them I inspect the entire
tree. But surprisingly, I will leave that
for you to work out, so this is the internal
tree plus
the full tree and on the divided by two average,
and then you can makes simplifying
assumptions, assuming that b and d are large.
So, you can simplifying the expression, but
the time complexity for B F S divided by the
time complexity of D F S, after we make the
simplifying assumptions is roughly b plus
divided by D. Death first search takes a little
bit more time, but not significantly much
more, you b is large for example, if b is
10, then it is 11 by ten times essentially.
So, if
not too much, it is kind of equals in some
way, for both of them, as for as time
complexity goes, what are the other factors
we can compare them on, completeness
and
what do we mean by completeness, the question
we asking is.
If there is the solution, which means, if
there is the path from the start state to
the goal
state, thus algorithm always fine it, if it
is, if he does than will see the algorithm
is
complete. Now, breath first search is; obviously,
going to be complete, because as you
can see, is going to go slowly in circles
and if there is the path, knew little find
it,
whatever death first search, if the search
face going to be infinite, which means this
boundary was not there, and even number theoretic
problems are an example of that,
then it will just go of in some direction.
And the goal may be here, it may just go of
some
.directions and the danger always exists essentially.
So, completeness for death first
searches, if the search pair is infinite,
it is not completely you can get lost.
Breath first search will still find the solution,
because it is not going to go off in any
direction, it is going to just gradually expand
it is, sort of set of nodes it has inspected,
till
it eventually it will hit this, and then it
will find the solution. So, breath first search
will
become will work, even for infinite graph.
For finite graphs, both are complete, because
eventually both will inspect all part essentially.
So, completeness, breath fast search is a
slight advantage that if the graph is infinite,
it will still weak complete essentially.
Quality of solution, the only . we can talk
of at this movement is the
number of the length of the path or number
of nodes in the solution path essentially.
And
we assumed that shorter paths are better,
what do you think about these two algorithms?
In terms of quality, is any of these algorithms
guarantee to give you an optimal solution,
you should speak a little bit louder.
. .
B F S now we have to say, what do you mean
a might . even B F S
might give up to essentially. It depends on
the order and which you done it moves
essentially. Let us take a graph start A,
B, C, D, let say we take a graph like this,
you
have to go from S to G, what will and let
us assumed that, the particular order and
we
choose the left most on the board first, what
will depth first search to, it will go from
S to
C, C to D, D to F, F to G. And let it will
say I found the path, but the path I could
have
found this one, what we breath first search
do, it will go from H to C; then it will go
to B;
then it will go to A; then it will go to D;
then it will go to E; then it will go to G.
G would be generated as the child of B, and
you should work this out as an example
yourself. And the parent of G would be B,
and the parent of B would be C, breath first
search will always find the shortest path.
So, I want to you to change this example and
un
simulated, to see that depth first search
and breath first search. Depth first search
always
guarantees . in terms of this you can see,
there is gradually moving
away from the source, and when it hits the
goal, it will always find the shortest path
to
.the goal. But, we have to sort of reason,
it out to a little bit, quality of solution
B F S
scores high heavily, it always current is
a shortest path essentially.
Let us look at the last criteria, which is
size of open, now we can see that, this time
complexity the way we are measuring it is
in some sense, measure of the size of closed,
because the number of nodes that you have
seen, will be the size of closed essentially.
And we are assuming, for the timing that it
takes you constant time to inspect get nodes
out of close, and all that kinds of that.
So, it is roughly call response the size of
closed,
what about the size of open, what is the length,
what is the size of the open for the breath
first search first. So, we have to visualize
what the algorithm is doing.
.
This is my search space and for breath first
search, what with the open list look like,
open would, so you will inspect this; inspect
this; inspect this and so on. So, let say
this
is, let say this is a closed list, we have
inspected so far. So, open would be all these
nodes, and all these nodes here, which are
the children of these nodes essentially. This
is
the open would list look for, depth first
search, and what is the size, how is it growing
in
terms of depth, it is growing, remember that,
then b is to d nodes here and b is to d plus
if you want to say. So, it has got some from
b is to d know and some from b is to d plus
row.
.In general it is growing exponential with
depth the deeper you go, the size of open
explodes, it becomes exponentially . what
about depth first search,
depth first search would come here. So, let
us let we draw separate this thing here, let
us
say it is three children here, this is gone
into closed; this is gone into closed and
so on,
what is happening with depth first search?
As I go deeper into the search piece, it is
going linearly, how is it going linearly,
because as I go deeper, I am adding a constant
number of nodes to open. I am adding basically
two extra nodes, at this level they were 3
plus 1 I am going to inspect, so this thing
then two extra here; two extra here; two extra
here.
In breath first search, I am multiplying by
a branching factor every time that is it is
why
growing exponentially. So, you should satisfy
yourself that the size of open, for depth
first search is b minus 1 into d plus 1, because
that every level I am going to keep b
minus 1 nodes into I am going to add b minus
1 nodes into open, one nodes I will inspect
this thing. So, b minus 1 that d plus one
extra node, because at the last layer, I will
have
one extra node essentially, so size of open
D F S means hands down, grows only linearly
as oppose to breadth first search for which
open grows exponentially.
So, we have seen this two algorithms, for
finite graphs, goals are complete, goals are
roughly the same time complexity, but one
of them wins on the quality of the solution,
which may be important. If you have planning,
let us say trips from here to the moon or
to mars, then thus smaller number of trips
is going to save your lot of money. Let us
say
from here to Bangalore the same thing, almost
the same thing, quality of solution,
breadth first search guarantee is you an optimal
solution. And you must have survey this
in other context, open requires only linear
space for, I mean depth first search requires
only linear space problem and that is a big,
big plus.
Time complexity is bad, we will addressed
that using heuristic methods, try to force
a
search to go towards the goal as we have seen.
This one is the .
close to home, this one is going off in some
random direction; know none of there is sort
of looking towards the goals essentially.
We will see that, then the complete heuristic
search, but even a blind search algorithm
or in from search, can I combine, can I device
an algorithm, which will combined these two
plus points of this, guarantee that it is
an
.optimal solution, yet require linear space
for open.
So, I will leave this as a small thinking
exercise for you, when we meet next on
Wednesday, we will look at an algorithm, which
does this. So, it should be nice, if one of
you can think of it without reading it from
somewhere else. After we discuss it here,
you
can go and read it out, but there is an nice
algorithm, which will combine these two
things, and it is a blind algorithm, so see
you on Wednesday.
.