With our objective of escaping local maxima
or local optima. So, remember our
algorithm for hill climbing
and
it basically says that, if c is a current
node
and if n is a
next node, whether you should move from a
node to a next node. And algorithm
essentially says that, if the best node that
you get from move gen of c, which is basically
in. So, you look at all the neighborhood of
c, c is a current node and take the best
amongst them, max or min value depending on
what you are doing. And if that is better
than c then you basically move to c and you
put this in a loop essentially.
So, it basically looks at the neighborhood
and so keeps this at problem in mind, all
the T
S C problem in mind, where we are looking
at a candidate solution and the neighboring
candidates solutions essentially. Now, what
was happening with this algorithm is that,
it
along some let us say one dimensional problem,
you would end up here and stop here,
because all neighbors are worse in this and
when in practices real optimum may be here
or some were else bit further away essentially.
.So, what do you want to now, look at this
is, how do we explore this space more? So,
that we do not get stuck at a local optima,
in this case a local maxima essentially. So,
what hill climbing does is exploitation
of the gradient, it basically follows the
gradient. If
there is a neighbor which is better, it goes
to that, otherwise, it gets stuck.
.
What explores, what this escape requires is
the ability for exploration. So, the simplest,
so first let us look at the deterministic
algorithm, which will allow us to explore
more of
the space and what do you mean by explores,
that we are allowed to go against the
heuristic function. It does not means that
you can only go to better states; you can
go to
states which are not necessarily better. So,
of course then we have to work out the
termination criteria and things like that.
..
So, let us look at the variation of this algorithm,
which says that n, we get the best as
before, but we will introduce another feature,
which is allowable or allowed
and we just
simply put this in the loop. So, we are not
checking whether it is better or not. Here,
we
have that condition, if the best neighbor
is better than c, then you move from n to
c.
Here, we are simply saying just move to the
best neighbor, but not just a best neighbor,
but something called allowed essentially,
which we will look at now essentially.
So, before we come to what is allowed means,
it basically means that, you can move to
the best neighbor, which means that, even
if you are at maxima, you can go to a
neighbor, which is not better than that essentially.
So, that is the key first thing that you
must remember essentially. Now, supposing
we wanted to allow this, that always go to
the best neighbor, which the criteria that
you it does not have to be better than the
current
node.
Then how do we stop, that is one small problem,
but there is a bigger problem and the
bigger problem pertains the fact, that if
I am stuck at this local maxima, how do I
get to
that maxima essentially. So, the first problem
of how do we stop, we will say that put
some other termination criteria. So, tell
some, it can be simply time based or it can
be
simply is that we are not finding a better
solution after a certain amount of time and
so
on. You can always store the best.
.So, looking at in general in optimization
terms, that in this process always keep track
of
the best solution that you have found ever,
even if you have moved away from it,
remember that, that was the best solution.
So, always keep track of the best solution,
so
that you can always do. Given that, we are
now exploring the states place and this
algorithm says that for example, in this case,
in a one dimensional word, they are two
neighbors here and here. So, I am allowed
to move to one of them essentially.
In a larger space of course, there are many
neighbors, so you can move to the best
amongst them essentially, but to illustrate
the point, illustrate the difficulty that
this
algorithm has supposing I am allowed to, so
I came from here to here. Then I am allowed
to move here that is allowed, because I am
no longer saying that, it should be better
than
what I am in, what will happen in the next
step. Next step, this will have these two
neighbors, this one and this one, what will
the algorithm do?
..
No, that we, that is the independent thing,
we just now talking about the behavior of
the
algorithm, where will it go next.
..
Unfortunately, it will go back to this place,
even if it takes one step down, but this one
say that, still that best criteria is still
there, go to the best neighbor, so that one
is still the
best neighbor essentially. So, it will go
back there, how do we get along this that
is
where this allowed thing is coming in. So,
remember we had this idea for a close list,
when we started doing the states space search
and what close list said that, do not go
back to the same node again that you have
seen, so what we could do.
So, we are looking at this now, one way to
do this is to maintain a circular list, maintain
a circular cube of some finite size. So, you
know what is a circular cube, that you keep
overwriting as you go round and round the
circle you allow to overwrite, but some k
number of elements will always be stored in
the cube, where you can you are allowed to
overwrite. So, it is, this is like a short
term memory. It is saying that these are the
last k
nodes that I went to and I am not allowed
to go back to them, but I can I am allowed
to
go back to any other neighbor.
..
So, what with this allowed factor, what we
are really doing is that, given a node c that
we
start with, we generate all the successors,
all the neighbors, from this neighbor we
disallow some. So, we say this move is not
allowed, this move is not allowed and this
move is not allowed. So, this is that allowed
thing that we are trying to do here, but from
the remaining move to the best one. Another
way of doing, this is the following that keep
track of what moves you made in the recent
past essentially. So, for example if you are
doing S A T and let us say for simplicity
sake that, you are changing only one bit at
the
time.
So, essentially move says that k in the highest
bit where I could be any bit essentially.
If
a bit is changed in the last t moves then
disallow it. Notice that, this is slightly
different
from maintaining a closed queue. In a close
list, we are maintaining our candidates and
saying we will not generate the same candidate
again. In this example, we are saying
that, if we are change, let us say the fifth
bit now, then for the next t moves, I am not
allowed to change that fifth bit essentially.
So, what will happen, I can maintain for
example, a memory and array called M, which
will start with 0 for everything that is one
way of doing it.
Let us say, I have a 9 bit problem, 9 bit
S A T. So, how many does this have 3, 4, 7
let
me add 2 more, I have a 9 bit S A T like this.
I can change any one of those 9 bits and
move to the best amongst them. Now, supposing
I have change the fourth bit that is the
.best, that I am allowing to do. So, what
am I doing, I have a valuation function for
every
node or every candidate solution, I have a
valuation function and we said that for S
A T,
it could be the number of clauses satisfied
or something like that essentially. So, I
have a
valuation function and I generate all this
neighbors and just move to the best amongst
them, does not matter, whether it is better
or not, but I am allowed to move to the best
amongst them.
So, if I change this, now let us say, so this
t is called the tabu tenure and this algorithm
is
actually called tabu search. So, this particular
spelling of tabu I mean, we are more use to
taboo t a b o o, but it the meaning is still
the same. This comes from some I think Fiji
Island or Tonga or somewhere, where they use
this spelling of the word. And basically,
it
means disallowed essentially, it is a taboo
move that you, you are not allowed to make
that moves essentially. So, if I am allowed
to, if I decide on tabu tenure of t, let us
say in
this example, let say 3 or something or 4
or something.
.
Then if I have changed this one, I could say
that make this 4, everything else remains
0.
So, this is like an array, which tells me
whether I am allowed to change that bit or
not, if
that value is non zero, I am not allowed to
change only. If the value is 0, I am allowed
to
change. So, after the first move I am allowed
not allowed to change the fourth bit, but
I
am allowed to change any other bit. After
the second move, this 4 will come down to
.automatically and some other bit. Supposing,
I change this bit, this will become 4
everything else will remain the same.
So, you understand what I am saying that,
this is that t equal to 1, this is t equal
to 2, then
t equal to 3 not this t, we will use a term
t t, which is a kind of a more standard term.
So,
t t stands for tabu tenure. So, my tabu tenure
is 4 then and that is time, this t is time,
the
first cycle, the second cycle, the third cycle.
Then in this next cycle, this will become
2,
this will become 3 and some other bit will
become 4 and eventually, this will become
and then become 0, which is when I am allowed
to change it essentially.
So, this will go to 2 meanwhile, this will
go to 3 and so on. So, after having change
this
here, then for 1, 2, 3, 4 cycles I am not
allowed to change it, but now it, the value
is
become 0 I am allowed to change it essentially.
There is just one way of implementing
this, you can insert simply for every bit
keep a time stamp of when it was last changed
and do an explicit comparison with that, and
decide whether you know, the current time
is more than four units from that time when
it was changed, you could do it in either
ways actually. But, this is the kind of a
standard way of doing this essentially.
So, for S A T you could maintain and array
which traditionally we called it M, which
stands for memory, for T S P we could maintain
a triangular matrix. So, this is 1 to 9 and
this is 1 to 9 for example, if it is a nine
city problem and you could keep track of which
edge that, remember that every square in this
will correspond to an edge. So, let us say
the seventh and the four, so the edge between
7 and 4 that I have removed that or
something like that. So, I can keep track
of that in a T S P like problem as well
essentially.
So, basic idea in tabu search is to have this
notion that you do not allow moves we are
made recently. So, that you do not go back
to the same local maxima from which you are
trying to escape that is the basic motivation,
do not go back to the same maximum that
would. Now, obviously if you look at this
way of doing tabu search that you are
controlling which bits to change, then given
any two bits. So, for example, I start with
let
us say bits, two bits which are 1 1 to start
with and then this gets changed to 0 1
essentially.
So, that means, I have changed the first bit
and this is some substring here, I have
changed this bit, I am not allowed to change
it for four units. Then after this let us
say I
.change this other one, 0 1 0, 0 0, I change
the other bit as well. So, if I made this
two
bits, where I change this bit, this substring
has become 0 1, then I change the other bit,
this is become 0 0, I have lost the ability
to move to one combination which is the 1
combination, because of this tabu, that I
am doing that I am not allowed to change either
of this two bits for the next four rounds.
I cannot change this to 1 0 that will not
be allowed essentially. So, I am moving I
might
lose out on something, but in general, experimentally
it has been found that, this tabu
search works well with these kinds of problem
essentially, right. So, we just observe that,
you cannot move to this 1 0 from here essentially,
what if that 1 0 really happen to be the
solution or something like that. So, actually
the more detail tabu, I will search algorithm
allows you to make an exception to this barring
of certain moves essentially.
.
And the exception can be made and then what
is called as an aspiration criteria, which
confusion sometimes I get into spelling. So,
the expression criteria’s says that, if
all
allowed neighbors are bad. So, I will just
write all are bad by bad we means worse than
current
and a tabu move leads to in which is better
than best, then allow the move. So,
obviously our goal is to optimize the valuation
function or the objective function of that
we are working on and if we are getting access
to a good move then we should not lose
it.
.So, this aspiration criteria says that, if
all this allowed neighbors, the once which
are not
crossed out are worse than my current node
c. And if one of those barred neighbors, a
one of the tabu neighbors is better than the
best, by best I mean this thing that you store
the best solution that you have found, if
I can find the node, which is better than
this also,
than you allow that exception. So, tabu in
general, recent moves are tabu, but we can
make an exception, if one of them in a bad
situation, when the other moves are bad,
gives us a much better solution.
So, for example, if let us say value of this
node is 27 according to some, let us say I
have
a 50 clause S A T to solve and this know this
satisfying 27 out of those 50 clauses and
all
these nodes, which are disallowed or less
than 27. And if these one of them happens
to
be let us say 40, somehow and the best that
I have seen is only 35 or something like that.
Then I will allow this move and that is an
aspiration criteria. So, again you can see
that
somehow this design of such algorithms is
kind of you know little bit of an art, you
are
trying to device algorithm, which will work
which will give you good solutions and so
on.
And what tabu search does is that, it basically
gives you a deterministic mechanism to
say that you can go past, local maxima and
explore the state further essentially. So,
it
does this by having this tabu tenure, which
says that for a certain period of time do
not
make the same move again essentially.
.
.Another feature which has sometimes been
used is called the frequency based method.
So, I have a frequency table, so all these
line bits. So, let us say this was changed
times, this was changed 7 times, in 6 times
and so on essentially, how many times did
I
change that bit essentially? So, I can also
bios the algorithm towards moves, which have
been made less often essentially. So, for
example, if somewhere here, there is a bit
which
has been change only twice in my whole this
thing and everything else is large number
of times.
Then I may want to say that try and change
this bit and see, if something good comes
out
of it. Remember that, what these numbers are,
these are the frequency of how many
times you have changes that bit essentially.
This is simply like a counter, which tells
you
whether you are allowed to change that bit
or not. If you want to bios a algorithm,
opposite towards those areas which the heuristic
function is not taking it to, why did you
not move this bit, because whenever this bit
was generated, it is the noted generated was
not the best amongst the neighbors and so,
it never got changed essentially.
So, if you want to push the search into that
direction, you can bios the tabu algorithm
by
sayings that modify your valuation function.
So, eval of n, let us call it eval prime of
n is
eval of n, which is the function that we are
using to compute the heuristic function that
we were calling, but the out, but we are calling
it evaluation function. Because it
optimization community calls with an eval
function minus some constant times
frequency of n, this is not very good notation,
because n is really known and here it is a
bit that is being saying the index of the
bit.
So, let me just call it frequency of b n,
the bit which makes leads you to this n th
essentially. So, as long as it is clear, we
will use some notation here. So, essentially
what
it is saying is that, you are your moving
from c, you are considering this move from
c to
n, from a node c to node n, when you are evaluating
this node n, take into account. How
frequently this particular move has been made,
which means which bit has been changes
and give a penalty for those bits, which have
been change very often.
So, if the frequency is very high, the valuation
value for the resulting node will be
decrease more, if the frequency is less than
this. So, this is like a penalty, in our case
it is
penalty for changing a bit too often, if you
are changing that bit all the time then this
valuation function kind of penalize it and
says that, no, no you have changed this bit
too
.many times. I will reduce evaluation values
to by this amount essentially. So, in the
end
of course, you can have this basic vanilla
tabu search than you can add the aspiration
criteria to say that, sometimes you do not
make moves tabu.
And then you can have general increasing bios
towards newer areas by saying that more
frequent moves will be penalized essentially.
So, this was the deterministic approach to
trying to escape local maxima. So, let us
move towards stochastic methods or
randomized methods. So, what we have seen
so far is the deterministic approach to
escaping from local maxima.
.
Let us look at stochastic or randomized method.
So, we will look at couple of them, we
will start with some very simple thing today.
So, the focus is still on exploration, how
can we make the search go onto newer areas?
So, you must keep in mind this two aspects
of search, one is exploitation of the gradient,
which is, what hill climbing does very
interesting, that it just looks at the neighborhood
and goes to the best neighbor. What
tabu searched it was that it modify that little
bit and allowed it to go to the best neighbor
even if it was not better than that.
Exploration simply says that somehow you must
allow the algorithm to go into different
areas. And what stochastic or randomize method
say is that give some degree of
randomness to the movement. So, just imagine
this earth, the algorithm searching
through this earth space and exploitation
simple says that the just follow the gradient
and
.now we are saying do not always follow the
gradient, but do something different at
sometime essentially. Now, the extreme example
of randomized movement is a random
walk.
And random walk, we can simply write as saying
generate n is a random neighbor
of c
and put this in a loop. So, a random walk
basically just takes says that, just take
one step
in some direction essentially. Of course,
we can add on other stuff to this algorithm
saying like keep track of the best node that
you have seen so far and that kind of thing,
but otherwise it is purely random essentially.
From a given node c, it will just randomly
choose one neighbor and go to that essentially,
no comparison of evaluation function
nothing essentially. But, of course you can
keep track of the best one and so far and
so
far essentially.
Now, obviously a random walk is not going
to be a great way for solving an optimization
problem, because first of all, it is not even
systematic, remember that we started out by
saying that some searches are complete or
systematic, which means that they explores
the entire space. Hill climbing, tabu search
they are not systematic, they do not guarantee
that they will explore the entire space and
this is an extreme example, it just go of
in
some random direction essentially. So, what
we really need to find is ways which are
somewhere between hill climbing, hill climbing
is an extreme of exploitation and
random walk is an extreme of exploration.
So, it is there is 0 exploitation in that,
only exploration whereas here, in hill climbing
there is 0 exploration, in a sense that it
never waivers from the path that has been
shown
to it and there is complete exploitation.
We want algorithms, which will be somewhere
in
between essentially. So, today I will just
give you the intuition of the algorithm that
we
have going to study and in the next class,
we will look at it in more detail. The basic
idea
is make a random move with a probability,
which is proportional to improvement
in eval
n.
So, what I was saying here, that first of
all I am talking about a random move. So,
I am
no longer saying that generate all the successors,
I am just saying make a random move
which means, you are at some given node c
and choose a random successor n, just
somehow generate one successor n. But, move
to that with a probability, which is
proportional to how better that move n is
from c, as compare to c, how better that
.candidate n is compare to c. So, the implication
of this is the following that, I am not
saying that n should be better than c.
I am only saying that, if n is better than
c then there is a greater probability of making
the
move, if n is worse than c, there is lesser
probability of making that move and secondly,
it depends on the magnitude. So, if I look
at this value, eval n minus eval c. So, let
us say
I am doing a maximization problem which means,
the more positive this is, the better for
me. I want to build an algorithm, which will
say that the more positive, this is the greater
should be the probability of making the move,
but allow a move even if this is negative,
just to include the exploration feature, but
with lesser probability.
So, I want to bios my search towards better
moves, but I do not want to stop it from
making bad moves, bad moves meaning moves
which decrease the evaluation function
values essentially, which go against the gradient
essentially. So, we will look at the
details in the next class, but let me ask
you one question at this moment, when I say
make a move with the probability. So, let
us say this probability is p and I gave you
a
value p, how will you make this move probably,
when you if you want to implement this
algorithm, how do you make a move probabilistically
in an algorithm that you are
writing
..
You
and
..
So, you generate a random number in the range
0 to 1 and if that number happens to be
greater than p, you make the move, if the
number happens to be less than p, you will
do
not make the move. So, eventually the move
is either made or is not made, but it is made
with a probability p and that, for that you
have to generate a random number. So, what
are we after we are after an algorithm, which
will have this stochastic play work, which
means that it will look at a neighbor and
may or may not make a move, but it should
be
bios towards better moves, but not barred
from making bad moves.
So, somehow I have to devise a way of computing
this p as the function of this
difference in the evaluation function, in
such a way that this behavior is manifested
.essentially. So, maybe I will ask you to
think about this and we will write it is not
a very
difficult thing to do. The only thing you
have to be careful is that, this being probability
it should come in the range 0 to 1 and it
should satisfy this criteria that the larger
this is.
So, if you want to plot this on x axis then
the more you go to the right hand side, the
probability should 10 to 1 and the more you
go to the left hand side, the probability
should 10 to 0 essentially. So, think about
a function which will do that and we will
specify it in the next class and the algorithm
which is based on that. So, we will stop
here.
.