So, you were looking at optimization. And
remember that we came to optimization from
state space search.
.
And the way with this was that, we looked
at the heuristic function. That was used in
best for search. And said that this, defines
at again over which we use an algorithm
called hill climbing, which is a local search
algorithm. As the first, a global algorithm
which best first search was, which means at
the algorithm looks only at it is
neighborhood. Immediate neighborhood in the
state, or in the solutions space and moves
to one of them especially.
And then, we saw that local search algorithms
can get stuck in local maxima, or local
minimize is the case may be. And so the theme
for our said this movement, is escaping
from those minima. That, how can we improve
upon hill climbing. So, what does hill
.climbing do? Hill climbing does, what we
will call as exploitation. And exploitation
of
the heuristic function essentially, that it
basically follows the heuristic function.
It looks in around it is neighborhood. And
wherever the heuristic function is getting,
a
maximum increase. Or in other words, in the
direction of the steepest gradient, it makes
one move. And then, repeats it process still
it cannot find the better neighbor. And in
escaping local maxima, we said that one of
the first algorithm that we looked at; or
in
fact, the only algorithm that we have seen
is variable neighborhood descent.
And what this algorithm did was that, it tried
out a variety of neighborhood functions.
So, for us the neighborhood functions is given
by the MoveGen function. And we also
said that, we are moving from state space
to solution space search, which means that
we
are perturbing candidate solutions to generate
new solutions. And we saw the example
with said, that you can flip 1 bit or you
can flip 2 bits or up to 2 bits or 3 bits
and so on.
You can generate a variety of neighborhood
functions. And what neighbor, variable
neighborhood descent is that when it get stuck,
it does a series of hill climbing's. And
when it get stuck, at a local maxima or at
a maxima it does not know, that is local or
not.
It increases the density of the neighborhood
function and tries hill climbing, all over
again essentially. So, we want to move, we
want to look at different other approaches
which will help us get around local maxima.
So, in the process when we are talking of
optimization, we will use the notion evaluation.
So, this is just particular to the optimization
community. So, but you must keep in mind
that, we are talking about the same function;
whether it is h of n or evolve of n. It is
basically a value that you get, for a given
candidate. And the task is to maximize, to
find
the candidate which has the maximum, this
value. So, when heuristic functions, if you
are thinking of heuristic as a distance, then
you want to find them.
State with the smallest distance, which is
the goal state or if you have pause it, like
within the block problem. That some heuristic
function, which has the maximum value at
the goal state, then you are maximizing essentially.
So, instead of calling it heuristic
function, we call it evolve function. But,
the process is still the same that, we all
want to
.find the note with the maximum value or the
minimum value, the case may be. So, today
let me introduce this. One of the most talked
about problems in computer science, which
is the tabling salesman problem.
.
I am sure, you are all familiar with it. So,
I will just write the acrolein here. TSP stands
for Travelling Salesman Problem. And it is
one of the simplest problems to state and
one
of the hardest problems to solve this easily.
So, a travelling salesman problem is
basically, the motivation is set to be to
help a travelling salesman, who has to visit
many
cities. Let us in one day or something like
that. And come to his home city. And do the
whole thing with some minimum cost, in some
manner essentially.
So, I suppose everyone is familiar with the
TSP problem. We will say that, we have city
1 to city n, n cities which we will also denote
by 1 to n. Just has a short hand. Easier to
refer to is essentially. So, there is n cities,
1 to n. And you have to go from one place
to
another essentially. one city to another,
without visiting the same cities twice. Now,
in
practice off course, in some problems it may
be necessary for you to visit the same city
twice essentially.
So, for example, if there is a small Ireland
near the coastline, to go you go to that Ireland
.from one city. Let us say Chennai for example.
And you come back to Chennai and then,
go somewhere else, essentially. But, we will
ignore all those problems. And we will
assume that, the classical problem of visiting
each city exactly once. Essentially is what
we want to solve. Now, in practice a city
network may not be completely connected.
In the sense that, if it is a road network,
you may have roads from some cities to other
cities and so on and so forth. But, not for
example a direct road from, let say here to
Nagpur or something like that. But, we have
indirect roads, in the sense. That may be,
you go from here to Vijayawada. And from Vijayawada,
you go Nagpur or something
like that. But, in general it has been found
that, it is easier to solve TSP when the graph,
underline graph is completely connected.
So, we will assume that, this is completely
connected. And we can always convert a nonconnected
graph to a completely connected graph. I adding
new edges. And making sure
those edges have very high weight. So, that
they never figure in the solution actually.
But, the solving process becomes easier. Now,
TSP occurs in many practical problem.
So, for example drilling circuit boards, if
you want to manufacture circuit boards then,
you have to drill many holes on that board.
And if you think of each hole as a city then,
you have to visit all these locations keep
drilling holes, essentially. So, we have something
like a TSP to solve them. And such
problems have something like thousands of.
So, it is not uncommon to have a problem
with eight thousand holes to be drilled and
think like that. And then, you can see that
the
complexity of the problems grows very quickly.
So, what is the number of tours that we
have. For, if you number of n cities, how
many tours can we have for the n cities.
So, we can have n factorial tours. And one
of the notations that we will use for tour
is,
something like this. So, for example, if you
have nine cities then, a tour could be
something like 2 7 1 6 4 3 8 5 9. So, list
city names or in this case city indexes or
city
numbers, gives you a candidate tour, essentially.
So, this is a tour says that, you started
cities 2 then, go to city 7, then go to city
1 then, go to city 6 and so on essentially.
We can represent a tour in this session. And
we can see that, we can honest choose the
.first number is n ways, the second one in
and so on. And that is, how we get that number
factorial n. But, many of these tours are
duplicates of each other. In particular, if
I rotate
this number, if you think of this is a number,
I start with 7 and 2 comes at this end. Then,
it is a same tour essentially. Because, remember
that in the travelling salesman problem,
you have to come back to the same cities.
So, after 9 we are going to come back with
2. So, I could started with 7 and return to
here. I could start with 1 and return 27 here
and that would be the same essentially. So,
you should device this way n, because there
are these n rotations that are possible. And
in the addition, if I write it in the reverse
order 9 5 8 3 4 6 1 7 2, then also we will
assume it is the same tour. So, we will assume
that the cost of going from city a to b is
the same as the cost of going from city b
to a.
So, you have to divide further by 2. So, you
have divide by 2 n. So, what we get is, n
minus 1 factorial divided by 2. So, this is
a number of distinct tours, which means say
no
2 tours are identical. Of course, in factors
it may not be easy to recognize the tours,
the
distinct tours. So, we can say that we have
about n factorial. The size of the space is
end
factorial, essentially. How bad is the factorial
function?
So, remember that we has said when we have
talking about sat, we had said that a 100
variable SAT problem has to raised to 100,
the size of the space is 2. So, 100 variable
SAT has 2 raised n, which we said was about
10 raised to 30. And we have in sought of
talking about this large numbers, and say
how big these numbers. We try to imagine how
big these numbers, really or essentially.
So, you must whenever you get time, look at
this
book call mathematical themes.
A mathematical theme, which is by I keep talking
about quite often. And one of the
articles in that book is or one of the chapters
in this book is, about how we cannot
distinguish between large numbers. So, we
cannot if I say 25 billion or if I say 25
million, they basically appears same to you
essentially. I mean in the sense, you do not
have a sense for large number. Essentially,
if I say that, it takes 10 is to 27 let say
seconds. And if I say it takes 10 to 29 seconds,
it sounds almost the same to us.
.But in fact, is of course, 10 is to 29 is
100 times 10 is to 27 and we sort of 10 to
lose
sense, of in essentially. So, we have seen
the 10 raised to 30, extremely large numbers.
And if you have to explore all of them, it
would be billions of years essentially. But,
variable TSP is about 10 raised to 157. So,
TSP is much, the factorial function is much
much much verse in terms of how fast it grows,
has compare to the explanation function.
So, the SAT problem is exponentially hard.
In fact, it known to be n p completes. It
for
the first problem, for that was shown to be
n p complete. TSP is verse an exponentially,
it is factorial and factorial tends to go
much much faster. And we can see that, the
variable TSP has about 10 is to 157 possible
different, possible to us. And that is the
number, that we cannot even began to imagine
essentially. So, as something to compare
with, we can say how many fundamental particles.
Let say as some level electrons for example,
are there in this entire universe. Does
anyone have an idea? How many particles are
there in the universe, at some level of
detail, essentially?
..
Yes. It is in similar, that somewhere 10 raise
to 75, 10 raise to 80 depending on what
level you looking at. So, the total number
of particles in the universe is about 10 raise
to
80. See each of them was a super computer,
examining billions of states per second. We
would still need billions and billions of
years. So, these are the very large numbers
that,
you have to tackle. And that is why, you cannot
even hope to solve this completely.
You cannot even hope to find them optimal
solutions for something like, TSP. And in
that sense, many people call TSP has the holy
grail of computer science that, how to find
good algorithms to solve TSP is a great motivator,
essentially. Now, one thing that we
have talking about so what is the problem?
The problem is that we have to find the tours,
the cost of the tour is minimal, essentially.
That is the problem essentially.
Now, the cost of course depends on the individual
distances between. So, distance city
distance from i to j, what kind of a function
are we using for distance function, much
.depends upon that as well. If we assume that,
the distance function is arbitrary then, of
course the problem is completely hard to solve
essentially. Then, we have to go back this
thing. But, sometimes the problems are not
so arbitrary. In the sense, distances are
not
necessarily arbitrarily.
So, one of course example is, simple example
is the Euclidean distance. So, if the
distance is the Euclidean distance. So, for
example, if you have manufacturing a circuit
board then, you can think of the distances
of the Euclidean distance. And then, at least
indubitably you can imagine that, you will
be able to find an optimal solution. So,
supposing it was the great, and you have to
drill many holes in the grid.
Then, you can at least hope to say that, I
will find a good solution, if not necessarily
an
optimal solutions. Now, in terms of that for,
so Euclidean distance we will call it as
Euclidean TSP. If this is the Euclidean distance,
as the distance measure it turns out.
That if the problem is the Euclidean TSP then,
you can solve it in polynomial time, not
optimally but, the community calls approximate
solutions.
So, we can find approximate solutions, in
polynomial time and you can specify it, what
degree it is approximate. So, it is something
like 1 plus 1, 1 upon c or something like
that
times optimal cost. So, in polynomial time
you can find very good solutions and you can
put a bound on, how bad they can be essentially
apart. From Euclidean distance, we can
say that the distance should satisfy, what
we call as a triangular inequality
which is the
weaker condition.
Then, Euclidean distance also satisfies triangle
inequality. But, what triangle inequality
says that, if you want to imagine a triangle
between three cities. Then, the distance
between of the length of one side is smaller
than the sum of the lengths of the other two
sides. So, that is the, this is known as the
triangular inequality. And if the distance
function satisfies the triangular inequality
then, also it is relatively easier to solve.
Easier to solve meaning, you can find good
solutions faster. You cannot solve it
optimally, essentially. Then, we have something
call the geographic TSP. So, imagine
that you are one of those globe floating executives,
who flies from here to Delhi and
.from Delhi to Tehran and Tehran to Budapest
and so on and so far. Going all over the
world then, your domain is a spherical domain.
The earth is the sphere as we all know.
Now, at least and distance is do not necessarily,
we are not necessarily we cannot talk of
Euclidean distance.
So, we have to talk about distance on the
curved surface. So, that is the slightly different
problem. People have try to solve these kind
of problems. Now, interestingly you must
look up for this website, it is called TSP
LIB. So, I do not remember the address but,
you
must look up for TSP LIB website. It is a
website, maintained in one of the German
universities. And it is a collection of very
interesting TSP problems.
So, you know there is a problem of all European
cities. For example, and some circuit
board problems and things like that. And more
interestingly, it has got problems in which
somebody has taken the travel to find the
optimal solution. If you have a problem of
15000 cities for with the optimal solution
is known then, you can write some algorithm
that will be used to calculate them when it
exploring.
And compare your algorithm with one of those
with the actual optimal solution. So, this
has the optimal solutions. So, there are examples
big examples, which their optimal
solutions given. And so you could use that
as a benchmark, to see how good your
algorithm is essentially. And we probably
give you one exercise, along those lines
essentially. Some of those optimal solutions,
see the only way we can guarantee an
optimal solution and we will study optimal
solutions, sub it later.
Is to say that, I mean this sound like a circular
argument but, to say that there is no better
solution, which is possible essentially. And
if you then, guarantee that there is no better
solution then, you will have an optimal solution.
And it is taken them, if you look at
some of the references. For example, this
book . Something,
like thousands of computing years of computing
time.
So, as they are many machines working in parallel.
And then, they compute this
exhaustibly anumulating all TSP and finding
optimal solutions. So, you must go and look
at this site, which will give you optimal
solutions essentially. So, today let us spent
a
.little bit of time. So, I am brought TSP
here, because one of the things you want to
do is
look at this variable neighborhood descent
again.
From and see how TSP can be solved using this
essentially. So, basically the idea being
that, what are the different neighborhood
functions that we can construct? But, before
we
come to that, so remember that we had said
that, there are two ways of solving problems.
.
One is constructive and the other is perturbative.
So, in constructive method we construct
a solution, bit by bit. And that is the whole
state space search that we started with. In
perturbative methods, we take a candidate
solution and perturbative to look at another
candidate solution. So, we did this for SAT.
For example, we said that any bits string
is a
candidate solution. Then, you can change some
number of bits, which is the perturbation
you have doing.
And look at another solution but, it also
constructs a solution edge by edge, if you
want
to say. So, let us first look at some algorithm.
So, constructive solving the TSP with
constructive methods and then, we will come
to Perturbative methods in which case. We
will look at variable neighborhood descent.
And whatever other algorithm, that we are
going to look at after that. So, for example
given a set of cities. So, let us assume that
we
.have working in this Euclidean space.
So, there are actual distance is the distance,
what kind of algorithm can you think of. You
must have tried something some time. So, let
simplest constructive method is to start.
Try to stimulate what you would do, if you
are doing this in the real world, so to speak.
So, you start the some city, let say this
one. And then, look at it is neighborhood.
Now,
remember this entire set is a neighborhood
because, assume that our graph is completely
connected it, essentially in this case.
But, when we come to perturbative methods,
we will look at smaller neighborhoods
where you know, all those in this the neighborhood
is different. In sense that, it is not a
candidate solution but, it is a neighboring
city. So, you will go to the city which is
nearest to you it. So, let us say you go from
here to here. And then, you repeat this
process. You go to the nearest city, you go
from here to here, when you go I mean, it
looks like this is the nearest and you will
get some solution and solve.
So, this is one simple heuristic algorithm.
It is a greedy algorithm. It says, started
some
city and go to the nearest neighbor. Then,
from there go to the nearest neighbor and
so on
and so far, essentially. Now, obviously in
some situations it will give you a very good
solution, if not the optimal solution. But,
you can imagine that what will happen with
situations, where I have a city somewhere
here. If I have a city somewhere there, what
will my algorithm do, ideally what should
it do?
It should go from here to that and come back
here and then resume its thing. But, it will
not do that because, my algorithm says go
to nearest neighbor. So, I will go from here
to
then, I will go from here to here, go from
here to here then here, here, here to here,
here
to here. Then I will go there and then I will
come back here. So, obviously you can this
is
just to illustrate, that this algorithm will
not always give you a optimal solution.
But, it will give you depending on what kind
of problem it is, it will give you reasonably
a good solution, essentially. Now, a simple
variation to this is, that instead of thinking
going like this, you can think of extending
you towards. So, at the any given time you
have a partial toward it. So, let say we have
done only, till this much. And instead of
.saying that, this is a one directional thing
you can say that, you can think of it is going
in
both directions.
And then, you can say you can extend at either
end of the tour. Instead of saying that,
only extend that where you verse trying to
stimulate a physical person moving around.
You can say which ever end of the tour has
a closer city extend, that towards end. That
is
as a simple extension of that essentially.
So, I am now how do you talk about cities
like
this, which are far away from the rest essentially.
So, one algorithm, so I am not writing
these things but, any of you look at any text
book on TSP, they will talk about these
algorithm.
You could say that, I splice this. So, in
the science that supposing I have already
constructive this toward, which is not a very
good toward but, I have constructed this and
I only left with that city. Instead of going
from this place to this place but, I will
do is
that, I will find out which point in the tour
is closes to this city. And connects that
with
this and then break the stage and connect
this with this. So, this will give you some
improvement essentially.
So, that is but obviously, every time we do
that, the complexity increases. Because,
notice now that if you write a general algorithm
for that, you will say that for every new
point in the city, which is the closes point
in the tour. So, you have to inspect in the
whole toward. So, complexity will go by a
factor of n in that case. So, this is one
set of
constructive algorithms for solving the TSP.
Another popular thing, which is known a
greedy heuristic says that, you sort the edges.
Maintain a sorted set of edges and work with
edges instead of working with cities
essentially. So, you can now imagine what
the algorithm is. It says that, you have all
the
edges that are available to you in this thing.
So, pick the shortest edge that is available
to
you and add that. So, in this example for
example, it could be this one. So, this could
be
my first says that I add, because that is
the shortest edge. Then, the next shorted
could be
this one. Then, it could be this one and so
on and so far.
So, this is a different algorithm. It is shorting
the edges. So, you short them once and
.then pick the shortest edges. The hope is
that, you will pick all the small edges because,
for the optimal solution the more the number
of shorter edges, the more likely it is
optimal essentially. Obviously, when you are
doing this greedy heuristic, you have to be
careful that. You do not have a loop on the
way essentially.
So, if you have connect a some number of cities
and if the next shortest edge is forming a
shorter loop then, you should not take the
edges essentially. Used that one thing you
should know. Then, there is another heuristic,
call the savings heuristic. And all these
have you know, available in many books. The
savings heuristic says that, first construct
n minus 1 tours of length 2. So, let me illustrate
this with this example.
.
You take some arbitrary city and you construct
tours with every other city. So, I will just
take a smaller example. So, there is some
city and from there you constructing this.
So,
there are, in this example there are five
cities. So, I have constructed four tours
of length
two. And then, you merge to tours. So, how
can you merge two tours? So, for example,
I
can say that, I will merge this two let most
two tours. So, I will take this one from here.
I will take this one from here. And I will
delete this edge and I will delete this edge
and I
will add in a edge, here new edge. So, the
only question is which two tours should I
.merge and that is where the name comes from
savings heuristic. It says, select that pair
of tours in which you get the maximum savings.
What is the savings? That, your length
you had four edges in this to start with.
So, you add at the lengths. So, l 1 l 2 l
3 l 4 and
now after merging, you have l 1 l 4 and a
new one, that is call it l 5.
How much is the saving, how much is l 1 l
4 l 5 better than l 1 l 2 l 3 l 4. Choose
that
combination, which gives you the maximum savings
essentially. So, now that you have
merge these two. Then, you could merge this
larger tour, with this third one. For
example, so you could delete this edge and
add this edge. And add this one and so on
and
so far. We keep merging. So, in the n minus
2 merge operations you will finally, get the
tour essentially.
Again, it is heuristic algorithm. Not guarantee
to give you an optimal solution but, in
general all these algorithms give you a reasonably
good solution for Euclidean TSP, at
least essentially. So, let us now go to the
perturbative approach. What does perturbative
approach says? That it, you take some candidate
and generate it is neighborhood
essentially. The which is, kind of different
from this. Here you are constructing the tours
gradually.
Here you are saying, I have one tour given
to be and I am going to produce a set up
neighborhood tours and choose one of the essentially.
Exactly like, what we did in SAT.
I have a candidate solution. I will perturb
it by changing some number of bits, to get
new
solutions and move to that new solution. This
was like hill climbing like algorithm, we
are approaching now. In this, the question
is what are the neighborhood functions at
we
can talk about here.
Can we think of that? So, given that tour
for example, 2 7 1 6 4 3 8 5 9. How can I
generate a neighborhood around? What is the
property that a tour by satisfy? And if
basically should be a permutation of those
n numbers essentially. So, essentially you
want to generate some new permutations and
explore one of them essentially.
..
.Swapping adjacent numbers, would give you
a new tours. So, instead of saying this I,
so
I can pick two, any place and swap two numbers.
So, for example, I can replace 1 6 by 6
1, that is what you have saying. So, that
is one. So, you can imagine how many such
moves are possible. You can make n minus 1
swaps here. So, this will have n minus 1
neighbors essentially. So, either the first
two are the second two are the third like
in line
it.
So, you can journalize that to something which
we call as a 2 city exchange. And what
that says is that, take any two cities in
the tour and exchange their positions. So,
this is a
particular case of that, it says that take
two adjacent numbers and exchange that. This
is
the operator says, the take any two cities
and generate essentially. So, how many
neighbors will this have. I can take n c 2.
Two cities in n c 2 ways and for each way
that
I pick, there is only one neighbor I would
be generate because, I can only exchange their
positions essentially.
So, I will have n c 2 neighbors essentially.
Or I can have 3 city exchange, what this says
is that, takeout any three cities from the
tours. And put them back in some different
order
essentially. So, I can pick them in n c 3
ways and then I can put them back in 3 factorial
minus 1 because, 1 I do not want to put it
back in the same order. So, 3 factorial minus
order. So, I will generate that many these
things. So, what is this two city exchange
is
doing?
If I have a tour like this then, if I am going
to exchange this one
with this one for
example. Now, what it means is that, I was
going in this order. But, now I am going to
go, instead of this I am going to come here.
And from here, I am going to go there. So,
this will go away. Then, instead of coming
here I will go like this. If you must visualize
this, this what happening when I am exchanging
this city with this city.
Originally, it was a circular looking tour.
Now, because I will exchange the position
of
this two cities from here, I am going to go
here, from here I am going to go there. And
then, continue here. And then, this something
finger will have essentially. Now, it turns
out that city exchanges are not the best way
of thinking about things. But, edge
exchanges are end of the easier to think about
essentially.
.So, for example, I have two edge exchanges.
It says that, remove some two edges from
here tour and insert two new edges, instead
of that. So, let us this see, what this means?
Supposing, I have tour like this or let us
see I have I am just trying them in the circle
because, this easier to this in factors. Of
course, it is going to be sought of distributed
over some space. I mean cities are never arrange
in nice circle edges but, it is easier from
me essentially.
So, one of the thing that we would want to
do is that, you know this Euclidean TSP is
to
generate random problems, which means take
a two dimensional space. Let us say a
computers, monitors screen and randomly place
it there. And then, say find the optimal
tour for that essentially. Now, if I have
a tour like this. So, ideally if I have a
tour which
is something like this, you can see that I
have two very long edges in this tour essentially.
If I could somehow remove them and replace
them, into two shorter edges, keeping it as
a complete tour, I can transform this problem
in to another problem in which, instead of
these edge and instead of this edge, I add
this edge. I add this edge and I add this
edge.
So, whatever them, I have deleted two edges
from my tour. And replaced it with two
more edges and there is only one way I can
do that essentially.
If I delete any two edges, I have only one
new tour that I can create, in this example.
How will I do this, two city exchange? So,
let us say we have that tour. So, something
like that, 2 7 6 5. Supposing, I have representation
like this, how can I implement two
edge exchange? So, anyways, so it is not comes.
So, once you know the answer, it is
simple. Essentially, you take a sub slink
here and reverse the sub slink.
So, 2 7 4 5 6 1 3 9 8, so let us see whether
it is really doing, what we are saying it
is
doing. So, which other two edges that I have
removed here? The edge that I have
removed is 1 from 7 to 6 and 4 to 1. The other
edges remain the same because, from. So,
here instead of going from 7 to 6, I am going
from 7 to 4 and 4 is still connect to 5. So,
maybe I should draw this. This
is called as cities. So, I go from 2 to 7,
7 to 6, 6 to 5, 5 to
4, 4 to 1, 1 to 3, 3 to 9, 9 to 8 and 8 back
to 2.
That is the last step. This is the tour that
I started with. Now, I am saying just rotate
this
.sub slink, 6 5 4 and that gives me, this
tour 2 7 4. So, let us follow that tour from
2, I am
going to 7, again from 7 I am going to 4,
4 I am going to 5 is part of the same tour,
notice. From 5 I am going to 6, from 6 I am
going to 1, from 1 I am going to 3, which
is
also part of the whole 2. Then, from 3 I am
going to 9, 9 I am going to 8 essentially.
So, everything all the edges except for this
1 to 4 edge and 7 to 6 has been replaced.
So, I
have taken up this edge 7 to 6 and 1 to 4.
And replace them with this edges, which goes
from 7 to 4, which is this edge and which
goes from 1 to 6, 6 to 1 in this new edge.
So,
this is this one and this one is new edges,
that I will introduced. So, rotating a sub
slink
will effectively do a two edge exchange for
use essentially.
Why this intuitively more appealing than city
exchange? I hope it is intuitively more
appealing than the city exchange because,
it is the edges it is the edge cost, bit adds
up to
the total cost of the solution. So, what would
you ideally want to do is, to inspect your
solution. And off course, between every two
cities there is an edge cost. Pick those
edges, which seem to be very high cost. And
replace them essentially.
So, the original example that I have drawn,
which was like you go some tour like this.
So, if you have some tour like this, where
you are going like this then, these two are
very
long edges. If I remove them and replace them
with this, I will get a shorter tour. So,
in
that sense manipulating edges is more appealing
because, you can at least apply the slink
of removing very long edges essentially. So,
2 edge exchanges just one example. You
can look at 3 edge exchange.
..
So, 3 edge exchange shows, you must compute
how many neighbors are there are and so
on. So, you can pick two edges in n minus
1 c 2 ways and then you will get n minus 1
c 2
successes. In 3 edge exchange let say, this
is the problem. This is the original tour
given
to me and I am removing this three edges.
So, one is this one, one is this one and one
is
this one. And now, we can see that we can
put them back in different ways.
So, one way you can put them back is, that
you can connect this to this, from here. So,
you must be careful not to form a cycle. So,
from here I cannot go to this. So, that not
allowed. So, from here I can go to, let us
it is this. And here I can to this. No, something
is wrong. Now, here there are 3. So, I cannot
do this. So, I can put this here. Then, from
here I can go to this. And from there, I can
go to this because, I have a new tours
essentially.
So, it turns out that there are four different
ways to put them back. So, let us try one
more
and I will leave the other two is an exercise
for you. So, you understand this notation.
It
is a kind of shorthand. This is some tour
with some n cities but, we have drawn only
six
cities, representing those six, three edges
that we are going to remove. So, this edge
we
are removing, this edge we are removing and
this edge we are removing.
.Less of the tour remains the same but, we
have puttng back three edges in slightly
different place. So, instead of bliss now
I can instead of going from here to here,
I can
say go from here to here. Then, from here
you go like this. Then, from here you go like
this. And there are two more different ways
of doing it. So, I will leave that as a small
exercise for you. So, three edge exchange
if you take of three cities three edges, you
can
put them back in four different ways.
And you can take of three edges in n minus
1 c 3 ways, so into 4. These many neighbors
you get essentially. So, what I am trying
to illustrate here is that, when you treat
the TSP
perturbative problem, you take any candidates
solution. And you can generate a
neighborhood of candidate solution surround
it, using two some number of city
exchanges or some number of edge exchanges.
And they are neighborhood functions of
different density essentially, which means
that you can apply the variable neighborhood
descent functions essentially.
I am not writing this algorithm again. This
variable neighborhood descent basically says
that, if you have a set of neighborhood functions
are raised in a order of increasing
density. So, by density means how many neighbors
thus, a given candidate have? So, if a
candidate has let us say 5 neighbors or if
a candidate has let us say 12 or 15 neighbors.
Then, this neighborhood functions would more
dense and this one essentially. And why
did we want denser neighborhood functions
because, it is likely that the best amongst
them is the local maxima essentially.
Or rather, it just likely that the given no
reason local maxima, which means it does not
have a better note surrounding it. So, there
have the more note surrounding a note, the
more the likelihood of a better note existing,
if there are better notes in the spaces
essentially. So, the idea of variable neighborhood
descent is that, to start with the
simplest neighborhood function. Why are you
do not we want to work with the most
dense function first?
Because the cost of making a move is proportional
to the number of neighbors, that we
have because, we have to inspect all the neighbors
and then pick the best amongst them.
So, I like in SAT if every, if we can change
any number of bits then, it amongst to doing
.the complete beautiful search. We do not
want to do that, we want to starts with
neighborhood functions move on to dense a
function and so on and so far.
So, in today's class basically what we have
done is, looked at the TSP problem. And we
are not really looked at the new method for
escaping local maxima, which you will do in
the next towards see classes. But, when we
are doing that, we will keep in mind how to
solve the TSP. So, remember that this kind
of this thing. Just a quite comment about
these two city exchange, remember this was
the two city exchange, I exchange this city
and this city.
And as the result, I added this four new edges.
Remove the four edges because, the
neighboring edges from here and I added for.
So, you can see that this is the particular
case of four edge exchange essentially. In
practice, off course if you remove those four
edges, you can put them back in many different
ways. So, two city exchange is just a
special, one of the cases of those four city
exchange. Four edge exchange, which is going
to give us a denser functions essentially.
So, the more the cities of the edges we remove,
the more the ways you can put them back
in and more the ways you can remove them in.
And they give you denser functions
essentially. So, that is one mechanism for
doing that this. I will just stop here. We
will,
when you comeback we will look at a new algorithm,
for try to escape local maxima.
How can we escape this local maximize? That
is going to be our objective in the next
few lectures essentially.
.