And we saw in a last class the alpha beta
algorithm, and the tree that was explored
by
alpha beta we saw here.
It is a binary game tree 4 ply deep and those
shaded nodes are
the ones which alpha beta did not explore
essentially.
Now, alpha beta algorithm
searches from left to right and we want to
now look for a algorithm which is not
uninformed, which is not blind in this manner,
but has a sense of direction.
So, just as we
moved from death first search to best first
search by introducing heuristic function,
we
want to look at an algorithm which will go
towards what it thinks is a good solution
essentially.
And indeed such an algorithm was given by
stockman in 1979 and it is called
SSS star.
..
Now, to understand this algorithm first we
must understand what is the space in which
this best first search will happen, and look
at what max does.
So, max is playing a game
of the many choices that it has available,
it makes one choice.
So, of course, on the
surface level it is selecting a choice, but
it is making a choice on the basis of having
searched a key up to some depth, which is
let us say k ply search we are doing.
And it is, it is on a basis of this look ahead
that max has made this move.
And on the
basis of having applied a evaluation function
on the horizon essentially.
So, in effect max
has force looked ahead at or foreseen what
would be min’s response?
So, in other words,
max is comfortable with all of min’s responses,
and for each of those min’s responses
max has thought ahead that I will make one
particular move and then, max is taken into
account, all of min’s responses.
So, let us say, this is also a 4 ply search
tree.
Max has
looked at this entire set of possibilities,
and on the basis of this has made the move
that
max has made essentially.
So, you can say that, this sub tree that we
are seeing is what max has concluded at the
result of this search.
He says if max will make this move, whichever
move min makes
max has an answer to that and then, whichever
makes min makes max has taken that into
consideration while evaluating this thing.
Now, you will remember that, such a sub tree
is called a strategy.
So, max has chosen a strategy of course, alpha
beta algorithm does
not search in the space of strategies, it
is does not even consider strategies as such,
but if
.we are going to look at a different algorithm
which is SSS star.
SSS star searches in the
space of strategies.
So, let us say, this strategy that max has
chosen this strategy and let us call this
S, and we
have discussed this earlier, what is the value
of this strategy?
And value in terms of the
leaf nodes that max has taken into account.
So, let us say, this is 10, 20, 40, and let
us say
all these are bigger values 60, 70.
Let us say this is 5, 10, 15, 30.
Some values, I am not
filling all the values, but let us say we
have some values 10, 20, 40, 60, 70.
There is a 5
here 10, 15, 30.
What is going to be the mini max value when
max uses this key?
It is going to be the minimum of all these
values.
Because once max has frozen max’s
strategy, it is only up to min to choose and
min will lose some analysis and say that,
okay
if I make this move and if then, if I make
this move then, I will get a value of 5, which
is
what min is going to drive it at.
And max has no more choices left because max’s
strategy has frozen essentially.
So, the value of a strategy is the minimum
of the value of
leaves in this strategy S. So, I just use
this notation to say that these are the leaves
of the
strategy S, and the value of the strategy
is the minimum of the value of the leaf of
this of
the strategy.
Now, as a corollary, if were to choose a random
leaf in a strategy.
So, if I chose some
leaf L value of L. So, let us say this is
L, some leaf, it does not matter.
How does it
influence us, what relation does it have with
value of S?
It is greater than or equal to the
value of the strategy, which means the value
of a leaf is an upper bound on a strategy
in
which contains that leaf.
Now, let us look at this binary search tree
again, if I were to
select this leaf 50, which has this value
50, how many strategies will this be a part
of?
You can see that, this of course, is min’s
choice and here max has made a choice, and
that choice has 50 as this leaf.
Max has to encounter so, so this strategy
would be this
choice for max, both these choices for min,
this particular choice for max, and both these
for min essentially.
Now, since max has to consider both these
choices for min, this as
well as this.
When max makes this move, max is either selecting
a strategy in which max
is making this move here, and this move here.
I mean max is considering this move, max
is considering a strategy in which max is
making that move and this move, and the
strategy may have this move precisely.
.Alternatively, this leaf will also be part
of a strategy where max makes that move, this
move here, but the other move at this place
here, that also will contain this particular
strategy.
So, you need to visualize this a little bit,
that in this particular game tree every
leaf belongs to 2 strategies, and that is
the one strategy is when max makes this choice
here, and the other strategy is when max makes
the other choice here.
Because max has
to take into account this choice of min here.
So, there are 16 leaves, and how many
choices, how many strategies does max have?
2 here, choices here, 2 choices here, and
choices here so, max has 8 strategies available
to that and as an.
.
So, I will just write it here number of strategies
equal to 8 for a 4 ply binary search tree,
and as an exercise you can see that for 5
or 6 ply it is the same it is.
So, 8 is equal to 2
raised to 3, for 5 or 6 it is 2 raised to
7, for 7 or 8 it is 2 raised to 15, for 9
or 10 it is 2
raised to 31 and you can extrapolate from
here.
And I will just give this as figures, you
can work this out yourselves that as you go
deeper, the number of strategies increases
considerably.
And as an exercise you can so, this 2 is a
branching factor that is playing
the role here.
If he replaces 2 with B what would the figure
be like this?
It is an interesting exercise, but you can
do that later.
For this particular tree, there are 8
strategies and if I choose any arbitrary node,
I will get 2 of those 8 strategies, choose
any
node and you will get 2 strategies.
So, what does SSS star do?
It is searches in the space
of strategies, and it must be exhaustive in
the sense that it must not miss out on the
best
.move.
So, it must consider all strategies to begin
with and then, choose one from that.
That is of course, brute force, but we do
not do brute force here especially.
.
Now, a leaf node, you can say is represents
a partial strategy.
In other words, it is a
strategy which is not completely refined,
if I have seen only one leaf in a strategy,
I have
seen only part of the strategy.
So, for example, if I have seen this leaf
20, its value is 20,
I have, I know that this part of this particular
strategy, it may be part of other strategies
as well.
But whichever strategy it is a part of, it
has this property that it is an upper bound
of the value of this strategy.
A leaf node also represents a cluster of strategies,
which is what we were discussing in
the moment ago that, if I were to choose this
node 50, the left most node then, it
represents a cluster of 2 strategies.
And the 2 strategies are the one where max
makes the
left choice at the top level, and if min were
to make this choice then, max has decided
the
left choice, but if min were to make this
choice, max could either choose this or it
could
choose that.
So, those are the 2 strategies.
This particular node 50 represents, and this
50 would be an upper bound on both those
strategies.
So, what we need to do is to select leads
to cover all strategies, that is the first
point of SSS star algorithm, that somehow
you select the leaves in such a manner that,
you have a representative from all possible
strategies, which means you have covered all
strategies.
How do you do that?
.It is very simple, you extract a sub tree
from the game tree in the following fashion
that
at max level choose all branches.
Why should we do that?
Because we want to cover all
strategies.
We want to not miss out on any strategies
so, for example, at the root level,
we must consider all possible moves that max
makes, and likewise at deeper levels
essentially.
So, at max level choose all branches, at min
level choose 1.
If I do this, so, I should write
here set of, I will construct a set of leaves
which will cover all strategies essentially.
So,
let us do that for this game tree that we
had considered for the alpha beta algorithm.
So,
we want to now explore how SSS star will do
it, but first it starts off by selecting a
set of
leaves where each leaf represents a cluster
of 2 strategies in this case, but you must
select
the leaves so, that all strategies are covered.
So, that we do not miss out on any strategy.
.
And the way to that is to select all choices
for max, one choice and let us say, arbitrarily
we are choosing the left most choice for min
then all choices for max and one choice for
min.
Likewise here, one choice for min all choices
for max, one choice for min.
SSS star,
this algorithm starts of by selecting this
set of nodes, leaves.
So, let me just underline these leaves here,
we are looking at this one, this one, this
one,
and this one.
And I will ask you to think about this and
convince yourself that of the 8
strategies that we talked about, these 4 leaves
cover 2 each, and they are all disjoint and
they cover all the 8 strategies essentially.
Now, max is basically tasked so, remember
the
.best first algorithm that we had talked about
and then, we also looked at the travelling
salesman problem which is the high level algorithm
is that define.
.
Best looking partial strategy, a partial solution
in that case, in our case the solution is
the
strategy till best solution is fully refined.
This is the high level algorithm for best
first
search A star fits into this, branch and bound
fits into this, best first fits into this.
At all
point, we are maintaining some sort a priority
queue in which we are able to pick the best
value strategy.
So, in A star the best is defined in terms
of the f value, which is h value plus g value.
If
you remember the travelling salesman problem,
we said that at the top most root level,
the set of cities represent all possible to
us.
And then, we partition this set into 2 sets
one
which contain one edge, and the other which
did not contain this edge.
So, this was a partial tour, both these are
partial tours, they are not fully specified
and we
had figured out a way to evaluate what is
the lower bound cost on those tours, and we
always picked up best looking tour and refined
it further essentially.
We want to do
something similar here in SSS star is that,
we first cover all the possible solutions
and
that is what we have done by choosing the
set of leaves to form the clusters which cover
all strategies.
.So, in this case we have 4 clusters, and
in each cluster we have one representative
leaf
50, 30, 30, and 70, and that leaf represents
an upper bound on the value of the strategy
that this cluster belongs to, this leaf belongs
to, each leaf belongs to 2 strategies.
So, we
will follow this, we find the best looking
partial solution until the best solution is
fully
refined when it is fully refined, when the
strategy is completely defined.
So, this
algorithm SSS star, it uses a priority queue
of clusters, but clusters are not represented
explicitly, they are represented by the representative
node essentially.
And each element
in the priority queue is represented by the
name of the node by a value which is either
live or solved and a bound.
So, initially when we start the algorithm,
we start it with the root and we say it is
live by
live we mean which is not solved essentially.
So, you can now also make a comparison
or with the AO star algorithm that we had
seen.
The AO star algorithm keeps refining a
solution till the root gets solved, root gets
level solved, which means that the solution
is
completely refined.
And at some point I had also made this observation
that, solving a game tree is similar to
solving an of problem because at the max level
we have to make one choice, so it is an
odd node.
At min level you have to consider all choices,
and it is like a min node except
that you do not sum up the pass cause of the
parsing solutions as we did in A star, but
we
take the minimum of the cost of the parsing
solutions here essentially.
So, it is very much like the A star, AO star
algorithm and this is the terminology we use
in the AO star also that is we had nodes levels
solved or not level solved.
In this case we
are explicitly calling them live.
The algorithm will proceed till the root gets
level solved
so, that is a similarity with AO star you
should observe.
AO star was the best first
algorithm if you remember and this is also
going to be the best first algorithm.
So, we start with this and this bounds.
Initially we insert this into the priority
queue, this
triple where the root node and level it live
and plus large.
And always the highest value
will be the head of the root, the priority
queue a max queue then, the algorithm picks
the
head element which is the value with the largest
bound or heuristic value if you want to
call it, and does the following.
So, this is, these are the cases when you
pick the head node from the root that, it
is max
and it is live then, you add all the children
to the queue with the same bound and call
.them live essentially.
So, I should in fact, say non terminal.
So, some where there is a
test so, remember the terminal nodes are those
on the horizon, and at the horizon we
allowed to apply.
In fact we have to apply the evaluation function
and get a value for that
node.
If it is max, it is a max node and if it is
a live node and if it is non terminal then,
add all
children to the queue.
So, you will see that this is the step, at
max level choose all
branches, at max level we are adding all the
children.
So, initially we would have added
this root then, we will add both these children
to this thing and then, we will call them
live essentially.
If it is a min and live and non terminal then,
add one child.
So, you can see these two steps correspond
to the initial formation of the clusters
essentially.
And since this is a priority queue with this
plus large values, all this will be
taken care of first and this whole tree would
be constructed here.
This tree that you see in
this pinkish color here at max level we will
add both the children, we will remove max
and add both the children.
At min level we will remove min and add one
child.
In this case we arbitrarily choose a left
side at max level we add both this children
at min
level we add one child.
And all this will vanish and so, only 4 entries
will remain in my
parity queue with the values initially large,
but the moment we take a terminal node.
If it
is terminal, you label it solved.
So, these 4 nodes will be terminal, we will
label them
solved and we will put the values that we
have, which is 50, 30, 30, and 70.
So, at the
end of this so, if you remember the AO star
algorithm had these 2 phases, the forward
phase and the backup phases essentially.
So, in some sense this is like the forward
phase, whenever we are looking at the live
node it is like forward phase because we are
adding the children.
Either all children, if it
is a max node or one child if it is a min
node, but we are moving forward or moving
down in the tree.
But once it is solved nodes, we go into the
backward tree essentially.
So, now, we have these 4 nodes and all 4 will
get label solved essentially.
Because they
have this plus large value, they will always
be ahead of the queue.
Even if this one will gets label solved, it
will go at the rear of the queue because those
will have plus large.
Then, eventually all 4 will get plus these
values, and they get sorted
70, 50, 30, and 30 in the priority queue.
We always pick so, it is a priority queue,
I do not
need to repeat that, we always take the node
at the head of the queue.
So, once we have
.this 4 solved nodes in my, in the priority
queue, the next node that will get picked
is this
one 70, one is 70.
So, these represent 4 clusters let us call
them A, B, C, D. Each of these clusters
represents 2 strategies, and each of these
values represents an upper bound on those
strategies.
And the best looking cluster is d, and d comes
to ahead of the priority queue
and so, SSS star picks that algorithm, it
is a max node.
So, if it is a max and solved, there
are two cases, one is that, it has a sibling
left in the tree all the other cases when
it does
not have a sibling left from the tree.
So, both these nodes 30 and 70 and in fact,
all 4
have a sibling still left in the tree.
So, they have this case essentially.
So, in case they have a sibling, you replace
with
sibling and lower value, whichever is the
lower of the 2 values is you give that value
to
that cluster, why?
Because remember that, the value of a strategy
is always the minimum
of the value of the leaves essentially.
And if you are looking at one more leaf in
the
strategy, and if it has a lower value, we
must keep the lower value.
If it has a higher
value, we must keep the lower value from the
first one, it does not matter where the
lower value comes from.
So, keep the sibling as a representative,
replace with sibling and with a lower value,
if
there is no sibling.
So, I will write else here, and this else
means that there is no sibling,
replace with parent.
So, we will come to this so, let us follow
these steps.
So, this 70
would be the head of the queue, and it will
get removed from the queue, and it is sibling
would be added.
So, which amounts to say that we are exploring
this node, and we are
looking at this node then, the value of this
cluster would still be 70 because that is
the
lower of this two values 70 and 80.
So, this would still be at the ahead of the
queue because it has its value 70, it has
no more
siblings left so, this will get added to the
queue and this will be get label solved.
So, let
me say this represents label solved as a,
as we had done in the AO star algorithm.
If it
has no sibling, we place it with the parent
with that value.
So, still this cluster D is
represented by this node here and its value
is 70.
At this point, observe that because this is
a max node here, this is never going to play
a
role any further because it has an upper bound
of 30, and max is getting 70 from here,
max knows it is getting 70 from here.
This is like an alpha cut off will take place
this
.place, either you do it explicitly or it
will languish at the end of the queue never
coming
to the fore essentially does not matter.
That is, that step of alpha cut off is captured
by this step here.
If it is min and solved
now, just think carefully about this, if it
is a min node and it is solved and implicitly
we
are not saying this here, it is at the head
of the queue, it is at the head of the queue.
So,
this is solved and it is at the head of the
queue.
It has a sibling, but the sibling is never
going to play a role, why?
Because it is a min node, it is, it is got
an upper, it is, it is value got a, got a
value of 70, it
is sibling has an upper bound of 30, and this
sibling is never going to influence this max
node, and it is going to not consider this
at all.
So, this is implemented by saying that, if
it is a min node and if it is a solved node
then, just replace it with its parent.
So, now, this
and the, parent gets label solved.
So, I should say that, parent and solved in
both cases whether it is a max node or a min
node.
For a max node if there are no siblings then,
the parent gets label solved and gets
the value.
If min node, it does not matter whether there
are siblings or not, but its parent
will get label solved, and it will get a value
of 70 in this case.
Now, we go back to this
step that node is solved and that is a max
node, its sibling is not yet solved essentially
it
is not a terminal node we are somewhere up
in the tree.
So, we replace this with the sibling, the
same process if max is solved replace with
sibling and lower value.
In this case the value is 70.
So, we basically this node becomes
live with a value of 70.
It amounts to say that I want to evaluate
this with a bound of 70
essentially.
Now, since it is a live node, it is like a
recursive call essentially henceforth.
It
is a live node, we follow this, add all children
for max, one child for min.
So, it is like a
recursive call which means we add all children
for max and one child for min.
So, we first look at this and then so, all
these added to the queue, this comes to the
head
of the queue because it has a value of 80,
it is a terminal node.
The moment we see a
terminal node we missed it.
This comes to the head of the queue then,
it gets a played
biased child with a value of 80 then, there
is no more siblings left, this is still at
the head
of the queue.
So, this gets added to the queue with the
value of 80 and solved.
The
moment this gets label solved with a value
of 80 its parent gets label solved with a
value
of 80, and when the, when a max node.
.So, remember that we are always considering
the nodes at the head of the queue and the
highest value node we are looking at that
all times.
This is at the head of the queue sorry,
this is not correct with the value of 80,
but with value of 70 essentially the lower
of the 2
values.
Now, there are no more siblings left for this
max node at the head is the max
node with the label solved so, this is already
gone away actually, it is been thrown away,
only one copy is been kept it is.
So, no more siblings are left so, this min
node gets label
solved with the value of 80.
Now, since it is a min node and it is solved,
it does not care about it, and it is at the
head
of the queue, it does not care because this
means whatever the bounds that are coming
from elsewhere will be lower than this, it
is in the hydraulic queue and max is going
to.
So, max is getting a value of 80 from here
it is getting a value of utmost 50 or 30 from
here depending on what happens in these other
nodes which we have not seen, but
utmost the value of 50.
So, they are behind in the queue, the moment
a min solved node comes into the head of
the queue as we have said here, we just replace
the parent with the solved node.
In this
case we replace this with a value of 70.
So, what have we done?
We have looked at this.
This SSS star algorithm has looked at 1, 2,
3, 4, 5, 6, 7, nodes essentially before it
terminated.
Notice, it terminates with the same value
of 70 which the alpha beta found
and which is of mini max would have found
essentially.
So, all the three algorithms mini max algorithm,
alpha beta algorithm, SSS star
algorithm, we find the same mini max value
obviously, otherwise they would be
different.
So, they find the same move with the same
mini max value.
Mini max would
have seen all these 16 nodes, alpha beta sees
only these 10 unshaded nodes that we have
drawn here, and SSS star sees only these 7
underlined pink nodes that we have seen here.
What is more important?
Observe that it is attention is always been
focused towards this
side of the tree where the best moves lie
for both the players, and it has basically
solved
this part and ignored this part altogether
essentially.
It is not seen this node for example,
which was seen by alpha beta of this node,
which was seen by alpha beta and so on
essentially.
So, in fact, it was shown by stockman that,
alpha beta that, SSS star, if any
node is seen by SSS star, alpha beta will
also see that essentially.
Where?
Yes because
this was 70, this also should be 70 and solved.
.So, SSS star is the best first variation
of alpha beta you can see.
The only difference
between what we said earlier when we talked
about best first search, we used a notion
of
a heuristic function which was domain dependent.
In this case we do not use the heuristic
function in that sense, but we use an estimate
of the solution.
A heuristic function also
gives an estimate of a solution, but here
we have a different mechanism to arrive at
an
estimate is that is by sampling.
By sampling all strategies to get upper bounds
on all possible strategies, and that in the
process we found these clusters.
And then we always refined the best looking
cluster.
So,
that is where the best first nature of the
algorithm comes into play.
So, I want to end with
a couple of things, one is that if you are
talking about a real world game playing
program.
.
Then, you do a certain amount of search, you
do a cape line look ahead, but there is a
danger of lurking here.
Of course, the farther you can see the better,
but because the tree
is growing exponentially, you cannot do too
much search and most algorithms do not go
beyond 10 ply also essentially.
Now, this something called the horizon effect,
and this is as follows that, this supposing,
there is one particular line of play which
is of interest, which is being evaluated by
certain mechanism as which happens naturally
in this.
So, let us say this sequence of
nodes has a role to play in determining that
either this better or something else is better,
.it does not matter.
It is an important sequence of events moves.
So, each is a move.
So,
max move, min move and so on.
Now, supposing in this you were to insert
a set of arbitrary moves which are pointless
let
us say, max makes some move, max makes a move,
min makes a move, max makes a
move, makes the move.
And let us for arguments sake say that, this
state is equal to this
state.
It is possible, if you are looking at a game
like chess for example, max might make
a knight move, min might make a knight move,
max might take the knight move back,
and make min take its knight move back.
So, both have made a move and undone the move
and so, they are in the same state here.
But what happens to the search?
In search supposing, we insert this whole
sequence here
then, this part gets pushed out of the horizon
because of this arbitrary move that you are
doing, this cart gets pushed out of the horizon
which means that, something that is
important which was happening in these moves
is no longer noticed by this algorithm
because it is search is only till the horizon.
So, this effect is called the horizon effect,
and what people have done is that, we often
do
a secondary search, before making a move they
do a little bit of secondary search to
verify that the move is indeed not a there
are no catastrophic lurking behind that move
or
something like that.
So, very often people do this.
Obviously, the secondary search will
only do this much amount of search, which
is at last less than actually searching this
whole thing up to this depth, that would have
been meant much more worth essentially.
And finally, I want to end with an example,
which shows that there can be a limitation
to
search.
So, this is a well known example which was
fed to this hi-tech program, this hitech was
a multi processor, 64 processor chess playing
machine developed by Berlino in
Seymour, and this position was given to hi
tech and it illustrates that search is not
always
capable of doing something, unless it is full
search of course, which are other forms of
reasoning can do.
So, the position is as follows.
So, let us say, these are pawns P, P, P, P,
P. So, white has this position.
So, it is a very
contrite position somebody invented it just
to show that search can have its drawbacks.
So, these are pawns, 8 pawns white house,
one in each column, and white has only the
king left here essentially.
Let us say, the opponent also has 8 pawns
which are kind of
.head to head with these 8 pawns.
In some sense, creating the kind of a dead
lock, but the
opponent has other pieces also.
So, opponent has for example, a bishop here
and a rook here, and a rook here, and a king
here.
So, the opponent is strong in terms of material
advantage.
This white player has 8
pawns and the king, this red player or black
player whatever you want to call has 8
pawns and a king, but also has 2 rooks and
a bishop essentially.
So, there is a significant
material advantage essentially.
What happens if this red moves this rook here?
That
makes this move and now its white’s turn
to move and this position was given to hi-tech
essentially, this is called the poisoned rook.
So, if you just look up poisoned rook on the
web, you will get this position and some
story behind this essentially.
So, what is the story?
Red moves the rook here, in some
sense offering it to this pawn, right?
White can capture this rook like this, if
you know
the chess rules, and white, the game playing
algorithm that we have been talking about
will basically do this.
They will do some k ply search, apply the
evaluation function.
What is the evaluation function?
We had seen it is a combination of material
advantage
and positional advantage.
And then, choose a best move based on this
evaluation function.
What will this poor
white program do?
It will see that, it is getting to capture
the rook.
As a result of which,
it makes this move of capturing the rook,
but this rook as a title says, it is a poisoned
rook because what happens?
Once this pawn moves away from here, this
impregnable
fortress that right had.
So, observe that these rooks cannot attack
any of the pawns
otherwise because rooks can move only in this
direction, and the only bishop that black
has it is the one which will attack its own
color.
So, if you know chess you will see that you
will be for example, all black squares and
these will be all white squares, and it has
a black bishop, it can never attack, it can
never
break, left to itself black can never break
into this fortress that white has constructed.
But
the moment white moves one pawn from this
chain, it opens its territory to black and
then, black can actually as you might say,
invade from here and win the game
essentially.
So, even players, most even players will look
at this position and say yes.
The only thing
that the white can do is to move the king
around and then, black cannot do anything,
but
.this chess program which was not able to
reason at a what you might say as a higher
level or a meta level, or see further it can
only do this search of a tree thought that
it was
going to get some material advantage.
So, it captured the rook and actually lost
the game essentially.
So, which is the, thus the
lesson here is that to build intelligence
systems, you need not just one form of reasoning,
but many forms of reasoning working together.
The other form of reasoning is that kind
of reasoning that we are talking about here
know, analyzing the structure in some way
or
making some difference about this thing which
this program is not able to do.
So, we will stop here with games, there are
other games plays algorithm, game playing
algorithms that we will not consider.
For example, Berlino had a algorithm called
B star,
which we will not consider, which is also
a kind of a heuristic search algorithm which
had a sense of direction, but we will limit
ourselves to the SSS star, which is a much
simpler algorithm to talk about essentially.
So, we will end with games here and move on
from this place essentially.
.