So, in the last class, we saw the definition
of constrain satisfaction problems and we
made this observation that solving the C S
P basically allows co-operation between two
kinds of algorithm, one, which the search
over possible assignments and the other which
does some kind of reasoning which we will
call as propagation. So, we have this notion
of consistency.
.
We are, this notion of I consistency, so we
say that a C S P or a network is I consistence,
if every consistence assignment to I minus
1 variables can be extended to I variable
which means that, if we have found values
for I minus for 1 variables any I minus
variables. Then, you can always take any I
variable, any next variable and extend find
the consistent value for that. So, of course
not all networks will be I consistence, but
the
general effort in reasoning is to enforce
consistency in some manner essentially.
So, we can start with the very simplest notion
of consistency, which is called node
.consistency or one consistency, when you
say one consistency then we use the term note.
So, it basically means that you take any variable
and you will find one value which is
consistent. What do we mean by consistence
with one variable? That if there happens to
be a constraints over only that variable,
a unary constraint then all the variables
satisfy
that. So, we can enforce node consistency
by simply saying that if there is some value
which does not satisfy constraint, remove
it from the domain.
So, in general node consistency and there
is one consistency, two consistency will
domain which essentially. So, two consistency,
what we will look at it cal A R C
consistency
and what two consistency says that you take
a assign a value 2, any variable
which is node consistence which means that
values satisfy any unary constraint that there
might be, you take any other variable and
you will be able to find a value for that
variable which is, which. So, that there is
a 2 values, for the first variable and second
variable are together consistence essentially.
.
So, to talk about A R C consistence is often
useful to draw, what we call is a matching
diagram, and the matching diagram basically
does something like this, that it creates
a
domain for each variable. So, this is X 1,
this is X 2 and then you have variables inside
is
domains, so these are the values that this
variable can take and edge represents the
fact
.that this value, let us call it A 1 and this
value let us call it B 1 belongs to the relation
essentially. So, basically it is a depiction
of relation essentially, so I whatever the
relation
is something like this, so such a diagram
column is matching diagram.
So, what we want to do in our consistency
over these two variables is to keep only those
values in the domain, for which there is a
corresponding value in the other domain
essentially. So, for example we do not want
to keep this value because there is no
matching value in the other domain, we do
not want to keep this value, we do not want
to
keep this value. So, to implement this, we
have a simple procedure called revise and
this
is kind a standard name for it D X D Y or
X Y it takes. So, we say that we are going
to
prune the values of D X to only those values
which have a value corresponding value for
this R X Y.
So, if this is X and that is Y we can prune
in this essentially, so for each A belonging
to d
X, if there is no B belonging to D Y, remove
A from D X very simple procedure which
looks at each value. So, this is A, this is
a procedure which is only pruning the domain
D
X, so it looks for each value this is A X
and that is Y, and it looks each value of
X. If
there is no value in Y, if there is no B belong
with D Y, I should have add it first, that
A
B belongs to R X Y. In other words, if we
have a binary constrain over X and Y, then
every value of X should have a matching value
in Y and this procedure revise is pruning
this domain X domain of X.
So, it looks at all these values and for A,
every value where there is no matching value,
on the other side this one, this one has two
values. So, it, this one has no values, so
it will
remove this from the domain, it will keep
this, it will keep this and will remove this.
So,
it will remove 2 values and keep one essentially,
so the process of doing our consistency,
basically doing this repeatedly so that all
pairs of variables are our consistency
essentially.
..
So, the simplest algorithm for doing that
is call A C 1, so and, so our consistency
1, and
it does basically the following for each
X Y, such that R X Y is the domain, R X Y
is the
real, is a constrain, call revise D X D Y,
R X Y and call revise in both directions D
Y D
X R X Y. So, we will assume that R X Y contains
the relation between them, so I instead
of writing R Y X, I am just writing R X Y,
for each pair X Y of variable we want do this
which means if I have 3 variables.
Let us see this one, and let us say I have
something like this, so this is X Y and Z,
so I
have 3 variables, 2 relations between X and
Y, Y and Z and I want to make this network
our consistence which means that every assignment
one of these variables can be
extended to an assignment of 2 variables?
Notice that, in the constrate network diagram
that we had drawn earlier, we would have drawn
this like this, this is Y, this is Z and this
is X. So, there is A between these two, this
is called a network from same network, it
basically a constrate graph which says which
variable is constrain, by which variable and
we are talking about binary constrain.
So, we have only edges, otherwise you would
have hyper edges, the constrain of,
basically identifies which variables are related
to each other. The matching diagram tells
you which values of variables, our participating
in those constrains, when we say
.something like, this that, this is a constrain
graph. So, if you remember this map coloring
example that we saw, we said that if this
is, if the domains of all 3 are red, blue
and this
is not equal to this, and this is not equal
to this. So, that is a constrain given to
first,
implicitly we have a constrain between this
and this which says that anything is allowed.
So, R B is allowed R, R is allowed, D B is
allowed, and B R is allowed, if we have not
specified, if we have not specified a constrain,
that means implicitly it is a universal
relation. It means anything allowed to anything
which means, what that our back
trekking algorithm said that if you first
want to give a value for X, and if you want
to
give a value for Z, it is not putting constraint
which means you can choose. If we choose
R for X, you can choose B for Z, it does not
care because it does not know any constrain
essentially.
So, there is the universal relations, but
of course this not expressed, it simply sit,
so it
does not participate in the matching diagram
here and it does not participate in this.
So,
when you say R X Y is the constrain, remain
it is an expressive constrain mention in the
C S P essentially.
.
So, before I come back to this, we have a
notion of 3 consistency which is known as
path
.consistency, remember the notion of I consistency
which is the generic notion. So, 3
consistencies say that any pair of values
which are constraint can be a extended to
a third
value. So, if I choose 2 values for this,
I should be able to extend to a third value,
so if I
choose Z for this and blue for this, I can
extend it to blue for this.
If I X, if I choose blue for this and red
for this, I can choose blue for that, but
if I choose
these two values first, if I choose red for
this and red for this then I can extend this
two
blue for this variable Y. But, if I go to
choose red for X and blue for Z, then I cannot
extend to Y, so this network is given to us
is node 3 consistence or is node path
consistence. What path consistency would do,
would to prune this relation in this
example?
So, what we do? It do that it will say that
you choose red for this and blue for this
and it
cannot extend it to the value. So, this red
blue must be removed from this relation you
choose blue for this and red for this and
you cannot extended to a value, so you must
prune this from the relation. So, enforcing
path consistency prunes relations the moment
you have pruning a universal relation, you
have making a express it, so in fact it adds
a
new relation. So, when you do path consistency
you get a new network, it looks like this,
it adds the relation in some sense, in the
sense that earlier it was a universal relation,
but
now it is not a universal relation.
So, you have to express it, represented which
means X is not related Z, so these two are
not equal to, but this one is equal to, so
we have new network. So, the general idea
of
enforcing consistency is to limit the choice
is a available to a search algorithm, to only
those which are like you to participating
and solutions. But, since an N variable problem
will have N variable, so we, to really achieve
full consistency you would have to achieve
N consistency, which off course is you can
take it from me is a hard task.
So, which is why we do not often do it, so
very often algorithms will do ache, some
degree of consistency, either node consistency
or path consistency, consistency or path
consistency, or some higher order consistency
depending on how much, how complex
the problem is. Then leave the rest to search
and leave the rest to those other kinds of
things that we just briefly mentioned in the
passing like dependency direct is back
.tracking or loop a heading search.
So, there are various tools in the, of a C
S P solver consistency enforcement is one
of
those which is what we are trying to look
at today. So, coming back to arch consistency,
I want to make this network arch consistence,
which means if I choose any value in any
variable, I should get the allowed to by the
consistency, given to me choose value for
the
next variable. So, obviously as you saw, when
we call, what will we do? We will call
revise with X and Y with Y and X with X and
Z with Z and X with Y and Z and Z and
Y. So, at least 6 calls to revise, we will
have to make remember, revise is the directional
call it prunes only the domain of the first
one.
That if for each X and D X, there is no corresponding
value in Y, remove this A from D
X, that is what revise does for this. So,
we have to make at least 6 calls to revise
the other
6 call, enough is a question I want to ask
you. If I say revise X Y, revise Y X, revise
X Z,
revise Z X, revise Y Z, revise Z Y, am I done,
and do I get a network which is our
consistence? Let us try it on this, so let
us call revise X Y first, which means we are
going to throw this away and we are going
to throw this away from this essentially.
Then
that is called revise Y X, which means we
are going to throw this away from the domain
of Y, so let me actually circle it.
So, the N cross it, so we know that those
things are not there essentially, then next
called
X Z, X Z we do not have a constraint at all,
the constraint given to us is this. This
constraint diagram which turns anything about,
which means it is a universal relation
which means there is no constraint, on choosing
any value from there. So, this revise call
will not do anything, but we have a constraint
between Y and Z, so let us try that. For
this, we have this value, for this we do not
have this value, so we have to delete this
for
this, we have this value for this, we have
this value, anyway this is not there, for
this we
do not have this value, so we have to delete
this. So, this
is gone, now let us see what
happen the moment I have deleted this, this
value
Well, this has one left here, but this related
this value this one does not have a matching
value, so I read something revise X Y. But,
now when I did revise wise it, I deleted the
value of Y and this value of X does not have
anything left, so at least one more to call
to
.revise, I will have to make essentially.
So, if you do this, then this one has this,
this one
does not have this, so this goes away, this
one has does not have this of this goes away
this one has this.
So, it is almost our consistence except for
this value, here this value does not have
corresponding value, here this value has,
this value here and then this value has that
value there, this value has this value here,
and that is that, but this one does not have
value here. So, I must make another call to
X Y, so which means I must put this into a
loop. What is the safest thing to do until
no more changes, until no domain changes?
I
will keep doing this, revise all these, revise
at the very outside, we can see calling revise
X Z does not really make a sense.
But, of course we are not calling revise X
Z, because the condition says for each were
X
Y. So, set R X Y is constraint, so R X Z is
not a constraint. So, it is we will make calls
revise X Y, Y X, Y Z and Z Y repeatedly, till
we come to a condition where no domains
as change because then we are show that it
is our consistence essentially. So, is this
algorithm, is it nice, is it a good algorithm?
The answer is no, because it can be argued
that the number of calls number of calls revise
that you make is actually very large that
in the worst case in every cycle you will
remove only one value from one domain.
In the worst case, you can construct a network
like there, so that in one cycle which
means a complete set up revise calls, you
will remove only one value from one domain,
and in the next cycle, you will remove one
value from one domain. So, if there are N
domains, and let us say all of them are connected
and each of them has K value, then you
will make N into K cycles which is obliviously
not in efficient things to do. The reason
for that is that, why should we do this route
force call to all combinations of revise.
Now, if we look at what is happening here,
what we should have done is the following
that when we made this revise at call, and
then we deleted this value from the domain
of
Y, we should we have said Y has change. So,
therefore any constraint participating in
relation in which Y is there, look at that
relation again because Y has change any X
Y
participating in this thing, so look at that
relation again. So, which means when we delete
a value from a domain then we should for future,
revise call only those relations which
.are participating with that variable essentially.
So, that actually leads just in algorithm
which I will not describing any more details
here
which is called A C 3, which was describe
a who is consider by many, to be in some
sense, the big boss of constrain satisfaction.
If you want to meet him, we can go to of
Ireland, where there is the big constrain
center and it probable the place which the
largest
population of the constrain researches essentially.
So, there are algorithms for some AC
3, there is no, there is A C 2 is missing
lost essentially, but this A C D 3 algorithm
,what
I will just refreeze describe. What we does
is that initially it maintain the cube of
all
possible revise called, but then it removes
elements from the and it makes a call it add
to
the queue only if it beans it necessary that
I need to check this relation again.
Essentially, which means if I deleted something
from Y then let I should check this
revise X Y call, again make this at least
time as loop again if I did it something from
in
this case it is only Y. So, if I did something
from y in a call from y to x then I must make
a revise call to Z, Z Y again essentially.
So, only if there is a danger of having lost
some
matching value I will make a call to revise
again. So, I will put that particular revise
call
in the queue which means only where changes
are matter are happening this constraint
will it propagated in that sense that is why
we call this constraint propagation.
We have to another algorithm which of course
we will not discuss call A C 4 does not
even make generic calls to revise, again it
says this value has change in this thing.
So, if
this value was a matching value for some this
thing some other, so let us say this value
was a matching value. For this value in X,
let me go and check if X still has a matching
value or not, otherwise I will remove X from
that. So, I does not even make this revise
X
Y call, again it is only looks at this particular
value to see if there is a corresponding
matching value left because it could have
another value.
But, in which case, of course we do not have
to delete it simply, because it does not have
any value remaining after this has been deleted,
this should be deleted. So, that is the still
final level detail algorithm A C 4 and, obviously
the complexity decrease as you go from
here to here representation increases, we
have to represent more things essentially.
So, I
want to talk about one particular constrain
satisfaction problem where an algorithm,
.which his claim to be some were between A
C 1 and A C 2 or close to. What would have
been A C 2? If it has been describe is use.
.
This is a famous problem know as Huffman close
labeling and there is a well know
algorithm call Waltz algorithm which is some
were like is A C 2, one more less, so it is
not officially called like that. So, let me
first describe the problem, the problem is
for
scene labeling and when you say seen labeling
we mean that we have a line drawing to
available to us and you must label it is essentially.
So, for example you have a figure like
this, so we will look at a variation which
talks of simple figures though Waltz algorithm
actually applies to more complex figures the
simple figure that we will talk about a
trihedral which have 3 faces.
So, each vertices has 3 faces and faces of
planer, so any object which is made up of
planers, whether surface of planer and where
every edge every vertices is made up of
exactly 3 edges. So, all this vertices qualify,
so these are 3 edges three edges and 3 faces
coming to meet there, these vertices 1, 2
and 3. Then every vertices made up 3 faces,
such object are called trihedral object and
certain object, for example if I am able to
draw
something like this, if you can imagine this
over this let me object like this. You would
not be trihedral object even if equal to be
object, so anyway this is not a, cana of object
.we are dealing with and interested in these
cana of object.
Now, it is a labeling problem which means
you have to label every edge and labels are
as
follows, class labels for stands for convex
edge. Remember, we are talking about an edge
by convex, we mean that the matter or material
is inside, in some sense I would label this
edges plus because it is a convex edge. As
when seen from outside, minus edge is a
concave and I would label this and this edge,
for example as minus because it made up of
a concave, so corner of a room between the
walls and roof.
For example, these are out concave edges essentially
and various books used different
some people use notion fold and blade. But,
we will use the notion of arrow, either
pointing this way or that way we will distinguish
between them, but the general idea is
matter on right side. What you mean by right
side? That if we are following the direction
of the arrow the matter is on the right side
and the other side is blank arrows of whatever.
So, if I went to look at this figure matter
is this side, so I must label it this side
and like
this and so on. So, this Huffman close labeling
task is to label a line drawing with these
kinds of labels, in a more general case there
are other kinds of labels that we use.
For example, we have shadows, then if we have
cracks in objects or if we have more
than 4, 3 edges, 3 phases meeting at vertex.
So, all kinds of edges in be there and they
could be other kinds of labels, but for this
very simple class of object which is trihedral
objects which are made up of planer where
each vertex made up of 3 faces, there are
the
4 kind of objects we can use to label. So,
object in the task is to find this labels
essentially, now this space for this problem
you can see is that each edge can be label
in
4 ways essentially and we in vertices.
So, when we look at a line, the line, the
drawing like this, we can distinguish between
kinds of verities, one which we call is the
Y vertices which look like this, which is
made
up of 3 vertices which are looking something
like this. One, we sometime call as a W
vertex which look like this, one we call as
a T vertex which look like this, so this is
edges, so this is the vertex, but the view
point is like this. So, if go to seat from
here,
exactly it should look like a tea essentially
and the 4 is an L vertex where you cannot
see
the third edge, which is coming to that.
.So, for A, these are the only 4 kinds of
vertex that we can see and we are assuming
here
that these are generic views and these vertex.
You know it is not as if we have 2 objects
and somehow by placement of 2 object it is
looks like it is a straight line, we avoid
such
views essentially where the little bit of
align change of camera, if you want to call
it will
change the view. So, we assume these are cana
of generic views essentially and the task
is to label
drawing like this, so if you go back to this
original drawing you want to find
this set of label for this.
Now, any vertex with 3 edges coming to it
in principle can be label in 4 into 4 into
4, 64
ways, so, 64 plus 64 plus 64 plus 16. But,
because these objects are trihedral, we know
that they can be ladled in less than 4 ways,
so let me take this example this W vertex,
it
can be label as. So, I will label it from
left to right, it can label, this can be minus,
this
can be plus and this can be plus, as we can
see here minus plus and plus that is one
possibilities or it can be
matter on. So, let me just label it, it can
be like this as you can
see here this is plus this is like this
or it can be plus minus.
We have an example, we have one here this
is plus this is minus and this is minus, now
it
turns out that for this W kind of vertex,
these are the only 3 physically possible set
of
labels. So, from 64, we have broaden it down
to 3, can we, this information is the
question we ask in this labeling problem and
I will leave this is an exercise. This is
broaden down 6, this is broaden down 6 and
this is also broaden down 6, there are only
base of labeling base T joints and so on.
So, this T can be, for example part of a table,
so
you have a table and this is a leg or something
like that.
You could see a T joint here in which case
you can imagine this will be like this, this
will
be like this and this will be like this. This
is one of the 6 base and there are 6 different
ways you can label it T joint and it should
be a interesting exercise for you to try and
find
this out. So, how can be exploit this information?
The one simple piece, the one simple
pack we should exploit is at one edge can
be labeled only in one way at both the end.
So,
every edge has 2 ends it participates in every
edge participates in 2 vertices, so it
participate it must be label does a same in
both the ways.
So, for example, once I have label this edges
plus it means, it plus at this end it is also
.plus at this end, obviously it is same edge
essentially it is a simple trihedral object,
we
are talking about. Essentially, once I know
that this particular edge is plus here, this
part
is plus I have constrains on this part, so
I can look up a table for this out of the
6 possible
relations which of them has a plus in the
middle. What are the 2 other things on the
side?
So, I can prune the domain of that particular
those 2 edges exactly like we prune the
domains for arithmetic puzzles when we got
some valuable prune values for the domain
essentially.
So, what Waltz algorithm essentially does
is that it does a, it first does a scan of
this
entire set of 9, drawing it makes an assumption
that this is a solid objects which means
that was edge is are the boundaries which
means matter lies inside them. So, it can
start
up by labeling this then labeling this then
labeling this then labeling this and so on
and
then it does propagation. Essentially, that
once we have this outer label they will
constrain the inner label, for example if
we look at this place here it allow only a
positive
label to be given here because in the W joint
we have only these three are possible.
So, we are, fix this variable we can propagate
to plus here and this is plus you will see
that this plus, plus, plus is the one of the
queue combination that is allowed essentially.
So, this is the idea of propagation, essentially
once you know a value at some place you
propagated to the next one and prune the domain
for the next one. Exactly, like what we
talked about here revise the domain of the
particular variable and these up to waltz
algorithm does essentially. So, let me give
another example where whole same
satisfaction has been use as a mechanism for
doing something.
..
This example comes from, what we call is consistency
base diagnosis, so let me use one
standard example which we use in this thing,
let say we have a small device made up of
3 multiplier. This is M 1, this is M 2, this
is M 3, it takes to inputs, let us say the
inputs
are fix, so let say I 1 I 2, I 3 I 3 I 4,
I 5 I 6, it produces, each produces one output.
Let us
say this output is to an adder, and
this output is produced, spread to another
adder and we
have 2 values, here is a small device which
does something from add an addition.
So, multiplication combination consistency
base diagnosis is kind of also called as model
base diagnosis. So, model base consistency
base diagnosis got it says is that you
construct a model of the system and a model
that we build is a constrain model. How do
we do that? We say that multiplier is defined
as follows that if it is, then I will use
this
for implications sine output of M equal to
input 1 into 2. So, I am defining a multiplier
which works I, saying that if the multiplies
is then this relation must old which is the
constrain between through variables, 3 variables
of that M is equal 2 I 1 into I 2, I N, so
on.
For the others, we can define then we can
talk about the connectivity, we can say that
the
output of M 1 is equal to input one of a,
one in some notation we can say this. So,
we are
saying essentially that this output is connected
to these input and that is the express by
.this con this also constraint between 2 variables
that this value must be the same as this
value that is all we are saying. So, by we,
so we describe these 3 multipliers plus 2
addressing constraint like this, this is the
logic constraint is the logical statement,
this
implies this essentially we can converted
in to a constraint which this being a statement
some sort.
So, we describe the whole device by saying
this, this part tells you what the connectivity
is, this part tells you what the behavior
of individual component is, and between these
2,
we have describe the whole device essentially.
So, now what supposing we get this input
2 input, 3, here what do we expect? We can
predict that what this device will produced
is
2 into 3 is 6, here 2 into 3 is 6, here 2
into 3 is 6, here and then 6 plus 6, it should
give us
12 and should give a 12, that is the expected
output essentially.
But, what happens if O A 2 is equal to 12,
as expected this is the real value real constrain
or observation some people would call it.
But, anyway in the C S P notation, it is a
constrain and O A 1 equal to 10, now supposing
I give you this problem I H, what is it?
It is a constrain satisfaction problem where
these is the variable, in variable it is a
either
true or it is falls and this whole statement
is also in variable it is either true or it
is falls
which can be from the mathematics. So, let
us not get in to the details here, but there
is
basically a set of constrains which as description
of the aiders predicts, what the output
should be?
But, the system given to us is at the inputs
are these 2, 3, 2, 3, 2, 3, this is a multiplier,
this is a multiplier, this is a multiplier,
this is an adder, this is an adder, the outputs
that
you seeing is output here is 10, the output
here is 12. So, what is happening? So, this
approach to diagnosis the task have diagnosis
here is to identify of faulty component and,
so we assume that connections are never faulty.
So, this is a simplified, we have looking
at things that one of these either the multiplier
or the adder has become faulty. So, how
do we do this?
So, that is has a description level, we say
that this is a C S P, each of these, the 3
inputs
are variables, this is constrain between those
variables 3 inputs and a this multiplier.
So,
M 1, I 1, I 2 and O 1, 4 variables, this is
a constrain between 4 variable, so if M 1,
if the
.multiplier is the then the output of multiplier
should be equal to the product of the 2
inputs for the adder, then the multiplier
of the multiplier. So, I have these constrains
I
have the constrains that I 1 equal to 2, I
2 equal to and so on and I simply say give
me a
solution for this C S P.
What are the variables which are missing the
variables, which are missing are that? So,
I
know, I know the input variables, I know the
output variables, I do not know the
intermediate variables and I do not know whether
all the devices are working or not. So,
without going into to the details of how this
C S P is search and it is quiet a domain in
itself and there is a whole community which
does model base diagnosis, the idea is to
find the solution to this C S P.
What will be the solution look like? The solution
will basically say some of these things
of fault essentially for the C S P, P to be
satisfiable some device. Some component must
be faulty, some component, some statement
which says this component is must be faults
and that will be discovered in the solution
which the solution remember must contain this
at this output is 10. So, which means I making
a statement like 10 is equal to 6 plus 6,
that is what the adder is saying, so obliviously
this is the faults statement.
Now, whether the fault is with the adder or
whether the fault which is the 2 inputs,
because nobody, Y is told me that the input
is 6, the input is hidden from me, it could
be
something else essentially. So, is this adder
faulty? Is this multiplier for faulty? May
be
these two multiplier is a faulty, which possible
that these two a faulty, in such a way or
not that these two are faulty in such a way
that this is doing something and this is
undoing that and producing 10. What this is
doing? Wrong is being reflected here which
possible, so diagnosis of course there is
no clear cut answer to this question, has
to why
are we seeing this 10 here.
But, the algorithms are given towards finding
minimal diagnosis which kind of is a laser
that you must heard out the simplest solution
are the best which says that all though
diagnosis in which only component as faulty
is other preferred diagnosis. Then we can
see it must be A 1 or M 1 and the algorithm
actually find that essentially that either
A 1
is not or M 1 is not and that is why we are
seeing 10 there. So, what I wanted to show
.here was that this is the another example
where the problem can be as a C S P, N solved
has a C S P essentially, and this is problem
of diagnosis essentially.
So, I will stop with constrain satisfaction
here because we do not have too much time
left
in the course and in the remaining part of
course I want to look at knowledge
representations which is really a core of
A I. We should not finish and course without
acknowledge in presentation. So, next will
lecture will focus on logic as a language
for
representation and listening essentially.
Thank you.
.