So, we are looking at planning and in the
last class, we had looked at this language
call
PDDL very briefly we are talked about this
planning domain description language. And
we are looking only at the simplest version
which we can say version 1.0 which equals
to
the strips domain. In this simplest version
of the language actions are instantaneous
the
world is deterministic, the world is completely
observable, the goals are simple in the
sense that only goal state is look that a
nothing else. And the agent is only 1 whose
changing the world, but we took the first
steps towards rejoining. A when we if starts
talking about the language like this planning
domain description language. We are
talking about representation how to represent
domains how to represent actions? So
typically if you will look at the periodical
document you would say they who start of the
defining domain.
So, the domain that we are looking at is the
blocks world domain so you would say
domain name is blocks world the predicates
or on table holding. And all those predicates
and some of the actions we saw. So, let me
the couple of the actions
stack
x on y and the
.pre conditions are thus set of predicates
which must hold further action to be applicable.
And the p conditions first stack was on x
y then clear y and arm empty. So a is stands
for
arm empty will use the short form. So, if
x is on y so of x and y have variables here
in
the operate us, but when we actually talk
about domain they will get bound to constance
which stand for specific blocks like a and
b and c and so on. So, if x is on y and y
is sorry
somebody should a point of this off. It should
be holding x if a holding x and y clear then
you can stack x on y. And the effects
positive are on x y and arm empty and the
effects
negative are holding x and clear y. There
were one more positive effect which is you
can
add as clear x. This is not precisely that
the syntax with periodical uses, periodical
uses
less like’s intakes so everything is in
brackets.
And you say if x then positive effects then
negative effects are actually a continuation
of
positive effects with a not prefix, but will
use this simpler notation here essentially.
So,
basically operators or actions are represented
by these 3 kinds of things 1 is set of p
conditions holding x clear y for example,
and then the effects so what the effects?
Effects
are what are the changes that this operator
makes in the world if that operators in the
world executed. So, what we a saying here
is that stack x y is possible when you are
holding x and y is clear. And if you executes
stack x y then x will be on y the arm will
be
empty. Because you would have draft x some
sense and x would be clear and this will no
long be true that you a holding x and clear
y essentially. Similarly, we have define
unstack x y which is a inverse of this so
the pre conditions are on x y arm empty and
clear x.
So, if you x is on y and arm is empty which
means robot arm is not holding anything
remember we are talking about 1 arm robot
which is moving blocks around. And clear x
which means nothing is on top of x essentially
then the effects positive are holding. So,
you can see here there is a kind of a association
will that clear y and the effects negative
all these things on x y arm empty and clear
x. So, in this version I have add clear x
go to
effects here and there so if you add it here
universe as it in this also yes in that earlier.
So, as a say this is a simplest version of
period l or period l 1.0 on which actions
in sent
an yes and the other effects let we talked
about. So, just before you move on to the
planning of it us let me illustrate a couple
of riches language construct essentially.
.(Refer Slide Time: 07:00)
So, one thing which a richer language you
to apply is called conditional effects. So,
conditional effects are effects which are
which come in to force only if certain conditions
are true essentially. So, as an example of
conditional effects let say that you have
a
domain in which you are talking about moving
objects around and so on and so forth and
you have trucks and you have this kind of
thing. And you want to move let say 1 table
from location a to location b. And you define
move truck action which says the truck
goes from location let us say x to location
y. And the conditional affects of that a that
if
there is any object in that truck then that
object also moves from location next to
essentially. Or if you look of the something
like a briefcase domain, so if a briefcase
goes from location x to location y.
So, let us say you have bag that you carry
from department to hostel then if there is
a
book a conditional effect will say if z is
in briefcase then z goes to location y. So,
and
was writing it in sort of semi English, but
the basic idea is that the act of moving a
briefcase from location x to y has conditional
effect within the sense that whatever inside
the briefcase we will also get move to the
target location essentially. Of course, in
this
there is no sustain the effects are determines
stack an every action very clearly well
defined effects essentially, but that said
is a language. Another feature which a richer
language is have a durative actions which
are been explore quit a lot now a days. So,
as
we said in the last class strips actions of
periodical one action have no concept of time
in
world at all and that is, because actions
a in sententious.
.So, if you a taking up a object or putting
down a object was stacking in object and
stacking in object we just assume that it
happens in sent essentially. And then once
a
action happened it is the effects a seen immediately
essentially. But in the real world of
course, actions are not in sententious. If
you go from here to the hostel it will take
a
certain amount of time from go from here to
the hostel so that must be a taken in to
account. So, durative actions are represented
by durations or intervals so this is a start
of
the action and this are the end of the action.
So, for example, we consider this action of
going from here to the hostel then the actions
start at a certain time t and it has a certain
duration so there is certain amount of time
t
that is this action takes. Now, this time
t could be constant or it could be a variable
for
example, move action in the real world go
from the here to the hostel it will take you
minutes. You go from here to the department
it will take you 5 minutes you will go from
here to the gate it may take you 15 minutes.
So duration could be dynamic in that sense
essentially and so this is a start of the
action this is the end of the action. So,
the action is
define over a duration and such search planning
domains a called durative such actions a
called durative actions. And what you have
is that you have start conditions or lets
use a
term p condition at of you is using and then
starts effects.
And you have end conditions
and you have end effects so what will meaning
by this?
That let say let you want to go from here
to a lab on the department and we have defined
an action for that. So, the start 3 condition
as you should be here and may be you have
a
bicycle or something what is, whatever is
other 3 condition that we have here, what
are
the start effects? Start effects are the effect
which comes into play as soon as actions
begin. So, the moment is start going towards
the lab your are no long a here essentially.
So, that is a starts negative effect essentially
what are the end effects? End 3 end may
have 3 conditions so 3 conditional could be
the for example, this a lab is opened that
is
the lab is open at this point of time then
the action will execute correctly. And the
end
effects could be you could be inside the lab
or something like that. And then we have
overall conditions which have predicate which
was being true throughout the action.
So, supposing you are cycling from here to
some place then the overall condition could
be said that all points your cycle has enough
air. It is in so if the condition fails any
time
then the action wills no longer work. Now,
as you can imagine once you start working
about durative actions then things become
much more complicated. You have to talk
.about start effects start conditions end
effects end conditions overall effects, overall
conditions and so and so for. So listening
becomes much more complicated and you can
imagine that 1 action may be like this another
action may happen like this. And then
there are different kinds of relations between
these intervals that you have to explore.
And there is a well define study about it
Aliens interval algebra which basically looks
at
all the relation between which 2 time intervals
can have or 2 interval can have their does
not want to be time. So, this is for example,
saying that a second interval begins before
the first interval. Hence and you can imagine
that a there are many different possibilities.
They can happen simultaneously 1 can second
one can start immediately after the first
one or the second one can be contain totally
in the first one or second one can totally
contain the first one. So, in there are 13
such intervals and then there is an talks
about
these thing with a intervals we will not get
into to this here. The third that is often
introduced is found is like metric values.
So, these are numerical values which can take
different values and to take an ex to illustrate
an example here. It could be that inside of
bicycle let us say you using a motor cycle.
Then one of the things that you will need
one
of the condition that you will need is that
at all points you must have certain amount
petrol essentially. So, this metric values
would keep track of amount of the petrol that
you have in a your motor cycle. And it could
say something like if you have ex amount
of petrol at the start then at the end of
action you will have x minus some k amount
of
petrol. So, that is a end effect that is they
were abreaction and that introduces a third
dimension which is that of continues numerical
values essentially. But we will in this
course not look at these richer domains and
focus more on the basic planning which is
done using the strips periodical can of a
domain essentially.
.(Refer Slide Time: 16:08)
So, we had define something’s we at said
that an action A is applicable if thus anyone
remember the pre conditions of A so will use
this as a predicate. This stands of a
conditions of A so this basically stands this
set you is a subset of S. So we should say
applicable in state s. So, with this planning
as you will notice we have set of making a
gradual transaction into representation. So,
for we did things like search, but you do
not
bother about representation. Now, we a talking
about how to represent a domain, how to
represent actions and also we have keeping
the reasoning part in mind. And the
reasoning part is at least to start with will
be the same kind of reasoning which is
searching for solutions essentially. So, because
we have this explicitly representations we
can talk about this kind of rule conditions.
So, an action A is applicable in state s if
the p conditions of a all the subset of s
essentially. Likewise we say a goal so when
we say goal g we essentially mean a set of
predicates that we want to be true. So, for
example, today we look at an example may
goal is the following 1 A B and on B B. Let
a say hich stands for the fact that A is on
B
and B is on B in the blocks for domain. So
this thing is the goal essentially and this
comma is to be in it is and which means at
both the things must be true A must be on
B
and B must be on D essentially. So, goal is
basically a partial description of a state
that
you want to be in of the desire state essentially.
So, we say that the goal g such so let say
a state S satisfies a goal g remember both
of these are sets of predicates. A state is
for
.example, what is true in the world on A on
B on C whatever likewise goal is what you
want to be true in the world essentially.
So, use a word goal a satisfies a state satisfies
a goal g. If in the representation that we
have use g is the subset of the S. So, you
can see that this can be use to define the
goal
test function that have be reach the goal
or not. We are working its simple goals here
and
we want to see whether we have reach the state
which is the goal or not. Then this can be
used to test for that essentially whether
action a is applicable we can define a function
call progress
let say in a state S using an action A and
what this progress does is an a
takes a state s and applies they action A.
And gives you a new state explain were explain
as is on the last class this S minus the negative
effects of A union the positive effects of
A. So, we have a progress function which allows
it a move from one states to next state
essentially. So, we have basically the machinery
for doing state space search here we can
test whether than action is applicable in
a state on a not by using this applicability
test.
We can progress from the state to the next
state so in the in effect we have done the
move gen function. By if we just select all
the actions which applicable in the state
we
have the move gen function and then we have
the goal test function here which says that
you can test for the S on goal is not essentially.
So, forward state space search essentially
does the kind of the search set we have in
talking about. So, let me give you a so a
planning problem
is define by a start is as before a goal so
start s let us call it goal g and
a set of actions essentially. So, obviously
we have define the domain using a language
an
having define the domain in the define in
we have define the set of actions of the
possible domain. And a specific problem is
when we have define the starts at s a goal
say
g and the set of actions that a available
to you defines which can be use to go from
start
to goal; essentially. So, let us that is assume
that we have some simple domain.
So, we want that A B and D so let a say a
given starts it is the following A is on B
lets
say this is on the table. And let a say C
is on D and then E is on the table Ff is on
the
table. Some arbitrary starts seat I have given
so let us say this is a start and that is
a goal
say that you want to achieve which is that
A should be on B and B should be on D
essentially. So, again that we repeat that
is a goal is a description and the description
may
be true in many states as you can imagine.
If you just have this a on b on d then the
rest
of blocks will be available in any way and
as long as those 2 predicates on A B and on
B
B or there in the state. That state is the
goal says that is what you have said here
that a
.state S satisfies the goal g if g is the
subset of S. Now, we want to do this planning
and
we start with forward state space search.
Because that is ((refer time 23:41)) familiar
with.
So, how it forward state space search? To
gets is exactly like space search that we
have
to been talk to about so far, that given a
start state S. You can apply many actions
and so
inside of writing the actions let me that
the action was saying by using this arrows.
So,
this arrow says that I am unstack A from B
that is one action I can apply I can unstack
C
from D, I can unstack F from E, I can unstack
I from H is I can pick up. If you remember
there a 4 actions we talked about stack unstack
and pick up and put down. The only
different between pick up and unstack is it
unstack happens from another block and pick
up happens from the table. So, just we will
a says how to use different action and this
one? So, the move gen function in this particular
state would generate these actions 1 2 3
4 5 6 7 actions. And your first algorithm
will have to take one of them essentially.
Let
say it picks this action for some reason now,
what is the situation? A situation is that
this
rubato is holding this block K that say it
pick this action.
It is the now, holding this block K everything
else it is the change so how do we define
this new state? Define it by doing this progress
action which says that if I am doing this
unstack K J action I must apply this I must
remove the negative effects of A. The
negative effects of unstack that ex so on
by in this case x is K on y is J. So, K J
is no
longer true, on K J is no longer true; arm
empty is no longer true, because you are
holding K. And clear x which is K is no longer
true and then I must add the positive
effects of this action. The positive effects
of the action he has it has A holding it and
wise
clear. So, this effect would be present at
fact you have holding K and. Because you have
lifted it K away from this j will become clear
so clear j will be added to the state. So,
that
is the progress action that you have to implement
to get this new state K. Now, you can
see that having done this action these actions
are still applicable sorry actually they are
not. But they would become applicable the
moment arm becomes empty this moment is
arm is not empty arm is holding K.
So, you do only action you can do with this
one arm robo unfortunately super case some
were either put it on the table or put it
on the one of the block. From this we can
illustrate
by saying that from here the actions are either
put it on this are either put it either put
it
on this and so on and so. So, I will have
a clause a state space here it 2 difficult
to draw,
.but you basic you gt the basic idea that
you move from state to state. And whichever
state you looking at you affair the move gen
function which is looking for all the actions
which are applicable pick one of them and
move forward essentially. So, this
representation mechanism allows a rule of
overall search you have doing which was we
listen even name to it. We are not is that
given a name to this we have only set forward
stack space search, because we have not talked
about what does strategy is now you
could do that first search or you could do
or you could even do did or some something
like that. You could do anything that we were
doing here essentially so what is the
difficulty with this? What is the drawback
of forward stack space search?
If you look at this given start state and
that given goal state can you observe what
this is
doing wrong? And when you make this observation
you must keeping mind that you are
not solving the only the blocks whole problem.
We are writing this as a generic
algorithm of a our stack space search in which
we can plug in the domain with all it set
of action on a operators and all the predicate
it is not goal riven essentially. And in fact,
you look at the I properly drawn this like
this, because the 3 blocks A B and D that
you
want in the goal to be true or here in the
left hand side. And this right hand side is
actually will does not care not of course
the real world is like that if you are let
us say
planning for yourself what to do next? Then
if you what simply try to describe what is
true at this moment in IIT.
You would have 100 in 1000 of statements in
something who is there in the office, who
is there in the lab, who is there in the canteen
what is happening in this class is going on
their this class is going on 100 in 1000 of
statements. You would have and then you 100
of 1000 actions would be possible essentially
when we look at this particular problem we
can see that is no point in picking up A or
I or K or L or M. Because they are all go
on to
help us achieve the goal where as something
should be done on this part essentially. So,
the problem is forward stack space search
and this arises from the fact that state
description can be large, the number of applications
can be large is that there is a large
branching factor. The number of actions which
are applicable in any given state is thus
too many to we consider by a grout force approach
and that is true in any real world
situations value essentially.
.(Refer Slide Time: 30:22)
How do we address this problem? One approach
is heuristic search and that is something
you will again not explore in this course.
Because we do not have enough time and you
have most welcome to come for the planning
course you entrance it. And when we talk
of heuristic search here we are not talking
in a domain independent fashion. Earlier we
said for this 8 puzzle this is a heuristic
you can use of a blocks world. This is a heuristic
you can use you have number of blocks which
are in the correct place. And that kind of
staff, but we are we do not want to define
you the 6 domain dependent fashion. We are
interested in talking about domain independent
fashions. And the idea of domain
independent heuristic is to solve simpler
problems essentially. And the approach that
we
use in planning is to solve the, what we called
is the relaxed?
So one approach is to solve the relax planning
problem and what why mean by that? I
mean that if I am in a start stage S and I
have all these possible moves from these stages
that is call them S 1 S 2 S 3 S 4 S 5. Then
I solve a relax planning problem going from
this S 1 to goa1l and S 2 to goal and S 3
to goal and S 4 to goal and S 5 to goal. Look
at
the solution produce by this relaxed or as
the solution is call the relax plan. Look
at the
relax plan and see which is the cheapest relax
plan may be in terms of number of moves.
So, if S 2 is given in the cheap cheapest
relaxed plan then I will say I am going to
make
this move from S 1 to S 2 exactly like in
the heuristic search that we said earlier.
We said
that we will apply the heuristic function
to all these things and choose the 1 with
sees to
be closes to the goal. Except that here we
are literally applying us problem solving
.strategy to solve from each of this positions
to go to the goal. And the seeing which one
seen which is which one seems to be close
to the goal.
Now, the first question arises to that you
would ask is that computing the heuristic
functions should not be as expensive as solving
the original grout force problem.
Because that is the case and what is what
is advantages of grout basic function is giving
you in the heuristic function that here seen
so for the domain dependent heuristic
functions. We had said that it is a static
function you only look at a state and do a
computation of a value. So for example, you
do it leaden distance or as we set the
number of blocks and so on so they are they
were cheap. In this case, we same the relax
problem in a such a way that it is a easy
problem to solve which means computationally
easy to solve and when we say computationally
easy time. So if each of the, these states
can be solve can be foes as a relax planning
problem and it can be solve in palynology
time. Then we will just have now, K times
that time polynomial time will be able to
decide on which 1 to use here.
So, remember we at said that the even in this
simple domain planning is hard in fact its
p’s space complete which means it requires
polynomial space and time. And here we us
trying to say that we will solve a simpler
problem, but try to estimate which of them
is
closer to the goal. And notice that this is
being done independent fashion how to be do
this? The relax planning problem is basically
says ignore the negative effects of actions
and those are called relax actions. So, I
just ignore this part essentially and then
you can
see that if you that visualize this become
monotonic situation. You keep adding new
predicates to the start set you are not deleting
any predicates the complexity of planning
comes. Because you are deleting things that
you pick up K from J K is no longer on J
essentially. But if I am living on K J relax
plan then I monotonically increasing the set
of
predicates. And at some point I will get those
to predicates in said my said. And then I
will say have solve all the relax planning
problem.
So, it terms out you should take my word for
it that solving relax planning problems
when the effects negative effects are ignore
is polynomial time essentially. And heuristic
search essentially uses that approach. There
are 1 or 2 other ways to compute heuristic,
but we will not going that what you will do
instead is to focus on doing what we call
is a
back word search. We are already works some
exposure to backward reasoning we said
that ((refer time 35:53)) for example, (refer
time 35:36)) and goal trees that you work
.from goals back words. But they the representation
was tailor to backward reasoning that
we said that this is how you decompose a given
goal into sub goals. And then that is a
goals into more sub goals and eventually you
have trivially sub goals to solve. Here we
are not changing the representation, but we
want to back ward reasoning. So, we need a
few things know again we have to so this machinery
will no longer we have applicable.
(Refer Slide Time: 36:30)
We talk about something called relevant actions.
So we say an action A is relevant for a
goal g this is an some sense applicable actions.
In forward stack space search actions are
applicable in a given state in backwards search
back ward we use a terms stack space
search here again. Actions are applicable
to goal descriptions and we say that in action
A
is relevant for goal g if the following is
true let me write. If you the effects plus
of A and
g is not equal to 5 that an action has a effect
which is required in the goal to be true
which mean so what you have simply saying
is that the inter section of the positive
effects of the action and goal must not be
empty. It must produce something which is
relevant for the goal then we say action A
is the relevant. But is another thing you
want
which is that effects minus of A 1 must be
equal to 5. There it not produces any negative
effects which you want in the goal to be true.
Remember what does the goal is the set of
predicate set a want to be cube.
And you are looking for actions which will
achieve the goal essentially. So, we say that
an action A is relevant to A goal if the positive
effects of the a has something for the goal
.which means intersection was goal is not
empty and the negative effects of the a is
empty
essentially. So, we now, 2 predicates in a
goal and you can see that we 2 actions are
relevant essentially. And you tell me what
were the 2 actions? So I have moving from
goal to sub goal now, I am saying that if
I want this to be achieved and if this is
my last
action then I will achieve it. But only I
am use I am only using this definition of
relevancy essentially I am not any deep reasoning
here and just applying this test to see
what actions are relevant. Anyone wants to
venture against hazard against.
Student: Stack A, B
Stack A on B and one more is stack B on D.
Now, you can see the principle advantage
that backward stack space search gives us
forward stack space search is in the branching
factor. Because backward stack space search
is focus on the goal. It is only looking at
actions which will achieve the goal. And in
this example you can see the branching
factor is small we have only 2 actions at
we can consider and here they were many
actions at we were considered. That is a main
advantage of doing backward reasoning
((refer time; 39:52)) reasoning then we have
to talk about a regression. So, regress goal
g
with action A it means how do you refine the
sub goal? So he get g plain h g minus
effects of A, because action A is producing
those effects. We do not then to be clue in
the in the previous state or the previous
goals description union any one p conditions
of a
because that actions must be true in must
be applicable in the previous goal state
essentially.
So this is called regression and if you want
to now, over this you can see that I must
remove the effects of stack A B which is on
A B, but I would be left with on B D. And
now, I need the 3 conditions of those stack
action which is holding B. And clear D in
the
similar fashion for this cycle regress to
on A B is here
holding B clear D. You can go in
the stack B on D I am must B holding and D
must be clear. So that is why I added it to
the so I have moving backward from the goal
to sub goals in some sense and this is the
process I will search backward. The main advantage
that I am looking for is lower
branching factor, because I am only looking
at actions which needed from a goal to be
achieved. But there is a problem here every
one there is a problem like what is the
problem here? So, look at these second action
so if you visualize what you are doing?
You have this A on B, B on D and you are saying
that may last action would be to stack
.B on D. To if you try to imagine that you
will see that it practically impossible, because
he cannot be holding B when A is on B.
So, if you look at these 2 then they are inconsistent
cannot be true at the same time.
Moreover if I want to regress from here I
could say stack I could take any goal, I could
pick an action to achieve this goal which
is to stack B on D. I could pick an action
to
achieve this goal with which will be unstack
b from somewhere or pick up b from the
table. And I could cube the action to achieve
this goal and that action would be
unstacking something from D of course, unless
D is already true. But I can choose the
first one for example, I can say stack b on
d and when I regress so this I get those holding
B clear D and then the p conditions of this
which are holding
A clear it should be clear
B. So, I will have holding A and clear B and
this holding B and clear D come, because of
the stack B D action. Again you can see that
this is an impossible state which call a this
is not possibly a state whereas this is a
state it you can agree.
Because B is on D an you a holding A and you
about to stack A on to B that is perfectly
feasible. In fact it will be part of the plan
that you will be a looking at. This is not
feasible this says you a holding B and you
holding A at the same time and then you have
these 1 arm which is trying to do this essentially.
So, backward stack space search has
this advantage that we branching we get a
low branching factor. Because it is goal
directed, but it has a disadvantage that what
we get are not states essentially may not
be
states. Now, this progress action is sound
and by sound I mean it is close over the other
state place. In some sense is that when you
apply a progress action to a state what you
get is a state?
So, in that is sense its close a other state
place the regress action is not sound when
you
apply a regress action to a goal. You get
a goal description which may not necessarily
be
state essentially which may not be possibly
part of a state. So, for example, this is
cannot
be part of the state how can we having on
A B an also holding B essentially that is
not
allowed in the rules of the game you have
defined you have a one arm robo which should
be holding B. And then so because is holding
b nothing on B on top of B so this not
possible. So, how do we get around this problem?
So this is not sound
so there 2 things
you can do basically is when the will stop
this backward stack space search, when we
what you mean by that what is the test that
will you use.
.Student: 3 condition of the actions applicable
You terminate this when that g whatever prime
that we have is part of the start state.
Remember that you have regressing from 1 goal
to another sub goal to another sub goal
to another sub. If at some points you have
set of predicate which are true in a starts
set
that you do not have to do any more actions.
You are already home is not to speak
essentially so this is a condition that you
will use. So, you should verify there is possible
for meet to construct a plan like this using
backward stack space search, but this is not
a
valid plan. So, I can do a check for a valid
plan how to a do that? So what is a check
for
valid plan check for a valid plan takes an
as arguments a plan pie. Basically takes a
problem description and a plan. And the problem
description is a starts states and a goal
description and a set of actions.
So, which this input you can like a small
routine which will begin with a start states
and I
will not write the detail essential running
out of time. It will begin with a start set
and
keep progressing with the actions what is
the actions pies A 1 A 2 A k. So, the plan
is of
k actions you begin with a start set apply
the force action. And we have seen that
progress is a sound you will get a new state
apply the second action to that you apply
the
third action. And till the end you keep applying
the actions and then you see whether the
state that you reaches the goal set on not.
And you will see that if you construct the
plan
like this test will fail that it will say
the, this is not a plan why because. For example,
this
action will not be applicable at all, because
you will ever reach a state where you a
holding both these things together.
So, you can do the check essentially another
thing we can do a check for consistency
and
proven, because start state may have 100 of
facts. So, for example, here we have facts
about F and E and H and G and K there will
never be generate it in the back ward face
from there we will never talk about K and
J. So it will never figure in the goal
description see what will happen is that you
will say I want to stack A on B and I want
to
stack B on D. So, first I want to stack B
on D and then I want to A on B so stack B
on B
add to first pick up B. To pick up B I have
to remove A so it will remove A pick it on
the
table then pick up B sorry pick up C and remove
it on A table so that D becomes clear.
Then it will pick up A and stack on B then
it will pick up S and stack into A those will
never come.
.So, those in the starts it so that is why
this subset is necessary. This check for consistency
is basically just a moment. This check for
consistency basically proving set saying move
this state do not go back ward from here.
Or remove this state do not go backward from
here inset go along this ration. No as you
can see in the actual plan this will be the
last
section stacking A on B that will necessarily
with a last section. The previous action
must be to make this clue or to make this
the previous action must be or maybe it is
make
clear B true. Once B is made clear and then
holding A for that the action will be pick
up
A as you shall look at this carefully. You
have to first put a on the table then you
will
have to pick up a from the table. So thus
third last action would be picking up A so
there
are parts which are which will yield the plan
there are parts which are can be proven.
And then even if you do not have well you
have this final check. That after you think
he
of solve the problem just see whether what
you have produce is the valid plan or not.
If it
is a valid plan then accept the solution otherwise
continues searching essentially. And the
good thing about this consistency check is
at it does not have to be perfect. If it is
perfect
it will it will proven this state if it is
not perfect it own proved. It you may produce
a
series of actions and you will find it not
a plan and then you come back and try again
essentially. So, even if you have a in consist
in perfect consistency check it will sell
work
essentially. So, in the next class, we will
try as we keep doing all these time. To look
at
an approach which will combine the good features
of backward search and forward
search.
The good feature of forward search is that
it is sound that whatever acts sequence of
actions it produces are valid plans, because
the applicability test is the sound. The good
feature about backward stack space search
is that branching factors is a low, but the
bad
point is that it produces the poorest states.
This is not state at all it is a poorer state
and
we have to know do unnecessary extra work
to remove the states essentially. So, will
try
and see an a algorithm which will search in
a backward fashion like this and construct
a
plan in a forward fashion like that essentially
for this is doing is searching in the
backward fashion and constructing a plan also
from the last action backwards. This is the
last action this is the second last section
will soon which as you are seen is a not a
sound
process. This one is constructing sound plans,
but it is doing too much searches you want
to combined the 2 and will do that next class.
So, will stop here.
.