Genetic algorithms and we want to look at
GAs for solving TSP. So, as you know the
TSP of the travelling salesmen problem the
problem where you have to have
Hamiltonian cycle b in which you visit every
city exactly once and come back to the
original cities essentially and 1. So, for
example, if you have 9 cities you may have
representation which is that you start with
2. And you go to 4 and you go to 5 and you
go
to 6 and you go to 9 go to 3 1 7 and 8. So,
this could be 1 to a and since I am doing
JAS.
I may want to take 2 to us and try to see
how I can generate new to us after that? So
let
us I another to so let to say this is 3 7
some 2 to as have had mention this problem
earlier
that how do you now, device cross over operators
for the TSP problem? Because you
cannot do a single point or multi point cross
aver have for the simple reason that
supposing have what a do of cross over some
point then I 2 a would be 2 4 5 6 4. Now,
I
able to came back 4 which means I close the
loop earlier and so I come do a simple thing
like that.
.So they at 2 questions we want to look at.
One is that given this representation and
this
representation is called the path representation.
Because if all the told represented by
path and it is implicit that from the last
city in the path you come back the first city.
If
you means start with 2 4 5 6 9 3 1 7 8 and
come back to 2 if I rotated this by certain
all
would see the same to. So, that the 2 question
we want to ask is what the representation
to choose and secondly what cross over function
to device all for that would the TSP is
problemise we said which your very interest
many people, because it is got estimated
many practical application as will. And people
would like to good get good solutions of
TSP problem what about the valuation function?
As a simple function in this case which
given a 2 you can the order commutates cost
an you can use valuation function keeping
in mind that it is a minimization problem
that you want to minimize total cost. So,
you
have to work out the problem will it is for
selection in a care full fraction which I
inversely proportional to the cost how is
it to solve the problem?
Because a very of a you can find representation
and it help use all the problem very
quickly essentially. So, let me try out a
small game with you. So, the game is that
that
say you and I playing this game and we have
to divided this 9 cities between us. And we
get to choose city by city so forget of the
cost to a cost nothing to do here this is
the
different game. And the game is the following
they give choose a city and I choose city
then you choose a city and I choose a city
and so on. The first person to pick up 3 cities
exactly which is adder to 15 men’s again
so nothing do with that your cost just a do
with
city labels in the labels are 1 to 9. So,
how would you play this game? Let me say I
choose you choose something I choose 5 when
will be look at my representation so your
choose on what 8 I choose 5 you will choose
a 1 which will n1 that i to a chosen 8 and
7.
.I chosen 5 and 4 you on some of 3 city 15
not 2 cities.
Any 3 cities you pick up any 3 cities.
.You cannot choose 7 I would suppose game
we cannot 7 will start again you
start 4.
I choose 6
.. I choose 2, I already chosen 6.
.
So you choose 4, I choose 6 any choose 5.
.no 5 not 5
You set pick 8; you choose 8 then your forcing
will choose 3 anyway the point is not to
spend the whole class they in this game. But
discuss at that I do not know what can of
is
in your doing but, they can of is in I was
doing is shown by this figure. That I created
this you recognize this it is a magic who
some is 15 and what I was doing? I was playing
cross a cost I do not worth came you’re
playing something you a doing with. So, what
the point of the whole thing is the representation
of and helps solve the problem.
Especially if in some situation you have knowledge
related to some mapping that you
can create with representation. So, will look
at representation here also, ideally we would
like to have a representation in which I can
do single point cross over for TSP. But this
is
not that 1 an there is 1 representation in
which we can do single point cross over, but
will
come to that later. So, let us look at the
various cross over that people have tried
working
with TSP is a GAs and if you just look of
the were will find quite of your. Now, while
devising cross over 1 thing 1 should keeping
mind is at if should be nice if you can
.device cross over which would allow us to
carry forward good feature of 2 hours.
So for example, 2 hour have me features such
that some cities thing of cities which away
close each other are covered one by one in
that order. And that would be nice feature
if
in carried forward from 1 parent to a child
to be nice. So, let us look at some cross
over’s
so 1 cross over which is called partially
mapped crossover also call PMX workers
follows. That you choose 2 random points this
is p 1 and this is p 2 so a choose 2 random
points lets a this 1 and this 1. Let me choose
1 here then first you copy whatever is their
between those 2 points so you have I would
not draw the segment know 6 9 3 1 here and
9 4 2 5. So, this is parent 1, parent 2 this
is child 1, child 2 your trying bill. So,
first part
some part of the solution in this copy in
to the child is respective child.
Now, remaining the part solution I really
would like to get something from the other
parents. So, in partially max map crosser
mapping between this city’s 6 and 9, 9 and
4, 3
and 2 and 1 and 5 can use this us following.
Now, remember this see 1 which is got part
of the 2 a from the first parent and you on
the next from the other parents. So, you try
to
copy the less so what are the less? Remaining
is 3 7 1 and 6 8 so you try to copy 3 here
in to this so this is c 1 in this c 2.
We find to c 1 can we want to get things for
this is p 1 and hence p 2. We are try to know
copy things in to c 1 from p 2 so we are try
to copy 3 with 3 we cannot copy, because 3
already exists in this. So, what this appropriate
that follow the point from there so from 3
go to 2 and copy 2 here so we get 2 here.
This is the class of this possible operators
if
you let you a repeat this you are try to copy
this 3 here, but you cannot copy 3, because
already exists in this child. So, you follow
this point a from here and take 2 so you copy
to 2 here then you want to copy 7 here from
here that is if you copy 7 here 1 you cannot
copy so if follow the point at to 5 and you
get 5 here. Then 6 you cannot copy, because
is here the follow the point got to 9, 9 you
cannot copy, because 9 is here follow he point
at 4 an 4 can be copy it here. And that is
8 anyways with does not matter. So, this is
the
partially mapped cross over and I just illustrated
to this example and these the algorithms
for you to like. So, let me us repeat the
example this part of the 2 are is common to
the
parent. So, this c 1 gets this from p 1 an
c 2 gets this from p 2. The remaining part
of the
2 which is 2 7 5 4 8 it is got from this process.
The right to copy with 3 here, but I cannot
.copy 3, because 3 is already in might to
so a follow the point if from 3 2 this is
the
mapping that we a talking about partially
mapped process.
So, the mapping is between these set of cities
that you can instead of 3 you can place 2
so and this copy the actually both piece when
you do the others city you would do a
similar process. So, because I could not copy
3, because already there I go to 2 I am
allowed I can copy to 2 here than 7 I can
copy directly. Because the does not interfere
with anything 1 I cannot copy, because it
is here so I got to 5 and copy that. And then
4 6
I cannot copies of 6 I go to 9, but 9 already
here of 9 go to 4 9 get 4 here and 8 here.
So,
let us to the other 1 just complete the example.
So, I want to copy 2 here, but I cannot
copy 2 I go to 3 and I can am allow to copy
with 3 here than 4 I cannot copy here.
Because its sales I go to 9 I cannot copy
9 so I go to 6 I can copy 6. Then 5 I cannot
copy, because 5 is here I copy 1 here from
the mapping then 7 I can copy directly and
8 I
can directly. As this process as a given only
these 2 children from this to parents. The
keep into many device is crossover operators
is see that the resultant things at you have
are valid to us the and the whole idea is
try in device cross over which are valid to
us.
Another popular cross over to be slinks is
the order cross over. And it works as follows
that that like in this crossover you copy
first some things 6 9 3 1 9 4 2 5. And for
the
remaining part you take the slinks in the
order in which they appear in the other parent
so
what do I mean by that? That basically I want
all the cities to appear in my 2 out of this,
but I want to select them from the second
parent now.
But I got 6 9 3 1 from the first parent so
in my first parent I already have for this
9 6 3
and 1 this 4 I already got and what this already
crossover is that for the remaining cities
which I want which is 7 4 2 5 and 8 I simply
copy them in the other in which appear in
the other parents. So, for example, I can
simply an added this in 7 4 2 5 8 how do can
this? 7 is here 4 is here 2 is here 5 is here
8 is here. So, in the order in which occurred
in
the other parent I copy them in to this new
child. So, this child is got have the 2 are
from
its first parent and the remaining 2 are somehow
it is got from the other parent with I self
good crossover not you should think about
this an may be .. Let us
say another representation anything of another
representation for the traveling salesman
problem. I mean this is the simplest representation
the past representation it tells you
.from which city to go to with city an so
an this is that self representation.
.
So, there is one representation which is called
ordinal representation
and another 1 which
is called adjacency representation. Let us
do the other 1 first and this works as follows
that I created representation for this to
find something 3 7 1 9 4 2 5 6 8 and it work
as
follows. That we haven index this is as index
in my representation and the value that is
a
told for each sell in the value that I would
go. So, you if i is a index which is one of
the
value. Then the value that I will tell is
the city that I will go to from higher cities.
So, if I
just look at this to this too is 3 7 1 9 4
2 5 6 8 from 1 I am going to 9. So, I have
9 here
then from 2 I am going to 5 I have 5 here.
From 3 I am going to 7 here, from 4 I am
going to 2, from 5 I am going to 6. From 6
I am going to 8, from 7 I am going to 1, from
8 going to 3 which is the first 1 from 9 I
am going to 4. So, this representation is
called
as adjacency representation this a different
representation of a too are
So, you got if how we got this representation?
So this is the representation of
with this 2 only same as this to its us senses
the representation is different. This choice
I
that I am going from 3 to 7 to 1 to 9 to 4
to 2 to 5 to 6 to 8.
This representation says that you tell me
any city and I tell you where to go from that
city. So, if you tell me city 3 where you
going from 3, so look at this index 3 you
say
.going to 7 where you going from 6 you going
from 6 to 8. So, if you see a 6 to 8, so
these a different is a called adjacency. Now,
every not every premonition is a legal
adjacency representation so let me given example.
Supposing I want to represent
something like this you go to 2 from 1 and
you go to 1 from 2 and so on. Now,
obviously, formation of number 1 to 9 I have
shown you formation the I do not care what
is the rest I am saying the this is not a
valid told. Because from 1 you going 2 according
to this is the index from 1 you going 2 from
2 you a going to 1 so already done know in
this cycle so it cannot to be part of a. So,
not so is my poser to you in the past
representation every formation in the value
to a in adjacency representation is not every
formation in the value to so is an in conscience
here I am losing out on some 2 hours
here.
So, if will member that in the past representation
if I what a located this representation
by cycle of any length. For example, I would
start with 4 2 5 6 8 3 7 1 9 then I would
get
same to our back which is the different formation,
but the same 2 hours essentially where
is every 2 are has a unique representation
in the adjacency representation. Whereas,
to be
may in 9 city to a you a start from any other
9 cities and that would be still the same
to
.. Now, given the adjacency representation
so again of will it as this is
the index can you thing of a crossover. Given
2, 2 as adjacency representation can you
know exploit this fact that you know that
from this city 1 parent is going to 1. So,
let us
to the other 1 in the other 1 you going from
1 to 7 from 2, 4 from 3 to 1 from 4 to 5 from
5 to 6 from 6 to 9 from 7 to 8 from 8 to 2
and from 9 to 3 S. I have this to 2 us in
the in
the first to this is p 1 and this p 2 the
different adjacency representation work and
of a
customer of at any think of.
Especially if you want to ensure that one
of the child is at least a better child better
than
the parents look as a 1 once simple crossover
operator it is called alternating crossover.
And we basically says that all alternating
cities you pick the parent from the you pick
the
next city from the different parent alternating
parents. So, choose from known parents so
that construct 1 2 so you choose let us say
the first so you a constructing lets a c 3
another child we choose the first 1 from p
1. So, this say you are going to 7 from 1,
we a
going to 7 then from 7 where are we going
to go 1 city says go to 1. And other city
says
go to 8 essentially from 7. So, here we cannot
choose 1, because if at know you can
.choose 1 in other problem we choose know
you cannot choose 1. If you go for 1 to 7
and
from 7 to 1 in you already in cycles so you
cannot choose 1. So, at this point you only
to
choose 1, but you are not to allow choose
1, because it is form a cycle you can either
choose other parent or you can make an random
choice so people if I both of something.
So, the basic idea in alternating crossover
is to try and choose as you construct that
the
parent from alternate all the next city from
the alternating parent. And if you cannot
then
you to result to some 10 of random process
any things next so either you can u use 8
here
or you can choose random process. So, let
us say we choose 8 here and than we say for
the next 1 from 8 you go to 3 choose from
the other 1 you put 3 here. And then from
choose from the first parent you 1 go to 1
so you go to 7 you 1 go to 7 so you choose
something random. So, you can see that neither
of them can come here, because if you
go to choose 1 here then you saying form 1
go to 7, from 7 go to 8 from 8 go to 3 and
from 3 go to 1. So, that is so cycle that
you do not want to form and for the single
reason
you we any way you cannot go to 7 from 2 cities
so you can put 7 there so you would put
7 random value here. You can the exchange
this idea in say the alternating you can say
subtour crossover.
So, thus as be selected subtour to here in
both these example you can say choose a
subtour from 1 parent then choose a next subtour
from the next parent an then choose
remaining from the first and so on. Also,
in say of the alternating cities you can alternate
subtour crossover you can exchange in this
idea. But the most in testing 1 here is called
Heuristic crossover, so let me write it here.
And what the heuristic crossover says is at
you first random a choose some city so let
us say you started city 6 or city 1 lets a
city 6
in another matter. Then for deciding as to
way to go from that city you look at the 2
toward if your chosen 6. For example, as a
starting point 1 parent says go to 8 the other
parent says go to 9 from 6 the heuristic crossover
says that take the short a of the 2 adjust
so 1 says go from 6 to 8 1 goes other says
go to 6 to 9. This one says the choose the
shorter of the 2 in this essentially. So,
depending on what the values are we will choose
the 8 or 9 in then construct the 2 of a from
8 other 9 in a similar. At every stage we
try to
choose where to go from that city based on
the distance to the next city and that is
easy
to do with this I, because you are now easing
in this fashion essentially. Try to do that
heuristic crossover with this and should be
quite difficult is an essentially. Because
this
.as the index representation it tells you
exactly that if you 1 go from 6 from city
5 what
are 2 parents in? Here you would at scan the
whole thing in say 5 from 5 go to 6 and then
5 from 5 go to 6 in this also.
.
So, the last one that you on look at is called
ordinal representation and it work as follows.
The let us take the first 2 an you just copy
here 2 4 5 6 9 3 in the ordinary representation
what you do? You just listen carefully to
this process you look at position, so think
of
this index this is 1 2 and so on as both.
So, this is the first city in a 2 a second
city is a
third city is a 4 city is and so on. You have
to a reference in this and is so less assume
as
the reference index simply this which is the
already in this cities name. So the first
city in
you 2 is 2 and that is second and the reference
index so you right 2 here. But your know
this from here reference here new reference
is the reference without the city 2 the next
city in your 2 are is 4 and its reference
is 1 2 3 so you right 3 here and we remove
that
from there. The next city here 2 are 5 and
its indexes 3 here we right 3 here again and
remove this from here. And next cities 6 and
its indexes 1 2 3 its again 3 next cities
9 so
remove 6 from here 1 2 3 4 5, 5 here we remove
that the next 3 which is 2 here. And we
remove this and 1 which is 1 an then remove
1 then 7 which is 1 we remover 7 and 8 at
this representation of the 2 are is calling
ordinary representation.
.So, just repeat what we are doing here is
that we have a reference index which is
dynamic which is only the index which have
the new cities the remaining cities.
Essentially we have all 1 to 9 so 2 is in
position to here so with 8 then we remove
to then
4 comes to position 3 then we remove 4 from
their 5 comes in position 3 remove 5 and
so on 1 we get this 2. As an exercise I will
ask to construct the to a ordinary
representation for the second 2 a as well
all lets to it know so 3 is in position 3
when we
remove 3 we get 7 which will be an position
6 and so on. So new I live it is an exercise
we to do. The interesting thing and this is
the exercise it I want to try would is at
1 to
represent 2 2 us using an ordinary representation
then you just to a single point
crossover. And you get 2 valued 2 us so why
do you like this single point crossover? We
like it simply, because it is very easy to
implement that is once you have a representation
the already do is cut of this thing at 1 place
and put together the cut race and new haven
1 new 2. But if you try to imaging words happing
here is at with is few different schemes
of representation they allow you different
says of crossover.
And for example, this adjacency representation
which is 1 of the most popular it allows it
you some form of heuristic knowledge we says
that from a given city you can makes
some in form choices to where to go next city.
So, even if you 1 not able to fill in the
parent from 1 of the 2 base on this whether
it is alternating crossover or subtour
crossover or heuristic crossover if you are
not able to filling from another parent. You
can say heuristically choose the closer city
which is the allowed and try to bill shorter
to us in the you are the ultimate go list
bill shorter to us where this presentation
does not
allow any such at all this presentation the
earn allow that. But it at is allows it do
a
simple crossover of essentially and remember
that is crossover as to be done in every
cycle for in every of parents at a choose
essentially.
..
So continue in our study of population based
methods. We look at nature again to get
inspiration from different way that the members
of the population interact with each
other. So, member, that we a said, that call
genetic algorithms some it action in genetic
level which is the process of recombination
at genotype level. So, recombination happen
as a genotype level where as selection . happens
of the phenotype
level. So, the such is happening at a micro
level the mixing of gens from 2 different
parents to come off with new candidates. And
those candidates fainting without in some
real the women training to serve I have essentially.
Now, there is the another clause of
methods which some people call as cultural
algorithms, because they involve high level
interaction between the agency at what you
my say is a cultural level.
..
And there are various names by which these
algorithms go so 1 is all swarm intelligence
and it is in quite popular as optimization
method in the recent pass. Even choose a term
ant colony of optimization and we will look
at continue looking at the TSP problem for
ant colony optimization. So, you must the
familiar with ant colony this ant colony was
a
terms which was use by . in one of this book
. the
very shows that an individual ant cannot be
a very effective feature in some sense. But
I
colony of fans all society of fans is very
successful in that task what is the main task
at
ant such trying do? There the building nest
that were there is the we and sitting out
they
an there is worker and who job is so go out
to in the world for verge in food and get
some food bag essentially. Now, in terms of
that am interact with each other to a process
of symbol essentially and this kind of interaction
called mimetic
is that 2 symbols 2 signs
ant symbol essentially. And is very common
in the animal world for animals for feature
to use symbol for examples you know animal
used to mark territory essentially dogs
another predators used to mark territory.
But these ants are using it know kind of cooperative
fashion and they want to used. They
want to convey were they having being to the
less of the ant community and they do this
by a process of pheromone trails. So, pheromone
is a chemical sentences which an ant
drops wherever it goes essentially. So, you
can a imagine situation in the real world
.where the ants are answer exploring some
piece an dropping pheromone on the way back
essentially. Now, how to the use is pheromone?
Either drop was themselves always
somebody else is that have a tendency to go
in a direction which as pheromone trails
essentially. So, it is like marking out pass
for each other and following the pass
essentially. So you can imaging the situation
where there is an ant nest and that is if
hypothetical ants go of in 4 different direction
in such of a food. And let us say this is
founds some sugar here some 4 it is found
essentially 1 some food as the end of the
trail
essentially. So, let us a why in this happens
after some time some more ants come out
and them what to the do? So initially 4 ant
spent out there after sometime 4 so let us
a 4
more just for the sake of the argument 4 more
ants come out then they likely to follow
the trails. Some goes this way some goes this
way some goes this way some go that.
Now, this ant which is found this piece of
food what was it do? Very unselfishly it brings
bag to the nest essentially so once it is
found this food it just follow its own trail
back
and goes back to the next and deposits a food.
But in the process if as tendency the trail
it
as deposited more pheromone on the way back.
So, this amount of pheromone on this
trail because more essentially. Now, if you
assume that that ant has a tendency to move
al1 pheromone trail in the more pheromone
there is in a kale the more the antive likely
to
following. So, the next ant which comes out
is more like to choose this selection then
in
your base directions and follow that kale.
And notice that once more and more ants go
along with trail more and more pheromone will
be deposited along the way and the kale
becomes strong and stronger. And eventually
after period of time you will find that this
entered ant colony is sub tour travelling
food and back essentially.
Hence it is a common pheromone you must have
absorb in the real world essentially. Not
only that if you go to put an optical in the
pass of these ants if you own experiment then
off course we cannot follow the trail. So,
this part the cannot full so they will start
diverting in different direction. But eventually
some of them will come back to this trail
or some of them may find different pass of
the trail some make come back to the trail.
And in the thing is that the ant switch come
back to this trail will do it faster essentially.
So, they will is establish of pheromone trail
faster than an ant with goals of wonders of
in
count pack. And this fact that ants which
happen to do things faster they live the trails
earlier. And more ants follow on that trail
can be seen as process of optimization,
.because they are so the fine in the shorter
paths shortest paths of found first. Assuming
the they enough number of ants in this environment
shortest pass will be found first and
they will be followed first in so on about.
In that sense you will see that ants for you
open fine go to task to the
to the source to the source of food an back
to the essentially.
.
Now, there was is group of miss chest that
by DORIGO at an who device is all go set up
all will comes call an colony optimization.
And we look at it with an example of the TSP
problem. And the way that is algorithms works
is follows that let they we N cities and let
they we M ants. And we assume that is ants
kind of distributed randomly across these
cities. The basic process that we will follow
is at each ant constructs a tour in a greedy
fashion. Each ant constructs to a Grady fashion
and this will take N time steps because
the to a will have to have N cities. And each
ant also deposits pheromone we just use at
the pheromone again on the tour it constructs.
So, you can imagine that all these M ants
are there trying to find so all that travelling
salesmen problem try to fine the shortest
tour. Each an constructs a tour in a Grady
fashion and deposits certain want of
pheromone on the tour it is created. So, the
way will be look at tour is that we will look
at the amount of pheromone at the end of N
time units after each ants constructs a tour.
So, we will use T i j to stand for the pheromone
on the link from the higher city to this j
i
.city. So, this is city i this is city j an
than off course there is the other thing essentially
so
how much pheromone is on this? You will do
not by T i j and we will update it at every
N time units. So, if you know the tau pherom1
on time t you can compute the pheromone
at time T plus N after each. And this will
be updated as
some of the whole pheromone
that was let from earlier times plus new pheromone
which has been deposited by ants in
the last 2. And the whole pheromone that will
deposit in earlier times as the tendency
you operate. So, we will assume that some
of it will you operate so whatever the value
was at time T it we get you operate by some
value which is 1 minus let us a lambda
where lambda we will calls as a coefficient
of you operation. So, lambda tells you how
fast the pheromone you operates. If lambda
is high if it is close to 1 then you can see
that
none of the whole will remain if lambda is
low.
Then you can see that some of 2 whole will
remain plus the new pheromone that is
deposits and that we will call as tau i j
n let a say. We can say the incremental amount
is
delta tau i j at time t plus n let us say.
So, this is the incremental amount of pherom1
that
and so deposited in the last cycle and this
is for tremens of the whole pherom1
essentially an how much is this amount? This
is basically the sum fall i is equal to 1
to n
for each of the ants the amount of pheromone
deposited while in the k let use k here were
using i n j here deposited by the k ant essentially.
So, the total pherom1 deposited in the
last cycle is the sum of the pheromone to
deposited by all the ants and for each ants
this
term delta tau i j k would be either 0 or
little be sum value it to be 0 if that and
does not
have this i j h in h 2 an it to non zero if
it is it has i at in this 2.
So that 2 cases a 0 if ant does not tours
edge i j otherwise it is a value it is denoted
by q
divided by l k were q is sum constant that
we use control this own computation. And l
k
is a cost of tour found by is ant kin the
k ant essentially. So, the important thing
here the
way the this dapples from the real world situation
is at the amount of tour amount of
pheromone that an deposits on an edge is inversely
proportional to length of the tour. It is
found which means that the ant switch fine
shorter to us will end of the deposits more
pheromone on those i j is and I am switch
a found long to us will at the deposited in
less
pheromone. So, again we want reinforce the
idea that an sit of fine shorter to us they
will
encourage other and so follow that real essentially
and that why I will do deposit more
pheromone essentially. So, this is how pheromone
is updated at the end of every cycle
.now that lives is part of the Grady to a
construction how does and actually constructed
to
is basically simple stochastic process in
which an ant and looks at a set of cities
at it can
move to and moves to it in a holistic fashion.
So, let us assume that ant at a city i
moves to city j with a probability little
bit like what
we did in the simulated . which is the proportional
to the following.
The amount of pheromone on that edge that
it is considering raise to sum power alpha
multiply it by a factor which is called eta
i j is to power beta, so again alpha and beta
to
constant, if you control the influence of
these 2 factors. So, there 2 factors tau i
j is a
want of pherom1 on that which an eta i j is
called visibility. Basically it is inversely
proportion to cost of that edge. So, in other
words if that the adjust very if the if the
city j
is very close to city i and this eta factor
will shoot up. Because this is inversely
proportion to cost and then the ants so this
factors says that the ant is likely to choose
a
city which is close to the city i at which
it is.
This factor says the ants likely to follow
that to good go to that city on which the
pheromone trails is higher. And then they
a control by these 2 parameters divided by
sum
of all a city that it can go to so T i h is
to alpha eta i h is to beta were h is the
set of
allowed city and what you mean by allowed
cities? Cities which will not close a loop
in
is remember the, that ask at we a try to find
is complete tour the ants a so as at ask of
constructing a complete tour in a Grady fashion.
So, it goes of city to city and at any
point it only considers those cities as prospective
destinations which will not close to
.. So, essentially what this ants it doing
is sitting at this location i and
it is got is we a assuming a completely connecting
graph here the it as we do in the TSP
so it can move to any other city.
But we will only choose those cities which
first of all it has not already tour, because
you
do not wonder close the loop again so it cannot
go to city which it has already tour
essentially. So, these only set of allowed
cities and from the allowed cities we chooses
is
to move to 1 of them call j probabilistically.
And the probability is proportion 2 thing;
one is how strong is pheromone trail on that
h. And secondly how close that new city is
to the current city, because eventually you
want to find shortest pass. In shortest pass
is
always be need of it adjust which are short
adjust essentially so this is the ant colony
.optimization algorithm.
You have the set up ants each ant construct
a tour then base on the 2 it is constructed
each ant deposits a certain amount of pheromone
on every edge that it has moved on and
that the end of this whole process, we update
the amount of pheromone on every edge in
the graph. So, edges on which ants will travel
will have pheromone edges on which ants
will travel to fine short to us will have
more pheromone. And they will influence more
ants to follow, because of this factor on
those adjust. So, in the end ideally like
in this
situation if all the ants of moving along
like 1 caravan. In the TS also 1 would expect
all
the ants would be travelling 1 optimal to
essentially. And it would be a go to exercise
for
you to influent this an colony optimization
and see how man, how the ants out up
converts to the shortest to at least for small
problems you can we seen quite easily. So,
will stop here and in the next class we will
move away from this optimization. And we
go back to state space such and try to see
deterministic algorithms for fine in shortest
pass essentially.
.