Our space saving versions of a star and today
we want to first look at pruning the close
list. So, just to recap assuming that you
are working with a heuristic function which
satisfies the monotone criteria or the consistency
criteria we are worried about two things
1 is that as a community, now calls it stop
the search from leaking back. This means
basically just imagine the search frontier
being pushed out into the search piece the
open
node should not come back from inside the
search piece whatever what could have been
in the closed list.
Essentially, that is the first objective and
the second objective would be of course to
reconstruct the path. So, let us first worry
about the first objective is it how can you
stop
the search from going backwards. So, in 2000
or so Koror old friend who is been
working on this for a while and his student
Zhang.
They devise the salary sum which I will name
in a little while, but it work has follows
that imagine that you have this node x and
you generate its children; let us only look
at
the forward children. So, let us say we expanding
the search frontier here and let us just
.call them a b c essentially now what Korf
and Zhang suggested was that you store along
with these nodes. So, this is open this is
only be the new open, so with every node in
open you store it is parents list of its parents.
So, with a for example, we will store x here
with b also we will store x with c also we
will store x what is the idea the idea is
it this
list forms a kind of a list essentially.
This means that when we in turn were to pick
a or b or c for expansion we would not
generate those children which we have listed
in this list here. So, it is a very simple
mechanism for search to be pushed only in
the forward directions essentially. Now, for
example, if there was a y here which was related
to x and let us say this y also connected
to this c and b essentially. So, either point
when y was expanded then this x this could
come x comma y this also will become x comma
y. So, with every node in open, we
maintain a list of nodes which will not be
generated when that node is when this is called
with that node essentially. So, it is like
at abort list with every node essentially.
So, with this simple mechanism we can see
it has a effect if you think about this that
every edge is diverged only once while searching.
So, this edge from x to a is only
diverged in this direction or in other words
a back pointer is put only in this direction
a x
can never become a child of a x can never
become a child of b x can never become a
child of c and. So, when a is generated some
new nodes where we generated may be
even b may be generated, but x would not be
generated. So, that the children of a are
going to be these nodes. So, this is 1 mechanism
for stopping the search from leaking
back which means that, so let us say this
source is somewhere here and search frontier
expanding.
So, when we when we generate children of a
it will only be the forward looking children
after a if we generate b then a will not be
generated, but some other children of b would
be generated and the search will only push
in the forward direction. So, one task of
getting into loops is taken care of by modifying
the nodes in open list by them with extra
information as to which nodes should not be
generated.
..
A little bit later 3 or 4 years later, another
Chinese student Zhou working with Hansen
supervisor produced a different algorithm
in which they had a slightly different
mechanism for search from leaking back. Their
mechanism always follows that the set
closed is partitioned into 2 sets 1 is called,
the kernel and the other is called the boundary
and the way to distinguish between the kernel
and the boundary is that this has no
children on open. This is a negation of this
which means at least 1child; this is
remembered this is the close list essentially.
So, if I want to draw the close list if this
is a
start node then everything inside this is
on the close list and everything on this frontier
is
open.
So, the boundary nodes which are if I can
draw in this colour would be these nodes
which are which have at least one child in
open and all other nodes. So, let draw them
as
a numbers which has children which are all
on closed would be the kernel essentially.
So, they distinguished between closed and
open and the idea here is that when you
generate children of open you only need to
look at the boundary and boundary serves the
old function of closed which has to avoid
the search from looping essentially. So, if
a
child is present in the boundary, then you
do not generate it, otherwise you generate
it.
It has a same function of pushing the search
in the forward direction, so this boundary
layer this intermediate layer of nodes the
boundary layer and it basically stops the
search
from coming back any node will not generate
a child in boundary and the boundary list.
..
So, now let us address the second function
of closed which is to reconstruct the path
because
it allows us to reconstruct the path from
the start to the goal know how do we
how to Korf and Zhang handle this. So, I hope
this is clear this mechanism for pushing
the search only in the forward direction and
taking care of the first path because there
is
no looping which is going to take place taking
care in this case by modifying.
The open list allows only successes, which
are not in the closed, in this case why actually
storing a pruned, closed list. They will see
that this kernel is not necessarily stored,
but
the boundary has to be stored and the boundary
is going to be only the edge of the closed
essentially in some senses. Hence, if you
only store those then you can stop the search
from coming back, so let us look at the other
problem of how to reconstruct the path. So,
Korf and Zhang’s algorithm actually maintains
only the open list it does not maintain the
close list at all essentially.
..
So, the algorithm the search face that this
algorithm generates something like this, so
I
have this start list and i have this open
list. I have a gold node here and that is
all I have,
only nodes on the open observe that these
nodes are modified they store information
about what nodes I do not want to generate.
So, basically it has some extra information
for every node there will be a list of few
nodes which are tabor for it to be generated
as
children. Now, instead of closed what they
maintain is a layer of nodes another layer
of
nodes which is roughly like this and this
is called the relay layer
and the relay layer is a
list of nodes.
So, let me draw the relay with these numbers
this time and we will keep it for the relay
nodes only and every node on the open. So,
remember that I a star we maintain the
parent pointer that every node had a parent
which we would if necessary if we found a
better path around. Now, we are saying we
will never find a better path anyway, so we
do not need to worry about that, but we still
and the function that the parent pointer did
for us was to allow us to reconstruct the
path when we found the goal now in this
algorithm by Zhang and Korf. Every node on
open maintains a pointer to earn ancestor
which is in the relay layer.
So, every node will have 1 ancestor in the
relay layer and so on essentially, so of course
it is not pruning the close completely it
is replacing close by a another layer essentially
which is a relay layer essentially.
.It is pruned everything else essentially
now what it tries to do is that the relay
layer is
roughly at the half way mark I will just write
half way mark here. So, I am not writing
the details here we will give pointers to
the papers as well as you can refer to my
book
and I have described the algorithm there initially
when the search starts it, you do not
maintain any pointer or you can say figuratively.
You maintain a pointer to the source node
essentially an ancestor point know which do
not really have to, but at some point it decides
that a given node is at the half way
marked from the start to the goal essentially.
It says I will make this node to the relay
layer, so the first question is relay node
the first question is how you decide that
the node
is at the half way mark it does not have to
be exact. Roughly, at the half way mark you
look at its values what would happen at the
half way mark at the f value g and h should
be roughly equally. So, I will say g of n
is roughly equal to h of n if your function
is
good, then it will be closer to me equal if
the function is very conservative.
Then, it will end up setting up relay layer
little bit earlier than actually it is requires,
so
maybe you can have a factor or something,
but let us not get into those details
essentially. So, this is how algorithm works
it maintains one boundary sorry it maintains
1 search frontier or the open list and after
a certain point in the search it maintains
a layer
relay layer essentially. Initially, you can
imagine when the open is here there is no
need
for relay only when it has pushed beyond roughly
the half way mark which is here. It
starts constructing a relay layer and then
it pushes forward essentially, so that is
a basic
search algorithm no closed, but this thing.
So, you can imagine that when a child when
this node is expanded into these 2 nodes
then this will be deleted this node will be
deleted and the parent pointer would be pointed
to this essentially. So, it will it will pass
on the pointer to its children and so on,
so at
some point to the goal is picked essentially
at some point the goal is picked and the goal
will have some pointer to some relay node
here. So, when you pick that goal you know
what is the cost of reaching that goal and
the optimal cost of reaching the goal because
you know its g value because we are we are
shown that a star finds an optimal path. So,
when you pick the goal node you have you know
the cause of the optimal path to the
goal, but you do not know the path only know
is that.
.There is one relay node let us call it r
which is an ancestor of the goal node on the
path it
is on the path and it is an ancestor of the
goal node. Now, how what do you do you want
the whole path you want all the nodes which
take you from the start node to the goal
node essentially. All we have is 1, it is
like somebody tells you that if you are going
from
here to Delhi, then Bhopal is a relay node
or something like that I do not know what
distance is. Let us see that that you have
to go to you have to first go to Bhopal, then
you
go to Delhi and you will get the optimal path,
so let us first reveal the name of this
algorithm it is called d c f s.
.
The expansion is divide and conquer frontier
search, this will give you clue as to how
do
you reconstruct the path.
..
So, to reconstruct the path you make two recursive
calls
to divide and conquer frontier
search 1 call goes from s to r and the 2nd
call goes from r to you make 2 recursive calls
and what would that give you?
.
That would give you two more nodes somewhere
here and somewhere here then you
make 4 recursive calls from here to here and
here to here, so all of this and you keep
doing that till the problem has just become
an edge that.
.The next node is just a child of first node
essentially that a base clause when you
terminate the questions essentially. So, remember
that once you have solved the first
once you made the first call to divide and
conquer frontier search you finish with all
your
memory requirements. All you know is that
there is a start node there is a relay node
and
there is a gold node and then you making a
fresh call which is to a smaller problem or
roughly of half a size provided this is this
holds that g is roughly equal to h. Otherwise,
there may be a unequal number of size which
means a as you can imagine it is like
working with a unbalanced binary rather than
a balance binary you may do more work in
1 half and less.
In the other half, but as long as you can
divide it roughly half you will split the
work half
and half and you will keep doing that till
f eventually reconstructed the path the full
path.
So, that is why this name divides and conquer
frontier search, so this space requirement
of the algorithm is only to maintain the open
list or the frontier and a relay layer
essentially and that is all it needs to do
essentially. So, we are thrown away most of
the
close list and in the kind of problems that
we discussed the sequence alignment problems
it is close which is going faster. Then, essentially
open is only going linearly close is
going as quadratic of the size of the problem
what would be the complexity of this.
.
So, you can say that if the original problem
of depth could be sized solved with prime
complexity d whatever d is, it depends on
the function rarely. Exponential function
in
.general plus the extra work that you are
doing what is the extra work 2 into to f d
by 2
plus 4 into t of d by 4 of depth 4 depth d
by 4 and soon and so on till you solve this
small
problem of depth 1. Essentially, for some
value x into c of depth 1, so all that is
extra
work you are doing, all the extra work is
done to reconstruct the path essentially how
much is the extra work.
So, you can solve this
its multiplied by log to the base 2 from the
depth of the complexity
of td multiply take the log of that. So, if
the td were to be exponential in nature be
there
as to d then this would be d times 6 log,
so you are doing if you are finding a path
of
length then essentially you are doing d times
extra work. So, if the path is of length 50,
then you are having 50 times extra work to
reconstruct the path, but in the process you
are saving on space essentially let us see
what Zhou and Hansen do.
What they say is why do we breakup the problem
into half what is the rational for
breaking up the problem into half. Of course,
we know that divide and conquer strategy
says that if you break it up into half then
you can know solve it using this complexity.
In
this era of increasing memory available they
say that you should do this pruning of
closed only if you are running out of memory
essentially.
.
So, their algorithm is called SMGS and it
expands to smart memory graph search. So,
what do Zhou and Hansen do they say you just
learn it like a star do not worry about
pruning or something. You keep track of how
many how much memory your algorithm
.is using somehow and if you can at some point
realize that you are running out of
memory, then you prune essentially. What do
you prune you prune the kernel
you keep
the boundary because you need it, in fact
when you prune the kernel at that same very
time you convert this into a relay. So, initially
this algorithm is working with this layer
boundary layer and the open layer going neck
to neck open layer is moving forward the
boundary layer is just following it at some
point.
.
So let us say this is a situation this is
a boundary layer this is the open layer. So,
the
outside 1 is the boundary layer the inner
1 is the sorry the outside 1 is the open layer
and
the inner 1 is the boundary layer and whatever
inside the boundary layer is closed all the
kernel. So, your counter something tells you
that you are running out of memory, so
what do you do you prune the entire closed
and convert this into
a relay layer and search
progresses from there as before, so let us
say its con here. It is got another boundary
layer following it essentially, so at all
points a boundary layer just follows this
search
frontier because it needs keep the search
from leaking back.
Essentially, every time you generate children
of open you check on the boundary layer if
they are children or not and then this is
the area between this curve and this curve
is the
kernel which you have not pruned essentially.
Then, again some somebody tells you are
running out of memory, so again you covert
this into another layer. So, that is why it
is
called smart memory in the sense it is aware
of how much memory it is using and
.whether it is running out of memory essentially.
So, unlike divide and conquer frontier
search this maintains one relay layer roughly
along the half way mark smart memory
graph.Search maintains as many layers as required
it could be 0 it could be 1, it could be
2, it could be 4 depending on how big the
problem is and how much memory is available
to you.
At some point, when it finds the goal it would
have some path up to some relay layer
which they call as a dense path
and from this layer to another layer by a
mechanism. You
can workout it would have a series of ancestor
pointers which they call it as a sparse
path. So, in their terminology divide and
conquer frontier search has 2 sparse paths
from start to relay and 1 form relay to goal
in smart memory graph search if you are
solving a very large problem, you may have
a bigger sparse path. Then, of course you
have to make that many recursive calls to
solve each of them, so it may be the case
that
the first time around you make 5 relay layers.
So, from start to 1, 1 to 2, 2 to 3, 3 to
4 and 4 to 5, so you will make 5 recursive
calls, but
for each of the recursive calls is possible
because it is a smart algorithm. You may not
do
many more recursive calls because you can
imagine that it is close to what this memory
can tolerate essentially. So, it is a little
bit different from this in that sense that
its aware
of how much memory it can use and only prunes
kernel when it is running out of
memory. Remember that pruning kernel incurs
this cost of reconstructing the path
because once you are thrown away all these
nodes you have to do all this recursive calls
to reconstruct this path. You have to do recursive
calls to reconstruct this path, but here
you are not thrown away.
So, you just have to follow the back pointers
and you can just get the path from there,
so
depending on the how much memory available
this behaves in a mode smart way
essentially now. So, let us move on to now
pruning the close list essentially which is
the
work, in fact, carried these two groups all
over again, so how does one prune the close
list. What Zhou and Hansen showed and this
was around 2004, so it is not so back in
time compared to looking at.
..
They give some idea some which is called sounds
like a curious name, but you can see
what they are doing breadth first heuristic
search it is it is sound like contradiction
in
terms. So, the basic idea behind breadth first
and we are talking about pruning open, now
most algorithms which prune the open list
relay on getting some upper bound on the cost
essentially. So, compute U upper bound on
f of the problem that you are trying to solve
what is the maximum possible value that the
cost of solving the solution can be.
Essentially, how do you compute an upper bound,
one way is to use some ready
algorithm to try to find the solution.
So, you do some beam search with very thick
beam based and hopefully you will get
some solution it may not be optimal, but it
will give upper bound. Essentially if you
know one solution the solution can be made
the upper bound and that is a theme which
runs in too many variations of these algorithms
that we are going to see either as and
when you find better solutions. You reduce
the upper bound essentially and then what
they say is the following that if this is
your start goal.
This is a goal node and if you have a boundary
which is the upper bound well that is not
quite correct. So, the upper bound serves
as a boundary which means that any node with
f value greater than this value u you will
not expand. So, if you generate a child here
for
example, then you will never expand these
two children essentially, so that is the purpose
that this boundary is serving.
.So, we are only going to search within this
hypothetical boundary, which is determined
by the f value essentially. So, before expanding
a node from open check whether it is less
than u only then you expand it essentially
now if you want to do a star like search.
Then,
the open at some point would look like this
the node that you would, whereas if you do
breadth first search keeping this upper bound
in mind. Now, if you want to do blind
breadth first search your search boundary
would look like this. Assuming that you now
costs are roughly equal for every edge essentially
thus visualise the problem, but if you
are doing this breadth first heuristic search
which means you are guided by this upper
bound which you have generated by some heuristic
algorithm.
Then, your open is only going to be this much,
so this is a open for this algorithm and
basically empirically one can observe that
the size of open for this breadth first heuristic
search is smaller than the size of open for
a star which is roughly like this. So, this
should give a visual intuition, but this is
do not take it at face value, but it just
to allow
you to give an intuition essentially now another
variation.
.
This is to prune this even for which is to
keep it of constant width and you can imagine
the algorithm is beam search. So, beam search
and we have explode beam search earlier
is the variation of beam search in the sense
that you keep searching till you find the
goal
rather than hill climbing like beam search
where you stop. If you do not find a better
node here, meaning of beam search is that
you maintain an open list of constant width.
.Then, you search towards the goal now; obviously,
it is not complete
because you are
throwing away other nodes, see breadth first
heuristic search is complete. It will find
a
path for the goal but beam search go off in
this direction away from the goal and we
never actually give you a path. So, it is
not complete, so how can we make beam search
complete before we do that Zhou and Hansen
also gave us.
.
So, this is Breadth first heuristic search
and you can convert this into divide and conquer
breadth first heuristic search by using a
divide and conquer mechanism of which we are
by now familiar which means that along with.
..
So, in general if you want to draw this graph
you would have an open which is to be seen
like this followed by a closed not closed
a boundary layer which is just behind it.
So, you
can imagine the search you know progressing
in this direction and this open will slowly
get converted into a boundary and the new
open will move forward and also 1 layer
somewhere in between. So, this is a relay,
this is a boundary
and this is open, so if you
maintain this 3 layers of node you can convert
breadth first heuristic search into divide
and conquer breadth first heuristic search
and you will have to do the same mechanism
of reconstructing the path.
So, even algorithm which is not only saves
on open it also saves on closed because you
are no longer keeping the close you only keeping
the boundary and then relay layers
essentially exactly like what smart memory
graph search would have done. Now, you
can of course do the same thing with beam
search beam stack search. So, we will
visualise this
algorithm as a search tree because it is easier
to do it like that. So, just
imagine that this is a search tree that that
search same search algorithm generates and
we
saw this mapping.
Earlier, we assume that the search tree is
ordered, so the lowest heuristic values are
from
the left and the right and the highest at
each layer is ordered. So, that this is increasing
h
just for the sake of visualization we assume
that this tree is ordered by increasing h
values.
.In this case, the boundary that we are talking
about their given by the u upper bound on
would look something like this. So, you have
to think a little bit about this and convince
yourself that this is how a u value. Remember
that this side is values lesser than u and
that side is values greater than you and because
u is on upper bound on cause that we
have somehow figured out we know that we do
not have to search that part of the tree.
So, we have to only search this part of the
tree essentially because it is a heuristic
search.
We can now assume that since we assuming that
in this visualization the tree is draw in
such a that heuristic values are increasing
from left to right, so you can imagine the
heuristic search also progress from left to
right essentially.
So, the divide and the beam search is essentially
beam search in this space, first of all it
is a beam search. Now, the beam of course
start searching from the left node that I
have
drawn it in the middle just to show what happen
now beam search is incomplete we has
observed essentially. So, you can make it
complete by introducing back tracking that
a
little bit like what recursive best for search
would have done no we are not talking about
the backed up values just back trucking and
retry. So, if it runs into this upper bound
it
back tracks and try something backtracks and
try something.
So, something like back trucking behaviour
we want to stimulate except that keep in
mind that in this visualization which is actually
my own idea, you would not find it in
that paper this heuristic values are ordered
from left to right. So, it is like a on this
space
it is like doing that first search from left
to right, but how do we do this back trucking
in
how do we n practice implement that.
..
We do it by maintaining another data structure
called the beam stack, where at each layer
we store 2 values 1 is f min and the other
is f max and it is a open interval on the
right
hand side and close interval on the left hand
side. So, these two values are telling us
as to
where in this space you are searching, so
the value of f min is here and the value of
f max
is here. So, it tells algorithm which part
of the search space you are searching essentially
and this it does.
For every layer, we have f min these two values,
so what is that mean that if you are back
tracking and you are coming back to this point
in this layer you not found the solution.
You have to come back to this layer you want
to start a second search here, and then
essentially these are the value f min at this
level and f max at this level you go back
to
this layer and reset this value. So, let us
say this is 100 and this is 1 50 let us say
in some
domain you replace it with 1, 50 and some
other value whatever because we have the
open list you generate the open list.
..
So, you go back to this parent here, generate
the open list take children only whose
values are greater that equal to this 1 50
or f max essentially and construct a new beam
layers depending on something it could something
like 1 80 or something like that. What
is the initial value for this beam stacks
every value will have 0 comma u. So, what
is
beam stack is doing is it helping with the
back tracking process once you back track
to a
layer and you generate. So, you go to these
nodes, generate their children again, so again
which of those children do you want to now
explode, this beam stack will tell you that
you have already seen values up to 100 and
50 and look at value which are greater than
50 essentially f values.
So, generate only look at those values, so
depending on of course how many there are
this value could be 1 80 or it could be 1
90 or whatever essentially. So, you must
convince yourself that maintaining this beam
stack allows us to search completely in the
search space. So, of course it is very difficult
to visualize in this space, but in this space
which is on ordered h value it is easy to
visualize that the search will progress from
left
to right. If you can search this entire space
inside this view, your algorithm is going
to be
complete essentially and this beam stack allows
us to do that essentially, so this is called
BSS beam stack search and the next step.
As you can imagine is divide and conquer beam
stack search you can expand this you
what used to this idea of DC BSS means what
is this to this maintains only 4 layers like
.those divide and conquer breadth first heuristic
search. It maintains one open layer, one
boundary layer, sorry one boundary layer here
and some relay layer in the peak. It
maintains only these 3 things beam stack search
maintains all this everything which is
inside this beam. So, the question I want
to ask which i hope has occurred to you is
in
beam stack search you have the parents of
every node. So, you could go back to the
parent and regenerate the parent’s children
and take the next set of children in divide
and
conquer beam stack search, you do not have
the open layer.
You only have the boundary layer and you only
have the relay layer how can you back
track. Now, I hope you see the problem isn’t
it may be I am going a bit fast here just
because I am running out of time, how can
how can this search go here? Retry this space,
let us say the relay does not matter let us
say this also relay or something does not
matter
how can it go here and how can it do this
type because we do not have the parent of
this
relay node here. What is more we do not have
the parent of the boundary node we cannot
go back to it is parent and then this parent,
so this was a paper published by Zhou and
Hansen ICAPS 2005.
ICAPS is international conference on automated
planning and scheduling and for this
paper, they got the best paper award in the
conference essentially. So, it is possible,
so let
me ask I want to do, I want to stimulate the
behaviour of beam stack search which means
I will go down searching down the beam and
if I hit the boundary I will come back and
try something else. I will come back and try
something else trouble is if I throw away
the
close list or the parents, how can I come
back and try something else we have 1 minute
to answer this question the answer is that
you do not talk of going back.
You regenerate from the source again and so
suppose think you are at the ninth layer.
You want to back track to the 8 layer what
do you do you go to the start and generate
layers which children should pick the beam
stack will tell you that of all the children
that
you are generating which once are the 1s.
These are inside this beam that beam stack
has
this information, so you go to the eight layer
and then you can generate of course there
is
a extra work again back tracking 1 step would
have been just going to the parent and
then retry.
Here, you have come from the source all the
way to the parent and there from this parent
to the next parent again you have to go all
the way and so on. So, if have to back track
.you have this extra work, but as a result
of this if you do not covered to the memory
required by the beam stack which goes linearly
with it, but these a small value. Let us
hope what is the space complexity of divide
and conquer beam stack search, it is
constant you are just keeping three layers
of constant width, the open layer, the boundary
layer and the relay layer. So, here starting
with an algorithm a star which required
exponential amount of space, we have an algorithm
which practically requires constant
amount of space.
In this era of huge memory sizes, you can
keep the beam width as large as you can isn’t
it and it will work. So, I will stop here,
I believe professor Shri Chaudary is waiting
outside, He should be waiting outside and
with this we will end the search part of it.
We
will look at problem solving from the slightly
different prospective in the next class that
we meet on Wednesday, which is you know looking
from the goal towards the problems,
essentially how can you move from the goal
to the problem.
.