.
Let us continue with state space search, let
me just do a very quick recap, and then we
will continue from there. So, the state space
is a space in which made up of many states
where each state represent the particular
situation. And the states are connected together
by the moves you can make of the decisions
we can make. So, that if you are in a given
state, and we had defined this function called
move gen.
Which takes, n we will use for a node in the
state space. So, the state space is implicitly
a
graph I say implicitly because, it is not
available to us. It is not that the graph
has been
given to us. And we have to find a path in
that graph we have given start state, and
we
are given either a goal state or the description
of goal state. So, for example, in the river
crossing problems we had given a goal state
that everybody must be on the other side of
the river. But on something like n queens
here given a description of the goal state
it will
says that, place and queens that now, no queen
attacks any other. Either way we have
.given some idea about the goal state, and
then the search algorithm explode the state
space. And how does it searches the state
space it applies the move gen function which
is
neighborhood function which gives you the
neighbors of each state, and then you inspect
one of the neighbor and see if that is a goal
state that you entrusted. If not then you
generate more states and so on ..
So, this search state space search generates
a search tree. The state space is at graph
at
least simplicity it exists even though has
it with us. And the state space search generates
a search tree, and we saw that this search
tree is characterized by. So, we start with
some
search node, and then we go down searching
for the tree we had seen this before so;
obviously, every tree has two kinds of nodes;
one kind of node is we will call as we have
called as open. Open is the set of leaves
actually the set of leaves we call as open,
and the
set of internal nodes we call as closed.
The open leaves are set of leaves is search
frontier that is the set of candidate nodes
that
you have generated but you have not inspected.
That we can think of the search frontier,
and set of internal nodes is the memory of
past nodes visited. So, I will just call it
seen
nodes. We started off by saying that open
and close are sets, then because, you want
to
implement this using some algorithms we said
let us call them list essentially. And as
we
will see today list notation is not necessarily
I mean list structure not necessarily the
base
structure we will come to that little bit
of a while.
But basically the search space is the search
tree is characterized by these two let us
call it
as set or lists whatever, open and close essentially.
And just recap the algorithm we
extract. We had moved from storing only the
states to a pair of states, and the pair
consists of a given state, and the parent
state. The parent state is the state from
that given
state was generated essentially.
So, we have this node space we said that initially
open gets this pair of start comma nil. I
will just write the outline today, and then,
while open not empty. If it is empty then
it
will turn failure. When will it be empty it
will be empty only for finite state spaces
that
you would have ended up by inspecting all
the states. And none of them happens with
the goal state in which case it will be empty,
and then you can say that goal state cannot
.be found.
For example, in the eight puzzles I had pointed
out that the state space is actually
partition into two sets of states which are
connected to each other. Once set is not
reachable form the other set. If you gave
the state say it in one set, and the goal
state in
the other state then it would not be reachable,
and you would end up storing all
inspecting all the nodes reachable from the
start state and say that we know we cannot
solve that problem.
If open is empty then you return failure that
will happen at the end we will not try it
here.
Otherwise we get node pair as head of open
I will not write the details we did it with
a
little bit in the last class, and otherwise
you can look up the book. From this node pair
we
extract a node let us call it as n. which
is the first element of the node pair, and
we apply
the goal test n we apply the goal test function.
Remember the goal test function takes a
node, and tells you whether it is a goal node
or not. Somehow you implement the goal
test. So, move gen n, and goal test n these
are the two domain functions that we have
the
rest of the search algorithm that we are writing
is independent of a domain. As long as
summery provides with you move gen function,
and the goal test function you can use
this algorithm to solve problems in any domain
essentially.
You do the goal test; if it is yes then you
reconstruct the path. If it is no you apply
move
gen n. And you get some success you get this
neighborhood this node n, and to this you
do some filtering you remove the things that
you have seen. So, I will just say remove
seen there some function which will take the
output of this, and filter out things we
which are already existing in closed or in
open essentially. We do not want to generate
the same node again because if it is in closed
we have already seen it, and if it inspected
again we are likely go into loop. If it is
opened we will see it sometime because, it
is an
open anywhere no point keeping two copies
of it in the open. So, this move gen basically
removes moves from open, and close the successor
of n.
And then we have a function called make pairs.
Whatever remains after this filtering we
make pairs what is the pairs. This node we
take this node n as the parent of each of
these
nodes inside this. This nodes will look like
x coma n because, these all the children of
n.
.n should be the parent of these nodes, and
then we add this things to open or to the
tail of
open. If you want to be precise because, if
you remove the head we have not removed the
head here. So, actually we should add . but
anyway that is a basic
idea. And then we saw that there are two ways
of doing this; one is as the stack, and the
other as a queue. which means that you either
add the new ends at the head of open then
it behaves like a stack because, they will
be first once to be inspected. Because we
always extracting the node from the head of
open. And when it is a stack we saw that this
behaves like depth first, and when it is a
queue we saw it behaves like breadth first.
What are the characteristics of depth first
and breadth first? Depth first basically dives
into the search tree. And breadth first is
more cautious its set of plots through these
things. These were the two characteristics
of these two. You can say depth first just
goes
where it is nodes takes how to speak, and
breadth first stays to close to start space
essentially.
Then we had looked at the properties of these
two algorithms. So, we want to compare
properties on two features; one is time complexity.
Now time is bad for both by bad we
mean the worst case situation or the average
case situation. In the best case they will
find
the goals for example, depth first search
finding the goals state in this branch itself
in
which case it would find it in linear time
a breadth first must finds the goals state
somewhere here which is very close to start
state. And it will find it very quickly
essentially that is a best case.
On the average case, and the worst case this
time complexity for both is of the order of
b
is to d, where b is the branching factor.
And d is a depth at which the goal occurs
essentially. which were there was a little
bit of a difference the first breadth search
had
slightly moved time complexity then that of
depth first search it was only slightly moves
essentially.
This is something that we will start addressing
today a bit later it is a time complexity
we
saw completeness. And by completeness you
mean will it find the goal state or will it
find a path to the goal state if one exists.
And the answer in the case of breadth first
was
vocally yes in the case depth first it was
it is guaranteed to find the goal state for
finite
.state spaces not for infinite state spaces.
Because in infinite state spaces they could
go
some infinite loop or some infinite branch.
We will assume that we have working with
finite state spaces and will answer yes to
this.
But keep in mind that this is only for finite
state spaces only. Then we saw two more
properties one is space complexity, and we
found that space was good for depth first
because it keeps only it adds only consent
number of nodes as it goes down because if
the branching factor is b it goes down it
will add b nodes inspect one of them then
again
add b nodes inspect one of them and so on.
Adds b nodes which means this space
required goes linearly.
Whereas breadth first search will first inspect
the entire loop generate till then of all
those nodes. So, it will become b into whatever
the width of that was, and therefore, it
multiplies by b as if goes down deeper and
deeper and therefore, these goes
exponentially.
So, this was the plus point for depth first
search. But quality was the plus point for...
I
will just write plus here for breadth first
search. Because, of the fact that breadth
first
search only floats slowly into the search
space. At whichever the layer the goal space
goal load occurs it will find that path till
the goal load essentially which means it always
find the shortest path to the goal. And I
scope you have convinced yourself by
constructing twice examples if we have not
please go and do it essentially.
These are, this is what we did last time.
There two things we want to do today one is
try
to see if we can find an algorithm which will
combine these two plus points. And the
other is to tried address this time complexity.
Somehow, because you if you have an
exponentially time algorithm nobody is going
to buy it is essentially you can only solve
very small problems with it not problems of
significance size.
Let us first look at this is there an algorithm
did anybody give a thought to this which
will combine these two properties of depth
first breadth first which means required linear
space but, guaranty an optimal solution. I
take it you are not been reading my book yet.
Let us look at some variations of this all
the algorithms that we are looked at today
are
.blind search algorithms, which means that
they have no sense of direction they always.
If given a state space if this is a start
state and this is, and where ever the goal
state may
be in this state space the behavior of the
algorithm would be the same. So, that first
would go of in the direction back track try
something else back track try something else
and so on. Breadth first will go down and
down and down till it expands the goal could
be here the goal could be here or goal could
be this side it does not matter from that
essentially.
So, let me introduce one new algorithm or
two new algorithms. One is he will call depth
bounded. It says that variation on depth first
search, and the variation is that we have
put
the depth bound do not go more than twenty
steps go and go more than forty steps
whatever some depth bound we have put and
said. So, what have done we have cut of the
search here some level
and we had said that do depth first search
on this truncated search
space. What is the characteristic of this
algorithm? Depth bounded depth first search
it is
linear in space why because, it is depth first
search to start with its complete.
Who said yes? Why is it yes? What is meaning
of complete? We said that if there is path
see this depth bound is something that you
have imposed it is does not come from the
problem. The goal could have been some where
here you know, what is the depth one?
depth one says that it is like a . do not
go beyond this line. So, if
you find the goal within that, yes you will
get the solution. But if the goal happens
to be
outside that like here which could be somewhere
here, and find the solution.
So; obviously, it is not complete. But, it
is faced efficient because it is depth first
search.
Now, let us do a variation let us have an
algorithm in which we say depth bound is equal
to zero. So, this is new algorithm I am writing
we initialized depth bound to, and then we
say while goal not found do this algorithm
let us call this d b d f s. And let us say
this a
depth bound d b. So, let me use d b here also.
This is algorithm it takes an argument of
course, it takes a start node and everything,,,
but that we will assume is hidden or glover
whatever.
So, while goal not found do depth bound depth
first search with the bound d b. So, zero
.means you just inspect the start node one
means you go one level deeper two means go
two steps deeper in that, and then you say.
So, we have this put this in a loop. So, this
a
new algorithm what is this algorithm? Call
it is very well know algorithm it is called.
So,
I will write it here in case in either space
iterative as a algorithm suggests. So, this
call
this is call iterative deepening in every
cycle you increase a depth bound by one, and
then do a depth first search. So, iteratively
you deepen this bound to which you will
search. And because, we are doing depth first
search this is called depth first iterative
deepening which is popularly known as d f
i d. This is algorithm d f i d that. So, first
we
should understand what the algorithm is we
us doing a sequence of this depth bound d
f f
s starting with depth zero then going to depth
one depth two depth three and so on.
What is the property of this algorithm? So,
let us talk about will come to time complexity
in a moment let us talk about space, and let
us talk about quality these are the two
quantities we are interested. In here because
breath first gave us on optimum solution
guaranty the optimum solution good on quality
depth first was space sufficient requires
only linear space. What about d f i d? Space
complexity, when he says space complexity
we mean the size of open that is the convention
we have been following.
Same as d f s why for the simple reason that
it is d f s of course, it is not one d f s
it is
many d f s 's every time you do a different
d f s with a different depth bound,,, but
you
are doing d f s. So, space is linear. Is anyone
having a doubt about this? You should
clarify this at this moment itself it is just
doing a series of depth first search inside
every
cycle in this loop it is doing one depth first
search, but it is doing depth first search.
So, it
must be requiring space complexity of depth
first search which is linear essentially.
What about quality? Not completeness, does
it guarantee an optimal solution does it
guarantee shortest path there is depending
upon I have given the algorithm completely.
I
am asking the question that this algorithm
does it guarantee you an optimal solution.
What is a argument behind the this? Argument
yes answer any one willing to ask talk
about. Why does it? How does it guarantee?
The answer is, what is the behavior of this
algorithm? If you look at only the new no
it is now what is this algorithm doing it
is
going to re inspect many nodes. So, let us
say we have a search tree in which
..
We started s then in the first on we look
at only s. Then in the second on we look at
s a b
c. Then in the third round we look at see
this is d e f and so on. In this third round
what is
the order in which you. So, in the first round
it should inspect only s in the first cycle
in
the second cycle, it would inspect in this
order s
then s a b c. In the third round it will
inspect them in s then
a then d then e then f then b and then whatever
the child of b is
actually.
So, in the first cycle it inspects only s
in the second cycle does search only till
this step s
then a then b then c in third cycle it inspect
this s I have not drawn the complete tree.
But
s a then d then e then f then the children
of b then the children of c in that particular
order
depth first order. But now, if you want to
mark the order in which it first time visits
a
node then, you can see that s is visited in
the first cycle then, a b and c are visited
in the
second cycle then, d e and f are visited in
the third cycle and so on.
It the order in which it is visiting you nodes,
if you look at the order inside this red circle
you can that s a b c d e f s a b c d e f this
is the order of depth first search. And if
it finds
the goal it should have found a shortest path
essentially goal. Because we know that
depth first search in this order always level
order as you all also call it always find
the
shortest path.
.So, you has convince yourself I think that
this algorithm behaves d f i d combines both
the things that we desired which is that space
should be linear which was depth first
search and quality there you should guarantee
the optimal solution which breadth first
search. And this is actually giving it to
us. You might say that this is actually sequence
of
depth first searches as a masquerading as
a breadth first search.
Because, the behavior in terms of the path
that it finds would be same as what depth
first
search have done. And because the very first
level at which the goal appears this will
terminate we know that it has found the shortest
path. Any questions…
h.
What I written here is while goal not found.
And So, I have lost over some detail if let
us
assume it is a finite graph it is a infinite
graph it will keep searching. So, let us assume
it
is a finite graph then I will leave this as
small excise for you to discover that at which
point no new nodes has been added which means
if you just inspect the next layer if
there is no new node. Then you have inspected
the complete graph, if you inspected the
complete graph it should report failure. But
till that point it should keep deepening and
searching till finds a goals.
.as number of as a height of the tree till
goals.
It is not a tree it is not a tree it is we
do not know where the goal is that is a whole
idea
about the searching. We are in some space
and we are exploring the space by using move
gen function. And we were trying to find a
path to the goal. So, first of all we do not
even know whether a goal exists for example,
in that eight puzzle I may give you the
goal state as one which is not reachable.
And secondly, we do not know where it exists
at
what level it exists. So, the whole idea is
to search for the path.
You know this iterative deepening algorithm
they were devised in a chess playing
situation. And you know we saw when we looking
at the history of e i that chess playing
has long be fusion with e i people, and they
want to make the programs play tournament
under tournament conditions. And tournament
conditions for those of you who play
.chess know that you have allotted certain
amount of time for making a certain number
of
moves actually. So, the time available to
the player is fixed essentially.
Now, we will see game playing programs later
in these codes. But essentially they also
explore tree of some kind they can also explode
tree up to various levels of depth. The
deeper the explore it so, exploring a tree
basically means you make you explore
combinations if I make this move then the
opponent will make this move then I will
make this move then the opponent will make
this move and so on. So; obviously, this
analysis you can do to any level till the
end of the game in fact. But that is not really
possible. You do this analysis and then try
to judge which is good move to make.
Now, in chess playing programs if you are
playing under tournament conditions you
have to be a aware of how much time you have
essentially. So, iterative deepening
algorithms devised that situation that you
learn the algorithm. And let it go deeper
and
deeper as long as time allows suddenly if
the calling algorithm calling program knows
that time is running out will say tell me
the best move, and it will play the best move.
So,
we look at iterative deepening again all at
least we will mention it again we look at
game
playing algorithms.
Now…
..
So, you are saying why do not you do breadth
first search. But the reason we are not
doing breadth first search is because, it
needs to store this entire. See, what is open
list of
breadth first search? The open list is something
like this across this tree, and this is a
shape. So, the search plenty of breadths first
search. In fact, looks like this, and as he
go
deeper and deeper this is growing exponentially,
we know that the number of nodes in
the d essentially. So, we do not want to store
breadth to d nodes that is a reason why are
not doing breadth first search. So, we are
doing depth first search. So…
..
.Already visited but, what is the option availability
you. So, if you think little bit about it
you will see that see, I can see, what you
are trying to say, you are trying say that,
what
is the point of starting with s all over again?.
But, where do you start otherwise? In
breadth first search you would have inspect
you would inspected all these nodes, and
then you would have inspected their children.
They were the children they would be in
open. But here we do not have them essentially
anything. So, you need to give a little bit
of thought to it yes that is a common doubt
when we look at d f d f i d first essentially.
So, we are doing this extra work, what this
extra work we are doing? We are doing a
sequence of searches in which we are inspecting
the complete tree at every level. First up
to level s here then this whole tree then
this whole sub tree then this whole tree and
so,
on. So obviously, we are paying an extra cost,
is this cost worthwhile? What are the
benefits we are getting. The benefits, we
are getting is that we are getting linear
space,
and optimal guarantee solution guarantee of
optimal solution the extra cost is going to
be
the price that you pay off inspecting all
these nodes, which are not inside the this
red
circle again and again. So, s we are seen
here again we are seen it here again we are
seen
it here.
We have seen here we are again seeing it here.
B we are seen here this whole count is the
count of measure of time complexity of d f
i d because we are seeing all these inspecting
all this nodes. So, how much is this extra
cost, is it worthwhile? Is the question, what
is
your intuition? So, let me repeat in d f i
d, we search up to some level let us say this
level. We do d f d f i at some for some depth
bound we come up to here and then to
inspect these next level nodes, we search
this whole tree again including this for depth.
So, this shaded portion is the extra work
we were doing for inspecting this new set
of
nodes how much is this extra work. Is it high
or low? Let me just ask way simple
question. So, we have go back to our study
of trees and you might have done in data
structures of some other course.
..
Let me take an arbitrary tree of branching
factor b, and we will take a complete. So,
for
this argument sake we will assume that the
tree is complete which means the every
internal node has exactly be children for
the sake of analysis which is not the case
as we
know. For example, in the eight puzzles corner
when the blank in the corner there are
only two moves that you can do? Whereas, when
the blank is in the center you can do
four moves so; obviously, the branching factor
is not constant. But let us assume for the
sake of analysis that branching factor is
b and it is constant. So, that and this is
the
frontier that we are looking at.
So, which the set of as I said right the leaves
of this tree are the is the search frontier
and
the internal nodes i of this tree are the
nodes that we are visiting again for the sake
of
inspecting these l nodes. At any given stage
for this is a depth first would have done
depth first search just inspecting this l
nodes, what is d f i d is doing? It is inspecting
i
plus l nodes that is a extra work it is doing
the whole question is and depth is should
give
us insight into the nature of this monster
that we ..
So, let me give you an nice argument of course,
I am sure you have done this. In some
course, what is the ratio of internal nodes
to leaves in a complete tree? But, I remember
in mathematics professor k Joshi from IIT
Bombay had given a very nice argument. And
.you can visualize tournament which is going
on. So, since branching factor is b we will
assume that it is something like that say
100 meter sprint or something like that. And
at
any note there are b children. So, any search
thing can be seen as one game or one race
that you want to call, if it is binary I could
have talked about tennis tournament but, it
is
not binary it is branching factor b. So, let
us assume it is like a hundred meter sprint
and
b people compete in a heat. And only one selected
form the top essentially. So, that is the
nature of this competition.
So, there are totally l competitors and in
every internal node i what happens every
internal node is a heat. In every internal
node one out of b goes head and the b minus
one
are eliminated is actually. And in the end
of course, there is only one winner in the
end,
and all the rest are should I use the word
loser or we should say also run may be I think
that is a better word. So, if you give some
thought to that you will see that the total
number of parties’ forms which is l which
is a number of leaves i n a world tournament.
So, these are also called winner trees you
might have studied them somewhere, actually
is equal to b minus one into i plus one. So,
what is a argument for this? Of course, you
can give a proof by indexation we are more
mathematically inclined.
But this is this argument is just a tournament
argument it says that in every internal node
b minus 1 players are eliminated. So, if i
is the number of internal nodes then b minus
one into i is the total number of base which
are eliminated, which is of course, l minus
one and thus one winner who stands out. So,
the total number of competitors is given by
this and this gives us a relationship between
i and l.
So, you can write i is equal to l minus 1
divided by b minus 1 and then you can compute
l plus i divided by l which is the ratio that
we are looking what which is the amount of
extra work d f i d is doing as compare to
breadth first search. Breadth first search
would
have inspected only l nodes only this boundary
nodes d f id inspecting the entire tree it
is
l plus i node essentially. So, if you if you
write this. Plug it and do a little bit of
simplification you will see that this is for
large l d over d minus one appropriately this
the small factor somewhere with I will leave
out.
So, what is what are we saying? We are saying
that the amount of work which d f i d is
.doing as compared to breadth first search,
which negligibly more essentially. Just d
over
d minus 1 times more essentially, and that
is should not be surprising to you because,
this
is the nature of these breadths explosion.
That we have b is to d nodes here in this
layer,
and all the internal nodes are b is to d minus
1 by b minus 1.
So, if you ignore that minus one next say
for large or large branching factor you can
ignore that you can that l is roughly b minus
1 times I, which is also what we have
written here? So, the number of leaves as
you go deeper down tree is b minus 1 times
entire set of nodes that you seen before.
Anything you did before feels in comparison
to
what you are doing at this level. So, what
and that everything you did before is extra
work which d f i d is doing, it just re seeing
visiting those nodes again and again
essentially. And if you go through this argument
you will see that the time complexity of
the d f i d is not significantly more than
breath first search.
We had that seen that breadth first search
was a little bit more than. So, b f s to d
f s was
b plus 1 over b or something like that i do
not remember exactly, but I think b plus one
over b. Breadth first search little bit doing
little more over than depth first search,
and d f
i d is doing only little bit more work than
d f i d. And what is that advantage we get?
We
allowed using linear space and we are guaranteed
the solution. So, it is very nice
algorithm think about this little bit i want
to... Before we move on to this other question
of, how can we get around time complexity?
I want to address this question this thing
that we did.
Remove seen, what is remove seen? Saying is
that for every new child that you are
generated or every new node that you are generating
check whether it is already present
in close. Let us assume that we have simple
collection nodes and we do not have these
node pairs and. So, on let us just ignore
that for a moment. But we have collection
of we
want to check whether the given node exists
in closed. What is the cost of this? actually
or complexity are we paying a heavy cost for
simple checking whether we have visited
on node again. What would be an algorithm
for doing this? So, what is the task? The
task
is given a new node n.
And given a list of nodes which you called
closed which is the node that we had seen
.before, well I use the term list. But and
it does not matter whether n exists in that
set or
list or not. What would be the algorithm for
doing that?
.. in which we can store a is not having a
bit bit director in
which we can store. So, it would be order
one.
We will refine that in the moment. But if
treated list how would i do it. I would have
to
sequentially search which would mean it would
be linear in the size of closed and how
was closed going? As depth close remember
is a measure. So, that is why when we said
that when we talk about time complexity we
will appropriate with the size of closed.
Which means the number of nodes that we are,
what is closed? Closed is a node that we
already seen.
And we had said we appropriate it with the
size of closed and there we had made an
assumption that checking in closed is not
expensive. When if closed is going to be
expensive checking in close is going to be
self if close growing expansible then checking
in that will each of each time will take expansion
amount of work then, it going to be a
tuff thing correct. So, there is a i want
to make a distinction between when conceptually
we think of close as a list its fine as per
as the problem solving algorithm that we are
considering. But if you want to put on your
software engineer or programmer had then,
you have to be more concern about how to implement
closed.
So; obviously, set is not good idea anyway
sets you have to implement in some way or
the other, list is good idea because, you
will have to cancel the list. And we will
take a
queue from what she said can we do this faster.
I am not saying that we should make in
area of bit factors you should be bit louder,
and bit more confident when you make that
answers.
..
While a binary search we would assume that
the given set is a ordered set because you
need to have a this thing. But a hash table
is the perfect solution to this you must
implement closed as the hash table. Even though
we say it is a list and that can that is
.only for discussion purposes. But if you
are going to implement the algorithm then
close
was be a hash table, and we know that on the
average if you design your hash table well
if your hash function in nicely chosen. Then
it will give you average consent time there
essentially. We come to open again in the
little while. So, I keep talking about these
as a
monster and a beast. So, what is a size of
this problem? So, let me give you some idea
about this.
.
if you look at the Rubik’s cube remember
that b is equal to 18 and Rubik’s cube is
a
nice example where b is constant at any given
state you can make this 18 possible
different moves. 3 for each face, and there
are 6 faces if you had to search up to a depth
of ten which means you want to explore the
space up to depth ten. Then you would have
18 is to 10, and that turns out to be 3.5
into 10 is to 12. If you have searching for
the
Rubik’s cube that what will happen if i
make try all combinations of 10 moves that
can
do then you have to inspect what 10 is to
12 states essentially. And what is a typical
length of a solution any idea of Rubik’s
cube problem is it less than 10 or more then
10.
It is more than 10 most of the time if you
have to search for depth 20 this an let me
get I
have the number somewhere is 1.27 in to 10
is to 25 how.
Long does it take it to inspect 10 is to 25
nodes you know we do not have a good idea
of
.big numbers 10 is to 25, 10 is to 30 they
sound same to us. So, let us say we assume,
do
some very rough calculations let us say we
can inspect a million states in a second.
So,
we need 10 is to 19 seconds. Let us assume
we do not want to divide by 6 multiply
divide by 60 and all that let us assume that
a 100 seconds in a minute. So, we will have
10 is to 17 minutes, and let us say there
are 100 minutes in an hour then, we have 10
is to
15 hours. Let assume that there are 100 hours
in a day.
Then we have 10 is to 12 days how many days
is 10 is to 12 days let us assume that there
are 1000 days in a year is 10 is to 9 years
it is about billion years. If you had a machine
which could inspect a million moves per second,
and it had to explore up to depth of 20
according to this calculation it would take
you about a billion years. But if you do the
actual calculation, and I did it at home it
actually takes 40 billion centuries to inspect
10 18 is to 20 nodes.
Is 10 is to inspect 10 is to 25 nodes it take
about 40 billion. I will sure you are not
willing
to wait for so, long essentially. So, will
try an address this how and I said people
have
more recently written programs which will
find you the optimal solution in a Rubik’s
cube essentially. How do they do it essentially?
So, let us answering this question, how
do you attack this exponential time complexity?
Can you set of improve open that?
Essentially. So, we will do that in the next
class, and we will take a break now. And
when we look at heuristic search essentially.
So, we will take a break and come back in
about five minutes.
.