So, today we start with first technical topic
and that is
state space search. So, let me
begin by first putting this whole thing into
perspective.
..
I will just write this . these. So, we are
looking at one aspect of A I,
which we will call as problem solving. As
we said, there are many other aspects that
we
will not cover in this course for example,
learning or using experience or reasoning
with
knowledge. We will focus on problem solving
and by problem solving we mean that, the
agent is in a desired, is in some situation
and wants to be in some desired situation.
So,
given to desired situation and the task of
the agent is to make a series of decisions
or a
series of moves, which will transform the
given situation to the desired situation.
So, the task is to find these decisions, and
that is the task we will be addressing. Now,
in
general, there are two approaches to this.
One is the one that we are following in this
course, which is search. Our first principles
base approach, which means that, you have
some kind of representation of the domain.
And you simulate, what would happen in the
domain as the consequence of your decisions.
And then try to find those decisions, which
will achieve the goal that you are aiming
at. The other is knowledge based, in which
you
are trying to exploit knowledge, which has
been accrued by some means essentially.
So, in general of course, knowledge says derived
from experience, either your own
experience or somebody else with experience
and convey through in a form of books and
lectures and things like that or stories.
But, given the knowledge, we want to up exploit
.those techniques. The knowledge base techniques
themselves could be classified into
two kinds, which is memory based and rule
based. Memory based techniques try to
exploit stored experience directly essentially.
So, this area is also known as case base
listening.
And in fact, we have a separate course, which
will be offered next semester called
memory based listening in A I, which will
focus entirely on this approaches to problem
solving. And what the memory based approach
does is that it, stores experience and what
do we mean by experiences. Each case as we
call it is the pair, made up of a problem
description and a solution that work for the
problem description. So, every time is solve
a
problem, he could be a human being solving
a problem and put in the case into the
memory and so on.
So, every time is solve a problem, you store
the problem and the description and the
solution description into this case base.
And when a new problem occurs, you retrieve
the best matching problem description and
use or reuse the solution that was told along
with that essentially. So, that is the way,
. of using experience, that
is how, we learn many things for example,
how to make . or
something like that or how to solve some kind
of integral equations, whatever the case
may be. The rule base approach is on the other
hand, does not use experiences directly,
but realize on rules or you might say negates
of knowledge extracted from experiences.
And very often a rule base approach needs
a human inter mediatory to convert
experience into rules. So, the standard approach
that was forward an expert system,
which we is we talked about dendral and mycin
and prospector. These were rule base
systems and the way there they were built
was that so called, knowledge engineers went
and spoke to domain experts and try to elicit
from them, the knowledge that the use for
solving their problem. It could be diagnosis
of whatever the problem was and try to put
that knowledge in the form of rules essentially.
So, we have knowledge base method as
suppose to search base method.
And we will be largely exploring search base
methods in this course essentially. Of
course, it is not as a search base methods
or divide of knowledge, because we have to
.still model the domain. We still have to
create the platform on which this search will
happen. So, that extent we do need knowledge
for search base methods essentially. As
we move along in the course, we will see that
search by itself is not a very efficient
means of solving problem. Because, we will
see that, we run into something call ((Refer
Time.) explosion, that as number of possibility
that we have to explore with be
too high essentially.
So, very soon in fact, in the next week itself,
we will introduce some element of
knowledge into search. We will try to see,
how search can be guided by some kind of
domain knowledge and we call this heuristic
search, and the knowledge that we will use
is called heuristic knowledge. After that,
we will move towards standardizing
representation of the domain. So, I to when
we begin with, we will just make some ad
hoc assumptions has to how the domain is going
to be represented, because we will be
focusing more on search. But, towards a letter
half of the course, we will also try to focus
on standardize behave to representing domains
and you will see logic base approach for
doing that.
So, we will do little bit about logic representation
and listing as we go along. Now,
search can be of course in many difference
spaces. We begin with, what we call is state
space search. So, let us a topic today, state
space search essentially. So, let me show
you
this puzzle, which I might have spoken about
some time ago. So, you know this is a
rubrics cube. And it is for this six faces
and you can move this face or you can move
this
face or you can move any of this six faces
by multiples of ninety degrees.
And so that is a problem that you have solve,
what is the problem you have to solve that,
unlike these faces that you can see here,
which have mixed up colors, you want all the
spaces to have only one color. So, every space
should looks something like this. So, this
space is green color and if I can somehow
make rest of the spaces of one color then
I can
say I have solved the problem. So, the situation
is that I am given this rubrics cube as it
is
and the goal is to solve it, meaning get all
faces to have the same colors essentially.
Now, I am sure you must be familiar with this
puzzle, it was a device in the mid
seventies, late seventies by architect called
rubric. And it became quite a craze in those
.days; people would spend hours and days together
trying to solve it essentially. Now,
you I want to, first thing I want to do with
this is to highlight the case that, between
these
two approaches the problem solving, search
base and knowledge base essentially. If I
were to give someone this rubrics cube, who
has lots seen at before and ask that person
to solve the rubrics cube. She or he would
essentially do it trial in error, he would
try to
see, what to do with this and what to do this
and try to explore a sequence of moves,
which will solve the puzzle.
Now, this puzzle is interesting it looks simple,
because as you can see, if you look at the
top face, it has got three faces, the top
faces is solved, everything green here and
these
sides, cube let us are of one color essentially,
I need to solve the rest. The trouble is once
I have solved this top face, I can only move
this bottom face and there is nothing yet,
no
other movement I can make essentially. Remember
there are six spaces, I could have
moved any of those six spaces, if I am not
going to disturb this, I can move only this.
But, if I move anything else for example,
if I make this change then you can see that
I am
disturbing this faces essentially.
And in the process, if I am trying to solve
the rest of the cube, I end up disturbing
this
cubes that is why, this problem is an interesting
problem and has been given quite a bit
of a study. Now, how many of you know how
to solve the rubrics cube, only one, two,
three, it is, so some people at least. So,
noticed that the question was how many of
you
know how to solve the rubrics cube, which
means that, if I want to give you this cube,
you with virtually without thinking do a sequence
of moves within then the making this
solve.
So, you are exploiting these techniques, which
we call as knowledge base techniques
essentially. So, it could be there this knowledge
has been given to you in a form of set of
macro moves that to achieve this into this
corner, this is the sequence of moves and
that
kind of thing essentially. So, that is the
knowledge base approach, this very once you
have the knowledge, it is the very simple
way of solving a problem, whether trouble
is
knowledge has to come from some were. And
what happens, when you have a new
problem to solve.
.Then there is no knowledge to fall back on,
it is then that we need to take records to
search base method. So, we call search base
method, just first principle methods that
you
want, you do not have any carry over from
the past. You are a given a problem and you
have to model the problem and you have to
find the solution, we have solving the
problem essentially. So, we does not matter
what the problem is, you can take any
problem and we will try to solve the problem.
So, one of the thing that we want to do in
A I is not to solve the rubrics you by itself,
but
to find is problem solving strategy on mechanism,
which will solve virtually any
problem, which can be posed as a state space
search problem. So, what do you mean by
state space search, that I am given the cube,
this particular configuration of this cubic
cube is a state. The desire configuration
of the cube is another state and in between
there
are thousands of other states essentially.
.
And I need to find a mechanism. So, this state
space is the set of states. So, let us say
we
draw it as the set like this and I will use
S for a start state or the given state and
G for a
goal state. So, each of the anything state
and there are other states as well, some well
you
know, which we. Now, how all these, how do
we transform the start stage to the goal
stage, we have to have a sequence of moves
essentially. So, what are the sequences of
.moves in the rubrics cube? So, if I call
this is a top face, I can say rotate the top
by 90
degrees or rotate the top by 180 degrees or
by 270 degrees.
So, these three moves are possible on this
space, more than that you will come back to
the same stage likewise, three moves for every
faces essentially. So, 6 into 3, 18 moves
I
have, which I can transform this state into
a different state essentially. So, we will
model
this process as moves, which will transform
you take you from one state to another state.
So, in this case I have drawn 6 states. So,
if some problem has some 6 moves, you can
move in moves you can make in given state
then the graph would look like that.
Now, you can see, that the once you incorporate
this motion of a move, what is the
move? The move is something an action, which
takes you from one state to neighboring
state essentially. And even any state, there
is the set of neighboring state that you can
move to, that is define by the domain essentially.
So, we will assume that we have a
function called Move Gen function. It will
take a state as an input and it term set of
neighbors.
So, what we are trying to do is to separate
the domain from the problem solving strategy.
So, what I am telling you at this moment is
that, choose a domain and take this as a small
exercise that you should try out yourself,
choose some domain of interest that you have
define, how to represent the state and define
the move gen function. The move gen
function is the function in the programming
sense, that it takes as input a state and
returns the set of neighbors for that state
essentially.
So, that is one thing that we want, so let
us take another small puzzle. So, if we look
at
the A I text books, you will find that they
are sort of sprinkle with puzzles, because
puzzles are easy to describe, easy to represent,
well defined and you know, you can do
work with them. So, there is you might say
a younger cousin of this rubrics cubes, which
is on a flat, two dimensional puzzle, which
is called things like 8 puzzle.
..
So, we are 8, 15, 24, in fact, any n square
minus 1 puzzle. So, 8 is 3 square minus 1,
15 is
4 square minus 4 and so on. So, the 8 puzzle
in particular is a puzzle any must have seen
this, which is got 8 tiles that is why, it
is called 8 puzzles and these tiles have labels
on
them. So, let us said number 1, 2, 3, 4, 5,
6, 7, 8 and this is let us say the start state
and
the goal state could be something like 1,
2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, so I am not going the
tiles
state, goal state.
Now, in this puzzle I can have, as we can
see basically, four different kinds of moves
and
some people can to think of it as a movement
of this blank, remember this, so what is the
puzzle you can slide. So, there is a blank
square here, blank location here, you can
slide
this tile here or you can slide this tile
here or you slide this tile here, essentially.
And
then in the process you will create the new
blanks. So, for example, you could do
something like this, 1, 2, 3, 4, 6, I could
do this. So, this could be a move that I could
make and you can give a label to this move.
So, you can either say that you are moved
four to the left or you can say that, you
have
moved the blank to the right; they are just
equivalent face of saying the same thing.
So,
let us say that we call this right, which
means I have move the blank to the right.
And
then you can see that, I can have an up move
and I can also have a down move. So, I can
.generate three successes states for this
particular stage essentially. The whole question
is
how do you represent this, so I will not go
too much into that detail and I will ask you
to
choose an interesting problem, describe the
state representation and construct the move
gen function.
So, in this case the move gen function will
return this state and this state, so it will
return
a set of states. We will not give too much
of importance, so the names of this moves
at
this moment, but later when we talk of planning,
we will be more interest than that. So,
we are interested in the set of states. Let
me take one more example, which is well
known river crossing puzzles. So, you must
have heard about this river crossing puzzles,
which basically says that, in most puzzles
there is a boat, in which only two things
can
go it one time, and there is a whole set of
entities on one side of the river, and they
have
to be transport to the other side of the river,
and there are some constrains about what can
to go together and what cannot go together.
So, you must have heard about the machineries
and the . puzzle
there, three machineries and three . and they
have to cross the river
and the boat can take only two people, how
do they cross essentially. So, as a simply
version of that is the man, goat, lion problem.
So, what is this saying, this is saying that,
I
have some river and on one side of the river,
there is the man, I forgot one more thing
that is the cabbage. So, there is a man, there
is a goat, there is a lion and there is the
cabbage and there is a boat of size two and
only the man can rode the boat.
And the man needs to take everything on the
other side of the river, but he can take only
one thing at the time. And the difficulty
is that, if he leaves the goat alone with
the
cabbage, the goat will eat the cabbage, and
if we leave the lion alone with the goat,
lion
will eat the goat. So, he does not want that
situation, how can he get these three positions
across on the other side. You must have seen
this recent movie, which these some boy
and lion in a boat together stuck for across
the ocean.
So, obviously this is the very simple puzzle,
it is not hard to solve, though the question
is
not that the addressing here. The question
is that, how can we pose this problem or this
problem or the rubrics cube as something that
we can apply some general purpose
.methods to solve essentially.
.
So, our goal would be to do something called
our search should be domain independent.
The algorithm that we are going to look at
should not depend upon the domain that we
are trying to solve the problem in. So, it
could be the rubrics cube or it could be one
of
these puzzles or it could be a scheduling
problem or it could be something different
essentially. If we can abstract away from
the domain, then we do not leave need to look
at the domain and what do a mean by obstructing
away from the domain.
In our case, the first thing is to design
a move gen function for the domain, which
says
that given a state, this function should tell
me, what the neighboring states are or should
a turn the set of neighboring states to be
essentially. And obviously, when I say given
a
state, I mean there is some representation
of the state that you have to be concerned
with
essentially. So, how can we represent? So,
these of course can possibly be represented
as
the 3 by 3 array or something in that, and
it might be useful to think about it like
that, but
I will leave it for you to decide.
Let us talk about this problem, how do we
represent this man, goats, lion, cabbage
problem? So, the solution is simple I am sure
you know it, we should first take the goat
.then come back with the boat, take the lion,
bring the goat back, take the cabbage, come
back and take the goat. So, you know likewise
the mistake is in cabbage, all of these
puzzles have solutions, which are not so hard
to find, can we write a program to do that
is the question, without having to write a
programs specifically for this puzzle, can
we
write general purpose program still solve
puzzles like these essentially.
So, there are many other puzzles, the water
jug problem you are given a jug 5 litre jug
and a 4 litre jug or you have given a 4 litre
jug and a 9 litre jug, can you measure out
liters, these kind of problems essentially.
So, how do you represent this? So, I want
some
input from the class, some suggestion how
can I represent this problem? How can I, what
is the state representation and secondly,
what is going to be the move gen function.
So,
the move gen function will be obviously something,
which is operate upon the
representation that we choose. A three cross
two arrays.
Student: .
Why three, why not four.
.
.So, you are saying that, I have an array
like this, and this stands for left show,
this stands
for the boat and this stands for the right
show is that what you are saying. So, it is
an
array of what, because there is more than
one thing which is possible on each location.
Let us say, array of list show, so it is an
array of list essentially, by how do you write
a
move gen function. So, what is the initial
stage, the initial state is everything is
in this
square, why do we have two, why do we have
second row.
Student: .
Then you should have four I think. So, that
is when possibility I think, but when you
create a representation, you should also worry
about the algorithm that you write on the
representation, because very often represent
the choose, the representation that you
choose is helpful in sort of writing algorithm
for in our case, we are interest in this move
gen functional algorithms. So, let me make
another suggestion, which is that I have a
list
of two lists. So, a list of two lists, the
first list contains things which are on the
left bank
and the second list contains things which
are on the right bank.
So, I could choose that essentially. If I
choose that list then my list were look like
this G,
this is my given start state and my goal state
is. But, the question is how do I write the
move gen function? So, that is the thing that
I am trying to derive at, what representation
is goat and what is known. Now, how would
you write a move gen function for this
representation, you would have to first search
the state. So, this is the state
representation, you have to first. So, will
we have a make, made an implicit assumption
here, that the boat, we are not talked where
the boat is.
And we can effort to do that, because we make
an implicit assumption that, wherever the
man is the boat is there essentially, because
the boat cannot go by itself some were. So,
having made that assumption, which is hidden
into some were here, how do I write a
move gen function. I will first need to inspect
this representation, this list of list find
out
where M is and then copy something from there,
out cuts something from there other
along with M and take it to the other side,
something could be nothing also essentially.
So, which means I can go from this state to
this could be even successes state
.essentially. The question is how do I write
this successes state. So, I will not spend
too
much time here, but may be will, we will look
at one more possible representation. Now,
one thing that you would observe is that,
this second list is . we do
not really need the second list essentially.
If we know that they are these only four
characters around, the first list is enough
to tell us what the state is, so that is one
thing
essentially.
And what was the first list represent it to
represent the entities, which are on the left
bank
or something like this. So, let me suggest
another thing, which is that you do not
represent things which are on the left bank,
but you represent things which are on the
side of the board and you will also represent,
which side the boat is essentially. So,
which means inside of this, I would have something
like this. So, let us say I do not
represent the man; I am just trying to explore
different possibilities, I just say left G
L C
and this is my representation.
So, what I mean by this is, their boat is
on left hand side and which means the man
is
also on the left hand side and along with
the man, there is the goat and the lion and
the
cabbage all of them. So, the advantage I see
of this representation is at my move gen
function would be simpler, at least that is
what I feel. Because, it is going to be
symmetric, whether I am going from left hand
side to right hand side or right hand side
to left hand side, the operations that I will
have to do would have to be identical, which
means that I will delete some elements from
my list and create a compliment set, which
will be the new list essentially.
So, for example from this, I will delete G
and take it to the right hand side. So, this
could
be a move essentially or if I want represent
the same move, I will delete L. So, I have
taken the lion to the other side essentially,
it not a very good moves of course, because
the goat will eat the cabbage, but the state
space algorithm has to search through all
possibilities. So, we are trying to look at
that essentially.
I would leave it as an exercise for you to
try out different representations for this
and see,
and actually write a program, which will take
a state as an input and return the set of
neighboring states as an output. So, there
are three moves possible in this case. In
fact,
.there are four moves possible, the man can
go alone or the man can take the lion or the
man can take the goat or the man can take
the cabbage. So, it is the written this four
sets
as my output to the function and this move
gen function is a function which will allow
it
and navigate the state space.
.
So, I will apply the move gen function to
this state, I will get a set of neighboring
states.
I will go to the neighboring state and see
if that is the state I was interested in.
Otherwise,
I will alive apply the move gen function to
that state. And in this process, I will navigate
the state space, trying to reach the goal
state that I will interest than essentially.
So, this
general strategy that we are going to follow
is has a generic name, which is called
generate and test. It says generate a candidate
in when we says, candidate we mean the
candidate state and test whether it is a solution.
And we put this into a loop, and this is the
high level strategy that we are going to refine
over the next few weeks generated. Generate
a candidate and see if we that is the goal
say that we interested in our task is to explore
this state space in search of the goal state
essentially. So, will keep trying out new
states and seeing whether that is the goal
state or
not, how do we see whether there is we are
in the goal state or not, we need another
domain function and that domain function,
we will call as a goal test function.
.So, goal test will take a state as an input
and output either yes or no. It will tell
me
whether the state that I am looking at is
a goal state or not a goal state. These are
the only
two functions I need, which know need to know
anything about the domain at all. So,
once I have return this two functions for
a domain, I can practically forget about the
domain, I can I do not have to worry about
whether I am solving the rubrics cube or
whether I am solving this eight puzzle or
whether I am solving the this river crossing
puzzle, does not matter.
I have a move gen function, I have a goal
test function and I would not find the sequence
of moves which will taking to the goal test
and so, this is a very abstract problem
essentially. Incidentally, while we are at
the rubrics cube, only very recently and by
recently I mean in the last five to ten years
have search algorithms been able to search
for
optimal solutions of a rubrics of a problem
like this essentially. And by optimal
solutions, I mean the shortest, the smallest
number of moves that you need to make
essentially.
If you follow the message that somebody has
thought you would says, take the top layer
first, then make the second layer, then get
this bottom corners, get the bottom squares
and then get the orientation. So, these kinds
of macro moves, they will not necessarily
give you the shortest solution essentially.
So, they will solve the problem, but they
will
not give you the optimal solution. So, this
is something that we had also mentioned about
human problem solving, that we do not necessarily
always try to optimize things, as long
as we can solve the problem reasonably well,
then we are happy with the solution
essentially, which is where the knowledge
base techniques are so important essentially.
So, the move gen function was this would be
an interesting exercise. As you can see
there would be 18 possible moves for every
given state, corresponding to the 3 moves
for
each space, so there are 6 spaces. So, any
of those 3 would give a move gen functions.
So, we can see the state space for this is
quiet large essentially and whether I can
leave it
as the small exercise for you to see, how
many possible different configuration there
are
to these puzzle.
So, whatever done we have abstracted away
from the domain and our, we are only going
.to work with these two functions. So, the
algorithm that we will write now, you will
just
use this functions and do not worry about
what the domain is essentially. And what is
that idea that once we have design these algorithm,
then we can plug in any domain and
it will solve problems in the domain for us.
So, there is this generality about our
approach essentially.
.
So, let us if find this algorithm a little
bit and we will call it simple search one.
So, let us
work with sets for this moment, we have to
see when we generate this successes or
neighbors, we have to store there somewhere.
And we will store them in a set, which is
traditionally has been called as the opened,
open list or open set essentially. So, we
begin
by saying open gets start state. So, we put
the start state in the open and though the
following, while or instead of y it is say
true, remove, I am using the set union operation,
because I forgot one step and the step that
is going to be here is pick some
node N from
open.
So, let us call this N now, because we are
not only talking about the start state, but
of any
note that we pick from this list, this set
open. So, what is this, this refinement of
this
algorithm is s, I create this open set, set
called open, in which I put the start state
to begin
with. And in general, my algorithm says pick
some note, so we are calling it on note,
.because we are set of already started thinking
about these as a graph over which we are
searching.
So, each state is a note, take some note N
from open, test whether it is a goal state,
so the
generate and test idea. If it is true, then
we should return, we are found the solution;
if it
is not true, we will remove this N from open,
and add instead the successors of open or
the neighbors of the open to that. So, I will
keep adding things to my open list and keep
picking some elements from that test .. So,
that is the simple basic
idea we start of it essentially, what this
is . is a search tree will start
by criticizing this algorithm very shortly,
because this is by no means an interesting
algorithm.
But, it gives as a basic idea for what we
are trying to do, what this algorithm does
it
generate the search tree. So, one thing that
I should sort of clarify is that, even though
we
see the state spaces as a graph, because of
every move we can go every state you can go
to the neighboring states. So, every edge
is the move from one state to a neighboring
state and the whole state is a graph. And
essentially, what we are trying to do is to
find a
path from a start state to a goal state in
this graph essentially.
So, it is basic into the graph search algorithm
that you must have encounter then some
other in this thing. The only difference here
is that the graph is not given to you, that
nobody says that, this is the entire graph
for the rubrics cube for example and then
finds
the path essentially. You have to generate
the graph on the fly and that is done, that
is
what generates the search tree essentially.
So, we can visualize what is happening with
this algorithm.
Now, notice that, there is the very, I do
not know whether you can read this, pick some
node N from open, so this some node is there
N. A considerable amount of time would
be spent on refining this notion of some,
because it really critically depends upon
this
some has together your heading towards a goal
or not heading towards a goal essentially.
So, will spent some time on that, but as of
now, we will has say that, we are not specified
it, so you some criteria to pick a node from
open.
..
And so, what is the search tree we are generating.
We start with some search, the start
node S. So, we will use state versus node
interchangeably at least for now. So, search
node is equal to state, the same representation.
We will move away from this in a
movement. So, the first, the route node is
a search start state or start note and we
inspect
that node, route note what do you mean by
inspect, we apply the goal test function and
we see, whether that is a goal.
Because, sometime the problem may not need
anything to be done essentially you know,
it is somebody gives you solved cube and says
solve it, you will say here, it is solved
already essentially, you do not have to do
anything, but so you test whether it is a
essentially. So, we inspect the start state
of the route note. And let us say that, this
double
circle stand for deleting it from open. So,
what I am drawing here is open list, I had
S in
open and then I delete it, but I replace it
with some successors of S. So, my open has
go
now got four, four successors.
So, for example, in this situation I would
have added three successors, because of the
moves I can make or in this situation, I would
have added four successors. So, depending
on the state, some numbers of the neighbors
would be generated and they would be
added. Then my algorithm says, pick some node
from open, we have not specified which
.nodes. So, let us say we pick some node and
we generate add it successors two. So, this
is the general process that our search algorithm
is doing to follow.
We have this set of open nodes, we will pick
one from there and see whether that is a
goal node or not essentially. So, this actually
reminds me of this in a moment, green this
interesting story about Hercules and hydra
in Greek methodology. So, as you know, how
many of you heard about this story. So, Hercules
fighting this many headed monster
called hydra. And the problem is every time
he cuts one head of the hydra many more
appearance essentially. So, we can see, that
is what our search algorithm is facing.
Every time, you cut one head or one node from
the search tree, you get many more. So,
as you can imagine this, the open is set is
going and going and we have to find a way
of
solving this. So, he does not have to be this,
the next one could be, so this is let us say,
number 2, this is number 3, this could be
number 4 you are not specified, which node
to
take, we will do that in a moment.
Student: .
So, we will start criticizing . in a moment.
So, his question is what
stops you from going in a cycle. So, that
is in fact, the first problem with our search
algorithm, I would have about to ask you,
what is wrong with this algorithm and that
is
the first thing, which is wrong. And so, if
I take this for example, rubrics cube again,
I
can say make this move rotate right, this
right face by 90 degrees. Then what are the
moves available to you, out of the 18 moves
that are available to me, one of them is this
one, what if I choose this, then what if I
choose this, then what if I choose this.
Then I have got in the cycle essentially and
of course, you can imagine that there are
hundreds of cycles hidden there, I can just
keep rotating this that is another cycle or
many other things are possible essentially,
that is one problem with this. So, let us
first
address that problem. So, one way of thinking
about this search algorithms is to imagine
that, you are in a maze. So, you know . have
this mazes in olden
times were there is some. So, you are at some
corner and you can see four roads, you are
inside some building, you can see some four
paths going, you go to this path, then you
.see another four paths and so on.
So, every, so this is like a node and this
is like an edge. So, you move from here to
here,
you see more nodes, how do you get . of a
maze without getting lost
without getting into cycles. There is again
this are another interesting story from Greek
times, I do not remember who was this person
who solved it by taking the thread along
with . said that he will mark every path,
if you see the thread again.
Then he has he knows at his back to that,
something some state that he has visited before.
So, in terms of looping, what do we want,
we want our search algorithm.
So, if I am going to start this particular
state, I do not want to come back to this
state by
going through a sequence of moves. I have
to somehow prevent that, which means one
side waits this move from here, I should never
visit this state again how do I do that.
Student: .
Mark that state has visited, that is the simplest
way of doing it. And traditionally, what
we do is we introduce another list and well
I am, I already started calling with the list
. I will be calling with the list.
.
.Another set let us see and we call it closed
essentially. So, the algorithm is modified
as
this. So, this is simple search two, open
as before gets the start state closed as is
the new
this thing, which start with the empty set
and pick some node from open. So, the same
and the new step, which is add it to closed,
I can right it as a set notation, but anyway
I
am writing it in English. Then, so let us
say that note is N as before, if N, I do not
know
whether you can read this I should write little
bit more carefully, if goal state N then
return N that is what I am saying that returns
the state, else before add.
So, what should I add to my open know, union
what move gen N minus, anything in
closed. And let me prove upon that the little
bit and say even anything in open
essentially, because it is possible that two
states may be generated by the same
successors may be generated by two states
essentially, two different states essentially.
So, for example, I can start with this state,
then go this state, then go this state and
this
state would have generated. This state would
have generated the 180 degree move, where
I could have gone here.
So, it would have put it in open or not that
move let us say this one. So, let me start
again, at this point on my open list is the
270 degree move, which will bring the green
thing here. So, I have added it to open, but
I have made this move, from this move I can
make a 180 degree move, which will again bring
the green thing here. But, I do not want
to do that, because I have already added this
in the open list essentially. So, you just
think a little bit about that, from this I
will remove the set open union closed. So,
I will
not add any note that I have generated before
or seen before to open, my open will get
new notes essentially.
So, this will stop me from going into loop
essentially. So, there is this, if right
what if
move gen this, this thing does not add anything
new. Then I am also getting into a loop
or some kind essentially. So, I should have
a test here, pick some node from open, if
open has become empty then I should say, there
is no possible solution. So, I am not
adding it right now, but we will add it this
thing, how can open become empty, if we
have seen all possible states and the solution
state is not available to you. So, for
example, this puzzle that 8 puzzle that you
know, all the permutations of these 8 tiles
are
actually into two disjoint spaces.
.So, there is one graph, where you can navigate
from one set of state to any other state,
but there is a disjoint set, where you can
also move from one set to another set, but
you
cannot go from this set to that set essentially.
And that can be obtain with simplify you
know flipping to two tiles essentially, they
are in . stage you can
never get them back, likewise the rubrics
cubes. So, this is the tricks with some people
know you can take it out, take out this thing
and reassembled the whole cube essentially.
But, the thing is you can reassemble the cube
back in twelve different ways.
So, it is possible that, this particular set
of states contains my goal state, but another
set
of state does not contain goal state. There
is one more problem with this algorithm or
this
algorithm, which we will. So, I will stop
here now, we will when we come back, we will
look at what this other problem is. So, I
wanted to think about this in the mean while
and
when we come back, we want to look at this,
what is the second problem in this state and
try to address that. And after that, we will
look at the behavior of difference strategy
is
when he says some, what are the options available
to us and how do the change the
behavior of our search essentially. So, we
will do that in some sense in the next class,
which is after five minutes.
.