We will go over the logic of Dijkstra's
algorithm without writing code.
If you are an advanced student and
know the algorithm,
you can skip to the next lecture.
The basic plan is to start from node I and
progressively traverse
a sequence of notes.
When the method attempts to choose
the next node to traverse to,
it chooses a node for which the total rate
of the path to that node is the lowest.
In the beginning,
the algorithm is on the start node I.
The distance from I to I is 0.
And the distance to all
other nodes is infinity,
because the system doesn't know them yet.
A second table, called a priority queue,
is currently exactly the same as
the distance row of the first array.
The system starts with processing node I,
the source node.
That means it finds the nodes
that can reach from I, F and J.
Note that the respective total weights,
that is 5 for F,
and 15 for J,
to get to these nodes in the distance row.
Then it marks I as done.
We have made the node I agree,
because the node is processed.
Next it looks at row d to find
the least distance, which is 5.
The corresponding vertex is F.
So next, the method traverses to F.
Now the algorithm on node F and
has determined that out of its possible
destinations, E, G, and J,
J is the least expensive.
The total path, that is the weight
of the path to J, is 10.
5 from I to F, plus 5 from F to J.
This diagram shows that the priority
is now shorter because it has
popped out the already processed load, I.
At step three, we are processing node
J but face the following situation.
We can go back to F from J, but
that will cost 10 plus 15, that is 25.
25 is worse than the cost of the current
path to F, which is 5 directly from I.
Thus we do not go from F to J, and
do not update the distance shown.
The other option is to go from J to G,
which incurs a cost of 10 plus 5, 15.
Hm, this does not improve the current
cost to reach G through F,
which is now at 15 already.
Therefore, we do not
update the distance for G.
So at this point,
we see that while J is processed,
it had no impact on
the traversal process.
We consider the distance row again, and
find that the next node to expand is G,
which is reached through F.
Continuing as before, G's processed.
It opens up the possibility of
diverging to C, at a cost of 35.
Or to D, at the cost of 25.
But wait, we have an issue,
there are two competing nodes,
E coming form F or D coming from G,
that are both expansion candidates.
At this point,
the algorithm can make a random choice
because there is no other information.
Let's say we make an arbitrary choice,
we expand to E next.
In an optional video, we will see
how we can use the additional information
to make a more informed decision.
After expanding to E,
we can find that we have already
reached the node B, so we are done.
The other choice, that is to go to D from
G, costs less than the path through B, but
it doesn't matter now,
because the destination is reached.
Just for the sake of completeness, if we
did let the algorithm continue to operate,
it will terminate when all
reachable nodes are reached.
We say all reachable nodes,
become some nodes like H,
are not reachable because
it has no incoming edge.
Such a node, as we said before,
is called the root node of the graph.
In general,
a graph can have more than one root node.
Now that we have reached our destination,
we need to construct the shortest path.
We start by taking the destination B and
find its predecessor, E.
Then we find the node E, and
check its predecessor, which is F.
Finally, we find the predecessor
of F to obtain I,
which is a source node for the task.
So these nodes can then be
stretched together in reverse,
thus building I to F, to E, to B,
which is highlighted in the film.
So, how well does this algorithm work for
big graphs?
Actually, not very well.
We often measure
the performance of an algorithm
in terms of the size of the data.
So, we saw that the Dijkstra Algorithm
has a very high worst case complexity.
Despite the high complexity of
the algorithm, there are several
practical improvements that will
enhance the performance of the method.
One of them is
Bi-directional Dijkstra Algorithm.
The idea is very simple,
we will go forward from the source now and
backward from the target node and stop
when the two expanding frontiers meet.
We will briefly illustrate
the process without going deep into
the details of every step.
So the technique starts just
like the regular method.
The control moves from
I to F at a cost of 5.
But then, it switches and
starts from the target, and
moves backward along the edges.
So from A, it comes to D or C.
We'll chose D,
because an AD is a least weight part.
Now the forward step is performed again,
and we traverse from F to G.
We are skipping the expansion
to J because as we saw before,
it does not contribute to the path.
So the total rate of the IFG path is 15.
The backward process
then reaches G through D.
The cost of the IFG is 15.
And the cost of ADG is also 15.
We stop because a common node is reached.
We need to ensure that the weight
of the forward path and
that of the reverse path are added, and
the total combined rate is minimal.
At this point,
we can concatenate the partial paths
to construct the full shortest path,
which is IFGDA.
Now one point to remember is that
the length of the smallest weight path
can be longer than the shortest hop path.
Here the FCA path has 2 hops but
a weight of 20.
But the weight of the 3 hop path,
FGDA, is 15.
So just remember that.
The final type of analytics
we'll discuss in this module
is called Centrality Analysis.
We call something central if it's
in the middle of a larger entity.
We also call something central
if it's important and vital.
For graphs, we'll identify important
notes by looking at how central they are.
In the graph.
Look at the the six node graph,
you don't have to know a lot
to figure out that the orange
node is pretty important, Why?
Well, one reason could be it's
the most vulnerable node.
If you remove it the graph
will fall apart.
because this is clearly one way to
look at the centrality of the node.
But it's not the only way.
Another way of looking at the orange node,
is that it can reach all other
nodes quicker, than any other node.
So this is the idea behind influences.
People in a social network who
are connected enough to reach out and
possibly influence a lot more
people than others will be able to.
If the little graph represents
a transportation network.
And you were asked to build a restaurant
somewhere around this network.
You'll possibly choose an area
near the central node.
Because more traffic will flow
through this node than other nodes.
And some of them will get
out at the station and
bring business to your restaurant.
We can give many more examples.
In biological networks,
house-keeping genes are genes needed for
the maintenance of basic
cellular function, and
are expressed in all cells of
an organism under normal and
abnormal conditions, these genes
are central because they're vital and
they're connected to many other
nodes in the biological network.
So much so that they need to
be taken out of the network so
that the rest of
the network can be studied.
Out of all these examples,
we'll focus on a kind of problem
researchers have called
the key player problem.
The problem comes in two flavors.
Now take a little time to
read the two examples.
The first is sort of a negative piece.
We have a network and we are trying
to find a small subset of people
who's removal will maximally
disrupt the network.
The key operative word here is maximally.
So if there is a node which removal
breaks the network into two parts,
it is not what we want if
there's another two nodes
whose removal will break
the network into ten parts.
The second case, however,
is a lot more conventional.
The goal is to find a small set of nodes
with maximal combined reachability
to other nodes.
That means, taken together, these nodes
should reach almost all other nodes.
You should know that
people use two terms to
characterize a general concept
of network centrality.
The first one, centrality,
is about a node.
It measures how central the node
is with respect to the network.
So the orange node in the left
graph has high centrality, and
the blue nodes have low centrality.
The second term, centralization,
is about the network.
Now look at the graph on the right,
where the dark orange node is still very
central for the light orange node, and
between the other nodes, and
therefore has reasonable centrality.
As more nodes start
having higher centrality,
the centralization of the network drops
because there is less variation in
the centrality values of the network.
So for each type of centrality that we
discuss next we can compute the network
centralization by considering the sum
of the difference between the maximum
centrality and the centrality of the node
divided by the maximum centrality.
There are thirty different
measures of centrality.
We will consider only a few of them and
explore the conceptual
principles supported here.
The first and the most intuitive
measure is degree centrality.
Quick measures, the degree of a node
divided by the possible edges it
could have if it connected to each of
the other N- 1 nodes in the graph.
Now, we have seen this before.
This measure gives us a sense
of the hubness of the node.
The higher the number is,
the more hub-like the node is.
Thinking of our second key player problem.
One way to approach this is to
find a hub-like measure for
a group with multiple nodes.
Instead of measuring the degree
centrality of individual nodes,
the measure simply counts the number of
edges coming into the group as a whole
compared to the number of outsiders.
In our example two red nodes here
together connect to all blue nodes.
Although there is just one
node neighboring both of them.
Closeness centrality takes a different
approach to the centrality problem.
It acts the shortest distance
of a node to all other nodes and
divides it by a minus one.
So in our graph, a node like I,
which is on the periphery of the graph,
will be quite far from
all nodes in general, and
therefore will have a very high
closeness centrality value.
On the other hand, nodes like F, C and
H are much closer to all other nodes.
Know that we define this measure
in terms of shortest paths.
So if a moving object, like information,
flows to the shortest path
in the network, F is more likely to
receive them earlier than other nodes.
And therefore can process into
other nodes more quickly.
Therefore.
If we look to inject a new piece of
information into the network with the idea
that it should read every other node
quickly, I should possibly inject it at F.
Recall however, that node information
flow is two shortest routes.
An example is gossip, that tends to
travel through centrality nodes.
Closeness centrality does not work well
for these types of information nodes.
Another very popular centrality measure
is called betweenness centrality.
For any node it measures the fraction of
shortest paths flowing through that node.
Compared to the number of
shortest paths in the graph.
Since B is at one end,
its between a centrality is 0.
But let's look at A.
A is in the path from B to E.
So is D.
Therefore, A's score for
the B to E path is 0.5.
Similarly, its score for the C to E path
is also 0.5, making the total score 1.
E is in the path from A to D,
for there is one more
path from A to do through C,
so E's score is 0.5.
Now can you verify why C's score is 3.5?
Betweenness centrality
is typically used for
problem where a commodity is
flowing through the network.
As in the case of closeness centrality.
Any quantity that does not flow in
shortest path channels like infection or
rumor on the internet doesn't work
well with betweeness centrality.
This lesson on graph analytics,
is about identifying and
tracking groups of interacting
entities in a network.
We call these groups communities.
Let's try to provide a more concrete
definition of communities in a network.
We multiply the definition
by this diagram,
showing a research study
on the Santa Fe Institute.
A theoretical research institute
located in Santa Fe, New Mexico, US.
They performed multidisciplinary
studies on fundamental principles
of complex adaptive systems.
The nodes in the graph are researchers.
And an edge exists
between two researchers,
if they collaborate with each other.
As you can see, there are distinct
groups among researchers.
A mathematically college researcher,
does not collaborate with researchers
who work on structure of the RNA.
So the graph,
is essentially a set of separate groups,
thinly connected through a handful
of cross-disciplinary researchers,
who collaborate across groups.
These groups are then the communities
in this collaboration graph.
What does this tell us?
It tells us that communities are highly
interacting clusters in a graph.
That is, they form pockets of
denser subgraphs that are more
connected to each other,
than to members of the other clusters.
Communities of humans, or otherwise,
are interesting things to study,
because it gives us an insight
into the interaction patterns.
And how they change with time.
Here, are some analytics
questions about communities.
We have divided them
into three categories.
Analytics questions that do not
depend on time, are called static.
Here, we ask questions about
the composition of the community,
how tight-knit members are connected,
and so forth.
In the second category, we involve the
formation, and evolution of the community.
Communities can form temporal,
for example,
around an event like a school shooting.
Or some communities,
despite the comings and
goings of members,
sustain themselves well.
A Facebook group, a political party,
fans of a music band,
are likely to continue over time,
and hence are non-transient.
One can also be interested in
the history of formation of a community,
like a criminal network.
The third category is about predictions.
Analysts would like to predict
how a community would grow.
Whether it's composition
of members might change.
Or whether there are emerging
power shifts within the community.
Now before we ask these questions,
however,
we need to first identify
communities in a large network.
To find communities, we need to
formalize the idea that there are more
connections within the community, and
fewer connections between two communities.
One way to achieve this, is to think
of dividing the degree of a node,
into an internal and
an external component.
The internal component is the count
of edges within community.
And the external degree, is the count
of edges outside the community.
An example,
will be to consider that my community
is where I live, that is San Diego.
And then count the number of my friends
within San Diego versus outside San Diego.
In the figure, the highlighted node
has four internal connections and
one external connection.
The next step, would be to think
of the internal degree, and
the external degree of an entire cluster.
We can sum up the internal degrees
of all nodes in a cluster.
And call it the internal
degree of the whole cluster.
And similarly,
sum the external degrees of the nodes,
to compute the external
degree of the cluster.
Now, we can define intra-cluster
density to be the ratio of the number
of internal edges of the cluster,
divided by the number of possible
connections inside the box.
The denominator is N cues 2.
Which is the number of pairwise
combination of nodes within the cluster.
We call this delta int.
Similarly, inter-cluster density,
delta x is the number
of inter-cluster edges divided by
the possible pairings between nC,
a node in the cluster, to n- nC,
the number of nodes outside the cluster.
There are two kinds of methods used for
finding communities in the network.
One of them focuses on local properties,
that is,
properties for which one only
looks at a node and its neighbor.
For the most ideal community
in a network is a subgraph,
where every node is connected to
every other node in the subgraph.
Such a structure is called a clique.
To find a perfect community
structure as a clique,
one can try to find the largest
clique within a graph, return cell.
That is a computationally
challenging problem.
It's much simpler to find cliques
if we know the value of k.
That means the number of
members in the clique.
We're going to show a simple
version of this in model three.
The more general problem has been
solved by complex algorithms,
that are beyond the scope of this course.
In the real world, perfect cliques larger
than three or four are harder to find.
So we need to relax the definition of it.
Now, there are two types of relaxations,
those based on distance,
and those based on density.
Two distance based definitions
are n-clique and n-plan.
We'll illustrate this over
a friendship graph shown here.
n-clique, is a subgraph,
such that the distance between each
node pair in that subgraph is n or less.
By this definition, Holly, Paul,
and Gary form a two clique.
That's a little awkward, isn't it?
Yeah.
They are within two
distance of each other.
But the two clique does not
include intermediate nodes that
connect the member nodes.
So, Mike, is not in the two clique.
This situation is corrected in n-clan.
Where, to belong to the n-clan,
the shortest part between any members,
without involving outsiders, is n or less.
Now, Holly, Mike,
Bill, Don, Harry, and
Gary form a two-clan.
Clearly, this group is more cohesive
than the two-clique we saw before.
n-clique and n-clan
are distance based measures for
finding cohesive groups of communities.
K-core is a density based method for
finding communities.
Let's look at the dark, orange subgraph.
Every node is connected to at least
three other nodes within the subgraph.
They form a 3-core.
Let's include the medium light
orange nodes in the subgraph now.
Each node is connected to at least two
other members within the subgraph,
they form a 2-core.
Relaxing further, we can add the light
orange nodes and the graph as a 1-core.
We have already defined
the degree of the node
as the number of edges connected to it.
Thus specifying if a node is
more connected than another.
Looking closer we can separate out
that two components denotes
degrees into in degree and out.
Which are the counts of the incident and
the outgoing edges of a node respectively.
In the example graph G has an indegree and
outdegree of three making
the total degree equal to six.
We first construct this degree table for
each node.
It's a simple procedure where we count
the number of nodes with degree.
0, 1, 2, and so forth.
The degree versus count table is
a degree histogram of the graph.
We can compare two graphs by computing
the vector distance between them.
One simplistic measure is
just the Euclidean distance.
For our case, the degree
histogram based on comparisons of
the histograms find the graphs
to be very similar.
The more sophisticated
methods are available but
are outside the scope of this course.
We can also compute histograms
of just the in degree or
just the out degree of the graph.
But perhaps more interesting is the joint
two dimensional histogram of the graph,
the colorful histogram of the graph
can be interpreted here as follows.
The graph has a maximum in degree of
three and a maximum out degree of three.
This creates a two-dimensional
histogram with four times four
equal to 16 different joined values.
The actual value for any combination
is computed from the graph and
color coded in the ratings.
For example, there is no node with
in degree 0 and out degree 0.
So the lower-left square of the graph
has value zero and color-coded blue.
On the other hand, there are two nodes
with in-degree three and out-degree three.
Thus, the top-right corner has the value
twp, which is 20% of the nodes.
Color coded as light green.
The 2D histogram provides
an interesting insight.
The nodes with more incident
edges than outgoing edges
represent entities that take
in more than they put out.
In a social networking setting,
they represent members who are listeners.
They receive a lot of posts,
but send much fewer posts.
On the opposite side of the spectrum,
there are talkers whose out-degrees
exceed their in-degrees.
The entities that are in between,
we have both large values of in-degree and
out-degree.
These are communicators.
In this graph, there seems to
be more talkers than listeners.
Not surprising though.
My social media friends
show similar statistics.