In this video, we'll talk about a new
that is usually not covered much.
It's called valence.
Simply put Valence
refers to Connectedness.
The more connected data is,
the higher it's valences.
The term valence comes from chemistry.
In chemistry, we talk about core electrons
and valence electrons of an atom.
Valence electrons are in the outer most
shell, have the highest energy level and
are responsible for
bonding with other atoms.
That higher valence results in greater
boding, that is greater connectedness.
This idea is carried over into our
definition of the term valence
in the context of big data.
Data items are often directly
connected to one another.
A city is connected to
the country it belongs to.
Two Facebook users are connected
because they are friends.
An employee is connected
to his work place.
Data could also be indirectly connected.
Two scientists are connected,
because they are both physicists.
For a data collection valence measures
the ratio of actually connected data items
to the possible number of connections
that could occur within the collection.
The most important aspect of valence
is that the data connectivity
increases over time.
The series of network graphs comes from
a social experiment where scientists
attending a conference were asked to meet
other scientists they did not know before.
After several rounds of meetings,
they found new connections
shown by their red edges.
Increase in valence can lead to emergent
group behavior in people networks,
like creation of new groups and coalitions
that have shared values and goals.
A high valence data set is denser.
This makes many regular,
analytic critiques very inefficient.
More complex analytical methods
must be adopted to account for
the increasing density.
More interesting challenges arise due
to the dynamic behavior of the data.
Now there is a need to model and
predict how valence of a connected data
set may change with time and volume.
The dynamic behavior also leads to
the problem of event detection,
such as bursts in the local
cohesion in parts of the data.
And emergent behavior
in the whole data set,
such as increased
polarization in a community.
Now we'll talk about a form of
scalability called variety.
In this case, scale does not
refer to the largeness of data.
It refers to increased diversity.
Here is an important mantra
you need to think about.
When we, as data scientists, think of
data variety, we think of the additional
complexity that results from more kinds
of data that we need to store, process,
and combine.
Now, many years ago when I
started studying data management,
we always thought of data as tables.
These tables could be in spreadsheets or
databases or just files, but somehow
they will be modeled and manipulated
as rows and columns of of tables.
Now, tables are still really important and
dominant, however today a much wider
variety of data are collected, stored, and
analyzed to solve real world problems.
Image data, text data, network data,
geographic maps, computer
generated simulations are only a few of
the types of data we encounter everyday.
The heterogeneity of data can be
characterized along several dimensions.
We mentioned four such axes here.
Structural variety refers
to the difference in
the representation of the data.
For example, an EKG signal is very
different from a newspaper article.
A satellite image of wildfires from
NASA is very different from tweets
sent out by people who
are seeing the fire spread.
Media variety refers to the medium
in which the data gets delivered.
The audio of a speech versus
the transcript of the speech
may represent the same information
in two different media.
Data objects like news video
may have multiple media.
An image sequence, an audio,
and closed captioned text,
all time synchronized to each other.
Semantic variety is best
described two examples.
We often use different units for
quantities we measure.
Sometimes we also use qualitative
versus quantitative measures.
For example, age can be a number or
we represent it by terms like infant,
juvenile, or adult.
Another kind of semantic
variety comes from different
assumptions of conditions on the data.
For example, if we conduct two income
surveys on two different groups of people,
we may not be able to compare or
combine them without knowing more
about the populations themselves.
The variation and
availability takes many forms.
For one, data can be available real time,
like sensor data, or it can be stored,
like patient records.
Similarly data can be
accessible continuously, for
example from a traffic cam.
Versus intermittently, for
example, only when the satellite
is over the region of interest.
This makes a difference between what
operations one can do with data,
especially if the volume
of the data is large.
We'll cover this in more
detail in course two
when we explore the different genres
of data and how we model them.
We should not think that
a single data object, or
a collection of similar data objects,
will be all uniform in themselves.
Emails, for example, is a hybrid entity.
Some of this information can be a table,
like shown here.
Now, the body of the email
usually has text in it.
However, some of the text may
have ornaments around them.
For example,
the part highlighted in yellow represents
something called a markup on text.
We'll get to markups later in the course.
Emails contain attachments.
These are files, or embedded images,
or other multimedia objects
that the mailer allows.
This screenshot from my Outlook
shows the image of a scanned image
of a handwritten note.
When you take a collection of
all emails from your mailbox, or
that from an organization,
you will see that senders and
receivers form a communication network.
In 2001, there was a famous scandal around
a company called Enron that engaged in
fraudulent financial reporting practices.
Their email network, partly shown here,
has been studied by data scientist to find
usual and unusual patterns of connections
among the people in the organization.
An email collection can also
have it's own semantics.
For example, an email cannot refer to,
that means cannot copy or
forward, a previous email.
Finally, an email server
is a real-time data source.
But an email repository is not.
Does email, and email collections,
demonstrate significant
internal variation in structure,
media, semantics, and availability?
Characteristics of Big Data- Velocity.
Velocity refers to the increasing
speed at which big data is created and
the increasing speed at which the data
needs to be stored and analyzed.
Processing of data in real-time to match
its production rate as it gets generated
is a particular goal
of big data analytics.
For example,
this type of capability allows for
personalization of advertisement
on the web pages you visit
based on your recent search,
viewing, and purchase history.
If a business cannot take advantage
of the data as it gets generated, or
at the speed analysis of it is needed,
they often miss opportunities.
In order to build a case for the
importance of this dimension of big data,
let's imagine we are taking a road trip.
You're looking for
some better information to start packing.
In this case, the newer the information,
the higher its relevance
in deciding what to pack.
Would you use last month's
weather information or
data from last year at this time?
Or, would you use the weather
information from this week, yesterday or
better, today?
It makes sense to obtain the latest
information about weather and
process it in a way that
makes your decisions easier.
If the information is old,
it doesn't matter how accurate it is.
Being able to catch up with
the velocity of big data and
analyzing it as it gets generated can
even impact the quality of human life.
Sensors and smart devices monitoring
the human body can detect abnormalities
in real time and trigger immediate action,
potentially saving lives.
This type of processing is what
we call real time processing.
Real-time processing is quite
different from its remote relative,
batch processing.
Batch processing was the norm
until a couple of years ago.
Large amounts of data would be
fed into large machines and
processed for days at a time.
While this type of processing is still
very common today, decisions based on
information that is even few days old
can be catastrophic to some businesses.
Organizations which make
decisions on latest data
are more likely to hit the target.
For this reason it's important
to match the speed of processing
with the speed of information generation,
and get real time decision making power.
In addition, today's sensor-powered
socioeconomic climate
requires faster decisions.
Hence, we can not wait for
all the data to be first produced,
then fed into a machine.
There are many applications where
new information is streaming and
needs to be integrated
with existing data to
produce decisions such as emergency
response planning in a tornado, or
deciding trading strategies in real time,
or getting estimates in advertising.
We have to digest chunks of data as they
are produced and give meaningful results.
As more data comes in,
your results will need to adapt to
reflect this change in the input.
Decisions based on processing of already
acquired data such as batch processing,
may give an incomplete picture.
And hence, the applications need real
time status of the context at hand.
That is, streaming analysis.
Fortunately, with the event
of cheap sensors technology,
mobile phones, and social media,
we can obtain the latest information
at a much rapid rate and
in real time in comparison with the past.
So how do you make sure we match
the velocity of the expectations
to gain insights from big data?
With the velocity of the big data.
Rate of generation, retrieval,
or processing of data is
application specific.
The need for real time data-driven
actions within a business case is
what in the end dictates the velocity
of analytics over big data.
Sometimes precision of a minute is needed.
Sometimes half a day.
Let's look at these four paths and
discuss when to pick the right one for
your analysis.
The dollar signs next to the numbers
in this example indicate how costly
the operation is.
The more dollars, the higher the cost.
When the timeliness of processed
information plays no role in decision
making, the speed at which data
is generated becomes irrelevant.
In other words, you can wait for
as long as it takes to process data.
Days, months, weeks.
And once processing is over,
you will look at the results and
probably share them with someone.
When timeliness is not an issue,
you can choose any of the four paths.
You will likely pick the cheapest one.
When timeliness of end result is an issue
deciding which of the four paths
to choose is not so simple.
You will have to make a decision
based on cost of hardware,
time sensitivity of information,
future scenarios.
In other words,
this becomes a business driven question.
For example, if speed is really important
at all costs, you will pick path four.
As a summary, we need to pay attention
to the velocity of big data.
Streaming data gives information
on what's going on right now.
Streaming data has velocity, meaning
it gets generated at various rates.
And analysis of such data in
real time gives agility and
adaptability to maximize
benefits you want to extract.
Characteristics of Big Data, Veracity.
Veracity of Big Data refers
to the quality of the data.
It sometimes gets referred
to as validity or
volatility referring to
the lifetime of the data.
Veracity is very important for
making big data operational.
Because big data can be noisy and
uncertain.
It can be full of biases,
abnormalities and it can be imprecise.
Data is of no value if it's not accurate,
the results of big data analysis are only
as good as the data being analyzed.
This is often described in analytics
as junk in equals junk out.
So we can say although big data
provides many opportunities to make
data enabled decisions,
the evidence provided by data
is only valuable if the data
is of a satisfactory quality.
There are many different
ways to define data quality.
In the context of big data,
quality can be defined as a function
of a couple of different variables.
Accuracy of the data, the trustworthiness
or reliability of the data source.
And how the data was generated
are all important factors
that affect the quality of data.
Additionally how meaningful the data
is with respect to the program that
analyzes it, is an important factor, and
makes context a part of the quality.
In this chart from 2015,
we see the volumes of data increasing,
starting with small amounts
of enterprise data to larger,
people generated voice over IP and
social media data and
even larger machine generated sensor data.
We also see that the uncertainty of
the data increases as we go from
enterprise data to sensor data.
This is as we would expect it to be.
Traditional enterprise
data in warehouses have
standardized quality solutions
like master processes for extract,
transform and load of the data which
we referred to as before as ETL.
As enterprises started incorporating less
structured and unstructured people and
machine data into their
big data solutions,
the data become messier and
more uncertain.
There are many reasons for this.
First, unstructured data on the internet
is imprecise and uncertain.
In addition, high velocity big data
leaves very little or no time for
ETL, and in turn hindering the quality
assurance processes of the data.
Let's look at these product reviews for
a banana slicer on amazon.com.
One of the five star reviews say that
it saved her marriage and compared it
to the greatest inventions in history.
Another five star reviewer said
that his parole officer recommended
the slicer as he is not
allowed to be around knives.
These are obviously fake reviewers.
Now think of an automated product
assessment going through such
splendid reviews and estimating lots
of sales for the banana slicer and
in turn suggesting stocking more
of the slicer in the inventory.
Amazon will have problems.
For a more serious case let's look at
the Google flu trends case from 2013.
For January 2013,
the Google Friends actually
estimated almost twice as many
flu cases as was reported by CDC,
the Centers for
Disease Control and Prevention.
The primary reason behind this was that
Google Flu Trends used a big data on
the internet and did not account properly
for uncertainties about the data.
Maybe the news and social media
attention paid to the particularly
serious level of flu that
year effected the estimate.
And resulted in what we
call an over estimation.
This is a perfect example for
how inaccurate the results can be if
only big data is used in the analysis.
Imagine the economical impact of
making health care preparations for
twice the amount of flu cases.
That would be huge.
The Google flu trends example
also brings up the need for
being able to identify where exactly
the big data they used comes from.
What transformation did
big data go through up
until the moment it was used for
a estimate?
This is what we refer
to as data providence.
Just like we refer to
an artifacts provenance.
As a summary, the growing
torrents of big data pushes for
fast solutions to utilize
it in analytical solutions.
This creates challenges on
keeping track of data quality.
What has been collected,
where it came from, and
how it was analyzed prior to its use.
This is akin to an art artifact
having providence of everything
it has gone through.
But even more complicated to achieve
with large volumes of data coming
in varieties and velocities.
Characteristics of Big Data- Volume.
Volume is the big data dimension that
relates to the sheer size of big data.
This volume can come from
large datasets being shared or
many small data pieces and
events being collected over time.
Every minute 204 million emails are sent,
200,000 photos are uploaded, and 1.8
million likes are generated on Facebook.
On YouTube, 1.3 million videos are viewed
and 72 hours of video are uploaded.
But how much data are we talking about?
The size and the scale of storage for
big data can be massive.
You heard me say words that
start with peta, exa and
yotta, to define size, but
what does all that really mean?
For comparison, 100 megabytes will
hold a couple of encyclopedias.
A DVD is around 5 GBs, and
1 TB would hold around 300
hours of good quality video.
A data-oriented business currently
collects data in the order of terabytes,
but petabytes are becoming more
common to our daily lives.
CERN's large hadron collider
generates 15 petabytes a year.
According to predictions by an IDC report
sponsored by a big data company called
EMC, digital data, will grow by
a factor of 44 until the year 2020.
This is a growth from 0.8 zetabytes,
In 2009 to 35.2 zettabytes in 2020.
A zettabyte is 1 trillion gigabytes,
that's 10 to the power of 21.
The effects of it will be huge!
Think of all the time, cost,
energy that will be used to store and
make sense of such an amount of data.
The next era will be yottabytes.
Ten to the power of 24 and
brontobytes, ten to the power of 27.
Which is really hard to imagine for
most of us at this time.
This is also what we call data
at an astronomical scale.
The choice of putting the Milky Way Galaxy
in the middle of the circle
is not just for aesthetics.
This is what we would see if
we were to scale up 10 to
the 21 times into the universe.
Cool, isn't it?
Please refer to the reading
in this module called,
what does astronomical scale mean,
for a nice video on the powers of ten.
All of these point to an exponential
growth in data volume and storage.
What is the relevance of
this much data in our world?
Remember the planes collecting big data?
Our hope, as passengers,
is data means better flight safety.
The idea is to understand that businesses
and organizations are collecting and
leveraging large volumes of data
to improve their end products,
whether it is safety, reliability,
healthcare, or governance.
In general, in business the goal
is to turn this much data into
some form of business advantage.
The question is how do we
utilize larger volumes of data
to improve our end product's quality?
Despite a number of
challenges related to it.
There are a number of challenges related
to the massive volumes of big data.
The most obvious one is of course storage.
As the size of the data increases so
does the amount of storage space
required to store that data efficiently.
However, we also need to be able
to retrieve that large amount of
data fast enough, and
move it to processing units in a timely
fashion to get results when we need them.
This brings additional challenges
such as networking, bandwidth,
cost of storing data.
In-house versus cloud storage and
things like that.
Additional challenges arise during
processing of such large data.
Most existing analytical methods
won't scale to such sums of
data in terms of memory,
processing, or IO needs.
This means their performance will drop.
You might be able to get good performance
for data from hundreds of customers.
But how about scaling your solution
to 1,000 or 10,000 customers?
As the volume increases performance and
cost start becoming a challenge.
Businesses need a holistic
strategy to handle processing of
large scale data to their benefit
in the most cost effective manner.
Evaluating the options across
the dimensions mentioned here,
is the first step when it comes to
continuously increasing data size.
We will revisit this topic
later on in this course.
As a summary volume is the dimension
of big data related to its size and
its exponential growth.
The challenges with working with volumes
of big data include cost, scalability,
and performance related to their storage,
access, and processing.