So up until now we've been
calculating path length
based on the number of hops between
our beginning node and our end node.
This is roughly equivalent to counting
the number of towns between one town and
another town.
But it doesn't really get at
the value that is usually of
greatest importance to us.
And that is the actual distance between
one location and another location.
Which is found in the values that we've
assigned to the edges between the nodes.
So in this next example, we're going
to perform that kind of a calculation.
So the first two lines of code
we're already fairly familiar with.
We're matching a path between node a and
node c,
where the first node is H,
and the second node is P.
And this third line of code
is also fairly familiar.
We're extracting the names of the nodes
and the path that's been returned, and
we're returning a listing of those
names as well as a length of the path.
All of that is being returned
as the variable pathLength.
We've added a third element
to our return statement, and
that is using the reduce statement.
So what we're doing here is,
the purpose of the reduce statement,
takes a set of values and
reduces them down to a single value.
So in this line of code we begin by
setting a variable s equal to 0.
And then we define a variable E, which
represents the set of relationships in
a path that's returned, or
in other words, the edges.
And we pass that into this variable s,
and add to it,
the value of the distance that
we've assigned to that edge.
So we're performing
an aggregate calculation.
And returning the final results
to a variable called pathDist.
And we're limiting that
results to a single value.
And so when we do this, we should
get a value that is more indicative
of the actual distance between
our source and our destination.
And so here's the results.
The path itself, as we know,
begins in H and ends in P.
And it has a pathLength of 7,
but it has a pathDist of 39.
So we could interpret this to mean
that even though there are 6 towns
between the source town and
the destination town, or
a pathLength of 7, the actual distance
in miles would be a value of 39.
So with that we can apply
Dijkstra's algorithm.
So here I'm going to match the node with
the name A, and the node with the name P.
And we're going to find the shortest
path in terms of hops from A to P.
And we'll set that equal
to the variable path.
Then we'll perform a reduce command,
and set the variable dist = 0.
And we'll go through, and
sum all of the distances of each
of the edges in our shortest path.
And return that value as a distance.
And we'll also return the path variable.
So remember, this is not the path in
our network with the least weights.
It is the weight of the shortest
path based on numbers of hops.
Now that's an inherent feature of
the shortest path command in Cipher.
So here is the path that's returned.
It's a five node path with four edges and
the total sum of the weights of
those edges sums to a value of 22.
So in our previous query,
we specified that we wanted a match for
the source node and the destination node.
But if I don't specify my destination
node, I can apply Dijkstra's single
source shortest path algorithm
from node A to any other node.
So when we apply this query,
the results displayed consist of
the actual original path from
A to P with a distance of 22.
And we'll see a display of all of
the intermediate paths generated in
the process, all the way down to
a single edge path between A and C.
So just to reiterate, what we've
calculated is the shortest hop path
with the weights added, the sum of
the weights of the edges in that path.
This is not the least weight
path of the entire network.
Okay, so let's switch gears for a moment.
As we learned in one of our previous
lectures, we can extract a subset
of nodes and edges from a particular
graph for various reasons.
Let's say for example that we want
to avoid a particular town or
a particular area where
there might be congestion.
And this would be represented
by one of our nodes.
So we're going to perform a similar
match as we've done in the past,
where we're going to match any node n with
any node m, with a two edge between them.
But we want to apply an additional
constrained in which none of the n nodes
are going to include the node D.
And none of the m nodes are going
to include the node D as well.
And then we'll return the resulting graph.
So when we do that, we get a graph but
looks very much as we might expect.
Very similar to our previous graph,
but it is missing node D, so
it only has ten nodes and
it's now been reduced to ten edges.
So now let's say we want to calculate
the shortest path over there graph that we
just returned in the previous query.
So in this case, we're going to match the
shortest path between node A and node P.
But in the second line, we want to
issue sort of a negative statement
in which the resulting list of
node names that we extract using
the extract statement
cannot contain the node D.
And then we'll return that path and
the length of that path.
So when we issue this command,
here's our resulting path.
It's a five node path of length four.
As we recall from one of our earlier
queries where we were trying to calculate
all of the shortest paths,
we returned two paths.
One path that contained D, and this is
the second path, which did not contain D.
So we can make this a little complicated.
Instead of avoiding a single node in
our resulting path, we're looking for
a graph that doesn't contain the immediate
neighborhood of a specific node.
This means all of the nearest, or
the first neighbors of a specific node.
So in this case we're going
to match the same node D, and
all edges between D, and any other node.
And then we are going to issue
a collect command to collect all of
the distinct neighbors of D.
And we'll apply a constraint to that,
in which the returned
list of neighbors cannot contain
the node with the name D.
Likewise, the neighbors list for
the target nodes,
can also not contain the node D.
And when we submit this command,
we see a network that looks like this.
Five nodes and four edges.
And that seems to makes sense.
Node D isn't in the network,
nor are its first neighbors.
But if you recall the original network,
there may be a peculiar result that you
might find a little bit disconcerting.
So let's look at our original network.
Now here's the node D, and
here are all it's nearest neighbors.
So these are the forbidden
neighbors that we want to
remove from our resulting graph.
And we seemed to have
done that successfully.
These are the five nodes that
are retained in the resulting graph, but
there's a node out here.
The node p, which seems to be neglected or
not handled in the results.
It's not a first neighbor of D.
So it, in some ways arguably should
be returned in our results, but
it's not part of the connected
graph that we saw returned.
This is one area in which Cipher does
not handle these situations by default.
So we'll need to supplement our
query with an additional query.
In this case, the node P was a leaf node,
so we want to make sure that
not only matching the nodes that
conform to these constraints above.
But we also want to include the node or
any nodes which are leaf nodes,
which may also be arguably part of the
results that you expect to be returned.
Now in our network,
we do have one root node,
but it doesn't impact the results
in this particular query.
In the interests of being complete, for
any network, most networks being much more
complex than the one we're working with.
We'd want to take into account not only
those leaf nodes that might be left out,
but also any root notes
that might be left out.
And finally, our last query
example extends the previous query
to find the graph which doesn't
contain a selective neighborhood,
in this case,
the two neighborhood of a particular node.
In this example we're
going to use the node F.
And we want to eliminate all of
the second neighbors of that node.
So initially we match all of those
nodes that are second neighbors of F,
including F itself.
And we'll place those in
a variable called MyList.
Then we go back through the network and
match all of the nodes and
edges, where the source nodes are not
part of the nodes in the MyList and
the target nodes are not
contained in MyList.
And then we return those nodes and edges.
And here's the resulting graph.
It does not contain F or
its first or second neighbors.
If we scroll down to look at the original
graph, here's node F, nodes H,
J, C, A and L are all the first and
second neighbors of F.
So those should be eliminated from the
graph that gets returned from our results.
And sure enough,
this subset of nodes represents the
results that were returned from our query.
It consists of nodes B, D, E, G, and P.
And so this concludes our review
of some of the more advanced
path analytics queries.
We were using a simple network, but
we're providing additional data
sets that are much larger and
present a more realistic challenge
in applying pathanalythics queries.
Hello everyone and welcome to this week's
module on graph analytics with Neo4j
using the Cypher query language.
I'm Jeff Sale and I'll be your
instructor for this series of lessons.
I've been an instructional designer at
the San Diego Supercomputer Center for
more than ten years, but I've also had
a passion for scientific visualization and
visual analytics in one form or
another for over two decades.
And I'm very excited about this
opportunity to introduce you to this
free and very powerful graph
analytics tool called Neo4j.
First we realized that many of you
may not have the systems capable of
pushing the boundaries of
Neo4j's performance limits.
Plus the fact that many of you are fitting
this course into your already busy
schedules means we'll be working with data
sets, which will load into Neo4j and can
be analyze in a reasonable length of time,
on the order of minutes not hours or days.
However you can be sure that Neo4j
is capable of processing and
analyzing extremely complex graph networks
consisting of millions of nodes and
relationships.
This module consists of a series of
hands-on demonstrations with Neo4j,
which begin with examples of
some basic cypher queries
that soon progress to some of
the more advanced cypher queries.
We'll begin by using a relatively simple
graph representing a road network, but
we'll also use much larger and
more complex data sets,
including sociological data on
global terrorist groups and
genetics data on associations and
interactions between genes.
These data sets are in fact sub
sets of much larger data sets and
we're making both of the sub sets and
complete data sets available for download.
Once you become comfortable working
with the smaller data sets,
we encourage you to explore
the larger sets on your own.
Finally you'll notice that each
video is accompanied by a text file
containing all of the code used
in the video demonstrations.
These files include dozens of sample
scripts, written in cypher, designed to
make it easy for you to learn, not only
basic cypher cards, but also queries which
focus on more advanced methods such
pathenoids and connectivity analytics.
When you're finished with this module
you'll be able to write cypher scripts to
import and
analyze your own data using Neo4j.
So thank you for
enrolling in this course and let's get
started doing some real graph analytics
with Neo4j and the Cypher query language.
A parallel computation is at
the heart of big data computing.
However, to specify what becomes parallel,
we usually think of a conceptual model
of parallel computation often called,
a programming model.
A parallel programming model is
a way to specify abstractly,
how a parallel program will run.
Naturally for a program to be parallel,
there must be a number of
concurrently operating processes.
But how do these processes communicate and
exchange data?
How do they decide,
when to communicate with each other?
Further, what exactly is done in parallel?
To think of the first question.
Two processes communicate
data by sharing memory.
Indeed, there are architectures in which
all memory in multiple machines can be
made to virtually look like,
one large addressable memory space.
However, two processes,
we also communicate by passing
messages to one another.
Either, directly from one
process to another, or
through a common message carrying pipe,
often called a message bus.
The second question can
also have multiple answers.
Two of the most common ways of achieving
parallelism are pass parallelism and
data parallels.
In task parallelism, a large task can
be decomposed into multiple sub-tasks,
each of which can be run concurrently.
In data parallelism, the data can be
partitioned into many smaller fragments
and operation can run on each partition,
independent of the others.
Typically, these partial operations
have then synchronized and
partially process data combined
to produce a full answer.
Many parallel data management systems,
operate a partition due
to parallel manner.
We need to remember that task
parallelism is somewhat independent of
data parallelism.
And it is possible to have both problems
of parallelism in a programming model.
It is important to emphasize
the issue of a programming model,
should be not be confused with
the issue of a programming language.
A programming language is independent
of the programming model.
And therefore,
a programming model can be implemented
in several different languages.
As I mentioned, the programming model
we are going to consider is BSP.
BSP wasn't initially created for
graph computation.
It was thought of as
a parallel computing model,
that will bridge the gap between software
models of parallel computation, and
hardware capabilities for
supporting parallelism.
The basic idea of BSP is as follows.
There are number of processors.
Each processor can perform local
computation, using its own local memory.
There's a router, which can serve to pass
a message from any processor to any other.
When one pair of nodes
are exchanging messages,
another third node can
still perform computation.
There's a facility that can
synchronize the state of
all auto-substative processes.
This synchronize may either
happen periodically,
at intervals of L time units or
there may be another way of specifying,
when this synchronization
is going to happen.
But when it does, all processors affected
by it, will come to a consistent state.
When synchronization is performed,
a fresh round of computation can start.
We call this.
Synchronization point.
Barrier synchronization.
Because all executed processes
must reach this barrier point,
before the next step of
processing can continue.
A BSP program is broken up into
a sequence stop supersteps.
In each superstep, each processor
will get the data, if needed.
Performance computation if needed and
then, exchange data
with the right partner.
Once all the nodes are done,
the system helps to synchronize.
Then, the next round starts.
Each processor can determine,
if it needs to compute or exchange data.
If not, it will make itself inactive.
If required later, a processor can
be woken up to be active again.
When all processors are inactive,
the computation stops.
In applying BSP model to graphs,
we make a few assumptions.
We assume that a processor
is synonymous with a vertex.
So for
a processor can only send messages to or
receive from, its neighboring processes.
We also assume, a vertex has an ID and
possibly a complex value.
And an edge,
we also have an idea and fact.
Each vertex knows,
which edges it's connected to.
We cannot think of a computation
as a vertex centered task.
We shall [INAUDIBLE] what this means.
In a now famous paper from Google.
This programming model was called,
think like a vertex.
Well to think like a vertex,
we need to know what a vertex can do.
Here's a list of actions,
a vertex can take.
The first one is easy.
A vertex can find its own identifier.
The second operation is to get or
set the value of the node.
This operation may be a little involved,
if the value is a complex data object.
For our purposes,
we'll assume the value is a scalar.
Next, a node can ask for
its own edges, the result of
the operation is a set of edge objects.
A node may also count its edges.
Since we are referring to
outgoing edges throughout,
this is the out degree of the vertex.
Recognize that,
this means a vertex does not natively
have access to its incident notes.
However, it does have control
of the outgoing edges.
So it can get inside the edge values.
There may be two different
ways of specifying an edge.
The edge we have an ID
that the node can get.
Passively, more commonly, an edge is
identified the vertex of targets.
So in our diagram V1 lasts for
the edge, targeting V4.
So in the situation like v3 and v5, we're
there are multiple edges between v3 and
v5, the source v3 can ask for
the values of all edges going to v5.
The operate operation can add or
remove an edge of a vertex.
Finally, since the vertices are processes,
they can start or stop computing.
Typically a node wakes up, if it
receives a message from another node.
Now in comparison to a vertex,
an edge can do far less.
It can get its own ID if the system
allows edge ID's, it can set and
retrieve its own values, and it can get
the ID of the node its pointing to.
That's it.
Now, we still have not defined,
how to think like a vertex.
That's what we'll do next,
using an example that we have
seen several times before.
It's Dijkstra's single source
shortest path, SSSP, algorithm.
We have seen this algorithm before.
But now, we'll show how to compute
it in a parallel setting using BSP.
Here is the edge value,
that's the weight of the edge.
This is known before the algorithm starts.
Each vertex,
runs the exact same routine concurrently.
Each vertex asks.
1, is it super step zero?
2, if yes,
then if this is a source vertex,
it sets the value to zero.
Else, it sets the value to infinity,
which is a large number.
The source vertex,
propagates its edge value to the nodes
at the other end of the edges.
Just the source vertex.
All other vertices are quiet.
The propagation process works like this.
A vertex gets its own value,
which for the source vertex is zero.
It gets its edges, for each edge,
it gets the value of the edge,
adds it to its own value and sends
the result to the end point of the edge.
The blue numbers indicate
that the messages are sent.
All vertices go to halt.
That is, they now have hit
a synchronization barrier.
Notice, that the receiving nodes
do not look at the messages yet.
It's the system's job to ensure that
the messages are available to these nodes
at the next superstep.
All nodes who have received messages
wake up and read the messages.
If a node receives multiple messages,
it picks the minimum.
In our case, the two active nodes
have received only one value each.
We have for the sake of convenience,
colored the processed edges in yellow.
This is just for
visualization purposes in this example.
Now, it compares this band for
a minimum value, to its own value.
And if its own value is greater, it sets
its own value with the minimum value.
In our case, both notes set their value
to that, of the incoming message.
The same propagation routine works again.
So, each note completes the new distance.
And sends the message along an edge
to the other endpoint, then halts.
The same step is repeated
in the next superstep.
At this point,
the nodes have updated their values.
The node with the value 6,
has received our message,
just along one of the three edges on it.
Continuing.
At the end of superstep 2,
all nodes are ready to receive messages
from all their incident edges.
The node with a value 6, received a value
which is lower than its current value.
Now the active nodes,
have no more messages to send.
So each vertex, votes to halt.
The vertex ID and the value
are read out from each vertex, and
then the process starts.
If these nodes are in different
machines of a cluster,
the system will rely on
the underlying platform like YARN.
Or sparks underlying
infrastructure to ensure,
that the edges going across machines can
send and receive messages effectively.
This should give you a sense of the speed
of this process for a large scale network.
As we said earlier,
while the Giraph paradigm implements BSB,
it must also be pragmatic.
One such point of pragmatism is
the computation of aggregate values.
In the think like a vertex paradigm,
operations local to a vertex can
be performed in parallel, and
each vertex only has to work
with its immediate neighborhood.
This is very useful, but
it isn't sufficient at times.
For example, we need to know and use
the total number of edges in the graph.
This will be computed by adding
edges connected to each vertex, but
once aggregated,
it does not belong to any specific vertex.
So whom does this vertex
send the aggregate to?
Also suppose, a vertex creates some
edges as part of its compute step.
When does this information get sent out?
Let's answer the first question first.
The class in charge of these aggregates
is called the DefaultMasterCompute class.
This class specializes MasterCompute.
How does the DefaultMasterCompute
relate to the basic vertex computation?
We have seen that all vertex programs are
created by first defining a vertex class.
This class has a compute function that
performs like the think like a vertex
logic.
Now let's add to it a basic vertex
function and an aggregate function.
Now this function, for
our example of all the total number
of aggregate edges looks like this.
The name of the function is aggregate.
As you can see in yellow, it just gets
the number of edges off this vertex.
What's a little strange is that the first
argument of this aggregation has
an id of something whose
name is total number edges.
What really happens is as follows.
The defaltMasterCompute class, which
is in charge of this global aggregate
operations, is specialized
by your aggregate class.
This class has an ID, and
the aggregator gets registered with
Giraph's defaultMasterCompute class.
The ID we saw before refers to your
registered aggregator's classes ID.
The MasterCompute class performs
the centralized computation between
supersteps.
This class is initiated
on the master node and
will run every superstep
before the workers do.
Communication with the workers
should be performed via aggregators.
The values of the aggregators
are broadcast to the workers before
the vertex compute is called.
And collected by the master before
the master compute is called.
This means the aggregator values
used by the workers are consistent
with the aggregator values from
the master from the same superstep.
And the aggregator used by
the master are consistent
with the aggregator values from
the workers from the previous superstep.
Now let's go back to the big picture for
a second.
Giraph is a big data software.
Why not implement the Giraph system
with a set of MapReduce jobs?
Too much disk requirement.
No in-memory caching.
Every superstep becomes a job.
So all intermediate steps
are written to files, and
that is not a very scalable solution for
iterative operations.
However, it will be incorrect
to think that Giraph works
only in an in memory process.
It can always have less
memory than it needs.
There are two broad categories of
what's called out-of-core computation.
The first situation occurs when the graph
is really large compared to the capacity
of the cluster it's running on.
Each worker stores the vertices assigned
to it inside a set of partitions.
Inside a partition are a subset of
vertices together with their data.
During a superstep, the worker node
processes multiple partitions
concurrently, one per thread.
If a graph is large, then not all
partitions are stored in memory.
Typically only N partitions
are kept in memory at all times and
the rest of the partitions
are swapped into disk.
The second situation occurs when
the number of messages becomes high.
Normally, vertices are processed
in the order of their IDs.
A large number of messages
is handled by creating
temporary message stores which
are sorted by their destination IDs.
All messages going to the same
vertex are placed together.
To do this, messages are sorted
in memory periodically.
The message store files
are accessed based on
which vertices are being
processed at this moment.
This whole system is managed by
Giraph's out of core message processor.
In this lesson, we'll talk about
two dominant systems developed for
large scale graph processing.
The first one, called Giraph,
is from Apache and
implements a BSP model on Hadoop.
The second system is called Graphx,
is developed on the Spark platform,
which as you know, emphasizes on
interactive in memory computations.
While BSP is a popular
graph processing model,
the actual implementation of
BSP in an infrastructure needs
additional programmability beyond
what we have discussed so far.
In Giraph, several additional capabilities
are added to make it more practical.
A thorough coverage of the Giraph platform
is beyond the scoop of these lectures.
However, we'll touch upon
a few of these capabilities.
We'll first consider graph IO,
that is how graphs can come into a system
represented inside the system, and
when completed are written out.
Next, we'll describe how Giraph
interacts with external data sources.
Some of these data sources
use a different data model,
other sources include databases.
Once a graph is imported,
it is important to make sure that
the system runs efficiently.
We will look at a method that uses a
special kind of global aggregate operation
which saves time by reducing
the amount of messaging
to compute aggregate functions
like sum and products.
Finally, we'll recognize that
even if Giraph is designed for
performing iterative,
in memory computation,
there are times where it is absolutely
necessary to store data on disk.
We'll briefly touch upon Giraph's
ability to handle out of core graphs and
out of core messages.
A graph can be written in many ways.
For Neo4J, we saw how graphs can be
important to the database from a CSV file.
In Giraph, two of the most common input
formats are Adjacency List and Edge List.
For an Adjacency List,
each line has the node ID, a node value
which is a single number here, and
a list of destination, weight pairs.
Thus, in line one,
A has a value of 10 and 2 neighbors B and
F with edge weights 2 and 5, respectively.
Since G has no outgoing edge,
the adjacency list is empty.
The current way of representing
graphs is in terms of triplets.
Containing the source and destination
nodes followed by an [INAUDIBLE].
Notice the way we have shown it here.
And the node values is not represented.
Let us simplify the Adjacency List
representation of it.
We remove the colons, commas, braces, and
parenthesis, and
get a space separated set of lines.
One line for each vertex.
We further replace the node IDs A,
B, C, etc., with 1, 2, 3, etc.,
so that these IDs are integers.
So what do we need to specify
to parse this for Giraph?
One, the graph is a text subject and
not, let's say, a database subject.
Two, it is a vertex based representation,
each line is a vertex.
This splitter here is a space.
The idea of the node is a first value for
each line.
The value is a second token.
The next pair of items you find an edge
with the target and the weight,
respectively.
And lastly, there is a list of these
pairs until the end of the line.
Therefore, each line would typically
lead to the creation of both notes and
a set of edges.
This shows a typical reader formula
decency matrix written in Java.
Again, you don't have to know Java
to get the elements of this program.
Our reader is clearly customized for
your specific input.
Very often the starting point is
a basic reader provided by Giraph.
Like the reader that knows how to read
vertices from each line of a text swipe.
To customize it, you extend it and
create your own version.
Now, you need to define
how to get the ID and
value of the vertex by writing
separate message for them.
Notice that the ID comes from
the zeroth item of each line after
the split by white space, and
the value comes from the next open,
the second term, marked by 1 for
the 0 base of the light.
The next code element is this block here.
This specifies how to create edges
by iterating through every line.
To keep the short, we'll remove
the part that gets the edges here.
As Giraph as mature it has
included many specialized
to interoperate with compatible resources.
This diagram is from Giraph where
the show some of these sources.
We can group them into
three different categories.
Group one interoperates with Hive and
HBase.
You possibly remember these
systems from a prior course.
These systems are designed to give
a higher level of data access on
interface on top of MapReduce.
Group two accesses relational
systems like MySQL and Cassandra.
But these systems have accessed indirectly
through a software module called Gora.
Gora uses a JSON schema to map
the relation schema of the SQL database
to a structure that Giraph can read.
Group three accesses graph
databases like Neo4J and DEX,
which is now called Sparksee.
These systems are all taxes indirectly.
Using the [INAUDIBLE]
service of Tinkerpop.
Which is a graph API layer that can use
many different Giraph stores including
[INAUDIBLE] graph and Titan.
Consider a relational
table stored in Hive.
The table shown here is extracted
from the bio grid data source that
we mentioned in module two.
Each row of the table represents
a molecule interaction.
We can create a network from here just
by considering the first two columns.
The first column represents the source
node of an edge colored red.
And the second column represents
the target node of the edge colored blue.
The label on the edge comes from
the fifth column of the table
which is a black bold font.
Let's assume that these predict items,
these are items that we want to
pick up from the Hive table.
The simplest way to get a record from hive
to Giraph is to extend the class
called SimpleHiveRowToEdge.
For this class, we need to specify
the source node, the target node, and
the edge value using three
methods as shown here.
My extension is called MyHiveRowToEdge.
It shows the implementation of these
methods where we just pick up the first,
second, and fifth columns,
as we described before.
Now, as mentioned before,
Giraph interacts with Neo4J through
the Gremlin API provided by Tinkerpop.
One can think of Gremlin as
a traversal API, which means,
it allows one to start from some node and
walk the graph step by step.
To show this,
consider disease gene graph on the right.
Let's call this graph G.
So g.V represents all the vertices of G.
Therefore g.V has name
MC4R selects the node that
has a property called
name whose value is MC4R.
Let's add to this path the condition .out,
which chooses the out
edges of the MC4R node and
then traverses the associatedWith edge
to the orange node called obesity.
For this call, returns the vertex only.
Now, adding the path to values
means gives us obesity.
We can also expand differently
from the obesity node.
When we say inV() we refer
to all nodes that have
incoming edges to the current node.
In this case, there is only one.
The LEPR node.
To this, we add the traversal out beam and
thus we get back the out going edge from
the LEPR node highlighted in together.
We can also look at the Giraph Gremlin
near project connection
from Tinkerpop's viewpoint.
Tinkerpop is trying to create
a standard language for graph reversal,
just like Neo4J is trying to create Open
Cypher as a standard query language for
graph databases.
In trying to create the standard,
Tinkerpop recognizes that the actual
storage management for graph databases
should be provided by another vendor.
The vendor needs to implement
the Gremlin API for access.
Similarly for graphic processing,
including expensive analytic operations
should be performed by what
they call a graph computer.
This is the role played by
Giraph as well as Spark.
Both of which interface with Tinkerpop.