YARN, The Resource Manager for Hadoop.
YARN is a resource manage layer that
sits just above the storage layer HDFS.
YARN interacts with applications and
schedules resources for their use.
YARN enables running multiple
applications over HDFC increases
resource efficiency and
let's you go beyond the map reduce or
even beyond the data
parallel programming model.
When Hadoop was first created,
this wasn't the case.
In fact, the original Hadoop
stack had no resource manager.
These two stacked diagrams, show, some of
it's evolution over the last ten years.
One of the biggest limitations
of Hadoop one point zero,
was it's inability to support
non-mapreduce applications.
It had several terrible
resource utilization.
This meant that for advanced
applications such as graph analysis that
required different ways of modelling and
looking at data, you would need to
move your data to another platform.
That's a lot of work if your data is big.
Adding YARN in between HDFS and
the applications enabled
new systems to be built, focusing on
different types of big data applications
such as Giraph for
graph data analysis, Storm for
streaming data analysis, and
Spark for in-memory analysis.
YARN does so
by providing a standard framework
that supports customized application
development in the HADOOP ecosystem.
YARN lets you extract maximum
benefits from your data sets
by letting you use the tools you
think are best for your big data.
Let's take a peek into the architecture
of YARN without getting too technical.
In this picture, notice the resource
manager in the center, and
the node managers on each of
the three nodes on the right.
The resource manager controls all
the resources, and decides who gets what.
Node manager operates at machine level and
is in charge of a single machine.
Together the resource manager and
the node manager form the data
computation framework.
Each application gets
an application master.
It negotiates resource from
the Resource Manager and
it talks to Node Manager
to get its tasks completed.
Notice the ovals labeled
Container The container
is an abstract Notions that
signifies a resource that is
a collection of CPU
memory disk network and
other resources within
the compute note to simplify and
be less precise you can think
of a container and the Machine.
We looked at the essential
gears of the YARN
engine to give you an idea of
the key components of YARN.
Now when you hear terms like
Resource Manager, Node Manager and
Container, you will have an understanding
of what tasks they are responsible for.
Here is a real life example to show
the strength Hadoop 2.0 over 1.0.
Yahoo was able to run almost
twice as many jobs per day with
Yarn than with Hadoop 1.0.
They also experienced a substantial
increase in CPU utilization.
Yahoo!
even claimed that upgrading
to YARN was equal into
adding 1000 machines to
their 2500 machine cluster.
That's big.
YARN success is evident
from an explosive growth of
different application that
the Hadoop ecosystem now has.
New to yarn?
You can use the tool of your choice
over your big data without any hassle.
Compare this with Hadoop 1.0 which
was limited to MapReduce alone.
Let's review a summary of
the key take-aways about yarn.
Yarn gives you many ways for
applications to extract value from data.
It lets you run many distributed
applications over the same Hadoop cluster.
In addition, YARN reduces
the need to move data around and
supports higher resource utilization
resulting in lower costs.
It's a scalable platform that has
enabled growth of several applications
over the HDFS,
enriching the Hadoop ecosystem.
At this point, you hopefully have a good
general idea of what big data means and
why big data is important.
So now, we need to focus on what to do
when we have an application
that uses big data.
In this video, we focus on
the problem of managing big data.
So at the end of the video,
you should be able to describe what data
management means in general, and then
specifically recognize the issues that are
involved in the management of big data.
First, let's see what data
management means in general.
Instead of giving you
definitions of data management,
let's think of some questions
that must be asked and
answered well if you're to manage
a reasonable amount of data.
Now, we can not possibly cover
all questions one should ask for
a data-centric application, but here are
some important ones, which range from how
we get the data, to how we work with it,
to how we secure it from malicious users.
We'll visit these issues one at a time.
Ingestion means the process
of getting the data
into the data system that
we are building or using.
Now you might think,
why is it worth talking about?
We'll just read the data from somewhere,
like a file.
And then using some command,
place it into the data system.
Or we'll have have some
kind of a web form or
other visual interface and just fill it
in so that the data goes into the system.
Both of these ways of
data ingestion are valid.
In fact, they're valid for
some big data systems like your
airline reservation system.
However when you think
of a large scale system
you wold like to have more automation
in the data ingestion processes.
And data ingestion then becomes a part of
the big data management infrastructure.
So here are some questions you might want
to ask when you automate data ingestion.
Now take a minute to read the questions.
We'll look at two examples to
explore them in greater detail.
The first example is that of a hospital
information system that we discussed in
course one in the context
of precision medicine.
We said that hospitals collect
terabytes of medical record
from different departments and
be considered big data systems.
The second example is a cloud based data
store where many people upload their
messages, chats, pictures,
videos, music and so fourth.
The cloud storage also supports active
communication between the members and
store their communication in real time.
So let's think of a hypothetical
hospital information information and
the answer to depressions
that we are putting there.
Now, do not take the numbers
to be very accurate.
They are just examples.
But it illustrates some important points.
One, note that there are two kinds
of likeness associated with data.
Some data like medical images
are large data objects by themselves.
Secondly, the records
themselves are quite small but
the size of the total collection
of records is very high.
Two, while there is a lot of patient data,
the number of data sources that is
the different departmental systems
contributing to the total information
system does not change
very much over time.
Three, the rate of data ingestion is
not enormous and is often proportional
to the number of patient activities
that takes place at the hospital.
Four, the system contains
medical records so
data can never be discarded even
when there are errors in the data.
The errors in this specific case
are flagged but the data is retained.
Now this is the kind of rule
called an error handling policy.
Which might be different for
different application problems.
An air handling policy is part of
a larger scheme of policies called
ingestion policies.
Another kind of ingestion policy involves
decisions regarding what the system should
do if the data rate suddenly increases or
becomes suspiciously low.
In this example we have deliberately
decided not to include it in the design.
Now compare the previous case with
the case of the online store of
personal information.
Again this is just an imaginary example.
So don't think of all
the parameters to be exact.
Now in this case one, the store will
have a fast growing membership.
Each member will use multiple devices
to capture and ingest their data.
Two, over all members together, the site
will be updated at a really fast rate,
making this a large volume data
store with a fast ingest rate.
Three, in this system, our primary
challenge is to keep up with the data
rate, and hence, erroneous data will be
discarded after just one edit to reinvest.
Four, now there is an actual policy for
handling data overflow,
which essentially says,
keep the excess data in a site store.
And ingest them when the data
rate becomes slower.
But if the site store starts getting full
start dropping some incoming data
at a rate of 0.1% at a time.
Now we should see why data
ingestion together with it's
policies should be an integral
part of a big data system.
Especially when it involves
storing fast data.
A very significant aspect of data
management is to document, define,
implement, and test the set of
operations that are required for
a specific application.
As we'll see later in the specialization,
some operations are independent of
the type of data and some others would
require us to know the nature of the data
because the operations make use
of a particular data model.
That is the way that it is structured.
In general, there are two
broad divisions of operations.
Those that work on a singular object and
those that work on
collections of data objects.
In the first case,
an operation that crops an image,
that means extracts a sub
area from an area of pixels,
is a single object operation because we
consider the image as a single object.
One can think of many subclasses
of the second category
where the operations
are on data collections.
We briefly referred to three very
common operations that can be done
regardless of the nature of the data.
The first is to take a collection and
filter out a subset of that collection.
The most obvious case is
selecting a subset from a set.
In this example, we select circles
whose number is greater than three.
A second case is merging two collections
together to form a larger collection.
In the example shown,
two three structure data items are merged
by fusing the node with a common property.
That is two.
In the last case,
we compute a function on a collection and
return the value of the function.
So in this example,
the function is a simple count.
In the real world, this kind of aggregate
function can be very complicated.
We will come back to this issue when
we talk more about map readings, but
in this course, we'll talk about
many different data operations.
Every operator must be efficient.
That means every operator must
perform its task as fast as possible
by taking up as little memory,
or our disk, as possible.
Obviously, the time to
perform an operation
will depend on the size of the input and
the size of the output.
So, if there is an opportunity to use
concurrency where the operator can split
its data and have different threads
operate on the pieces at the same time,
it should definitely do so.
We present a simple example of
an operator we saw on the previous slide.
So this operator, called selection,
refers to choosing a subset of
a set based on some conditions.
Here we are choosing a subset of
circles whose numbers are even.
To make it more efficient,
we can take the input data and
partition it randomly into two groups.
Now, for each group,
we can concurrently run the subset
algorithm and get the partial results.
For this operation, the partial results
can be directly sent to the output
without any additional processing step.
Okay we in essence store
the data efficiently.
But is it any good?
Are there ways of knowing if the data is
potentially error free and useful for
the intended purpose?
This is the issue of data quality.
There are many reasons
why any data application,
especially larger applications need
to be mindful of data quality.
Here are three reasons, of course
there are more that we do not mention.
The first reason emphasizes that
the ultimate use of big data
is its ability to give
us actionable insight.
Poor quality data leads to poor
analysis and hence to poor decisions.
The second related data in regulated
industries in areas like clinical
trials for pharmaceutical companies or
financial data like from banks.
Errors in data in these industries
can regulate regulations leading to
legal complications.
The third factor is different
than the first two.
It says if your big data should
be used by other people or
a third party software
it's very important for
the data to give good quality to
gain trust as a leader provider.
A class of big data applications
is scientific, where large,
integrated collections of data
are created by human experts to
understand scientific questions.
Ensuring accuracy of data will lead
to correct human engagement and
interaction with the data system.
Gartner, the well known
technology research and
advising company created a 2015
industry report on big data qualities.
In this report,
they identify the approaches to meeting
the data quality requirements
in the industry.
This methods include the adherence
to standards where applicable.
It also refers to the need to
create the rules in the data system
that can be use to check if the data
passes a set of correct this qualities.
Like is even employed above 18.
It also includes methods to clean
the data if it's found to have errors or
inconsistencies.
Further the data quality management should
include a well define work flow on how
low quality data could be corrected to
bring it back to a high level of quality.