So far we have seen two versions
of the Dijkstra Algorithm.
Both these versions assume that the edge
weights provided by the network
must be used as is.
Now that can lead to some
interesting problems.
We saw one such problem before.
Remember we were trying to decide
whether we should go from G to D or
from F to E because both options
had the same total weight?
Now had we chosen to go from G to D,
it would take us a few extra steps
to arrive at correct solution.
One way of handling this problem
is to use additional knowledge.
So intuitively, we want to say that
we know that we want to go to B.
So traversing through
D is not a good idea.
Because it will take us away from B.
In other words we use the knowledge
of the destination of B's location
to steer the direction of search.
This variant is called
Goal-Directed Dijkstra Algorithm because
it is using the information about the
target known at any point in the search.
The trick to use this information is to
change the edge weights as we diverse.
How do we change the weight?
We use a formula, where the new weight
is the original weight together with
a function called the potential function.
Now we'll show this in our example.
Since our graph is a proxy for
a road network, we can assume that we
know the coordinates of every node.
Therefore, we can compute
the distance between any two nodes.
In practice, we will choose a few nodes so
that we can compute the distance of every
other node from these chosen nodes.
These chosen nodes are called landmarks.
Let's assume B, which is our target,
is a landmark node, and
let's rewind to the state where
we are trying to choose between
the GD expansion or the FE expansion.
So we calculate the distance of F,
G and E from B.
BF is 20, BG is 80, and BE is 15.
Now we'll apply the formula like this.
For the FG case,
we subtract the BF distance
from the weight and
add the BD distance to the weight.
This gives us 70 because G is far from B.
Similarly for the FE case,
we subtract the BF distance and
add the BE distance to the weight and
it gives us 15.
Now, with these modified weights
we choose the FE expansion.
In practice this significantly improves
the actual performance of the algorithm.
So, this technique is used by many online
mapping services when they give you
directions.
So now let's bring back the constraints
that we have ignored so far.
There are two constraints here,
parts of the graph to include and
parts of the graph to exclude.
In this example we have to go to B, but
we should go to J first, and
then travel from B to J.
Also, we cannot use any
of the paths through E.
This really means two things.
First, we split the problem into two
independent shortest path problems
that we can solve in parallel if needed.
Second, when we go from J
to B We need to extract
the useful subgraph that
we need to consider.
For a large network and
a complex exclusion condition,
we will essentially operate
over a smaller graph,
thereby reducing the effective
size of the problem.
As we'll see in module three,
this kind of subgraph extraction operation
can be done effectively and
efficiently with a graph database system.
This concludes our short
tour of path analytics.
So, in this optional module, we'll look
at the two key player problems again.
The goal of the first problem is
to identify a small set of nodes,
whose removal will create
maximum disruption.
Now, in this case, a traditional
centrality algorithm may not work,
because the optimization goal
is to break up the network.
So we need a quantitive
measure of the breakage.
If dij is the distance between nodes i and
j, then 1 over dij is
the closeness of these two nodes.
If we add the closeness of all nodes and
normalize it by the number of node pairs,
we'll get a measure of
cohesiveness as a fraction.
So, 1 minus this value is
a measure of fragmentation.
Our goal is to maximize
this fragmentation metric.
In the model terrorist network shown here,
removing the red nodes A,
B, and C will break up the network
into seven components,
with F reaching a value of 0.59.
The second key player problem, is trying
to find a group of S influencers,
which can reach a maximum
number of nodes within K steps.
The number of unique nodes reachable from
a starting node is called the reach,
of the starting node.
For this we need to adapt the concept
of reach to limit it to k steps.
We also need to adapt it to measure
the distance of an arbitrary node
from a group of nodes
between our influences.
The distance from one node to a group
of nodes can be defined as a maximum,
or average, or minimum distance,
of the node from the members of the group.
Often, the minimum
distance is a good choice.
So the distance, we could reach,
can then be through of, as the proportion
of all nodes reached by the group,
where the nodes are weighted
by the distance from the set.
And only nodes at distance
1 are given full rate.
Hence, a distance we could reach
that use a maximum value of 1,
where every outside node is adjacent to at
least one member of the set of influences.
In the network shown,
just three nodes, A, C, and D,
are sufficient to reach every other
member within just four steps.
Now this concludes this module, where we
looked at several analytic techniques and
measures to extract different
kinds of insights from a network.
We saw how a community
in a graph can evolve.
To track the nature of evolution,
we need to measure how
the community changes over time.
So here are three cases.
One, two and three of a community
changing between two observation points.
The goal is to figure out whether these
are normal fluctuations in the network or
are more drastic changes occurring.
Look at them for a second.
Just visually, the first case
seems to show just minor changes.
Whereas case two shows a merger,
and case three shows a split.
Now, to come up with a quantitative
measure of change over time, we need to
take two observations from two consecutive
time points and fuse the graph.
If you do it for case one,
you'll find one new node,
one living node, and
the rest will come on over time.
For case two, you will see
that two previous communities,
colored differently, are internally
connected the same way as before.
But some members of the two communities
have created new crosslinks.
Now can you tell me what
you observe in case three?
Well I see one join node, color purple.
Apart from it, there are just two
edges connecting the two groups.
Now with these observations,
we can now compute the autocorrelation
between the graphs across time t and
t plus 1.
This is just a measure of
the number of common nodes
divided by the number of
nodes in the combined graph.
If the community does not change at all,
this number is 1.
If a community has only a few connection,
the number is lower.
After computing autocorrelation
over every pair of time steps,
we can then compute stationarity,
which measures the overall change in
the autocorrelation over a period of time.
So if we measure over 100 time steps,
we will add the 99 correlation values
from the steps and then divide it by 99.
This will tell us what fraction
of members remain unchanged
on an average over these 100 time steps.
Therefore, the 1 minus zeta tells
us the average ratio of members
that are changed in a time step.
Let's take three cases.
In the first plot,
the size of the graph is small and
nothing much is happening here.
A note occasionally joins or leaves,
keeping the stationarity pretty flat.
In the second case, the graph is small,
but there are a lot of changes, especially
at time step seven a whole bunch of purple
nodes have joined and then they went away.
The size of the graph
clearly reflects this
with a purple spike that you see
on the size versus the time graph.
This spike on the time series
by the way is called a burst.
The third plot shows a large graph
with many nodes joining and leaving.
The stationarity of this graph will be
quite low given the abrupt changes we
observe over time.
In this video,
we'll discuss what paths are and
how to find your way as it travels
along the nodes and edges of the graph.
Let's start with an example.
For this example,
we'll consider an edge weighted
graph with no loops as shown here.
Term edge weighted means
the edges have weights.
The weight of the edge I to J is 15.
We can think of this graph as a small road
network, where the nodes are cities, and
the edge weights are highway
distances between them.
To walk, or traverse, through this
graph we'll define what a walk is.
A walk is an arbitrary
sequence of nodes and
edges that starts from some node and
ends on some node.
Here we can go from H to F
to G to C to
F to E to B.
Notice that in this walk,
we went through the node F twice.
In many applications, we do not want
to consider arbitrary walks but
consider a walk where
we do not repeat nodes
unless we need to come back
to the starting point.
Such a constrained walk is called a path.
The green arrows indicate
a path from J to B.
We said on the last slide that a path
can start from a node and end on it.
Such a path is called a cycle when
the path has a three or more nodes.
The J, G, C,
F, J, is a four node cycle,
sometimes called a four cycle.
C, F, E is a three cycle.
However, although there is an edge from
F to J and another from J back to F,
this two node path is not
a cycle by our definition.
A network with no cycles
is called acyclic.
A graph that is both directed and
acyclic is called a directed
acyclic graph, in short, a deck.
A trail is a concept similar to a path,
it is a walk with no repeating edges.
In the graph shown in the walk,
H, F, G, C, F, E,
C, F, J, is not a trail.
Because C, F Is traversed twice.
Remember the seven bridges of
the Konigsberg problem that we described
in module one?
In that problem,
we had the constraint that one
cannot cross the same bridge twice.
Often we see such constraints
in path planning problems.
A common notion in directive
graphs is called reachability.
If there is a path from node U to node V,
V is reachable from U.
Reachability is not symmetric.
Even if V is reachable from U,
U may or may not be reachable from V.
As we can see in this graph,
I is not reachable from A.
Look at A more carefully.
There is no outgoing edge from A at all.
So no node in this graph
is reachable from A.
A is a terminal, a leaf node of the graph.
Where do we see this in real life?
Think of road network with one way streets
and road blocks through the construction.
This can make some areas
unreachable by cars.
In biology,
there are gene regulation networks,
in which the nodes represent genes and
edges represent the fact that gene
A regulates gene B and not visa verse.
This makes it a directed graph.
We can easily think of a case where
A regulates B, and B regulates C, but
C does not regulate B or A.
That's making A unreachable from C.
The final concept you will
explore in this graph,
in this lecture,
is that of a graph diameter.
The diameter of a graph measures the
maximum number of steps, also called hops,
want us to traverse to go to
the most distant node in the graph.
That means,
if you go from an arbitrary node
to any other arbitrary node in the graph,
following only the shortest paths roots,
what is the maximum number
of steps you have to take?
Let's see how this is computed.
For this task, we'll create a matrix
called the shortest hop distance matrix.
Just like the adjacency matrix, the rows
and columns here represent graph nodes.
And each cell contains the distance
from the I eighth node,
to the G eighth node
via the shortest path.
The distance from any
node to itself is zero.
So all diagonal elements
of the matrix are zero.
If a node I cannot reach
node J through any path,
the distance is marked as infinity.
Thus, the distance from
B to C is infinity.
You can go from E to F in two steps,
E to C to F.
Therefore, the wait at the C cell is two.
If you fill this matrix, you will
notice that the largest reachable value
is 4 in doing the infinite distance.
Thus, the diameter of this graph is
4 where It represents the part from I
to A, through J, G and D.
There are a few noteworthy
items in this Distance Matrix.
The row of A has a value of 0 with itself
and infinity for every other node.
This happens because A is a leaf node.
Similarly, except for
the 0 distance with itself,
the H column has infinity for
all of the nodes.
This happens because H
has no incoming edges and
therefore no other node can reach H.