There are many ways of
looking at scalability.
And we'll consider them as
we go forward in the course.
One way is to consider scaling up and
scaling out.
Simply put,
it is a decision between making a machine
that makes a server more powerful
versus adding more machines.
The first choice will
involve adding more memory,
replacing processes with
process of more course and
adding more processes within a system with
a very fast internet connection speed.
The second choice will involve adding more
machines to a relatively slower network.
Now, there are no absolutes here.
In many cases, we'll choose the former
to get more performance for
large leader systems.
The general trend in the big data world,
however, is to target
the scale out option.
Most big data management systems today
are designed to operate over
a cluster up machines and
have the ability to adjust as more
machines are added and when machines fail.
Cluster management and management
of data operations over a cluster
is an important component in today's
big data management systems.
Now we'll briefly touch upon
the complex issue of data security.
It is obvious that having more sensitive
data implies the need for more security.
If the data is within
the walls of an organization,
we'll still need a security plan.
However, if a big data system
is deployed in the cloud,
over multiple machines, security of
data becomes an even bigger challenge.
So now we need to ensure the security for
not only the machines,
but also the network which will be
heavily used during data transfer
across different phases
of data operations.
For example, if the data store and
the data analysis are performed over
different sets of servers that
every analysis operation gets to
an additional overhead of encrypting the
data as the data gets to the network and
decrypting when it gets
to the processing server.
This effectively increases
operational cost.
As of today, while there are many
security products, the methods for
ensuring security and achieving data
processing efficiency at the same time
remains a research issue
in big data management.
Now the goal of a storage infrastructure,
obviously, is to store data.
There are two storage related
issues we consider here.
The first is the issue of capacity.
How much storage should we allocate?
That means, what should be the size
of the memory, how large and
how many disk units should we have,
and so forth.
There is also the issue of scalability.
Should the storage devices be
attached directly to the computers
to make the direct IO fast but
less scalable?
Or should the storage be
attached to the network
that connect the computers in the cluster?
This will make disk
access a bit slower but
allows one to add more
storage to the system easily.
Now these questions do
not have a simple answer.
If you're interested, you may look up
a website given on your reading list.
A different class of questions deals
with the speed of the IU operation.
This question is often addressed with
this kind of diagram here called a memory
hierarchy, or storage hierarchy, or
sometimes memory storage hierarchy.
The top of the pyramid structure shows
a part of memory called cache memory,
that lives inside the CPU and
is very fast.
There are different levels of cache,
called L1, L2, L3,
where L3 is the slowest but
still faster than what we call memory,
shown here in orange near the middle.
The figure shows their speed
in terms of response times.
Notice the memory streamed here
is 65 nanoseconds per access.
In contrast,
the speed of the traditional hard disk
is of the order of 10 milliseconds.
This gap has prompted the design
of many data structures and
algorithms.that use a hard disk but
tries to minimize the cost of
the IO operations between the fast
memory and the slower disk.
But more recently,
a newer kind of storage.
Very similar to the flash drives or
USBs that we regularly use have made
an entry as a new storage medium.
These devices are called SSDs or
Solid State Devices.
They are much faster
than spinning hard disks.
An even newer addition is
the method called NVMe,
NVM stands for non-volatile memory,
that makes data transfer between SSDs and
memory much faster.
What all this means in a big data system
is that now we have the choice of
architecting a storage infrastructure
by choosing how much of each type of
storage we need to have.
In my own research with large amounts
of data, I have found that using SSDs
speed up all look up operations in data by
at least a factor of ten over hard drives.
Of course the flip side of
this is the cost factor.
The components become increasingly more
expensive as we go from the lower layers
of the pyramid to the upper layers.
So ultimately, it becomes an issue
of cost-benefit tradeoff.
[SOUND] Let us consider
a real life application to
demonstrate the utility and
the challenges of big data.
Many industries naturally deal
with large amounts of data.
For our discussion, we consider
an energy company that provides gas and
electricity to its
consumers in an urban area.
In this news report, you can see
that Commonwealth Edison, or Con Ed,
the gas and electric provider of New York,
decided to place smart meters
all through its jurisdictions.
That comes to 4.7 million smart meters.
Now smart meters are smart because aside
from measuring energy consumption,
they have a two way communication
capability between the meter and
the central system at the gas and
electric company.
In other words, they generate real time
data from the meters to be stored and
processed at the central facility.
How much data?
According to this report,
the number of data received at
the center is 1.5 billion per day.
So the system will not only consume
this data, but process it and
produce output at 15-minute intervals,
and sometimes, 5 minute intervals.
Let's do the math.
That comes to ingesting and processing
about 10.5 million data
points per 15 minutes.
So what kind of computation must
take place within these 15 minutes?
Well, one obvious computation is billing,
where one needs to compute who, especially
in the commercial sector, who actually
owns the meter and should be billed?
This requires combining the meter data
with the data in the customer
database maintained by the company.
But let's just consider
computation related to analytics.
We can list at least four
different kinds of computations.
The first is computing the consumption
pattern per user, not per meter.
Per user, where the output is
a histogram of hourly usage.
So the x axis of the histogram
is hourly intervals And
the y-axis is a number of units consumed.
This leads to the computed both daily and
over larger time periods.
To determine the hourly requirements for
this consumer.
The second computation relates
to estimating the effects of
outdoor temperature on the electricity
consumption of each consumer.
For those you who
are statistically inclined,
this often involves fitting a piece-wise
linear progression model to the data.
The third task is to extract the daily
consumption trends that occur
regardless of the outdoor temperature.
This is again a statistical computation,
and may require something like
a periodic alter regression algorithm,
for time series theta.
The algorithm is not that important there.
What's more important is the ability to
make make good prediction has a direct
economic impact because the company
needs to buy energy from others.
For example, an under-prediction
implies they'll end up paying more for
buying energy at the last moment to
meet the consumer's requirements.
The fourth task is to find groups of
similar consumers based on their usage
pattern so that the company can determine
how many distinct groups of customers
there are and design targeted energy
saving campaigns for each group.
This requires finding similarities
over large number of time series data,
which is a complex computation.
Regardless of the number and
complexity of computation required,
the company's constrained by the fact that
it has only 15 minutes to process the data
before the next and
computation has to be performed.
That issue is not just
the bigness of the data, but
the strip and
strings of the arrival to output time.
The analytics has value, only if it can be
completed within the life-cycle deadline.
So if we were to design a big data system
for such a company, you would need to
understand how much are the computation
can be executed in parallel And
how many machines with what kind of
capability are required to handle the data
rate and the number and complexity of
the analytical computations needed?
Hi, my name is Chad Berkley.
I'm the CTO of FlightStats, and I'm here
today to talk to you a little bit about
our platform and
how we acquire and process data.
But first of all, I'd like to start by
just kind of introducing the company and
telling you a little bit
about what we're all about.
So FlightStats is a data company and
we basically are the leading provider
of global real-time flight status data.
We pull in data from over 500 sources and
we aggregate that data back together, and
we sell it out to our customers which our
other businesses as well as consumers.
So just to give you a little bit
of information about the scope and
scale of what we do.
Like I said,
we have over 500 sources of data.
And on a daily basis,
we process about 15 million flight events,
those that includes landings,
arrivals, departures.
Any time the status of the flight changes,
we got some sort of message on that.
We process about 260 million aircraft
positions per day, so we have an extensive
network that monitors graph positions for
realtime flight tracking applications.
And we also handle about One million PNRs,
or passenger name records,
which are the actual data type
of an itenerary any time you
book travel, a PNR is created for
you, for your travel.
And it includes all of the segments,
like air travel, ferries,
hotels, taxis, Anyhting that
can be scheduled on your trip.
And we basically take in all that data and
we aggregate it together and
we sell it back out.
And how most people kind of know us for
FlightStats.com, that's our
consumer site for business where we
handle about 2 million daily requests.
And we handle about 1
million mobile app requests.
That our b to b side, we cert out a lot
of data by APIs and real time data feeds.
People make about 15 million
API requests to us everyday.
And we also send out about one and half
million flight and trip notifications.
So if you get a push
notification to your phone,
telling you that your flight is delayed or
on time.
That possibly has come from us.
So a little bit about how the data
flows through our company.
We bring in all these
different types of data and
our sources and it flows through
our data acquisition team.
We have a team whose primary purpose
is to pull in all sorts of raw data,
a very heterogeneous datasets.
And process that into a normalized form.
So if you kind of follow the blue arrow
in this diagram you can see that it goes
through this raw data
channel through the data hub.
Which the data hub is a central
component of our system that I'll talk
a little bit more about in a second.
So the blue data, the blue line is
raw data coming in from the source
It goes through our data
acquisition system,
it turns into that purple line
which is a normalized form.
It then goes back through our data hub
again and into our processing engine.
Our processing engine is really where
most of the business logic happens.
The first thing we have to do
is we have to match any piece of
flight information against
a flight that we know about and
primarily the way we know about
flights is through schedules.
So we import schedules on a daily
basis from one of our partner
schedule providers.
That data,
once it's matched is then processed and
the processing basically looks at each
message, and tries to determine if
we think that that message needs
to be passed on to consumers.
So you know it looks at things like,
have we seen that message before.
Or is it a duplicate?
Is it from a data source that we trust?
Are there other things going on
that we need to know about that
may impact whether that message is true or
not?
And once we decide that a message
should be passed through,
if you follow the green line.
It goes into our process
data channel on our hub, and
it's then pushed out to
a couple different places.
So first of all,
it goes into our production database which
is where all of our real time data lives.
That database serves data to our websites,
to our mobile apps, and
a variety of other places.
It also goes into our
data warehouse which,
is where our analytics products use it.
I'll talk a bit more
about that in a minute.
And then, the stream of data actually
goes up to so many of our customers.
We don't need a database on our side.
They would rather build
a database on their side so
we actually just stream all of
the processed data directly to them.
They then host it within
their own systems.
So a little bit more about the hub, the
hub is central to how we move data around.
It's a technology that
we developed in-house.
And it's an object storage based,
scalable, highly available,
multi-channel data queuing and
eventing system.
The object storage part is,
we use Amazon S3 to store this data.
So it's an object storage system.
It's scalable,
we can scale it horizontally or
vertically depending on, but the what
type of data is flowing through it.
It's highly available meaning,
that we have multiple instances
of it in different data centers.
So if one that goes down we can
easily pull another one up or
it's we're going to cross
multiple instances.
And then it's multi channel.
So it's got a rest interface and
any surface can create
a new channel within the system and
start posting data to it.
That data is then queued based on
the time that it comes in, and
other services can be listening for
events on those channels.
So, as soon as a new piece of data
comes into one of those channels,
any service that's listening on that
channel, gets an event notification.
They, that service can then
act upon that piece of data.
And do whatever processing
it may need to do.
This project is open source and
anybody can download it and use it.
So a little bit about some of the data
that we collect and aggregate.
And FLIFO is kind of the industry term for
flight information.
And primarily we look at kind of
the five different parts of flight.
So we pull in information on gate
departure, and then that becomes a runway
departure, basically when the wheels
go up, that is a runway departure.
We do in-flight positional tracking,
so when your flight is moving along,
about once every ten seconds we get
notified of its latitude and longitude.
And its heading and its speed and
its vertical center descent rate and
several other variables.
Then once it lands,
as soon as the wheels touch the ground,
we're notified of a runway arrival and
when the door is opened at the gate,
we have gate arrival information.
All five of these data fields
come in three different forms.
So we have a scheduled,
scheduled departure and arrival.
We have estimated departure and arrival
which can come from a variety of sources,
either airlines, airports,
positional data, et cetera.
And then, we have actuals so
if we have an airport or
an airline that's sending us data about
exactly when the wheels touch down, or
exactly when that door opens on that
aircraft, we push that data as well.
We also generate some
data at flight stops.
So special incidents, if an aircraft
has an issue It's in the news.
We do flag our content with
a message from our support staff.
We do some prediction.
Right now we're just starting to get into
that market, or we're actually trying to
predict 24 hours out whether a flight
will be delayed, disrupted or on time.
We do some synthetic positions,
so over oceans, primarily.
We don't get tracking data
on aircraft over the oceans.
There is currently no satellite-based
tracking system for aircraft.
So we basically take the last
known position a heading, a speed.
And if we have a flight plan, we'll use
a flight plan to synthesize the positions
when we're not getting actual
positions over large bodies of water.
We also generate notifications,
so the push alerts,
the preflight emails,
delay notifications those types of things.
We create those based on what we see
in the data that's coming in to us.
We store all of our historical
data in a data warehouse,
so right now we have six years
of historical flight data.
And that powers our analytics products,
so we allow airlines to do competitive
analysis, and route analysis.
Routes are very important to airlines.
That's how they compete
with each other and
that's primarily how they
are judged by the FAA and
other governmental organizations
on whether they're on-time or not.
We also do airport operations analysis
things like taxi in and taxi out times.
Very important for lots of airports,
runway utilization,
hourly passenger flows through airports,
that type of information.
And we do on-time performance metrics so.
Airlines can look at how they're doing.
How many flights did they complete?
How many flights were on
time within 14 minutes?
And they can compare themselves
to their competitors.
So we host all of this in
a hybrid cloud architecture.
Hybrid cloud basically means that we have
our own private datacenter resources and
we also host resources in
the Amazon Web Services cloud.
Most of our core data processing and
service layer is in our private data
center and we're getting ready to spin
up a second private data center as well.
Right now, our main data center is in
Portland, Oregon, and we're going to spin
another one up on the east coast of
the United States probably in Q2 or Q3.
For our API's we try to keep
those close to our customers so
API end points and
web end points live in Amazon.
And they are automatically routed to
whichever end point is closest to you,
you will automatically be routed to them.
All of our private infrastructure
is virtualized with VMWare.
We pretty much have a fully
virtualized environment.
And we're an Agile shop, so
we have six small, fast teams.
Those are product centric teams, we
allow them to be as customer interactive
as they need to be, and
we try to make our teams semi autonomous.
So, teams get to choose their own tools,
they get to choose their
own development methodologies,
they choose a variety of things.
And We physically allow them
to do what they need to do to get
their job done as quickly as possible.
We try to automate everything.
You do something once manually and
then the next time you write a script or
program to do it.
And we also measure everything.
Right now, we're taking in about
2.5 billion metrics per month off
of our systems.
And we use those metrics to monitor
our application performance,
to monitor revenue, to monitor pretty
much everything we do in the company.
We really try to enable
total system awareness,
everything from the hardware layer
up to the website is monitored.
And we use industry best practices and
tools and of course, we try to recruit and
hire the best talent possible a little
bit about our software stock.
We're primarily a Java shop.
Our core processing services
are all written in Java.
We do use node JS in our
Microservice Edge layer.
And node JS is actually starting to move
more down into the processing service
layer as well.
We use many different types of data bases.
Our primary realtime
database is Post Press.
And we use Mongo for
the backend of our API services.
On the website, we're all HTML5 and
we're moving to React and Redux, and
we're making use of Elasticsearch for
quick searching and indexing on our data.
And, of course, we have iOS and
Android mobile applications.
So you can find out more about
Flightstats on our website.
If you need data for your applications,
please go to the developer center
at developer.flightstats.com.
You can sign up for
a free test account and
be able to pull data
directly off of our APIs.
If you're interested in the Hub,
like I said that's open source.
Please check out the Git Hub page and
if you have any additional questions,
feel free to contact
myself John Berkeley and
I'd be happy to answer any
of your questions via email.
Thanks for listening today and
hope you have a great day.
Bye.
Different data sources in the game
industry include using your finger.
What type of device is coming from?
The amount of headsets.
It's pretty much infinite,
as far as the number of ways we
can bring data in from the game.
And it could be joystick or mouse,
keyboards, there's lots of ways
as well as what happens inside
the game itself as far cars or
the driving, tires,
flying machines, anything.
The volume of data,
it really depends on the type of game and
how often they want to send the data in.
How many types of events they've tagged
and how many users are playing the game.
So if you have a user, you've 5 million
users that are playing your game and
you're tapping and
you're tracking each tap of the screen,
of where they went or each click of
the mouse as they were using it,
you're going to get
a lot of volume of data.
And so
you need to be prepared to bring in a lot
of different data very, very quickly.
As far as the variety of data, it depends.
You have round pizzas and
you have round tires.
I mean, they're completely different.
They're both round, but there's different
ways that you're going to want to know how
many pepperoni are on one pizza and
how many lug nuts go on a tire.
So the variety is really unlimited,
as well.
It really just depends on each game.
So, you have to be prepared to
bring in all kinds of data.
Touch data, wheel data,
track speeds, anything.
And if you put taxonomy together that
you can define as an example of verb,
object, location, value and any number
of other sources, then you can basically
track anything you want as long as they
all fall into the same kind of buckets.
And the buckets can be different
sizes based on the type of events.
They don't all need to be 4,
some can be 2, some can be 20,
it doesn't really matter.
The modeling challenge has really come
down to who designs the structure at which
you store your data and
how you want to retrieve that data.
Those kind of of storage and
retrieval models are very, very important,
because what it really
comes down to is speed.
You can record a lot of data and
it can take you five years to query it,
it doesn't really do you any good.
So you need to make sure you plan for
reporting speed, because that's ultimately
what within the organisation needs is
the ability to report on it very quickly.
The management challenges really come
down to trying to figure out what data to
store.
A lot of times we go into various
companies and you've got producers sitting
across the hall from designers, and
they don't even know each other.
They don't realize what they want and
the programmer says,
I'm going to put these events in and the
product manager who wants to figure out
how many times somebody crashed says,
well, I need these events in.
So unless they're communicating, you're
going to get the wrong type of data.
So the management challenge is trying
to make sure everybody communicates,
they decide on the taxonomy and
the structure and
then we can go forward with tagging and
getting in the entire game working.
We process, stayed in two main ways.
One is streaming data.
One is batched or scheduled data.
Streaming data has scripts that run
instantly the minute the data arrives.
And so as the data come in,
it gets processed and
then stored In a reporting format.
So they can easily generate reports
up to the second very, very quickly.
Batch processing data really depends on
the type of data where it's coming from.
Most of the time when we download
data from iTunes or YouTube or
something like that, it comes in a CSV or
a very similar format.
There's not really a lot of
processing we need to do.
It's more of ingesting that data.
There are processes we need to run
with some type of batch data, but
most of the batch data we
receive comes in as a CSV or
other similar already processed formats.
So typically, while you can do processing
in both modes most processing typically
happens with the streaming real-time data
than it does with offline batch data.
We actually didn't use any
technology in the a big data space.
We created our own, from scratch.
What we did was we decided
what kind of model we wanted.
How we were going to store data?
How we were going to retrieve data?
And ultimately,
how we were going to reduce the data?
Because the more and more and more data
you have, the slower it is to actually do
a query, because you have to look through
all the different pieces of data.
A lot of databases solve this problem for
you, but they were really doing it in more
generic way were we needed
something very specific.
So we started from scratch building our
own data storage and retrieval, and
reporting from the ground up.
When it came to scalability,
it was really about designing the parts of
the system that could be
independently scaled.
So if data's coming in in real-time,
we send that into what we call a gateway.
And the gateway could be three gateways,
let's say.
But if the data starts
getting over loaded,
I just have to add another gateway.
And a gateway is just this little
light layer that just receives data,
passes it on and goes back to it's job,
doesn't do anything else.
So it can receive a lot
of data very quickly, but
also I can just add another one.
And it just automatically logs in and
adds itself to a list and
now the data is being distributed
amongst four gateways instead.
Query engine is the same way.
When you're doing queries to try
to get data out of the system, so
you can build reports.
If I need more query engines,
because people are doing more reporting,
we can add more query engines.
So, the idea behind scalability is
trying to break the services up into
the type of services that
they most make sense.
So that if you need to,
you can add just the service without
rebuilding the entire platform.
My advice for people designing systems for
big data is to first,
try to understand what
you want to accomplish.
What's the goal?
I mean, we're going to ingest everything
and we're going to report on everything.
It's not really something that you can
achieve without some special thought.
If you're going to focus on,
your area's going to be say gardening,
then look at what kind of things you're
going to do in the gardening area and
try to focus on what that
type of data is going to be.
This isn't going to restrict you
to only being a gardener, but
it is going to give you focus
on how to design your system, so
that they're actually going to work for
you.
You're going to continually evolve your
systems, add more things to them and
grow them.
I wouldn't suggest starting with
an unlimited variety of options and
hoping you're going to
solve all the problems.
Start with the goal of what your current
solution is and expand from there.
Data can be fun, but
it can also be overwhelming.
So, try to keep the data in mind
without keeping the world in mind and
I think you'll be just fine.