Next, we'll count the number of
vertices and edges, define a min and
max function for Spark's reduce method,
computer the min and max degrees,
and compute the histogram data
of the degree of connectedness.
In this hands on,
we will cover the degree distribution of
the metros graph from
the first hands on exercise.
This will help you practice finding
the degrees of connectedness in a graph.
These numbers will be used for
plotting the visualizations in
the next hands on exercises.
The degree of a vertex is
the number of edges or
connections the vertex has to
other vertices in the graph.
In directed graphs,
each vertex has an in degree,
the number of edges
directed to the vertex.
In and out degree, the number of
edges directed away from the vertex.
The metros graph is an example
of a directed graph.
Each metropolis vertex has one
outgoing edge to a country vertex.
Each country vertex has one or more
incoming edges from metropolis vertices.
This will be a quiz question.
Starting again where we left off from
the previous hands-on exercise, first,
ensure your Cloudera VM is started, and
that you downloaded the dataset
examples of analytics.
The link is in the content for this week.
Use the numEdges attribute to print
the number of edges in metrosGraph.
As you can see the result is 65,
which matches the number of
lines in metro_country.csv.
Now use the numVertices
attribute to print the number
of vertices in metrosGraph.
As you can see the result is 93,
which matches the number of
lines in metro.csv65 plus the number
of lines in country.csv, 28.
Define the max and the min reduce
operation to compute the highest and
lowest degree vertex.
Let us find the vertex with
the most outgoing edges or
the vertex with the largest
out degree by passing the max
function to a reduced operation on
the out degrees of metrosGraph.
The result in this case is vertex
ID five with one outgoing edge.
The result could have been any metropolis
because every metropolis in this graph
has one outgoing edge to its country.
Let us find the vertex with
the most incoming edges, or
the vertex with the largest inDegree.
This is done the same way
as the previous example,
except you'll run the reduce operation
on the inDegrees of metrosGraph.
The result is VertexId 108
with 14 incoming edges.
Apply a filter to the metrosGraph
vertices to find out which vertex is 108.
The answer is the United States.
This means that the United States has
14 metropolises in the metros.csvfile.
We can also compute how many vertices have
one out going edge by applying a filter of
one to the outgoing degrees and
counting the results.
The result is 65 because there are 65
metropolises with one outgoing degree.
None of the countries have
any outgoing degrees.
Let us ignore whether or
not the edge is in or out, and
just find which vertex has the most edges.
Again, we will run the reduce
operation with the max function.
But this time we will run it on
metrosGraph's degrees attribute.
The result is 108 again
with 14 connections.
This means that the United States is
the most connected vertex in metrosGraph.
Finally, let us calculate
the histogram data of the degrees for
the countries in metrosGraph.
First, create a map that
only includes countries.
So create a filter to only include
the vertices with the vertex ID that is
greater than or equal to 100.
Then you will group the map
by the size of the degree and
sort the map from lowest
to highest degree.
The output shows six pairs in an array.
The first number is the number of edges,
and
the second number is the number of
vertices that have that number of edges.
In other words, the result of
the query shows that there are 18
countries with 1 metropolis,
4 countries with 2 metropolises,
2 countries with 3 metropolises,
2 countries with 5 metropolises,
1 country with 9 metropolises, and
1 country with 14 metropolises.
Next, we'll import the GraphX libraries,
import the Vertices, import the Edges,
create a Graph, and use Spark's filter
method to return Vertices in the graph.
Hi, this is Cristine Kirkpatrick,
division director for
Information Technology Systems and
Services at
the San Diego Super Computer Center.
I'll guide you through
the hands-on exercises.
I recommend you follow
along with the video once.
Then, either using the video or
the hands-on reading, go through the
hands-on exercise on your own computer.
This hands-on exercise will show you
how to build a graph using GraphX,
Spark's API for graphs, and
graph-parallel computation.
We'll start with importing the data and
then build a simple graph.
Note that the first four hands on
assignments are meant to be completed
sequentially.
That is, you will need to have your
Cloudera VM running continuously.
If you must shut down your VM and
restart, you will need to run the commands
from this first hands on assignment again.
Otherwise you may receive error messages
because the data has not been imported.
The data references metro areas.
In an effort to disambiguate or
distinguish between metropolitan areas and
an English word also used
to refer to a train or
light rail, when we mean metro
area we will say metropolis.
First, ensure your
cloudera vm is started and
that you've downloaded the data set,
examples of analytics.
The link is in the content for this week.
The download process might name
the zip file something very long.
Copy the examples of analytics.zip
file to the cloudera's home folder.
If the zip file is on the desktop,
simply drag it to the Cloudera's
home folder on the desktop.
If the file is saved elsewhere,
then you will need to navigate
to the folder where it is saved before
dragging it to the Cloudera's home folder.
Open the terminal window by clicking the
terminal icon at the top of the screen.
Use the unzip command to extract the zip
file to the cloudera home directory.
You can copy and
paste the name of the zip file.
Let it extract with the default name,
ExamplesOfAnalytics.
Go into the ExamplesOfAnalytics
directory and
list the contents of
the EOA data directory.
You should see five .csv files and
one .txt file.
In order to access the CSV and TXT files,
we have to first copy the files to HDFS.
Rally HDFS foot command to copy
the EOA data directory to HDFS
then less the contents of
the EOA data directory on HDFS.
Start the spark shell and include the
graph stream and breeze fizz libraries.
Don't worry about copying
the full command from the video.
A text version will be included within
the course reading that contains the full
command for you to copy and paste.
Import the log for j classes and
suppress the notice in info messages.
Import sparks graphx and
rdd classes along with scala source class.
The data set we are going to use in
this hands on is from three files.
The metro.csv file and the country.csv
file contain the vertices for
the graph and
metro underscore country.csv.
contains the edges that make up the
relationships between the metro areas and
the country they belong too.
Before importing any of the CSV files, we
are going to list the first five lines of
each file to verify that
they are indeed CSV files.
Notice that the metric.csv contains an ID,
the metropolis name and the population.
The country.csv file contains
only an ID and the country name.
The metro_country.csv file
contains the metro ID and
the ID of the country that
the metropolis belongs to.
Create a class called PlaceNode to store
the information about the vertices.
Then extend the PlaceNode class
with case classes specifically for
the metro's and the countries vertices.
Create attributes for
the metro class to store the name and
the population from the CSV file.
The country class only needs
an attribute to store the name.
To import the metro.csv file, create
a spark resilient distributive data set or
rdd named metros made up of
a vertex id in the metro class.
An rdd represents an immutable
partition collection
of elements that can be
operated on in parallel.
When the contents of
the .csv files printed,
the line with the column names
started with the symbol #.
So create a filter to ignore any
line that starts with a # so
that the column names
don't import into the RDD.
The .csv files being imported
contain values separated by commas.
So you will need to split each line
in the metro.csv file into rows,
by using a comma as a delimiter.
Map the first row to the vertex ID.
The second row is the metro
name attribute, and
the third row is the population attribute.
You're going to import the country's .csv
feed file the same way as the metro.csv
feed file.
However this time since the ids in both
the metro.csv file and the country.csv
file start with one you will add 100
to the vertex id of the countries.
So that the vertex ids are unique
between both data sets.
If the ids are not unique
that will prevent us from
creating an accurate graph.
This will be on the quiz.
Import the edges into
an RDD named mclinks.
This is done the same way as
the previous two examples.
Remember to add 100 to
the countries vertex ID.
Concatenate the metros and countries
vertices into a single variable and
use GraphX's graph function to
create a graph of the metros and
countries vertices with
the MC links edges.
Let us take a look at
what is in the graph.
Use the vertices and edges attributes
to print five vertices and
five edges from the metros graph.
Query the graph to find
how the metropolises and
the countries are related.
Let us find which country Tokyo is in.
Tokyo has a vertex ID of 1.
Use RDD's filter method to filter
all of the edges in metro's graph
that have a source for text ID of one and
create a map of destination vertex ID's.
The result is 101 which is Japan.
You can verify this by looking at
the metro.csv and country.csv files.
Remember, we added 100 to
the IDs in country.csv.
Now, let us do the opposite and
find all of the metropolises that are in
China which has a vertex ID of 103.
This time we're going to filter
all of the edges in metro's graph
that have a vertex ID of 103 and
create a map of all of the source IDs.
The result is 3,4, 7, 24, and 34.
You can look in metrostats.csv and verify
that those metropolises are in China.
Next, we'll create a new dataset,
join two datasets with JoinVertices,
join two datasets with outerJoinVertices,
and create a new return type for
the joined vertices.
In this hands-on exercise,
we will create a new graph made
up of five airline flights.
The vertices will represent the airports,
and the edges will represent
the departures and the arrivals.
Once the graph has been created
we will add a second dataset
with additional airport information and
practice using GraphX's join methods to
create new graphs by joining the datasets.
We will start a new spark shell session,
so
we will be opening a new terminal window.
Open the new terminal window by
clicking the terminal icon at the top
of the screen.
Start the spark shell.
Import the log for j classes and
suppress the notice and info messages.
Import sparks graphics and rdd classes.
Now we will create the vertices
ourselves from a list.
The list will contain the vertex ID and
the name of the airport.
Now we will create the edges.
The edges will represent a flight
departing from one airport and
arriving at another.
We will set the edge property
to a fake flight number.
Create the flights graph
by joining the vertices and
the edges using graph
flexes graph functions.
Let us explore the graph so far.
Look through each triplet in flights graph
and print the contents of the graph.
We will specify which airport
the flight departs from,
which airport the flight arrives at,
and the flight number.
You'll just put all of
the vertices in the graph.
Now we are willing to create an additional
dataset to store additional information
about each airport.
First, we will create a case class called
airport information with the city and
airport code properties.
Then we are going to create the airport
information vertices from a list
as we did earlier.
We will make sure the vertex ID for
the airport information matches the vertex
ID of the airport defined earlier.
Note, there does not have to be a one
to one relationship between the airport
vertices and
the airport information vertices.
Los Angeles International Airport is
present in the airport vertices, but
it is missing from the airport
information vertices.
The airport information vertices contains
information about airports in London and
Hong Kong.
But we don't have any flights departing or
arriving from those airports.
Let us complete our first join.
A mapping function has to be defined in
order to join vertices with graphics join
vertices method.
We are going to define a map function that
will join the name of the airport from
the airport vertices with the city name
from the airport information vertices.
In order to create a new graph with
the vertices that has the airport name
colon city name.
After the map function in defined,
then we will use the joined vertices
method to create the new graph.
Vertices without a matching value in
the RDD, retain their original value.
Now, print out the vertices
of the new graph.
Notice all of the vertices contain
the airport and city names,
except Los Angeles International Airport,
which retained its original value.
Now we will join the vertices using
GraphX's outerJoinVertices method.
OuterJoinVertices is
similar to JoinVertices,
except that the user-defined map
function is applied to all vertices and
it can change the vertex property type.
Here, we are using the OuterJoinVertices
method to create a new graph where
the vertices contain a property
with the name of the airport and
a property makeup of
the airport information class.
Print the vertices once
the new graph is made.
Notice that the type of the second
vertex property is sum.
This is because
Los Angeles International Airport
does not have a corresponding
vertex in airport information.
Therefore GraphX assigned all of
the properties the sum type so
that all of the vertex
property types are the same.
We can use the get or
else method to assign a default
value if one does not exist.
Now, let us rerun
the outer join vertices but
this time use the get, get or
else method to create an airport
information class with NA as the values
for the city and the airport code.
Print the vertices once
the new graph is made.
Now, the type of the second vertex
property is airport information in
Los Angeles International Airport,
airport information class,
has the properties NA and NA.
Finally, in this last exercise, we will
create a new case class called Airport
that contains property for the name,
city, and code of the airport.
First, we will define the new Airport
case class with the name, city, and
code properties.
Then use the outer join vertices
method to join the data sets, and
create the new graph.
Create a mapping so if the airport has an
airport information vertex, the city and
code are taken from the instance
of the airport information class.
Otherwise, only include the airport name.
Finally, print the vertices
of the new graph.
The new graph has only one vertex property
which is an instance of the airport class.
GraphX has lots of methods for
joining graph datasets.
This hands on example only scratched
the surface of GraphX's power.
Next, we'll create a new graph by
adding the continents dataset,
import the GraphStream library,
import the countriesGraph into
a GraphStream SingleGraph,
visualize the countriesGraph,
and visualize the Facebook graph.
In this hands-on exercise we
will use the GraphStream library
to visualize countries graph.
The metros graph that we have been
working with in the previous exercises.
This time with the continent vertices and
edges added.
Starting again where we left off
from the previous hands-on exercise,
ensure your [INAUDIBLE] has started and
that you've imported the data.
First, in order to make
the graph more interesting,
we are going to import additional
vertices from the continent.csv, and
additional edges from
country_continent.csv to create
a relationship between the country and
the continent it belongs to.
We will show the steps for
importing the datasets, but
we do not cover the steps in detail.
If you aren't sure how to
import a dataset, go back and
view the video called
hands-on building a graph.
Now, we are going to concatenate the
metros, countries, and continents vertices
into a single variable and concatenate
the metros to countries edges, and
countries to continent edges
into another single variable.
Finally, you will create a new
graph called countriesGraph.
Now, import the GraphStream library.
We will not go over in detail how
to use the GraphStream library.
You can review its documentation and
other online resources on your
own if you are interested.
First, create a new instance of
GraphStreams SingleGraph class,
using the countriesGraph.
Next, we will set some attributes for
the graph we are going to visualize,
including setting a style for the graph.
GraphStream uses cascading style sheets or
CSS just like ordinary web pages,
to control the appearance of the graph.
The zip file that you downloaded from
Coursera contain the CSS file that we will
use in this hands-on exercise.
Now, load the countries graph
vertices into the visualization
using GraphStreams add node method.
Notice that we are setting
the style UI.class of each vertex
depending on if the vertex is an instance
of the metro, country or continent class.
Add the edges of country's graph to
the visualization using GraphStreams
add edge method.
Finally, call the display
method to visualize the graph.
The graph will look similar to this.
The small blue dots are the metropolises,
the medium sized red dots
are the countries, and
the large green dots are the continents.
By looking at the clusters
you can easily identify which
continent in the visualization
is Antarctica.
It is the green dot that
has no connections or
it is the least connected
cluster in the network.
I hope your paying attention,
because this will be on the quiz.
The large cluster of dots at the bottom is
Asia because it has the most countries and
metropolises in the graph.
The Asia cluster is the most
connected cluster in the network.
Can you identify which clusters
are the other continents
by looking at the visualization?
Let's look at the visualization
of a much larger dataset,
the Facebook dataset with 90,000 vertices.
You've seen these techniques
before with the metro dataset, but
that graph had only around 90 vertices.
Because we want you to learn the concepts,
not be bogged down with repetitive tasks,
we've supplied this Cloudera file in order
to create the visualization of the graph.
All you need to do is open
a new terminal window.
Go into the examples of
analytic directory and
run the spark shell with
the Facebook.Cloudera file.
Don't worry about copying
the full command from the video.
A text version will be included
within the course reading
that contains the full command for
you to copy and paste.
What do you see?
My first reaction is that
it looks like broccoli.
A green vegetable reviled by many
American children, unjustly.
Social networks are made up of
several clusters of communities or
pockets of people who interact densely
that are brought together by people who
are members of multiple communities.
This interlinking of clusters
gives the social network
a broccoli like shape when visualized.
I hope you heard the last thing I said
because that will be on the quiz.
Next we'll import the BreezeViz library,
define a function to calculate the degree
histogram, calculate the probability
distribution for the degree histogram, and
graph the results.
In this hands on exercise,
we will plot the degree histogram created
in the previous hands on exercise
using the BreezeViz library.
Starting again where we left off
in the previous hands-on exercise,
ensure your is started.
First we will import
the BreezeViz library.
Next, we will define a function to
calculate the degree histogram of Metro's
graph, so we can plot it with BreezeViz.
The definition of the degree histogram
function is nearly identical
to the code from the previous
exercise that helped us create.
The histogram data array.
Now we will calculate the probability
distribution of the vertex degrees over
the whole graph by normalizing the vertex
degree by the total number of vertices so
that the degree probabilities add up to 1.
The output of the first command is 28,
the number of countries in country.csv.
The output of the second command
is an array of numbered pairs.
The first number is the vertex degree,
and the second number is
the probability distribution.
Notice that the sum of all
the probability distributions equals one.
Now we will plot two graphs to
visualize the degree histogram.
The first graph will be a line
graph of the degree histogram and
the second will be
the degree histogram itself.
We will not go over in detail how to use
the BreezeViz library to create graphs.
The project is well documented and there
are many resources online if you want to
explore the BreezeViz library on your own.
For the first graph we will define
the X axis as the vertex degree and
the Y axis as the degree probability.
For the second graph we will
just pass the metro graph
degree attribute to
BreezeViz's histogram function
You should see two graphical
representations of the data.
The bottom one is the histogram.
The top shows the degrees
distribution plotting the histogram.
As we saw in the previous exercise's
array most countries have one metropolis.