The Hadoop Distributed File System,
a storage system for big data.
As a storage layer, the Hadoop distributed
file system, or the way we call it HDFS.
Serves as the foundation for
most tools in the Hadoop ecosystem.
It provides two capabilities that
are essential for managing big data.
Scalability to large data sets.
And reliability to cope
with hardware failures.
HDFS allows you to store and
access large datasets.
According to Hortonworks,
a leading vendor of Hadoop services,
HDFS has shown production
scalability up to 200 petabytes and
a single cluster of 4,500 servers.
With close to a billion files and blocks.
If you run out of space, you can simply
add more nodes to increase the space.
HDFS achieves scalability
by partitioning or
splitting large files
across multiple computers.
This allows parallel access to very large
files since the computations run in
parallel on each node
where the data is stored.
Typical file size is
gigabytes to terabytes.
The default chunk size, the size of
each piece of a file is 64 megabytes.
But you can configure this to any size.
By spreading the file across many nodes,
the chances are increased that a node
storing one of the blocks will fail.
What happens next?
Do we lose the information
stored in block C?
HDFS is designed for
full tolerance in such case.
HDFS replicates, or
makes a copy of, file blocks on
different nodes to prevent data loss.
In this example,
the node that crashed stored block C.
But block C was replicated on
two other nodes in the cluster.
By default, HDFS maintains
three copies of every block.
This is the default replication factor.
But you can change it globally for
every file, or
on a per file basis.
HDFS is also designed to handle
a variety of data types aligned with
big data variety.
To read a file in HDFS you must
specify the input file format.
Similarly to write the file you must
provide the output file format.
HDFS provides a set of formats for
common data types.
But this is extensible and you can provide
custom formats for your data types.
For example text files can be read.
Line by line or a word at a time.
Geospatial data can be read as vectors or
rasters.
Data formats specific to geospatial data,
or
other domain specific data formats.
Like FASTA, or FASTQ formats for
sequence data genomics.
HDFS is comprised of two components.
NameNode, and DataNode.
These operate using a master
slave relationship.
Where the NameNode issues comments
to DataNodes across the cluster.
The NameNode is responsible for metadata.
And DataNodes provide block storage.
There is usually one NameNode per cluster,
a DataNode however,
runs on each node in the cluster.
In some sense the NameNode
is the administrator or
the coordinator of the HDFS cluster.
When the file is created,
the NameNode records the name,
location in the directory hierarchy and
other metadata.
The NameNode also decides which data nodes
to store the contents of the file and
remembers this mapping.
The DataNode runs on
each node in the cluster.
And is responsible for
storing the file blocks.
The data node listens to commands from
the name node for block creation,
deletion, and replication.
Replication provides two key capabilities.
Fault tolerance and data locality.
As discussed earlier, when a machine in
the cluster has a hardware failure there
are two other copies of each block
that are stored on that node.
So no data is lost.
Replication also means that the same block
will be stored on different nodes on
the system which are in different
geographical locations.
A location may mean a specific rack or
a data center in a different town.
The location is important since we
want to move computation to data and
not the other way around.
We'll talk about what moving computation
to data means later in this module.
As I mentioned earlier, the default
replication factor is three, but
you can change this.
A high replication factor means more
protection against hardware failures,
and better chances for data locality.
But it also means increased
storage space is used.
As a summary HDFS provides
scalable big data storage by
partitioning files over multiple nodes.
This helps to scale big data
analytics to large data volumes.
The application protects
against hardware failures and
provides data locality when we move
analytical complications to data.
The Hadoop Ecosystem: So Much free Stuff!
How did the big data
open-source movement begin?
In 2004 Google published
a paper about their
in-house processing framework
they called MapReduce.
The next year,
Yahoo released an open-source
implementation based on this
framework called Hadoop.
In the following years,
other frameworks and
tools were released to the community
as open-source projects.
These frameworks provided new
capabilities missing in Hadoop,
such as SQL like querying or
high level scripting.
Today, there are over 100
open-source projects for
big data and
this number continues to grow.
Many rely on Hadoop, but
some are independent.
With so many frameworks and tools
available, how do we learn what they do?
We can organize them with a layer diagram
to understand their capabilities.
Sometimes we also used the term
stack instead of a layer diagram.
In a layer diagram,
a component uses the functionality or
capabilities of the components
in the layer below it.
Usually components at the same
layer do not communicate.
And a component never assumes a specific
tool or component is above it.
In this example,
component A is in the bottom layer,
which components B and C use.
Component D uses B, but not C.
And D does not directly use A.
Let's look at one set of tools in
the Hadoop ecosystem as a layer diagram.
This layer diagram is organized
vertically based on the interface.
Low level interfaces, so storage and
scheduling, on the bottom.
And high level languages and
interactivity at the top.
The Hadoop distributed file system,
or HDFS, is the foundation for
many big data frameworks, since it
provides scaleable and reliable storage.
As the size of your data increases,
you can add commodity hardware
to HDFS to increase storage capacity so
it enables scaling out of your resources.
Hadoop YARN provides
flexible scheduling and
resource management over the HDFS storage.
YARN is used at Yahoo to schedule
jobs across 40,000 servers.
MapReduce is a programming model
that simplifies parallel computing.
Instead of dealing with the complexities
of synchronization and scheduling, you
only need to give MapReduce two functions,
map and reduce, as you heard before.
This programming model is so
powerful that Google previously
used it for indexing websites.
MapReduce only assume a limited
model to express data.
Hive and Pig are two additional
programming models on
top of MapReduce to augment
data modeling of MapReduce
with relational algebra and
data flow modeling respectively.
Hive was created at
Facebook to issue SQL-like
queries using MapReduce
on their data in HDFS.
Pig was created at Yahoo to model data
flow based programs using MapReduce.
Thanks to YARN stability
to manage resources,
not just for MapReduce but
other programming models as well.
Giraph was built for
processing large-scale graphs efficiently.
For example, Facebook uses Giraph to
analyze the social graphs of its users.
Similarly, Storm, Spark,
and Flink were built for
real time and
in memory processing of big data on
top of the YARN resource scheduler and
HDFS.
In-memory processing is a powerful way of
running big data applications even faster,
achieving 100x's better performance for
some tasks.
Sometimes, your data or
processing tasks are not easily or
efficiently represented using the file and
directory model of storage.
Examples of this include collections
of key-values or large sparse tables.
NoSQL projects such as Cassandra,
MongoDB, and HBase handle these cases.
Cassandra was created at Facebook,
but Facebook also used HBase for
its messaging platform.
Finally, running all of these tools
requires a centralized management system
for synchronization, configuration and
to ensure high availability.
Zookeeper performs these duties.
It was created by Yahoo to wrangle
services named after animals.
A major benefit of the Hadoop ecosystem
is that all these tools
are open-source projects.
You can download and use them for free.
Each project has a community of users and
developers that
answer questions, fix bugs and
implement new features.
You can mix and match to get only
the tools you need to achieve your goals.
Alternatively, there are several
pre-built stacks of these tools
offered by companies such as Cloudera,
MAPR and Hortonworks.
These companies provide the core
software stacks for free and
offer commercial support for
production environments.
As a summary, the Hadoop ecosystem
consists of a growing number
of open-source tools.
Providing opportunities to
pick the right tool for
the right tasks for
better performance and lower costs.
We will reveal some of these
tools in further detail and
provide an analysis of when to use
which in the next set of lectures.
Generating value from Hadoop and
Pre-Built Hadoop Images that
come as off the shelf products.
Assembling your own software stack
from scratch can be messy and
a lot of work for beginners.
The task of setting up the whole stack
could consume a lot of project time and
man power, reducing time to deployment.
Getting pre-built images is similar
to buying pre-assembled furniture.
You can obtain a ready to go software
stack which contains a pre-installed
operating system, required libraries and
application software.
It saves you from the trouble
of putting the different
parts together in the right orientation.
You can start using
the furniture right away.
Packaging of these pre-built
software images is enabled
by virtual machines using
virtualization software.
Without going into too much detail,
one of the benefits of virtualization
software is that it lets you run a ready
made software stack within minutes.
Your software stack comes as a large file.
Virtualization software provides
a platform where your stack can run.
Many companies provide images for
their version of the Hadoop platform,
including a number of
tools of their choice.
Hortonworks is one of the companies that
provides a pre-built software stack for
both Mac and Windows platforms.
Cloudera is another company
that provides pre-installed and
assembled software stack images.
Cloudera image is what we will
be working with in this course.
Many other companies
provide similar images.
Additionally, lots of online tutorials for
beginners are on vendors websites for
self-training of users
working with these images and
the open source tools they include.
Once you choose the vendor,
you can check out their website for
tutorials on how to get started quickly.
There are plenty of resources online for
that.
You can deploy pre-built
images over the Cloud.
This would further accelerate your
application deployment process.
It is always best to evaluate which
approach is most cost effective for
your business model and organization.
Companies such as Cloudera,
Hortonworks and others,
provide step-by-step guides on how to
set up pre-built images on the Cloud.
As a summary, using pre-built software
packages have a number of benefits and
can significantly accelerate
your big data projects.
Even small teams can quickly prototype,
deploy and validate their project ideas.
The developed analytical solutions
can be scaled to larger volumes and
increase velocities of
data in a matter of hours.
These companies also provide
Enterprise level solutions for large,
full-fledged applications.
An added benefit is that there
are plenty of companies which provide
ready-made solutions.
That means lots of choices for you to
pick the one most suited to your project.
What is a Distributed File System?
Most of us have file
cabinets in our offices or
homes that help us store
our printed documents.
Everyone has their own
method of organizing files,
including the way we bin similar
documents into one file, or
the way we sort them in alphabetical or
date order.
When computers first came out,
the information and
programs were stored in punch cards.
These punch cards were
stored in file cabinets,
just like the physical
file cabinets today.
This is where the name,
file system, comes from.
The need to store information in
files comes from a larger need
to store information in the long-term.
This way the information lives
after the computer program, or
what we call process,
that produced it terminates.
If we don't have files, our access to
such information would not be possible
once a program using or producing it.
Even during the process, we might need
to store large amounts of information
that we cannot store within the program
components or computer memory.
In addition, once the data is in a file,
multiple processes can access
the same information if needed.
For all these reasons, we store
information in files on a hard disk.
There are many of these files, and
they get managed by your operating system,
like Windows or Linux.
How the operating system manages
files is called a file system.
How this information is stored
on disk drives has high impact
on the efficiency and speed of access to
data, especially in the big data case.
While the files have exact addresses for
their locations in the drive, referring
to the data units of sequence of these
blocks, that's called the flat structure,
or hierarchy construction of index
records, that's called the database.
They also have human readable symbolic
names, generally followed by an extension.
Extensions tell what kind of file it is,
in general.
Programs and
users can access files with their names.
The contents of a file can be numeric,
alphabetic, alphanumeric,
or binary executables.
Most computer users work
on personal laptops or
desktop computers with
a single hard drive.
In this model, the user is limited
to the capacity of their hard drive.
The capacity of different devices vary.
For example, while your phone or
tablet might have a storage capacity
in the order of gigabytes, your
laptop computer might have a terabyte of
storage, but what if you have more data?
Some of you probably had
issues in the past with
running out of space on your hard drive.
A way to solve this is to have
an external hard drive and
store your files there or,
you can buy a bigger disk.
Both options are a bit of a hassle, to
copy the data to a new disk, aren't they?
They might not even be
an option sometimes.
Now imagine, you having two computers and
storing some of your data in one and
the rest of your data in another.
How you organize and partition your data
between these computers is up to you.
You might want to store your
work data in one computer and
your personal data in another.
Distributing data on multiple
computers might be an option, but
it raises new issues.
In this situation, you need to know
where to find the files you need,
depending on what you’re doing.
You can find it manageable,
if it’s just your data.
But now imagine having
thousands of computers
to store your data with big volumes and
variety.
Wouldn't it be good to have a system
that can handle the data access and
do this for you?
This is a case that can be handled
by a distributive file system.
Now, let's assume that there
are racks of these computers,
often even distributed across the local or
wide area network, because such file
systems, distributed file systems.
Data sets, or parts of a data set,
can be replicated across the nodes
of a distributed file system.
Since data is already on these nodes,
then analysis of parts of the data
is needed in a data parallel fashion,
computation can be moved to these nodes.
Additionally, distributed file
systems replicate the data
between the racks, and also computers
distributed across geographical regions.
Data replication makes
the system more fault tolerant.
That means, if some nodes or
a rack goes down,
there are other parts of the system,
the same data can be found and analyzed.
Data replication also helps with scaling
the access to this data by many users.
Often, if the data is popular, many
reader processes will want access to it.
In a highly parallelized replication,
each reader can get their own node
to access to and analyze data.
This increases overall system performance.
Note that a problem with having
such a distributive replication is,
that it is hard to make
changes to data over time.
However, in most big data systems,
the data is written once and
the updates to data is maintained
as additional data sets over time.
As a summary, a file system is
responsible from the organization of
the long term information
storage in a computer.
When many storage computers
are connected through the network,
we call it a distributed file system.
Distributed file systems provide data
scalability, fault tolerance, and
high concurrency through partitioning and
replication of data on many nodes.
When to reconsider Hadoop?
The Hadoop ecosystem is
growing at a fast pace.
This means a lot of stuff
that was difficult, or
not supportive, is becoming possible.
In this lecture,
we will look at some aspects that
clearly make a good match for Hadoop.
We will also look at several
aspects that might motivate you
to evaluate Hadoop at a deeper level.
And does Hadoop really make sense for
your specific problem?
First let's look at the key features
that make a problem Hadoop friendly.
If you see a large scale growth in
amount of data you will tackle,
probably it makes sense to use Hadoop.
When you want quick access to your old
data which would otherwise go on tape
drives for archival storage,
Hadoop might provide a good alternative.
Other Hadoop friendly features include
scenarios when you want to use multiple
applications over the same data store.
High volume or
high variety are also great indicators for
Hadoop as a platform choice.
Small data set processing
should raise your eyebrows.
Do you really need Hadoop for that?
Dig deeper, and find out exactly why you
want to use Hadoop before going ahead.
Hadoop is good for data parallelism.
As you know, data parallelism is
the simultaneous execution of the same
function on multiple nodes across
the elements of a dataset.
On the other hand, task parallelism,
as you see in this graph,
is the simultaneous execution
of many different functions
on multiple nodes across the same or
different data sets.
If your problem has task-level
parallelism, you must do further
analysis as to which tools you plan
to deploy from the Hadoop ecosystem.
What are the precise benefits
that these tools provide?
Proceed with caution.
Not all algorithms are scalable in Hadoop,
or
reducible to one of the programming
models supported by YARN.
Hence, if you are looking to deploy
highly coupled data processing algorithms
proceed with caution.
Do a thorough analysis
before using Hadoop.
Are you thinking of
throwing away your existing database
solutions and replacing them with Hadoop?
Think again.
Hadoop may be a good platform where
your diverse data sets can land and
get processed into a form
digestible with your database.
Hadoop may not be the best data store
solution for your business case.
Evaluate, and proceed with caution.
HDFS stores data in blocks
of 64 megabytes or larger,
so you may have to read an entire
file just to pick one data entry.
That makes it a bit harder to
perform random data access.
The Hadoop ecosystem is growing
at a faster pace than ever.
This slide shows some of the moving
targets in the Hadoop ecosystem and
the additional needs which
must be addressed by new tools
to the Hadoop ecosystem.
Mainly, advanced analytical queries,
latency sensitive tasks, and
cyber security of sensitive data.
Here, we give pointers to tools you
might want to look into further
to understand the challenges
these need tools address.
As a summary, although Hadoop is good with
scalability of many algorithms, it is just
one model and does not solve all issues
in managing and processing big data.
Although it would be possible to find
counterexamples, we can generally say
that the Hadoop framework is not the best
for working with small data sets,
advanced algorithms that require
a specific hardware type,
task level parallelism, infrastructure
replacement, or random data access.