Big data, generated by organizations,
structured but often siloed.
The last type of big data we will discuss
is big data generated by organizations.
This type of data is the closest to
what most businesses currently have.
But it's considered a bit out of fashion,
or
traditional, compared to
other types of big data.
However, it is at least as important
as other types of big data.
So how do organizations produce data?
The answer to how
an organization generates data
is very unique to the organization and
context.
Each organization has distinct
operation practices and
business models, which result in
a variety of data generation platforms.
For example, the type and source of data
that a bank gets is very different from
what a hardware equipment
manufacturer gets.
Some common types of organizational big
data come from commercial transactions,
credit cards, government institutions,
e-commerce, banking or
stock records, medical records, sensors,
transactions, clicks and so on.
Almost every event can
be potentially stored.
Organizations store this data for
current and
future use, as well as for
analysis of the past.
Let's say you're an organization
that collects sales transactions.
You can use this data for pattern
recognition to detect correlated products,
to estimate demand for
products likely to go up in sales, and
capture fraudulent activity.
Moreover, when you know your
sales record and can correlate it
with your marketing records, you can find
which campaigns really made an impact.
You are already becoming
a data savvy organization.
Now think of bringing your
sales data together with other
external open public data,
such as major world events in the news.
You can ask, was it savvy marketing or
a consequence of external events
that triggered your sales?
Using proper analytics,
you can now build inventories to match
your predicted growth and demand.
In addition, organizations build and
apply processes to record and
monitor business events of interest,
such as registering a customer,
manufacturing a product or
taking an order.
These processes collect
highly structured data
that include transactions,
reference tables, and
relationships, as well as
the metadata that sets its context.
Usually, structured data is stored in
relational database management systems.
However, we call any data
that is in the form of
a record located in a fixed field or
file structured data.
This definition also
includes spreadsheets.
As I have mentioned before,
traditionally this type of
highly structured data is the vast
majority of what IT managed and
processed in both operational and
business intelligence systems.
Let's look at the sales transaction
data in our previous example.
If you look at the data in
the relational table on the right.
As the name structured suggests,
the table is organized to store data using
a structure defined by a model.
Each column is tagged to tell us what
data that column intends to store.
This is what we call a data model.
A data model defines
each of these columns and
fields in the table, and
defines relationships between them.
If you look at the product ID column,
you will see that it includes only
identifiers that can potentially be linked
to another table defining these products.
The ability to define such relationships,
easily make structured data,
or in this case relational databases,
highly adopted by many organizations.
There are commonly used
languages like SQL,
the Structured Query Language, to extract
data of interest from such tables.
This is referred to as querying the data.
However, it could even be a challenge
to integrate such structured data.
This image shows us a continuum
of technologies to model,
collect and query unstructured
data coming from software and
hardware components
within an organization.
In the past, such challenges
led to information being stored
in what we call silos,
even within an organization.
Many organizations have traditionally
captured data at the department level,
without proper infrastructure and
policy to share and integrate this data.
This has hindered the growth of
scalable pattern recognition
to the benefits of
the entire organization.
Because no one system has access to
all data that the organization owns.
Each data set is compartmentalized.
If such silos are left untouched,
organizations risk having outdated,
unsynchronized, and
even invisible data sets.
Organizations are realizing
the detrimental outcomes of this rigid
structure.
And changing policies and infrastructure
to enable integrated processing of
all data to the entire
organization's benefit.
Cloud-based solutions
are seen as agile and
low capital intensive
solutions in this area.
As a summary, while highly structured
organizational data is very useful and
trustworthy, and
thus a valuable source of information,
organizations must pay special
attention to breaking up
the silos of information to
make full use of its potential.
The key, integrating diverse data.
Whatever your big data application is, and
the types of big data you are using
the real value will come from integrating
different types of data sources,
and analyzing them at scale.
So how do we start getting this value?
Sometimes, all it takes,
is looking at the data you already
collect in a different way.
And it can mean a big difference
in your return on investment.
This new story from June 2015
mentions that Carnival Cruises
is using structured and unstructured
data from a variety of sources.
Carnival turns it into profit
using price optimization
techniques on the integrated data.
For you to achieve such a success story,
you will need to include data
integration into your big data practice.
However, there are some unique challenges
when attempting to integrate these
diverse data sources and
scaling the solutions.
Course Two on on the specialization,
we'll teach you more about these issues.
But let's take a moment to define why
effect of data integration is useful?
Data integration means bringing
together data from diverse sources and
turning them into coherent and
more useful information.
We also call this knowledge.
The main objective here is taming or
more technically managing data and
turning it into something you can
make use of programmatically.
A data integration process
involves many parts.
It starts with discovering,
accessing, and monitoring data and
continues with modeling and transforming
data from a variety of sources.
But why do we need data
integration in the first place?
Let's start by focusing on
differences between big data sets
coming from different sources.
You might have flat file formatted data,
relational database data,
data encoded in XML or JSON,
both common for internet generated data.
These different formats and
models are useful
because they are designed to express
different data in unique ways.
In a way, different data formats and
models make big data more useful and
more challenging all at the same time.
When you integrate data in different
formats, you make the final
product richer in the number of
features you describe the data with.
For example,
by integrating environmental sensor and
camera data with geographical
information system data, such as in
my wildfire prediction application,
I can use the spacial data capabilities
with non-spacial data to more
accurately run fire simulations.
In the past, although we were able
to see the images of the fire
from mountain top cameras,
just like this image, we were still
not able to tell what the exact
location of the fire is automatically.
Now, when a fire is detected
from a mountain top camera,
viewsheds are used to estimate
the location of the fire.
This location information can
be fed into the fire simulator
as early as it's detected
to predict the size and
location of the fire in the next
hour more accurately and faster.
Similarly, I can use real time
data with eye curve data sets, and
use them all together.
Additionally, by bringing
the data together, and
providing programmable access to it, I'm
now making each data set more accessible.
Moreover, integration of
diverse datasets significantly
reduces the overall data complexity
in my data-driven product.
The data becomes more available for
use and unified as a system of its own.
One advantage of such an integration
is not often mentioned.
Such a streamlined and
integrated data system
can increase the collaboration between
different parts of your data systems.
Each part can now clearly see
how their data is integrated
into the overall system.
Including the user scenarios and the
security and privacy processes around it.
Overall by integrating diverse data
streams you add value to your big data and
improve your business even
before you start analyzing it.
Next, we will focus on the dimensions
of the scalability and
discuss how we can start tackling
some of these challenges.
What launched the big data era?
In this video, you will learn about
two new opportunities that have
contributed to the launch
of the big data era.
Opportunities are often
a signal of changing times.
In 2013, an influential report by
a company called McKinsey claimed that
the area of data science will be the
number one catalyst for economic growth.
McKinsey identified one of our new
opportunities that contributed to
the launch of the big data era.
A growing torrent of data.
This refers to the idea that data seems to
be coming continuously and at a fast rate.
Think about this,
today you can buy a hard drive to store
all the music in the world for only $600.
That's an amazing storage capability over
any previous forms of music storage.
In 2010 there were 5 billion
mobile phones in use.
You can be sure that
there are more today and
as I'm sure you will understand,
these phones and
the apps we install on them
are a big source of big data,
which all the time, every day,
contributes to our core.
And Facebook, which recently just set
a record of having one billion
people login in a single day,
has more that 30 billion pieces
of content shared every month.
Well, that number's from 2013.
So I'm sure that it's much
higher than that now.
Does it make you think how many
Facebook share's you made last month?
All this leads to projections
of serious growth.
40% in global data per year,
and 5% in global IT spending.
This much data has sure
pushed the data science field
to start remaining itself and
the business world of today.
But, there's something else contributing
to the catalyzing power of data science.
It is called cloud computing.
We call this on demand computing.
Cloud computing is one of
the ways in which computing
has now become something that
we ca do anytime, and anywhere.
You may be surprised to know
that some of your favorite
apps are from businesses
being run from coffee shops.
This new ability,
combined with our torrent of data,
gives us the opportunity to perform novel,
dynamic and scalable data analysis,
to tell us new things about our world and
ourself.
To summarize, a new torrent of big data
combined with computing capability
anytime, anywhere has been at the core
of the launch of the big data era.
Asking the Right Questions.
The first step in any process is to define
what it is you are trying to tackle.
What is the problem that
needs to be addressed, or
the opportunity that
needs to be ascertained.
Without this,
you won't have a clear goal in mind, or
know when you've solved your problem.
An example question is,
how can sales figures and
call center logs be combined
to evaluate a new product,
or in a manufacturing process,
how can data from multiple
sensors in an instrument be used
to detect instrument failure?
How can we understand our customers and
market better to achieve
effective target marketing?
Next you need to assess the situation
with respect to the problem or
the opportunity you have defined.
This is a step where you need to
exercise caution analyzing risks,
costs, benefits, contingencies,
regulations, resources and
requirements of the situation.
What are the requirements of the problem?
What are the assumptions and constraints?
What resources are available?
This is in terms of both personnel and
capital,
such as computer systems, instruments etc.
What are the main costs
associated with this project?
What are the potential benefits?
What risks are there in
pursuing the project?
What are the contingencies to
potential risks, and so on?
Answers to these questions will help you
get a better overview of the situation.
And better understanding of
what the project involves.
Then you need to define your goals and
objectives,
based on the answers to these questions.
Defining success criteria
is also very important.
What do you hope to achieve
by the end of this project?
Having clear goals and and
success criteria will help you to assess
the project throughout its life cycle.
Once you know the problem you want to
address and understand the constraints and
goals, then you can formulate
the plan to come up with the answer,
that is the solution to
your business problem.
As a summary, defining the questions
you're looking to find answers for
is a huge factor contributing to
the success of a data science project.
By following the explained set of steps,
you can formulate better questions
to solve using analytical skills and
link them to business value.
Building a Big Data Strategy.
Before we focus on big data strategy,
let's look at what strategy means.
Although it is associated
with a military term,
a dictionary search on strategy shows
the meaning as a plan of action or
policy designed to achieve a major or
overall aim.
This definition calls out the four major
parts that need to be in any strategy.
Namely, aim, policy, plan, and action.
Now, we are talking about
a big data strategy.
So what do these four terms mean for us?
When building our big data strategy,
we look at what we have,
what high level goals we want to achieve,
what we need to do to get there,
and what are the policies around
data from the beginning to the end.
A big data strategy starts
with big objectives.
Notice that I didn't say it
starts with collecting data
because in this activity we
are really trying to identify what
data is useful and
why by focusing on what data to collect.
Every organization or team is unique.
Different projects have
different objectives.
Hence, it's important to first
define what your team's goals are.
Have you ever had the scenario where you
see the temperature on the weather report
and someone else highlights
the humidity instead?
To find problems relevant to solve and
data related to it, it might be
useful to start with your objectives.
Once you define these objectives, or
more generally speaking, questions to turn
big data into advantage for your business,
you can look at what you have and
analyze the gaps and actions to get there.
It is important to focus
on both short term and
long term objectives in this activity.
These objectives should also be linked
to big data analytics with business
objectives.
To make the best use of big data,
each company needs to evaluate how
data science or big data analytics would
add value to their business objectives.
Once you have established that
analytics can help your business,
you need to create
a culture to embrace it.
The first and foremost ingredient for
a successful data science program
is organizational buy-in.
A big data strategy must
have commitment and
sponsorship from the company's leadership.
Goals for using big data analytics should
be developed with all stakeholders and
clearly communicated to
everyone in the organization.
So that its value is understood and
appreciated by all.
The next step is to build
your data science team.
A diverse team with data scientists,
information technologists,
application developers, and business
owners is necessary to be effective.
As well as the mentality that everyone
works together as partners with
common goals.
Remember, one for all.
No one is a customer or
service provider of another.
Rather, everyone works together and
delivers as a team.
Since big data is a team game,
and multi-disciplinary,
a big part of a big data
strategy is constant training
of team members on new big data tools and
analytics.
As well as business practices and
objectives.
This becomes even more critical if your
business depends on deep expertise
on one or more subject areas with subject
matter experts working on problems,
utilizing big data.
Such businesses might have subject matter
experts who can be trained to add big
data skills, and provide more value added
support than a newcomer would have.
Similarly, any project member would
be trained to understand what
the business objectives and
products are, and how he or
she can utilize big data to improve those
objectives using his or her skills.
Many organizations might benefit by having
a small data science team whose main job
is do data experiments and test new ideas
before they get deployed at full scale.
They might come up with
a new idea themselves
based on the analysis they perform.
They take more research level role.
However, their findings can drastically
shape your business strategy
almost on a daily basis.
The impact of such teams
becomes evident over time
as other parts of your organization starts
to see the results of their finding and
analysis affecting their strategies.
They become strategic partners of
all verticals in your business.
Once you see that something works,
you can start collecting more data to see
similar results at organizational scale.
Since data is key to any big
data initiative, it is essential
that data across the organization
is easily accessed and integrated.
Data silos as you know, are like
a death knell on effective analytics.
So barriers to data
access must be removed.
Opening up the silos must be encouraged
and supported from the organization's
leaders in order to promote a data
sharing mindset for the company.
Another aspect of defining
your big data strategy
is defining the policies around big data.
Although it has an amazing amount
of potential for your business,
using big data should also raise some
concerns in long term planning for data.
Although this is a very complex issue,
here are some questions you should
think of addressing around policy.
What are the privacy concerns?
Who should have access to,
or control data?
What is the lifetime of data,
which is sometimes defined as volatility,
anatomy of big data?
How does data get curated and cleaned up?
What ensures data quality
in the long term?
How do different parts of your
organization communicate or
interoperate using this data?
Are there any legal and
regulatory standards in place?
Cultivating an analytics
driven culture is crucial
to the success of a big data strategy.
The mindset that you want to
establish is that analytics
is an integral part of doing business,
not a separate afterthought.
Analytics activities must be tied
to your business objectives, and
you must be willing to use analytics
in driving business decisions.
Analytics and business together bring
about exciting opportunities and
growth to your big data strategy.
Finally, one size does not fit all.
Hence, big data technologies and
analytics is growing rapidly as your
business is an evolving entity.
You have to iterate your strategy to
take advantage of new advances and
also make your business more
dynamic in the face of change.
As a summary,
when building a big data strategy,
it is important to integrate big data
analytics with business objectives.
Communicate goals and
provide organizational buy-in for
analytics projects.
Build teams with diverse talents,
and establish a teamwork mindset.
Remove barriers to data access and
integration.
Finally, these activities need to be
iterated to respond to new business
goals and technological advances.