In this hands-on activity,
we will be querying documents in MongoDB.
First, we will start a MongoDB server and
then run the MongoDB Shell.
We will see how to show the databases and
collections in the MongoDB Server.
We will look at an example
document in the database and
see how to find distinct values for
a field.
Next, we will search for
specific field values and
see how to filter fields
returned in a query.
Finally, we will search using
regular expressions and operators.
Let's begin,
first we'll start the MongoDB server.
Open the terminal window by clicking on
the terminal icon, the top of the toolbar.
We'll cd into
Downloads/big-data-3-mongodb.
We'll start the MongoDB server by running
./mongodb/bin/mongod --dbpath db.
The arguments dbpath db
specified that the database on
MongoDB is in the directory named db.
Run this to start the server.
Next, we'll start the MongoDB Shell so
that we can perform queries.
We'll open another terminal window.
Again, cd into
Downloads/big-data-3-mongodb.
We'll start the shell by
running ./mongodb/bin/mongo.
We can see what databases are available in
the MongoDB server by running the command,
show dbs.
We've created the sample database
with JSON data from Twitter.
We can use the use command
to change to this database.
We'll run use sample.
We can see the collections in this
database by running, show collections.
There's only one collection called users.
So, all of the queries will be
using the users collection.
Let's count how many documents there
are in the users collection by writing
db.users.count.
We can look at one of these documents
by writing db.users.findOne.
This document contains
Jason from a Twitter tweet.
You can see the field names
here with their values.
There are also nested fields
under the user field.
And each of these fields also has values.
You can find the distinct values for
particular field,
by using the distinct command.
Let's find the distinct values for
the username field.
We'll write
db.users.distinct("user_name").
Next, let's find all the documents in
this collection where the field username
matches the specific value.
The value we'll search for
is ActionSportsJax.
We'll run the command db.users.find.
And the field name is username, and
the value we're searching for
is ActionSportsJax.
Results of this query is
compressed all in one line.
If we append the .pretty
to the previous query.
We can see the formatted output.
So we'll run the same
command with append .pretty.
We can filter the fields
returned from the queries.
Let's perform the same query again but
only show the tweet_id field.
We can do this by adding a second
argument to the find command.
So we'll run the same command again,
but add a second argument,
saying tweet_ID: 1.
The underscore ID field is a primary
key used in all documents in MongoDB.
You can turn this off by adding
another field to our filter.
We'll run the same command again,
but turn of _ID.
Next, we use the regular expression search
to find strings containing the document.
For example, if we want to find all
the tweets containing the text FIFA,
we can run db.users.find tweet_text FIFA.
There are no results in this query
because this query is searching for
tweet text equals FIFA.
That is the entire contents and
the value of tweet_text must be FIFA.
Instead, if we want to look for
FIFA anywhere in the tweet_text,
we can do a regular expression search.
To do this,
replace the double quotes with slashes.
So we'll run the same command again.
But replacing double quotes with slashes.
We can count how many documents are
returned by this query by running the same
command again, but appending .count.
We can also search for documents in
MongoDB where the field values are greater
than or less than a certain value.
For example, lets find tweet
mention count greater than six.
We'll run db.users.find, and
the field name is tweet_mentioned_count.
And we want to look for the value
where this field is greater than six.
So I'll enter a .
In a prior course we looked at JSON as
an example of semi-structured data,
and we demonstrated that JSON
data can be thought of as a tree.
In this course,
we'll focus on querying JSON data.
Before we start, lets review
the details of the JSON structure, and
get an initial sense of how
to query this form of data.
Let's consider a simple
JSON collection and
look at the structures,
substructures actually, it's composed of.
The atomic element in the structure
is a key value pair, for example,
name is the key and sue is the value,
in this case, an atomic string value.
To query a key value pair,
we should be able perform one basic
operation given the key, return the value.
Now, the value can also be an array,
an array is a list.
So the query operations on it can either
be on its position in the list or
on the value.
Thus, we should be able to ask for the
second element of the array called badges.
Or we should be able to seek objects
of which the key called badges
has a value of blue.
Notice here that the document
collection here is itself an array,
within square brackets and
it's just two elements in it.
The top level array does not have a key,
by default it's called db.
These key value peers
are structured as tuples,
often with a name In the snippet shown,
favorites has a tuple
of two key value pairs.
Now, tuples can be thought of as
relational records, as the operations
would include, projection of an attribute,
and selection over a set of tables.
On the other hand,
the area called 'points',
has two tuples, these two tuples named.
As you will see, we'll address
these tuples by their positions.
Finally, this one has nesting,
that means a mini structure can be
embedded within another structure.
So we need operations
that will let us navigate
from one structure to any of
it's embedded structures.
Now just like a basic SQL query states,
which parts of which records from one or
more people should be reported,
a MongoDB query states
which parts of which documents from
a document collection should be returned.
The primary query is expressed as a find
function, which contains two arguments and
an optional qualifier, there are four
things to notice in this function.
The first is the term collection,
this tells the system which
document collection to use, and
therefore is roughly similar to the From
clause when restricted to one table.
So if the name of the collection is beers,
the first part would say db.beers.find.
The second item is a query filter
which lists all conditions that
the retrieved documents should satisfy,
so it's like a Where clause.
Now, if we want to return everything,
then this filter is left blank.
Otherwise, we'll fill it in a couple
of ways shown in the next few slides.
The third term is a projection class
which is essentially a list of variables
that we want to see in the output.
The fourth and last item sits
after the find function ends and
is separated by a dot,
it's called a cursor modifier.
The word cursor relates back
to SQL where cursor is defined
as a block of results that is
returned to the user in one chunk.
This becomes important when the set of
results is too large to be returned all
together, and
the user may need to specify how much, or
what portion of results
they actually want.
So, we'll start out with a few queries,
where we show how the same query
can be expressed in SQL, and
in MongoDB The first query
wants everything from Beers.
The SQL query is structured
on the table Beers, and
the SELECT * asks to return all rows.
In MongoDB the same query
is more succincted,
since the name of the collection
is already specified in
calling the find function,
the body of the find function is empty.
That means there are no query conditions
and no projection clauses in it.
The second query
needs to return the variables beer and
price for all records.
So the find function here needs an empty
query condition denoted by the open and
closed brace symbols, but the projection
clauses are specifically identified.
There is a 1 if an attribute is output and
a 0 if it is not.
As a shortcut,
only variables with 1 are required.
Okay, so when do you use 0?
A common situation is the following.
Every MongoDB document has
an identifier named _id.
By default every query will
return the id of the document.
If you don't want it to return
this designated attribute,
you should explicitly say, _id:0.
Next we will add query conditions.
That is the equivalent of
the Where clause in SQL.
Our query number three has the query
condition where name is equal to a value.
In MongoDB, that equal to translate
to a variable colon value form.
Notice the symbol used for
a string is quotes.
Query four is more interesting for
two reasons.
First, we see a way in which
the distinct operation is specified.
Notice here that the primary query
function is not find any more but
a new function called distinct.
As we'll see later again in our slides,
MongoDB uses a few special query
functions for some of the operations.
So, you need to know, which function
should be used in what context,
when you write MogoDB queries.
Secondly, in this query,
we have a non-equality condition,
namely, the price is greater than 15.
This example shows MongoDB style
of using operators in a query.
It's always variable:
followed by MongoDB's name for the
operator, and then the comparison value.
So where would you find
MongoDB's operators?
Here are some of the operators
supported in MongoDB.
These operators and others are listed
in the URL shown at the bottom.
The operators shown here are color coded.
The top blue set
are the comparison operators.
We see the $gt, greater than,
operation that we used in the last slide.
The green colored operations are array
operations which we'll see shortly.
And the yellow operators at the bottom
are logical operations that
combine two conditions in different ways
like the AND operation we saw in SQL.
Now, the last operator $nor,
is interesting,
because it is used to specify queries
when neither of two conditions must hold.
For example, find all beer
whose name is neither bad nor
is the price less than $6 per bottle.
Now I would strongly encourage you
to play with these operators in
your hands on session.
Now I'm sure you remember
the like query in SQL.
MongoDB uses regular expressions
to specify partial string matches.
Now some of you may not know
what a regular expression is.
Let's first use some examples.
The first example is the same query
we saw before when we're asking for
beer manufacturers,
whose name has a sub string A-M in it,
so A-M can appear
anywhere within the name.
To do this,
the query condition first states that
it is going to use a $regex operation.
And then we have to give
the partial string as /am/.
Then it gives the directive
that this match
should be case insensitive by placing
an i after the partial string.
And if we just wanted to do names we
would stop right after the find function.
But here we also want to do a count,
which is a post operation
after the find, so we use .count
at the end of the find function.
Now, what if we have the same query,
but we want the partial string A-m?
To appear at the beginning of the name and
you'd like the A to really
be a capital letter.
In this case we use
the caret sign to indicate
that the partial string is at
the beginning of the name.
Naturally we also drop the i at the end
because the match is no longer case
insensitive A more complex
partial string pattern will be a case
where our name starts with capital A-m,
then has a number of characters
in the middle and ends with corp.
So for the first part,
the string pattern is ^Am.
For the second part, that is,
any character in the middle, we use dot
to represent any character, and star
to represent zero or more occurrences.
For the third part, we say corp but
put a dollar at the end to say that it
must appear at the end of the string.
The regular expression pattern is
a sub-language, in itself, and
is supported by most
programming languages today.
We will refer you to the following
URL to learn more about it.
Also, note an example that,
instead of saying, find.count,
we can directly use the count function,
natively defined in MongoDB.
One important feature of JSON is that
everything contain arrays, as a type of
collection objects, this enables us
to query arrays in multiple ways.
One of them,
is to consider an array as a list and
perform intersection operations,
the first query shows this.
The data item is shown on the right.
It has the area value attribute
called tags with three entries.
The first query asks if two specific
strings belong to the array.
In other words, it wants to get
the document whose tagged attribute
intersects with the query supplied array.
In this case, there is an intersection and
the document is returned.
In the second case, it is asking for
a documents who's tags
attribute has no intersection.
Now notice the $nin operator so
there is no intersection with this list.
So in this document there exists and
intersection so nothing will be returned.
A different kind of array query uses
the positions of the list elements and
wants to extract a portion of the array.
This is illustrated in
the third query which asks for
the second and third items of the array.
To encode this in MongoDB,
we use the $slice operator
which needs two parameters,
the number of variable limits to skip,
and the number of variable limits
to extract after skipping.
In this case, we need to extract items two
and three, so the skip value is one and
the number of items is two,
thus returning summer and Japanese.
Now, we could get the same result if we
pose the query using the last statement.
In this case, the minus says that
the system should count from the end and
the true says that it should
extract two elements.
Now if we omitted the minus sign,
it will come from the beginning and
fetch the first two elements.
Finally, we can also ask for a document
who's second element in tags is summer.
In this case we use an array index
tags.1 to denote the second element.
Compound statements are queries
with multiple query conditions that
are combined using logical operations.
The query shown here has one condition,
which is the and,are in terms of MongoDB,
the $and of three different clauses.
The last clause is
the most straight forward,
it states that the desired
item should not be Coors.
The first clause is an or, that is,
a $or, between two sub-conditions,
A the prices either 3.99, or B it is 4.99.
The second clause is also an or
of two sub conditions,
A the rating is good, and
B the quantity is less than 20.
This query shows that the $and and
the $or operators need a list
that is an array of arguments.
To draw a quick comparison,
here's the example of the same
query imposed with SQL.
Now, an important feature of
semi-structured data is that
it allows nesting.
We showed three documents here,
where there is an area named points,
which in turn has two tuples with
the elements points and bonus.
Let's assume that these three
documents are part of a collection, so
they form three items in
an area called users.
Our goal is to show how we can
write queries to extract data
from these documents with nesting.
The first query wants
to find documents for
which, the value of points should
be less than or equal to 80.
Now, which ones?
Now, points.0,
refers to the first tuple
under the outer points, and
points.0.points, refers to
the first element of that tuple.
Clearly, only the second
documents satisfies this query.
Now, what happens if we have
the same query but we drop the zero?
Now, we are looking for points.points
without specifying the array index.
This means that the points element in
any of the tuples should
have a value of 80 or less.
So now, the first and the second
document will satisfy the query.
We can put multiple conditions
as seen in the third query.
It looks for a document where the points
element of a tuple, should be utmost 81,
and the bonus should be exactly 20, and
clearly the second document qualifies.
But does the third document qualify?
In this case, the first tuple
satisfies points greater than 81 and
the second tuple satisfies
bonus equal to 20.
The answer is no, because the comma
is treated as an implicit and
condition within the same double,
as shown in the yellow braces.
Now remember that we said in course
two that all semi-structured
data can be viewed as a tree.
Now, what if I pick a node of a tree and
ask for all the descendents of that node?
That would require the system
to recursively get chideNodes,
over increasing depth from the given node.
Unfortunately, at this time,
MongoDB does not support recursive search.
A different kind of scaling problem arises
when we try to answer queries over a large
number of data sources, but before we do
that let's see how a query is answered in
the virtual data integration setting.
We are going to use a toy
scenario in a medical setting
simple as we have four data sources.
Each with one table for
the sake of simplicity.
Notice that two sources, S1 and
S3, have the same schema.
Now this is entirely possible because
sources may be independent of each other.
Further, there is no guarantee that
they would have the same exact content.
Maybe these two sources represent
clinics at different locations.
So next, we look at the target schema.
For simplicity, let's consider that
it's not an algorithmically creative
probabilistic mediator schema but just a
manually designed schema with five tables.
But while we assume that
the target schema is fixed
we want the possibility that
we can add more sources.
That means more clinics
as the system grows.
Now I'm beginning to
add the schema mapping.
Now there are several techniques
of specifying schema mappings.
One of them is called Local-as-View.
This means we write the relations in each
source as a view over the target schema.
But this way of writing the query,
as we can see here, may seem odd to you.
It's called syntax, but
you don't need to know it.
Just as an example, the first few things
the treats relation in S1 maps to,
so you see that arrow, that means maps to.
So it maps to the query select doctor,
chronic disease from treats patient,
has chronic disease.
Where treatspatient.patient Is equal
to has chronic disease dot patient.
We see the query here in the yellow box.
The only thing we should notice here
is that the select class on the query
has two attributes doctor and
chronic disease which are exactly the same
attributes of the treats relation in S1.
Now let's ask a query that
gives the target schema.
Which doctors are responsible for
discharging patients?
Which translates to
the SQL query shown here.
Now, the problem is how to translate
this query to a query that can
be sent to the sources.
Now ideally this should be simplest query
with no extra operations as shown here.
S3 treats means treats
relation in sources 3.
Now you can see the ideal answer.
To find such an optimal query
reformulation, it turns out that this
process is very complex and becomes
worse as a number of sources increases.
Thus query reformulation
becomes a significant scalability problem
in a big data integration scenario.
Let's look at the second use case
public health is a significant
component of our healthcare system.
Public health systems monitor detect and
take action when epidemics strike.
Not so long ago we have witnessed public
health concerns due to Anthrax virus,
the swine flu and the bird flu.
But these epidemics caused a group
called WADDS to develop a system for
disease surveillance.
This system would connect all local
hospitals in the Washington, DC area, and
is designed to exchange
disease information.
For example, if a hospital lab has
identified a new strain of a virus,
other hospitals and the Centers for
Disease Control, CDC,
in the network,
should be able to know about it.
It should be clear that this needs a data
integration solution where the data
sources would be the labs, the data would
be the lab tests medical records and
even genetic profiles of the virus and
the subjects who might be infected.
The table here shows the different
components with this architecture.
We will just digest the necessary
parts for our requirement.
Just know that RIM which stands for
Reference Information Model is global
schema that this industry has developed
and expects to use as a standard.
Why we want to exchange and combine new
information from different hospitals?
Every hospital is independent and
can implement their own information
system any way they see fit.
Therefore even when there
are standards like HL-7 that
specify what kind of data a held
cache system should have an exchange.
There are considerable variations in
the implementation of the standard itself.
For example the two wide boxes show
a difference in representation
of the same kind of data, this should
remind you of the data variety problem.
Let's say, we have a patient
with ID 19590520 whose lab
reports containing her plasma protein
measurements are required for
analyzing her health condition.
The problem is that the patient
went to three different clinics and
four different labs which all
implement the standards differently.
On top of it?
Each clinic uses its own
electronic medical record system
which we have a very large amount of data.
So the data integration system's job is to
transform the data from the source schema
to the schema of the receiving
system in this case the rim system.
This is sometimes called
the data exchange problem.
Informally a data exchange
problem can be defined like this.
Suppose we have a given database
whose relations are known.
Let us say we also know
the target database's schema and
the constraints the schema will satisfy.
Further we know the desired schema
mappings between the source and
this target schema.
What we do not know is how to populate
the tuples in the target database.
From the tuples in the socialization in
such a way that both schema mappings and
target constraints
are simultaneously satisfied.
In many domains like healthcare,
a significant amount of effort has been
spend by the industry in
standardizing schemas and values.
For example LOINC is a standard for
medical lab observations.
Here item like systolic blood pressure or
gene mutation are encoded in this
specific way as given by this standard.
So, if we want to write that
the systolic/diastolic pressure of
a individual is 132 by 90, we'll not write
out the string systolic blood pressure,
but use the code for it.
The ability to use standard code
is not unique to healthcare data.
The 50 states of the US all
have two letter abbreviations.
Generalizing therefore, whenever we have
data such as the domain is finite and have
a standard set of code available, we give
a new opportunity of handling big deal.
Mainly, reducing the data
size through compression.
The compression refers to a way of
creating an encoded
representation of data.
So that this encoder form is smaller
than the original representation.
A common encoding method is
called dictionary encoding.
Consider a database with 10 million
record of patient visits a lab.
Each record indicates a test and
its results.
Now we show it this way like
in a columnar structure
to make the point that the data is kept
in a column stored relational database
rather than a row store
relational database.
Now consider the column for test code.
Where the type of test is codified
according to the standard.
We replace a string representation
of the standard by a number.
The mapping between
the original test code and
the encoded number are also
stored separately.
Now suppose there
are a total of 500 tests.
So this separate table called
the dictionary here has 500 rows,
which is clearly much smaller
than ten million right?
Now 500 distinct values can be
represented by encoding them in 9 bits,
because 2 to the power of 9 is 512.
Other encoding techniques would be applied
to attributes like date and patient ID.
That's full large data we cannot reduce
the number of total actual rules.
So we have to store all ten million rules.
But we can reduce the amount of space
required by storing data in a column
oriented data store and
by using compression, indeed modern
systems use credit processing algorithms
to operate directly on compress data.
Data compression is an important
technology for big data.
And just like is a set of qualified
terms for lab tests, clinical data
also uses SNOMED which stands for
systematized nomenclature of medicine.
SNOMED is a little more
than just a vocabulary.
It does have a vocabulary of course.
The vocabulary is the collection
of medical terms in human and
medicine to provide codes, terms, synonyms
and definitions that cover anatomy,
diseases, findings, procedures,
micro organisms, substances etcetera.
But it also has relationships.
As you can see,
a renal cyst is related to kidney because
kidney's the finding site of a renal cyst.
If we query against an ontology,
it would look like a graph grid.
In this box,
we are asking to find all patient
findings with a benign tumor morphology.
In terms of querying, we are looking for
edges of a graph where one noticed
the concept that we need to find which is
connected to a node called benign neoplasm
that is benign tumor through an edge
called associated morphology
that applying this query against
the data here produces all benign tumors
of specific organs as you can
see by the orange rounded group.
But now that we have these terms,
we can use these terms to search
outpatient records with these terms would
have been used so
what's the essence of this used case.
This is can shows that an in division
system in a public health domain and
in many other domains must
be able to handle variety.
In this case there's a Global Schema
called RiM shown here all queries and
analyses performed by a data analysts
should be against this global schema.
However, the actual data which is
generated by different medical facilities
would need to be transformed
into data in this schema.
This would require not only
format conversions, but
it would need to respect all constraints
imposed by the source and by the target.
For example, a source may not distinguish
between an emergency surgical procedure
and a regular surgical procedure.
But the target may want to
put them in different tables.
We also saw that
the integration system for
this used case would need to use
quantified data but this gives
us the opportunity to use data compression
to gauge story and query efficiency.
In terms of variety, we saw how
relational data like patient records XML
data like HL7 events, and
graph data like ontologies, are co-used.
To support this, the integration
system must be able to do both model
transformation and query transformation.
Query transformation is the process of
taking a query on the target schema.
Converting it to a query
against a different data model.
For example, part of an SQL query against
the RIM may need to go to snowmad and
hence when you to be converted to
a graph query in the snowmad system.
Model transformation is
a process of taking data
represented in one model
in one source system and
converting it to an equivalent data
in another model the target system.
Hello, my name is Victor Lou.
I am the Solutions Engineer of
Global Philanthropy of Daameer.org.
Helping researchers, academia,
and non-profits find the insights
that matter using data.
Today I am here to give you
a production environment,
personalized music recommendation project.
That was done for PonoMusic and
so what is Pono Music?
Pono Music is revolutionizing music
listening by bringing back native,
high-resolution audio.
It's the way that artists intended and
recorded their music.
Neil Young, the iconic artist and
musician is also the founder and CEO.
Pono Music is the only complete
high-resolution music ecosystem.
That includes the Pono player, the Pono
Music store, the Pono Music community.
They have been super
generous in allowing us to
take a look behind the scenes as how
we built out the recommendations.
So, David Meer supports their mission
by providing a music recommendation
engine that is both scalable and
flexible as Pono grows their user base.
Let's begin by visiting Pono
music's website as you can see,
they have a few shelves that focus on
various recommendations that are not
tailored to each individual user.
If you login,
then an additional shelf would appear
that would deliver the recommendations
that are created in data gear.
So how does DataMirror accomplish this.
In a nutshell, DataMirror is a end to end,
antalis platform which contains ingestion,
preparation analysis, visualization and
operationalization all the same platform.
And having all the capabilities
in one platform is superior to
traditional technology stack.
Integration between disparate technologies
brings a lot of unnecessary challenges.
We take advantage of open
source big data technologies.
Specifically, we run natively and
Hadoop and Spark for our back end.
And we leverage D3JS on the front end for
visualizations.
Our Excel-like interface makes it easy for
folks who don't know how to code to
also get in with the data modeling.
It is very much self-service.
In the case of Pono Music's
data mirror deployment,
we have deployed a Hadoop
on Amazon on web services.
But we can also be deployed off premise if
needed it doesn't have
to be in the clouds.
In fact, we could work with many many
different distributions of Hadoop.
We can access dean rear through
any modern web browser.
As you can see here we're using Google
Chrome but it works on any browser, right?
So lets go ahead and take a look at
the a; let's log into data grip,
so we're going to go ahead and
log in here..
So what you're seeing here is the browser
tab and we can see various artifacts
which include connections such
as connections to the pull nose,
salesforce.com instance or
a connection to AWS S3 instance.
Because DataMirror comes with so
many prebuilt connectors which include
Connections to salesforce.com and S3.
We can easily grant access to
those systems in order to pull or
push data in and out of the dev.
For example, let's take a quick look at
the salesforce.com configuration here.
As you can see, we've already configured
salesforce as the connector type.
When we hit next here,
we'll we that you can authorize
a data manager to retrieve data.
We're not going to do it because
this is a production environment, so
I don't want to disrupt the pools.
But if we were to click it, it'll give
us a salesfloor.com blogging stream.
And so as soon as we login, the Datameer
would have access via the O-Off token.
And so this is valid for a period of time.
I'm going to go ahead and
hit the cancel button as this
is a production environment.
And so now we're ready to look
at an import job artifact.
So this is the sales force import job and
as you can see we go in here and
we configure it.
We can see that it's connected to
the Pono Music SMDC connection.
I'm going to go ahead and
hit next here.with salesforce.com,
we just have to simply define the SOQL,
which is basically a querying
language that's based on SQL.
To locate data contained within
the salesforce.com objects.
You can see the select statement here,
you can also see the familiar
from statement, and you can also
see the where statement as well.
So in order to protect
the privacy of the users,
Datameer has the capability to obfuscate
sort of columns that are sensitive.
And so in other words, we can scramble
sensitive fields such as email or
physical addresses.
And at this point in time, I'm going to
go ahead and cancel out, and I'm going to
show the next part of this demo in
an obfuscated workbook environment.
The artifacts contained in the obfuscated
folders are duplicates of the import job
of the workbook from their production
counterparts as you can see here.
So as you can see in the import
job settings we have configured
the same connections here but
for the obfuscated columns here.
Now we're obfuscating the owner
email as well as the street address.
Now we hit Next here.
And so you can see, various fields are
being pulled here from Salesforce, right.
And in particular,
I want to highlight the.
The owner email, that field, so as you
can see these are the obfuscated fields.
Similarly, the actual street address,
that's also masked as well.
I'm going to go ahead and hit Cancel.
I will go back to, rather we're going to
go check out the workbook environment,
which is where we do the preparation and
analysis.
To the obfuscated workbook environment.
As you can see we're starting
with a raw source of data here.
This was the data that was
contained in the data sheet.
Take note that there's a variety of icons
that indicate different types of sheets.
So you could see here this
is the raw data type.
This is a regular worksheet.
You have a union sheet and
you have a joint sheet and
we'll go into a little bit
more detail as we get to them.
So, as you can see,
the interface is very much like Excel.
Looking at the second sheet pairs, and
it's using a function called group by.
So the group by function is a type of
aggregation function in Datameer speak.
As you can see, you can build
the functions by pointing and clicking.
But you can also enter the formula
to create nested functions or
Apply arithmetic
operations just as a cell.
We take all the unique combinations
of albums purchased for
each of the unique email
using a group pair function.
Then we pull out each of the elements
of the pairings using a list element
function, so let's see here.
If you were to build a function
from scratch, you can see this.
So then you create a group by function,
and then direct it at a column.
You basically pass it to argument.
To find out the occurrence
of each pairing of albums,
we're going to go ahead and
look at this LR sheet.
And so these are, we're using group
by functions as well here, so
we're grouping by the first item one,
and then item two.
And then, we're doing a group count,
which is counting the frequency
of occurrences of those cells.
Similarly, we're going to
do a similar thing but
with the item two first now, and then
item one, and then doing a group count.
And the reason is,
we don't care about the order.
And so, we repeat this on the next sheet
reversing the order of the albums to make
sure that we capture all the combinations
since the order doesn't matter to us.
And then we use our unit sheet function
to append the second frequency
counting sheet to the first frequency
counting sheet, as you can see here.
It's drag and drop, of course, and
so we've connected them together.
You can do multi-sheets but
in this case we only have two, right.
So it's, okay.
We ignore the co-occurrent set sheet as it
is currently not used in the final output.
We were kind of experimenting
with other recommendation models.
We're rebuilding those workbooks.
So one of the really cool features for
we can execute the workbook, but
deselect the storage of
intermediary sheets.
This means that we only need
relevant functions are executed
at a to the data lineage of columns that
are contained in the selector sheet.
Moving on, we have to create
a separate sheet from the raw data,
that counts the number of times an album
occurs across all of the purchases.
So you can see here, which students will
buy an album and then we do a count.
We bring the code occurrences and
the frequency together using the join
feature as you can see,
it is a drag and drop interface.
You got the obfuscated workbook
each of the worksheets here and
within each worksheets,
you got various columns.
You can bring those, you can drag and
drop them into here to do the joins.
You can do different types of joins,
you got the inner, outer, etc.
You can also do multi column joins.
You can do multi sheet joins.
You can also select which columns
you want to keep during the join.
Go ahead and cancel out here.
Datameer does not allow us to add
additional functions to a joint sheet so
we duplicate it by right clicking and
then hitting the duplicate button.
And then we create the next sheet,
which contains a link to columns, so
it will be linked to the rating sheet.
This is, see the link columns back
to the joint sheets and then.
We simply add a calculation
where it's the number of times
the co-occurrence occurs divided by
the number of times that the first album
in the column appears
throughout the data set.
The idea is to give a high recommendation
for albums that appear frequently
together While simultaneously
penalizing albums that are too common.
And so at this point,
I would like to write a few more joins
that bring together the album ID,
the email,
recommended album ID based on the album
ID and email, so take a look here.
So, as you can see here and then,
before we finish,
we also do an anti joint by performing
the outer left joint with
the almighty in the email.
And then filtering, so this is,
by the way, this is a double column joint.
And then we do a filter, so
then we filter out all the, for
the obfuscated owner
fields that are empty.
We apply a filter to it.
So finally, we use a few group I
functions to do some deep duplication,
so we use group by functions again.
And then, so we make sure that the album
functions are unique for each user and
then we use a group max function.
In order to preserve the highest
rating for each of the unique
recommendations the final desired
output is on the recommenders sheet.
It leverages the group top end function,
so you can see here group top numbers.
So we only want to look at the to
20 recommendations for each user.
And in addition,
we also create a email row number field,
which is a key that needed for
salesforce.com, and
it is generated by a simple
concatenation function here.
Something that note that [SOUND] is
big on data governance, data lineage.
As you can see, we can keep track of
how all the raw data flows through
from the raw data set all
the way to the end product.
So each workbook functions can be
also exported in JSON format to keep
track of revision history.
We're not ready to operationalize
things and so how do we do it?
Get our workbook configurations.
Go ahead and exit out of the workbook.
Let's go back to
the production environment.
As you can see,
the workbook recalculation retriggers
when the import job is completed.
We also only retain the latest results, so
we select purge historical results,
as you can see here.
As I mentioned earlier, a data mirror
makes it easy to operationalize a workbook
because we only select
the final output sheets.
And, so you see everything's unchecked
except for the recommended sheet.
And Datameer basically will automatically
determine what is a critical path
of the intermediary sheets to
produce the desired output sheet.
Once the recommendation
workbook is calculated,
then this triggers the export job run.
I'm going to go ahead and
move to the export job artifact.
Exit out of this.
Go ahead and save, or not save.
We'll see the export job,
let's go ahead and configure that.
Hit Next, Share.
CSV outputs, so.
This triggers the export job to run,
which is how we basically push
the results of the recommendations to S3.
We elected to use S3 because we
are already hosting at services and
S3 is an affordable storage solution.
We cannot push directly to
salesforce.com at the present because
It's a only connection.
Therefore, we need to push
data to the storage area,
which can be scheduled for using Apex.
A general challenge for
is the role limitation on each pool.
Fortunately, DataMirror comes
with the option to push
files that are broken
into one megabyte chunks.
So as you can see here in
advanced settings 1 megabyte, and
then we set a type of
consecutive numbering scheme.
And so it's dynamic naming conventions
using time stamps and numbering for
each of the chunks.
So that sums up the current
co-curds/d deployment.
As you've seen, we have easily
integrated data from Salesforce.com,
created a recommendation model, and
set up a push to S3 automatically for
easy consumption back to Salesforce.com.
Finally, we operationalized this by
triggering each of the steps sequentially
all in sitting on top of
the powerful Hadoop platform.
What's next?
Well, Pono Music is working on
implementing Google Analytics tracking for
each user at the Apple pages.
So let's go back to
the Apple Music Store here.
Just for an example, let's take a look
at the Train Led Zeppelin Two Album.
As you can see all of those album
IDs that we were looking at earlier,
these are actually embedded in the URL.
This means that in the near future, we
can actually adapt recommendations based
on the buying behavior to recommendations
based on both buying and browser behavior.
We can look at recommendations based on
genre, perhaps we can try to look at most
recent purchases or browsing behavior in
the last three to six to nine months.
Or we could use album metadata such as
album release date to give additional
recommendations.
Also, it is quite simple to just
duplicate the recommendations workbook in
[INAUDIBLE] to try any
number of these options.
And so,
that means we can do a lot of AB testing,
as we track how users react to each of
the modified recommendation algorithms.
The possibilities are literally endless.
So anyhow, thanks again for
checking out how Data Mirror
builds a simple code current
recommendation engine for music.
Please feel free to direction questions or
comments to me at
victor.liu@datamirror.com.
Thanks again.
Amarnath just finished overviewing
querying and integrational big data.
Although, fundamental understanding
of these concepts are important.
Some of these tasks can be accomplished
using graphical user interface
based tools or software products.
In this short module,
we introduce you to two of those tools.
Splunk and Datameer.
We have selected a few videos from
the site of our sponsors Splunk,
to give you an overview of using such
tools for different applications.
You will also have a short
hands-on activity on Splunk.
In addition,
we provide you a comprehensive video on
using Datamere in
the digital music industry.
Keep in mind, Splunk and
Datamere are just two of the many
tools in this category, but
they represent a huge industry.