What is a data stream?
After this video,
you will be able to summarize the key
characteristics of a data stream.
Identify the requirements of
streaming data systems, and
recognize the data streams
you use in your life.
When we talked about how
big data is generated and
the characteristics of the big
data using sound waves.
One of the challenges we mentioned was the
velocity of data coming in varying rates.
For some applications this
presents the need to process data
as it is generated, or
in other words, as it streams.
We call these types of applications
Streaming Data Processing Applications.
This terminology refers to a constant
stream of data flowing from a source,
for example data from a sensory machine or
data from social media.
An example application would be making
data-driven marketing decisions in
real time.
Through the use of data from
real-time sales trends,
social media analysis,
and sales distributions.
Another example for streaming data
processing is monitoring of industrial or
farming machinery in real time.
For monitoring and
detection of potential system failures.
In fact, any sensor network or
internet of things environment
controlled by another entity,
or set of entities falls
under this category.
For example,
as you have seen in an earlier video,
FlightStats is an application.
That processes about 60
million weekly flight events
that come into their
data acquisition system.
And turns it into real-time
intelligence for airlines and
millions of travelers
around the world daily.
So, how then do we define a data stream?
A stream is defined as
a possibly unbounded sequence of
data items or records.
That may or may not be related to,
or correlated with each other.
Each data is generally timestamped and
in some cases geo-tagged.
As you have seen in our examples,
the data can stream from many sources.
Including instruments, and
many internet of things application areas,
computer programs, websites,
or social media posts.
Streaming data sometimes get
referred to as event data as
each data item is treated as an individual
event in a synchronized sequence.
Streams pose very difficult challenges for
conventional data
management architectures.
Which are built primarily on the concept
of persistence, static data collections.
Due to the fact that most often we
have only one chance to look at and
process streaming data
before more gets piled on.
Streaming data management systems cannot
be separated from real-time processing
of data.
Managing and
processing data in motion is a typical
capability of streaming data systems.
However, the sheer size, variety and
velocity of big data adds further
challenges to these systems.
Such systems are designed to manage
relatively simple computations.
Such as one record at a time or
a set of objects in a short time
window of the most recent data.
The computations are done
in near-real-time,
sometimes in memory, and
as independent computations.
The processing components
often subscribe to a system,
or a stream source, non-interactively.
This means they sent nothing
back to the source, nor
did they establish
interaction with the source.
The concept of dynamic steering involves
dynamically changing the next steps or
direction of an application
through a continuous
computational process using streaming.
Dynamic steering is often a part of
streaming data management and processing.
A self-driving car is a perfect example
of a dynamic steering application.
But all streaming data applications
fall into this category.
Such as the online gaming example we
discussed earlier in this course.
Amazon Kinesis an other open-source Apache
projects like Storm, Flink,
Spark Streaming, and
Samza are examples of big
data streaming systems.
Many other companies also
provide streaming systems for
big data that are frequently
updated in response
to the rapidly changing
nature of these technologies.
As a summary, dynamic near-real-time
streaming data management,
processing, and steering is an important
part of today's big data applications.
Next, we will look at some
of the challenges for
streaming data management and processing.
Now that we have seen what
streaming data means,
let’s look at what makes streaming data
different and what some management and
processing challenges for
streaming data are.
After this video you will
be able to compare and
contrast data in motion and data at rest.
Differentiate between streaming and
batch data processing.
And list management and
processing challenges for streaming data.
We often hear the terms data addressed and
data in motion,
when talking about big data management.
Data-at-rest refers to mostly
static data collected from one or
more data sources, and the analysis
happens after the data is collected.
The term data-in-motion refers to a mode
although similar data
collection methods apply,
the data gets analyzed at the same
time it is being generated.
Just like the sensor data processing
in a plane or a self-driving car.
Analysis of data addressed is called
batch or static processing and
the analysis of streaming data
is called stream processing.
The run time and memory usage of most
algorithms that process static data,
is usually dependent on the data size, and
this size can easily be calculated
from files or databases.
A key property, of streaming data
processing is the size of the data
is unbounded and this changes the types
of algorithms that can be used.
Algorithms that require iterating or
looping over the whole data set are not
possible since with stream data,
you never get to the end.
The modeling and management of streaming
data should enable computations on
one data element or a small window
of group of recent data elements.
These computations can update metrics,
monitor and
plot statistics on the streaming data.
Or apply analysis techniques
to the streaming data
to learn about the dynamics of
the system as a time series.
Since computations need to
be completed in real time,
the analysis tasks processing
streaming data should be quicker or
not much longer than
the streaming rate of the data.
Which we define by it's velocity.
In most streaming systems,
the management, and
processing system subscribe to
the data source, but doesn't
send anything back to the stream source
in terms of feedback or interactions.
These requirements for streaming data
processing are quite different than batch
processing where the analytical steps
have access to often, all data and
can take more time to complete a complex
analytical task with less pressure
on the completion time of individual
data management and processing tasks.
Most organizations today
use a hybrid architecture.
Sometimes get referred to as
the lambda architecture for
processing streaming and
back jobs at the same time.
In these systems, streaming wheel over
the real-time data is managed and
kept until those data elements are pushed
to a batch system and become available
to access and process as batch data.
In such systems, a stream storage
layer is used to enable fast
trees of streams and
ensure data ordering and consistency.
And a processing layer for
data is used to retrieve data from
the storage layer to analyze it and
most probably little bit to a batch
data stream and notify the streaming
storage that the data set does no
longer need to be in streaming storage.
The big data challenges we discussed
were scalability, data replication,
and durability, and fault tolerance arise
in this type of data very significantly.
Among many there are two main
challenges that needs to be overcome
to avoid data loss, and
enable real time analytical tasks.
One challenge in streaming data
process is that the size and
frequency of the mean data can
significantly change over time.
These changes can be unpredictable and
may be driven by human behavior.
For example, streaming data found on
social networks such as Facebook and
Twitter can increase in
volume during holidays,
sports matches, or major news events.
These changes can be periodic and occur,
for example, in the evenings or weekends.
For example, people may post messages
on Facebook more in the evening
instead of during the day working hours.
Streaming data changes may also
be unpredictable and sporadic.
There can be an increase in data size and
frequency during during major events,
sporting matches and things like that.
Other changes include dropping or
missing data or even no data
when there are network problems or device
generating the data has hardware problems.
As an example of streaming
data fluctuation,
consider the number of Tweets per second.
On average,
there are 6,000 tweets sent every second.
However, in August 2013,
the world record was
set when over 144,000 tweets
were sent in a second.
That's a factor of 24 increase.
At the end of this lesson we will ask
you to focus on Twitter streams for
trending topics and any other topic.
You will notice how the rates
of Tweets streaming
changes between different times and
different topics.
To summarize, streaming data must be
handled differently than static data.
Unlike static data, where you can
determine the size, streaming data is
continually generated, and
you can not process it all at once.
Streaming data can unpredictably
change in both size and frequency.
This can be due to human behavior.
Finally, algorithms for
processing streaming data must
be relatively fast and simple.
Since you don't know when
the next data arrives.
In a previous lecture,
we said that new interesting solutions are
emerging in the big data product space.
While these solutions do not have
the full fledged power of a DBMS,
they offer novel feature combinations that
suit some application space just right.
One of these products is Aerospike,
which calls itself a distributed
NoSQL database and
key value store, and
goes on to say that it is architected for
the performance needs of
today's web scale applications.
The diagram here is from
an Aerospike whitepaper.
It shows how Aerospike relates to
the ecosystem for which it is designed.
The top layer shows several applications
for real time consumer facing systems,
such as travel recommendation systems,
pricing engines used for
stock market applications,
real time decision systems that
analyze data to figure out whether
an investment should be done and so forth.
Now, all of these systems
have the common need
that large amounts of data should be
accessible to them at any point of time.
The Aerospike system can interoperate
with Hadoop-based systems, so
Spark, or a Legacy database, or
even a real time data source.
It can exchange large volumes
of data with any such source and
serve fast lookups and
queries to the applications above.
Now that translates to a very
high availability robust and
strong consistency needs.
The figure here presents a high level
architecture diagram of Aerospike.
The first item to notice here
is what they call a fast bat,
which essentially refers to
the left side of the architecture.
The client system processes transactions.
That is data that are primarily managed in
a primary index that is a key value store.
This index stays in memory for
operational purposes.
However, the server also interacts with
the storage layer for persistence.
The storage layer uses three
kinds of storage systems,
in memory with a dynamic RAM or
DRAM, a regular spinning disk,
and flash/SSD, which is solid state device
for fast loading of data when needed.
In fact the Aerospike system
has optimized its performance with
characteristics of an SSD in mind.
For those of who are not sure
what an SSD is, you can think of
an SSD as a kind of storage device
whose random read performance is much
faster than speeding hard disk and the
write performance is just a little slower.
One vendor recently advertised its SSD
has sequence share read speeds of up to
2,500 MBPS and the sequential write
speeds as fast as 1,500 MBPS.
Now why is this important
in a big data discussion?
When we speak of scalability, grade
efficiency, fast transactions, and so
forth, we often do not mention
that part of the performance
guarantee is governed by the combination
of hardware and software.
So the ability to offer more efficient
persistent storage with fast IO
implies that while a significant amount
of information can be stored on disk,
it can be done without compromising
the overall system performance for
an environment that
needs fast data loading.
The second point of uniqueness
is a secondary index there.
Aerospike built secondary index
fields that are non-primary keys.
A non-primary key is a key attribute
that makes a tuple unique,
but it has not been
chosen as a primary key.
In Aerospike, secondary indices
are stored in main memory.
They are built on every node in a cluster
and co-located with the primary index.
Each secondary index entry
contains references to records,
which are local to the node.
As a key value store,
Aerospike uses standard database like
scalar types like integer, string, and
so forth, as well as lists like Reddis.
The map type is similar to the hashtag of
Reddis and contains attribute value pairs.
Since it is focused on real time web
application, it supports geospatial data,
like places with latitude and
longitude values or regency polygons.
This allows them to perform KV store
operations, for example, like is
the location of this in La Jolla,
which is a point-in-polygon query.
Or a distance query, like find hotels
within three miles of my location.
KV queries are constructed
programmatically.
Now interestingly, Aerospike also provides
a more declarative language called AQL.
AQL looks very similar to SQL,
the Standard Query Language for
relational databases.
A query like select name and
age from user star profiles projects
out the name and age values
from the profile's record set that
belongs to the ding space called users.
The language also allows
advocate functions, like sum and
average, and other user defined functions,
which the system may evaluate through
a map produced time operation.
We mentioned earlier that while most
medium assists today offer base
guarantees, Aerospike, despite being
a distributor information system,
actually offers ACID guarantees.
This is accomplished using
a number of techniques.
We'll consider a few of them to give you
a flavor of the mechanisms that current
systems use to balance between
large scale data management and
transaction management in a cluster
where nodes can join or leave.
You may recall that consistency
means two different things,
one is to ensure that all constraints,
like domain constraints, are satisfied.
The second meaning is applied
to distributor systems and
ensures all copies of a data
item in a cluster are in sync.
For operations and
single keys with replication and
secondary indices,
Aerospike provides immediate consistency
using synchronous writes to
replicas within the cluster.
Synchronous write means the write
process will be considered
successful only if
the replica is all subdated.
No other write is allowed on the record
while the object of replica is pending.
So what happens if there is an increase
in the number of write operations due to
an increase in ingestion rate?
In Aerospike, it is possible to relax
this immediate consistency condition
by bypassing some of
the consistency checks.
But if this is done, eventual
consistency will still be enforced.
Durability is achieved by storing data
in the flash SSD on every node and
performing direct reads from the flash.
Now durability is also maintained through
the process of replication because we have
multiple copies of data.
So even if one node fails, the latest copy
of the last data is available from one or
more replica nodes in the same cluster,
as well as in nodes residing
in remote clusters.
But does that just
contradict the CAP theorem?
The CAP theorem holds when
the network is partitioned.
That means when nodes in
different parts of the network
have different data content.
Aerospike reduces and tries to completely
eliminate the situation by making
sure that the master knows exactly
where all the other nodes are.
And the replication is
happening properly even when
the new nodes are joining the network.
In the previous modules, we talked
about data variety and streaming data.
In this module, we'll focus on a central
issue in large scale data processing and
management and that is when should
we use Hadoop or Yarn style system?
And when should we use a database system
that can perform parallel operations?
And then we'll explore how the state
of the art big data management systems
address these issues of volume and
variety.
We start with the problem
of high volume data and
two contrasting approaches for
handling them.
So after this video, you'll be able to
explain the various advantages of
using a DBMS over a file system.
Specify the differences between
parallel and distributed DBMS.
And briefly describe
a MapReduce-style DBMS and
its relationship with the current DBMSs.
In the early days,
when database systems weren't around or
just came in, databases were designed
as a set of application programs.
They were written to handle data that
resided in files in a file system.
However, soon this
approach led to problems.
First, there are multiple file formats.
And often, there was a duplication
of information in different files.
Or the files simply had inconsistent
information that was very hard to
determine, especially when the data was
large and the file content was complex.
Secondly, there wasn't
a uniform way to access data.
Each data access task, like finding
employees in a department sorted by their
salary versus finding
employees in all departments
sorted by their start date needed to
be written as a separate program.
So people ended up writing
different programs for
data access, as well as data update.
A third problem was rooted to
the enforcement of constraints,
often called integrity constraints.
For example, to say something like every
employee has exactly one job title.
One had arrived that condition,
as part of an application program called.
So if you want to change the constraint,
you need to look for
the programs where such
a rule is hard coded.
The fourth problem has to
do with system failures.
Supposed Joe, an employee becomes
the leader of a group and moves in to
the office of the old leader, Ben who has
now become the director of the division.
So we update Joe's details and
move on to update, Ben's new office for
the system crashes.
So the files are incompletely updated and
there is no way to go back,
and start all over.
The term atomicity means that all of
the changes that we need to do for
these promotions must happen altogether,
as a single unit.
They should either fully go through or
not go through at all.
This atomicity is very difficult to handle
when the data reside in one or more files.
So, a prime reason for the transition
to a DBMS is to alleviate these and
other difficulties.
If we look at the current DBMS,
especially relational DBMS,
we will notice a number of advantages.
DBMSs offer query languages,
which are declarative.
Declarative means that we
state what we want to retrieve
without telling the DBMS
how exactly to retrieve it.
In a relational DBMS, we can say,
find the average set of salary of
employees in the R&D division for
every job title and sort from high to low.
We don't have to tell the system how
to group these records by job title or
how to extract just the salary field.
A typical user of a DBMS who issues
queries does not worry about how
the relations are structured or whether
they are located in the same machine,
or spread across five machines.
The goal of data independence is to
isolate the users from the record
layout so long as the logical
definition of the data,
which means the tables and
their attributes are clearly specified.
Now most importantly, relational DBMSs
have developed a very mature and
continually improving methodology of
how to answer a query efficiently,
even when there are a large
number of cables and
the number of records
exceeds hundreds of millions.
From a 2009 account,
EB uses the tera data system with
72 machines to manage approximately
2.4 terabytes of relational data.
These systems have built powerful
data structures, algorithms and
sound principles to determine how
a specific array should be onset
efficiently despite the size of the data
and the complexity of the tables.
Now with any system,
bad things can happen.
Systems fail in the middle
of an operation.
Malicious processes try to get
unauthorized access to data.
One large can often underappreciated
aspect of a DBMS is
the implementation of transaction
safety and failure recovery.
Now, recall our discussion of atomicity.
In databases, a single logical operation
on the data is called a transaction.
For example, a transfer of funds
from one bank account to another,
even involving multiple changes
like debiting one account and
crediting another is a single transaction.
Now, atomicity is one of the four
properties that a transaction should
provide.
The four properties,
collectively called ACID are atomicity,
consistency, isolation and durability.
Consistency means any data
written to the database must be
valid according to all defined
rules including constrains.
The durability property ensures that
once a transaction has been committed,
it will remain so, even in the event
of power loss, crashes or errors.
The isolation property comes
in the context of concurrency,
which refers to multiple people
updating a database simultaneously.
To understand concurrency, think of
an airline or a railway reservation system
where hundreds and thousands of
people are buying, cancelling and
changing their reservations and
tickets all at the same time.
The DBMS must be sure that
a ticket should no be sold twice.
Or if one person is in the middle
of buying the last ticket,
another person does not see
that ticket as available.
These are guaranteed by
the isolation property that says,
not withstanding the number of people
accessing the system at the same time.
The transactions must happen as if they're
done serially, that is one after another.
Providing these capabilities is
an important part of the M in DBMS.
So next, we consider how traditional
databases handle large data volumes.
The classical way in which DBMSs
have handled the issue of large
volumes is by created parallel and
distributed databases.
In a parallel database, for
example, parallel Oracle,
parallel DB2 or post SQL XE.
The tables are spread across multiple
machines and operations like selection,
and join use parallel algorithms
to be more efficient.
These systems also allow a user
to create a replication.
That is multiple copies of tables.
Thus, introducing data redundancy, so
that failure on replica can be
compensated for by using another.
Further, it replicates in
sync with each other and
a query can result into
any of the replicates.
This increases the number of simultaneous
that is conquer into queries
that can be handled by the system.
In contrast, a distributed DBMS, which
we'll not discuss in detail in this course
is a network of independently running
DBMSs that communicate with each other.
In this case, one component knows some
part of the schema of it is neighboring
DBMS and can pass a query or part of
a query to the neighbor when needed.
So the important takeaway issue here is,
are all of these facilities
offered by a DBMS important for
the big data application that
you are planning to build?
And the answer in many
cases can be negative.
However, if these issues are important,
then the database management
systems may offer a viable option for
a big data application.
Now, let's take a little more time to
address an issue that's often discussed in
the big data word.
The question is if DBMSs are so powerful,
why do we see the emergence
of MapReduce-style Systems?
Unfortunately, the answer to this
question is not straightforward.
For a long while now, DBMSs have
effectively used parallelism, specifically
parallel databases in addition to
replication would also create partitions.
So that different parts of a logical
table can physically reside on different
machines,, then different parts of a query
can access the partitions in parallel and
speed up creative performance.
Now these algorithms not only improve
the operating efficiency, but
simultaneously optimize algorithms to
take into account the communication cost.
That is the time needed to
exchange data between machines.
However, classical parallel DBMSs did
not take into account machine failure.
And in contrast, MapReduce was
originally developed not for storage and
retrieval, but for distributive
processing of large amounts of data.
Specifically, its goal was to support
complex custom computations that could
be performed efficiently on many machines.
So in a MapReduce or MR setting,
the number of machines
could go up to thousands.
Now since MR implementations were
done over Hadoop file systems,
issues like node failure were
automatically accounted for.
So MR effectively used in complex
applications like data mining or
data clustering, and these algorithms
are often very complex, and
typically require problem
specific techniques.
Very often,
these algorithms have multiple stages.
That is the output from one processing
stage is the input to the next.
It is difficult to develop these
multistage algorithms in a standard
relational system.
But since these were genetic operations,
many of them were designed to work
with unstructured data like text and
nonstandard custom data formats.
Now, it's now amply clear that this
mixture of data management requirements
and data processing analysis requirements
have created an interesting tension in
the data management world.
Just look at a few of
these tension points.
Now, DBMSs perform storage and
retrieval operations very efficiently.
But first,
the data must be loaded into the DBMS.
So, how much time does loading take?
In one study,
scientists use two CVS files.
One had 92 attributes with
about 165 million tuples for
a total size of 85 gigabytes.
And the other had 227 attributes
with 5 million tuples for
a total size of 5 gigabytes.
The time to load and index this data in
MySQL and PostgreSQL, took 15 hours each.
In a commercial database running on
three machines, it took two hours.
Now there are applications like
the quantities in the case we discussed
earlier where this kind of loading
time is simply not acceptable,
because the analysis on
the data must be performed
within a given time limit
after it's arrival.
A second problem faced by
some application is that for
them, the DBMSs offer
too much functionality.
For example, think of an application
that only looks at the price of an item
if you provide it with a product name or
product code.
The number of products it serves
is let's say, 250 million.
This lookup operation happens
only on a single table and
does not mean anything
more complex like a join.
Further, consider that while there
are several hundred thousand customers
who access this data,
none of them really update the tables.
So, do we need a full function DBMS for
this read-only application?
Or can we get a simpler solution which
can use a cluster of machines, but
does not provide all the wonderful
guarantees that a DBMS provides?
At the other end of the spectrum,
there is an emerging class of optimization
that meets all the nice transactional
guarantees that a DBMS provides.
And at the same time, meets the support
for efficient analytical operations.
These are often required for
systems like Real-Time Decision Support.
That will accept real-time data like
customer purchases on a newly released
product will perform some
statistical analysis, so
that it can determine buying trends.
And then decide whether in real-time,
a discount can be offered
to this customer now.
It turns out that the combination
of traditional requirements and
new requirements is leading
to new capabilities, and
products in the big data
management technology.
On the one hand, DBMS technologies
are creating new techniques that make
use of MapReduce-style data processing.
Many of them are being
developed to run on HDFS and
take advantage of his data
replication capabilities.
More strikingly, DBMSs are beginning
to have a side door for
a user to perform and
MR-style operation on HDFS files and
exchange data between the Hadoop
subsystem and the DBMS.
Thus, giving the user the flexibility
to use both forms of data processing.
It has now been recognized
that a simple map and
reduce operations are not sufficient for
many data operations leading to
a significant expansion in the number
of operations in the MR ecosystems.
For example,
Spark has several kinds of join and
data grouping operations in
addition to map and reduce.
Sound DBMSs are making use of large
distributed memory management
operations to accept streaming data.
These systems are designed with the idea
that the analysis they need to perform on
the data are known before.
And as new data records arrive,
they keep a record of the data
in the memory long enough to finish
the computation needed on that record.
And finally, computer scientists and
data scientists are working
towards new solutions
where large scale distributed algorithms
are beginning to emerge to solve different
kinds of analytics problems like
finding dense regions of a graph.
These algorithms use
a MR-style computing and
are becoming a part of a new
generation of DBMS products
that invoke these algorithms
from inside the database system.
In the next video, we'll take a look at
some of the modern day data management
systems that have some
of these capabilities.
As we mentioned in the last lesson, there
is no single irricuteous solution for
big data problems.
So in this lesson,
our goal will be to explore some existing
solutions in a little more depth.
So after this lesson, you'll be able to.
Explain the at least five
desirable characteristics of
a Big Data Management System,
explain the differences between acid and
base, and
list examples of BDMSs and describe some
of their similarities and differences.
So we start from high level, suppose there
were an ideal big data management system.
What capabilities or
features should such a system have?
Professor Michael Carey of
the University of California Irvine
has described a number of characteristics.
We'll go through them and
use them as an idealistic yardstick
against which we compare
existing solutions.
First, the ideal BDMS would allow for
a semi-structured data model.
Now that does not mean it will only
support a specific format like XML.
The operative word here is flexible.
The flexibility can take many forms,
one of which Is the degree to which
schemas should be supported by the system.
In a perfect world, it should support
a completely traditional application which
requires the development of a schema.
At the same time, it should also support
applications which require no schema,
because the data can vary in terms
of its attributes and relationships.
A different axis of flexibility
is in the data types it supports.
For example, it should support
operations on text and documents.
It should also permit social media and
other data that have a time component and
need temporal operations, like before,
after, during, and so on.
Similarly, it should
allow spacial data and
allow operations like find all data
within a five mile radius of a landmark.
As we saw in a previous lesson,
a big advantage of a DBMS is that
is provides a query language.
There is a notion that query languages
present a steep learning curve for
data science people with no
background in computer science.
However, to effectively
manage large volumes of data,
it's often more convenient
to use a query language and
let the query processor automatically
determine optimal ways to receive data.
Now this query language may or
may not look like SQL,
which is the standard query language used
by the modern relational systems, but
it should at least be equally powerful.
Now this is not an unreasonable feature
given that most DBMS vendors offer their
own extension of SQL Of course it's not
enough to just have a good query language.
Today's big data systems must
have a parallel query engine
which will run on multiple machines.
The machines can be connected to
a shared nothing architecture, or
shared memory architecture,
or a shared cluster.
The shared nothing means two machines
do not share a disk or memory.
But this is a critical requirement for
any BDMS regardless of how complete
the supported query languages is for
efficiency sake Continuing with our list,
the next
capability of a BDMS is often
not emphasized as much as it should be.
Some applications working on top
of a BDMS will issue queries
which will only have a few conditions and
a few small objects to return.
But some applications, especially those
generated by other software tools or
machine learning algorithms can
have many many conditions and
can return many large objects.
In my own work, we have seen how internet
bots can blast an information system
with really large queries that
can potentially choke the system.
But that should not happen in a BDMS.
Now, we discussed streaming
data in a previous lesson.
In many cases,
a BDMS will have both streaming data,
which adds to the volume,
as well as to the large data that
need to be combined with the streaming
data to solve a problem.
An example would be to combine
streaming data from weather stations
with historical data to make
better predictions for wild fire.
We have discussed the definition,
significance and
importance of scalability before.
However, what a BDMS needs to guarantee
that it is designed to operate over a
cluster, possibly a cluster of hundred or
thousand of machines and
that it knows how to handle a failure.
Further the system should be able
to handling new machines joining or
existing machines leaving the cluster.
Finally, our BDMS must have
data management capabilities.
It should be easy to install, restart and
configure, provide high availability and
make operational management as
simple as possible even when
a BDMS is declined across data centers
that are possibly geographically apart
In a prior module, we discussed
the ACID properties of transactions and
said that BDMSs guarantee them.
For big data systems,
there is too much data and
too many updates from too many users.
So the effort to maintain ACID properties
May lead to a significant
slowdown of the system.
Now, this lead to the idea, that while
the ACID properties are still desirable,
it might be more practical to relax
the ACID conditions and replace them
with what's called the BASE properties,
beginning with Basic availability.
This states that the system
does guarantee the availability
of data in the following sense.
If you make a request,
there will be a response to that request.
But, the response could still
be failure to obtain data or
the data isn't Inconsistent state or
changing state.
Well this is not unusual because
it's much like waiting for
a check to clear a bank account.
Second, there is a soft state.
Which means the state of the system
is very likely to change over time.
So even during times without input,
there may be changes going on through
the system due to eventual consistency.
Thus the state of
the system is always soft.
And finally there's eventual consistency.
This means that the system will
eventually become consistent
once it stops receiving input.
When it stops receiving input,
the data will propagate to everywhere
that it should sooner or later go to but
in reality the system will
continue to receive input.
And it's not checking the consistency
of every transaction at every moment
because there's still lots
of transactions to process.
So, if you make a new Facebook post,
your friend in Zambia, who is supposed
to see your update but is served by a very
different data center in a different
geographic region, will certainly
see it but may not see right away.
Now for those of you who have a bit
of computer science background,
we just want to mention in passing that
there is actually some theoretical results
behind this relaxation.
The result comes from what's
called the CAP Theorem.
Also named Bauer's theorem after
the computer scientist Eric Bauer.
He states, that it is impossible for
a distributed computer system
to simultaneously provide all
three of the following guarantees.
Consistency.
It means all nodes see the
same data at any time.
Availability, which is a guarantee
that every request receives a response
about whether it succeeded or failed.
And Partition Tolerance.
Which means the system
continues to operate
despite arbitrary partitioning
due to network failures.
Now, most of the big data systems
available today will adhere
to these BASE properties,
although several modern systems
do offer the stricter ACID properties,
or at least several of them.
Now given the idealistic background
of what is desirable and
achievable in a big data system,
today's marketplace for
big data related products
looks somewhat like this.
Now this is Matt Turk's depiction of big
data products from a couple of years back.
You would notice that the products
are grouped into categories, like no SQL,
massively parallel databases, analytic
systems, real time systems, and so forth.
In this lesson, we'll do a quick
tour through a few of these products
from different areas of this landscape.
In each case our goal will to be assess
what aspects of our ideal BDMS they cover,
and whether they have obvious limitations.
Now we will not cover all features
of every system, but will highlight
those aspects of the system that
are relevant to our discussion on BDMS.