In this short video we’ll
talk about how Meltwater
helped Danone using sentiment analysis.
Meltwater is a company
that helps other companies
analyze what people are saying about
them and manage their online reputation.
One of the case studies on their
website is about Danone baby nutrition.
Meltwater helped Danone to monitor
the opinions through social media for
one of their marketing campaigns.
They were able to measure what
was impactful and what was not,
through such monitoring.
Meltwater also helped Danone manage
a potential reputation issue.
When a crisis occurred
related to horse DNA
being in some meat products across Europe.
While Danone was confident that they
didn't have an issue with their products,
having the information a couple of
hours before news hit the UK press.
Allowed them to check and
reassure their customers that their
products were safe to consume.
You can imagine millions of mothers
having been reassured and happy for
Danone's efforts on this.
This is an excellent story about how
big data helped manage public opinion.
And I'm sure Meltwater was able to help
them to measure the opinion impact through
social media as well.
Big data is now being
generated all around us.
So what?
It's the applications.
It is the way in which big data can
serve human needs that makes it valued.
Let's look at a few examples of the
applications big data is allowing us to
imagine and build.
Big data allows us to build better models,
which produce higher precision results.
We are witnessing hugely innovative
approaches in how companies
market themselves and sell products.
How human resources are managed.
How disasters are responded to.
And many other applications that
evidenced based data is being
used to influence decisions.
What exactly does that mean?
Here is one example.
Many of you might have experienced it,
I do.
Data, Amazon keeps some
things I've been looking at
allows them to personalize
what they show me.
Which hopefully helps narrow down
the huge raft of options I might get
than just searching on dinner plates.
Now, businesses can leverage technology
to make better informed decisions
that are actually based on signals
generated by actual consumers, like me.
Big data enables you to hear
the voice of each consumer as
opposed to consumers at large.
Now, many companies,
including Walmart and Target,
use this information to personalize their
communications with their costumers, which
in turns leads to better met consumer
expectations and happier customers.
Which basically is to say, big data
has enabled personalized marketing.
Consumers are copiously generating
publicly accessible data through
social media sites,
like Twitter or Facebook.
Through such data, the companies
are able to see their purchase history,
what they searched for, what they watched,
where they have been, and
what they're interested in
through their likes and shares.
Let's look at some examples of how
companies are putting this information to
build better marketing campaigns and
reach the right customers.
One area we are all familiar with
are the recommendation engines.
These engines leverage user patterns and
product features
to predict best match product for
enriching the user experience.
If you ever shopped on Amazon,
you know you get recommendations
based on your purchase.
Similarly, Netflix would
recommend you to watch
new shows based on your viewing history.
Another technique that companies use is
sentiment analysis, or in simple terms,
analysis of the feelings around events and
products.
Remember the blue plates I
purchased on Amazon.com?
I not only can read the reviews
before purchasing them,
I can also write a product
review once I receive my plates.
This way, other customers can be informed.
But more importantly, Amazon can keep
a watch on the product reviews and
trends for a particular product.
In this case, blue plates.
For example, they can judge if a product
review is positive or negative.
In this case,
while the first review is negative,
the next two reviews are positive.
Since these reviews are written in
English using a technique called natural
language processing, and
other analytical methods,
Amazon can analyze the general opinion of
a person or public about such a product.
This is why sentiment analysis often
gets referred to as opinion mining.
News channels are filled with
Twitter feed analysis every time
an event of importance occurs,
such as elections.
Brands utilize sentiment analysis
to understand how customers
relate to their product,
positively, negatively, neutral.
This depends heavily on use of
natural language processing.
Mobile devices are ubiquitous and
people almost always carry
their cellphones with them.
Mobile advertising is a huge market for
businesses.
Platforms utilize the sensors
in mobile devices,
such as GPS, and
provide real time location based ads,
offer discounts,
based on this deluge of data.
This time, let's imagine that
I bought a new house and
I happen to be in a few
miles range of a Home Depot.
Sending me mobile coupons about paint,
shelves, and
other new home related purchases
would remind me of Home Depot.
There's a big chance I
would stop by Home Depot.
Bingo!
Now I would like to take a moment to
analyze what kinds of big data are needed
to make this happen.
There's definitely the integration
of my consumer information and
the online and offline databases
that include my recent purchases.
But more importantly,
the geolocation data that falls under
a larger type of big data,
spacial big data.
We will talk about spacial
data later in this class.
Let's now talk about how the global
consumer behavior can be used for
product growth.
We are now moving from
personalize marketing
to the consumer behavior as a whole.
Every business wants to understand
their consumer’s collective
behavior in order to capture
the ever-changing landscape.
Several big data products enable this
by developing models to capture user
behavior and allow businesses to target
the right audience for their product.
Or, develop new products for
uncharted territories.
Let's look at this example.
After an analysis of their sales for
weekdays,
an airline company might notice that their
morning flights are always sold out,
while their afternoon
flights run below capacity.
This company might decide to add more
morning flights based on such analysis.
Notice that they are not using
individual consumer choices, but
using all the flights purchased without
consideration to who purchased them.
They might, however,
decide to pay closer attention to
the demographic of these consumers
using big data to also add similar
flights in other geographical regions.
With rapid advances in genome
sequencing technology,
the life sciences industry is experiencing
an enormous draw in biomedical big data.
This biomedical data is being used
by many applications in research and
personalized medicine.
Did you know genomics data is one of
the largest growing big data types?
Between 100 million and 2 billion human
genomes could be sequenced by year 2025.
Impressive.
This [INAUDIBLE] sequence data demands for
between 2 exabytes and
40 exabytes in data storage.
In comparison, all of YouTube only
requires 1 to 2 exabytes a year.
An exabyte is 10 to the power 18 bites.
That is, 18 zeros after 40.
Of course, analysis of such massive
volumes of sequence data is expensive.
It could take up to 10,000
trillion CPU hours.
One of the biomedical applications
that this much data is enabling
is personalized medicine.
Before personalized medicine,
most patients without a specific type and
stage of cancer received
the same treatment,
which worked better for
some than the others.
Research in this area is enabling
development of methods to analyze
large scale data to develop solutions
that tailor to each individual,
and hence hypothesize
to be more effective.
A person with cancer may now still receive
a treatment plan that is standard,
such as surgery to remove a tumor.
However, the doctor may
also be able to recommend
some type of personalized
cancer treatment.
A big challenge in biomedical big data
applications, like many other fields,
is how we can integrate many types of data
sources to gain further insight problem.
In one of our future lectures,
my colleagues here at
the Supercomputer Center,
will explain how he and his colleague have
used big data from a variety of sources
for personalized patient interventions.
Another application of big data comes
from interconnected mesh of large
number of sensors implanted
across smart cities.
Analysis of data generated
from sensors in real time
allows cities to deliver better
service quality to inhabitants.
And reduce unwanted affect such
as pollution, traffic congestion,
higher than optimal cost on
delivering urban services.
Let's take our city, San Diego.
San Diego generates a huge volumes
of data from many sources.
Traffic sensors, satellites,
camera networks, and more.
What if we could integrate and
synthesize these data streams to
do even more for our community?
Using such big data,
we can work toward making San Diego
the prototype digital city.
Not only for life-threatening hazards, but
making our daily lives better, such as
managing traffic flow more efficiently or
maximizing energy savings,
even as we'll see next, wildfires.
If you want to read more,
here's a link to the AT Kearney report,
where they talk about other
areas using big data.
As a summary,
big data has a huge potential
to enable models with higher
precision in many application areas.
And these highly precise models
are influencing and transforming business.
Big Data Generated By People,
how is it being used?
We listed a number of challenges for
using unstructured data
generated by human activities.
Now let's look at some of the emerging
technologies to tackle these challenges.
And see some examples that turn
unstructured data into valuable insights.
Although unstructured data specially
the kind generated by people has
a number of challenges.
The good news is that the business
culture of today is shifting
to tackle these challenges and
take full advantage of such data.
As it is often said,
a challenge is a perfect opportunity.
This is certainly the case for
big data and
these challenges have created
a tech industry of it's own.
This industry is mostly centered or
as we would say, layered or
stacked, around a few fundamental
open source big data frameworks.
Need big data tools
are designed from scratch
to manage unstructured information and
analyze it.
A majority of these tools
are based on an open source
big data framework called Hadoop.
Hadoop is designed to support
the processing of large data sets
in a distributed computing environment.
This definition would already give you a
hint that it tackles the first challenge.
Namely, the volume of
unstructured information.
Hadoop can handle big batches
of distributed information but
most often there's a need for
a real time processing of people generated
data like Twitter or Facebook updates.
Financial compliance monitoring is another
area of our central time processing is
needed, in particular
to reduce market data.
Social media and market data are two
types of what we call high velocity data.
Storm and
Spark are two other open source frameworks
that handle such real time
data generated at a fast rate.
Both Storm and
Spark can integrate data with any
database or data storage technology.
As we have emphasized
before unstructured data
does not have a relational data model so
it doesn't generally
fit into the traditional data warehouse
model based on relational databases.
Data warehouses are central repositories
of integrated data from one or
more sources.
The data that gets stored in warehouses,
gets extracted from multiple sources.
It gets transformed into
a common structured form and
it can slow that into
the central database for
use by workers creating analytical
reports throughout an enterprise.
This Exact Transform Load
process is commonly called ETL.
This approach was fairly standard in
enterprise data systems until recently.
As you probably noticed,
it is fairly static and
does not fit well with today's
dynamic big data world.
So how do today's businesses
get around this problem?
Many businesses today are using a hybrid
approach in which their smaller
structured data remains in
their relational databases, and
large unstructured datasets get stored
in NoSQL databases in the cloud.
NoSQL Data technologies are based
on non-relational concepts and
provide data storage options
typically on computing clouds
beyond the traditional relational
databases centered rate houses.
The main advantage of using
NoSQL solutions is their ability
to organize the data for
scalable access to fit the problem and
objectives pertaining to
how the data will be used.
For example, if the data will be used
in an analysis to find connections
between data sets, then the best
solution is a graph database.
Neo4j is an example of a graph database.
Graph networks is a topic that
the graph analytics course
later in this specialization,
we'll explain in depth.
If the data will be best accessed using
key value pairs like a search engine
scenario, the best solution is probably
a dedicated key value paired database.
Cassandra is an example
of a key value database.
These, and
many other types of NoSQL systems will
be explained further in course two.
So we are now confident that there
are emerging technologies for
individual challenges to manage
people generated unstructured data.
But how does one take advantage
of these to generate value?
As we saw big data must pass through a
series of steps before it generates value.
Namely data access, storage,
cleaning, and analysis.
One approach to solve this problem is
to run each stage as a different layer.
And use tools available to
fit the problem at hand, and
scale analytical solutions to big data.
In coming lectures, we will see
important tools that you can use
to solve your big data problems in
addition to the ones you have seen today.
Now let's take a step back and remind
ourselves what some of the value was.
Remember how companies can listen to the
real voice of customers using big data?
It is this type of generated
data that enabled it.
Sentiment analysis analyzes social
media and other data to find
whether people associate positively or
negatively with you business.
Organizations are utilizing
processing of personal data to
understand the true
preferences of their customers.
Now let's take a fun quiz to guess how
much Twitter data companies analyze
every day to measure sentiment
around their product.
The answer is 12 terabytes a day.
For comparison,
you would need to listen continuously for
two years to finish listening
to 1 terabyte of music.
Another example application area for
people generated data is customer
behavior modeling and prediction.
Amazon, Netflix and
a lot of other organizations,
use analytics to analyze
preferences of their customers.
Based on consumer behavior, organizations
suggest better products to customers,
and in turn have happier customers and
higher profits.
Another application area where the value
comes in the form of societal impact and
social welfare, is disaster management.
As you have seen in my wildfire example,
there are many types of big data that
can help with disaster response.
Data in the form of pictures and
tweets, helps facilitate
a collective response to disaster
situations, such as evacuations through
the safest route based on community
feedback through social media.
There are also networks that
turn crowd sourcing and
big data analytics into collective
disaster response tools.
The International Network
of Crisis Mappers,
also called Crisis Mappers Net,
is the largest of such networks and
includes an active international
community of volunteers.
Crisis Mappers use big data in the form
of aerial and satellite imagery,
participatory maps and
live Twitter updates to analyze
the data using geospatial platforms,
advanced visualization,
live simulation and computational and
statistical models.
Once analyzed the results get reported to
rapid response and humanitarian agencies
in the form of mobile and
web applications.
In 2015, right after the Nepal earthquake
Crises Mappers crowd source the analysis
of tweets and mainstream media to
rapidly access disaster damage and
needs and to identify where
humanitarian help is needed.
This example is amazing and shows how
big data can have huge impacts for
social welfare in times of need.
You can learn more about this
story at the following link.
As a summary, although there are
challenges in working with unstructured
people generated data at a scale and
speed that applications demand.
There are also emerging technologies and
solutions that are being
used by many applications to generate
value from the rich source of information.
Big Data Generated By People,
The Unstructured Challenge.
People are generating massive amounts of
data every day through their activities on
various social media networking sites
like Facebook, Twitter, and LinkedIn.
Or online photo sharing sites like
Instagram, Flickr, or Picasa.
And video sharing websites like YouTube.
In addition an enormous amount of
information gets generated via
blogging and commenting,
internet searches, more via text messages,
email, and through personal documents.
Most of this data is text-heavy and
unstructured,
that is non-conforming to
a well-defined data model.
We can also consider this
data to be content with
occasionally some
description attached to it.
This much activity Leads
to a huge growth in data.
Did you know that in a single day,
Facebook users produce
more data than combined US
academic research libraries?
Let's look at some similar
daily data volume numbers
from some of the biggest online platforms.
It is amazing that some of these
numbers are in the petabyte range for
daily activity.
A petabyte is a thousand terabytes.
The sheer size of mostly unstructured
data generated by humans
brings a lot of challenges.
Unstructured data refers to data that does
not conform to a predefined data model.
So no relation model and no SQL.
It is mostly anything that we
don't store in a traditional
Relational database management system.
Consider a sales receipt that
you get from a grocery store.
It has a section for a date, a section for
store name, and
a section for total amount.
This is an example of structure.
Humans generate a lot of
unstructured data in form of text.
There's no given format to that.
Look at all the documents that you
have written with your hand so far.
Collectively, it is a bank of unstructured
data you have personally generated.
In fact, 80 to 90% of all data in
the world is unstructured and
this number is rapidly growing.
Examples of unstructured data generated
by people includes texts, images,
videos, audio,
internet searches, and emails.
In addition to it's rapid growth
major challenges of unstructured data
include multiple data formats,
like webpages, images, PDFs,
power point, XML, and other formats that
were mainly built for human consumption.
Think of it, although I can sort my
email with date, sender and subject.
It would be really difficult
to write a program,
to categorize all my email messages
based on their content and
organize them for me accordingly another
challenge of human generated data
is the volume and fast generation of data,
which is what we call velocity.
Just take a moment to study this info
graphic, and observe what happens in one
minute on the internet, and
consider how much to contribute to it.
Moreover, confirmation of unstructured
data is often time consuming and costly.
The costs and
time of the process of acquiring, storing,
cleaning, retrieving, and processing
unstructured data can add up to quite and
investment before we can start
reaping value from this process.
It can be pretty hard
to find the tools and
people to implement such a process and
reap value in the end.
As a summary,
although there is an enormous amount of
data generated by people,
most of this data is unstructured.
The challenges of working with
unstructured data should not
be taken lightly.
Next, we'll look at how businesses are
tackling these challenges to gain insight.
And thus, value out of working
with people generated data.
As we have already seen, there are many
different exciting applications
that are being enabled
by the Big Data era.
As part of my core research here at
the San Diego Supercomputer Center,
I work on building methodologies and
tools to make Big Data useful to dynamic
data driven scientific applications.
My colleagues and I work on many grand
challenge data science applications,
in all areas of science and engineering,
including genomics, geoinformatics,
metro science, energy management,
biomedicine, and personalized health.
What is common to all these applications
is their unique way of bringing
together new modes of data and
computing research.
Let me tell you the one I'm passionate
about, Wildfire Analytics,
which breaks up into two components,
prediction and response.
Why is this so important?
On May 2014, in San Diego County where
the instructors of this
specialization live and work,
there were 14 fires burning,
as many as nine at one time,
which burned a total of 26,000 acres,
11,000 hectares,
an area just less than the size
of the City of San Francisco.
Six people were injured and
one person died.
And these wildfires
resulted in a total cost of
over $60 million US in damage and
firefighting.
These wildfires can become so severe
that we actually call them firestorms.
Although we cannot
control such fire storms,
something we can do is to get ahead
of them by predicting their behavior.
This is why disaster management
of ongoing wildfires relies
heavily on understanding their
direction and rate of spread.
As these fires are a part of our lives,
we wanted to see if we can use Big Data to
monitor, predict and manage a firestorm.
Why can Big Data help?
As we will see in this video,
indeed, wildfire prevention and
response can benefit from many
streams in our data torrent.
Some streams are generated by
people through devices they carry.
A lot come from sensors and satellites,
things that measure environmental factors.
And some come from organizational data,
including area maps,
better service updates and field content
databases, which archive how much
registers vegetation and other types of
fuel are in the way of a potential fire.
What makes this a Big Data problem?
Because novel approaches and
responses can be taken if
we can integrate this many
diverse data streams.
Many such data sources have already
existed for quite some time.
But what is lacking in disaster
management today is a dynamic system
integration of real time sensor networks,
satellite imagery,
near real time data management tools,
wildfire simulation tools,
connectivity to emergency command centers,
and
all these before, during,
and after a firestorm.
As you will see,
the integration of diverse streams and
novel ways is really what's driving
our ability to see new things and
develop predictive analytics,
which may help improve our world.
What are these diverse sources?
One of the most important data sources
is sensor data streaming in from weather
stations and satellites,
such sensed data include temperature,
humidity, air pressure.
We can also include image
data streaming from
mountaintop cameras and
satellites in this category.
Another important data source
comes from institutions
such as
the San Diego Supercomputer Center,
which generate data related
to wildfire modeling.
These include past and current fire
perimeter maps put together by
the authorities and fuel maps that
tell us about the vegetation,
and other types of fuel in a fire's path.
These types of data sources are often
static or updated at a slow rate,
but they provide valuable data
that is well-curated and verified.
A huge part of data on fires is
actually generated by the public
on social media sites such as Twitter,
which support photo sharing resources.
These are the hardest data sources to
streamline during an existing fire, but
they can be very valuable once
integrated with other data sources.
Imagine synthesizing all the pictures
on Twitter about an ongoing fire or
checking the public sentiment
around the boundaries of a fire.
Once you have access to such
information at your fingertips,
there are many things you
can do with such data.
You can simply monitor it, or
maybe you can visualize it.
But it's not until you bring all these
different types of data sources together
and integrate them with real time analysis
and predictive modeling that you can
really make contributions in predicting
and responding to wildfire emergencies.
So now,
I will like you to take a moment and
imagine how Big Data might help
with firefighting in the future.
All these streams of data will come
together in 3D displays that can show
all the related information along
with weather and fire predictions,
just like the way tornadoes
are managed today.