In this video we will explore
another fundamental property
of graphs called Connectivity.
We list two important kinds
of graph analytic questions
that are based on connectivity.
In the first case we are asking
about the robustness of the network.
Suppose we have a computer
network with many servers and
a hacker is trying to
bring the system down,
you set a small set of servers that the
hacker can target to disrupt the network.
What we mean by disrupt is to disconnect
a part of the network from the rest.
A similar problem may occur in
the power distribution network.
In that case, an attacker may be able to
attack one or two central components so
that large portions of
the network loses power.
I have a geneticist colleague at
Tech Graduate Institute who studied
the robustness of biological networks.
He told me that many biological
networks have built in redundancy, so
that even if you disrupt one important
gene, there are other genes in the network
which will support the biological
function, possibly through other routes.
Therefore a network is robust,
if removing one or
more edges or
nodes still keeps it connected.
The second category is about network
comparison in terms of their
overall connectivity.
The two graphs shown here are very
different in their structure.
What are some parameters by
which we can compare them?
That to talk about connectivity, we must
first define the concept of connectivity.
Very simple.
A graph is connected if we can
reach any node from any other node.
Let's look at the crypto graph in
the picture, clearly we cannot
reach from all nodes to all nodes here
because this graph is not connected.
However, we can identify four parts of
the graph that are themselves connected.
These islands of connected
parts are called components or
connected components of a graph.
For directed graphs, we need to be
a little more specific about connectivity.
We say that the directed graph is strongly
connected, if we follow the direction of
the edges and still reach every
node from every other node.
A weaker form of connectivity is if we do
not care about the direction of the arrows
and can reach every node
from every other node.
Another way of saying it is that
the undirected version of the graph
is connected,
this is called Weak Connected.
Look at the graph that we have seen so
many times in this course.
Is it strongly connected or
weakly connected?
This leads to some big graph challenge.
Given an arbitrarily large graph,
can I find the connected components
of the graph efficiently?
Second given an arbitrarily large graph,
can we find its sub graphs
that are strongly connected?
We'll touch upon these
questions in Module Four.
So there are two ways to break a graph.
Identifying the smallest node set which
if removed will disconnect the graph.
Here, if we remove F, D and
H or H, F, G,
we have disconnected the graph.
So the separating set is either H,
F and G, or H, F and D.
So the connectivity is three.
Similarly, removing C-F, D-G, D-F and
H-E edges will also disconnect the graph.
Therefore, the edge connectivity is four.
So this is how network
robustness is defined.
Now, let's ask, is this network robust?
Suppose the attacker removed node F.
Why remove F?
Because F is the most connected node.
That is, F has the highest degree.
If we remove F, five paths are disrupted.
For example,
there is no way to go from C to G, or
from I to E,
because these paths went through F.
Let's try this exercise.
Suppose the attacker
has already removed F.
And would like to cause more
damage to the rest of the network.
Which node should be targeted next?
The answer is C,
because C is the next most connected node.
Higher degree nodes make
the network more vulnerable.
So far, the centrality of a node
is defined using the degree and
the shortest distance to other nodes.
Now, we introduce a different idea.
We would like to say that
if you are important and
I'm connected to you,
then I must be somewhat important too.
In other words, my centrality
is proportional to the combined
centrality values of my neighbors.
Now, if we write that down mathematically
it would look like the top formula.
The centrality of (Vi) is
the sum of its neighbors.
Now, we can write that as an equation
where Lambda is
a proportionality constant.
The resulting equation looks exactly
like the Eigenvector equation we have
seen before.
Now again, you really do not
have to understand how it works.
It's fine to know that if
we solve that equation,
we will get the Eigen values lambda.
Now, let's take the largest lambda and
find the corresponding Eigenvector, which
will give you the centrality of each note.
Notice the difference between
the degree centrality and
the Eigenvector centrality
in the same graph.
The yellow node in the middle
has a low degree centrality
compared to its neighbors.
However, with the Eigenvector centrality,
the node becomes comparably more important
because the neighbor centrality status
boost some of the centrality of this node.
In contrast,
consider the second highlighted note.
It had the same on normalize degree
centrality as the previous node.
But because the neighbors
are low centrality nodes,
the eigenvector centrality goes down.
So, this is the intended consequence
of the eigenvector centrality measure.
Speaking of consequences,
Eigenvector centrality essentially says
if you know the right people,
your importance will go up.
Well, that's kind of risky proposition.
Here is me in a social network,
and let's say I'm connected to
this somewhat dubious character, and
I think it doesn't really matter.
What I don't know is that my connection
has it's own set of connections, and
look at who they are.
So, on the one hand, these shady
characters that are now connected to
indirectly does raise my
eigenvector centrality, but
it also has quite a damaging
effect on my reputation.
My EV centrality almost makes
me look like a suspect.
Now, think about that.
Now Brin and Page, the founders of Google
had an interesting way to think
about the eigenvector centrality.
They thought about a server.
Well no, not that kind of server.
This kind of server.
The kind that surfs the web.
But, this is a special web
surfer called a random surfer.
And here is what he does, he picks
a web page and looks at the links.
Then he chooses a random link, goes to
that page and does the same thing again.
Except sometimes when you kind of get
bored and goes to totally new page.
How often does he do this random jump?
Let's say, there's always sort
of a 15% chance that he will.
Or more generally,
with the probability of 1 minus alpha.
So, Page and Brin's idea was to figure out
that this surfer will visit a page with
a high chance, if the page is central.
They came up with a measure for
this stationary probability of a page
being visited by the random surfer.
They did not call it centrality,
they called it pagerank.
Let's see a YouTube video to
understand how pagerank behaves.
Okay, now we are talking about
the World Wide Web which is a huge graph.
How do we of such a graph?
The answer is iteratively using
a method called power iteration.
This method can be used because we
are looking for the largest eigenvalue.
Let me show you.
Let's take a small graph.
Let's initialize the still unknown
page rank as zero for all nodes.
Now, page rank A is a 0.15 chance,
that I was at A already.
And 0.85 chance that I come to A from B,
or I come to A from C.
However, at this point,
the page rank of B and C are at zero.
So, in the first iteration,
page rank of A is 0.15.
Now for B, I can only come to B from A,
but we cannot claim all of pagerank of A,
because there is always a half chance
that the surfer will come to B
from A because he could
also get to here from C.
This, plus the 0.15 chance that
the surfer is already at B,
makes Bs pagerank 0.21.
Now after doing a few rounds of this
computation, between 50 and 100 iteration,
let's say.
The values will converge.
Now, this computation has been
demonstrated to perform well
in the MapReduce framework.
In module four, we'll talk about
another way of computing this metric.
Welcome back to the second
module of the course.
In this module, we will cover
a number of basic principles and
techniques of graph analytics.
As we mentioned in the last module,
the goal of graph analytics
is to utilize the mathematical
properties of data and provide
efficient algorithmic solutions for large
and complex graph structure problems.
As I said, in this module, we'll learn a
number of basic graph analytic techniques.
After this module,
you'll be able to identify the right
class of techniques to apply for
a graph analytics problem.
To be more specific,
in this module we will consider
the mathematical and
algorithmic aspects, and not so
much the computing frameworks
to implement these methods.
In Modules 3 and 4, we will look at
two different kinds of computing
platforms that are used for implementing
the techniques discussed in this module.
Here is the lesson plan for the module.
First, we'll discuss a few basic terms and
their definition which we'll use for
the rest of the course.
Of course, they are not the only terms and
concepts we will learn.
As we go through each technique,
we will add more terms and
definitions in our vocabulary.
Now following these definitions we
will consider four categories of
graph analytic procedures.
The first, called Path Analytics,
is centered around the Analytic Techniques
where the primary objective involves
traversing to the nodes and
edges of the ground.
The second analytic technique inquires and
explores the connectivity
pattern of the gaps.
Where the term connectivity pattern
refers to the structure and
organizations of the edges of the graph.
The third analytics category
involves the discovery and
behavior of communities which are closely
interacting entities in a network.
The fourth category, termed Centrality
Analytics, detects and characterizes
significant nodes of a network with
respect to a specific analysis problem.
Of course there are many more types of
graph analytic techniques that we'll cover
in the course.
We'll provide some additional reading
material for those who are interested.
But we start by recapitulating
our definition of graphs
as a collection of vertices and edges,
which represent ordered pairs of nodes.
While this mathematical
definition is indeed correct,
in practice it needs to be extended to
give you other information elements.
Let us consider a single Tweet.
As we have mentioned previously,
a Tweet is a complex information output
because it is a graph in itself
with several nodes and edges.
But over and about the structure, a Tweet
actually contains much more information
and code inside the nodes and edges.
First, there several kinds
of nodes in a Tweet.
For example it has a Tweet node,
a User node, a Media node,
a URL node, a hashtag node and so forth.
This assignment of kinds or labels to
nodes is often called node typing.
Every graph application will
have its own set of types.
And it'll assign one or more types to
a node but it is not mandatory for
an application to use node types.
Mathematically we can extend our original
definition with two more elements.
The set of node types and the mapping
function that assigns types to nodes.
That means it associates
a type to every node.
However, not all nodes need to have
a type but in many applications they do.
In addition to types,
a node also has attributes and values.
In our Tweet example,
text is the name of an attribute that
refers to the textual body of the Tweet
whose value is a character string
written by the author of the Tweet.
For a specific kind of data like a Tweet,
one has a fixed set of attributes
as decided by Twitter.
This collection of attributes
is called a node schema.
For a general graph,
a node schema may have an arbitrary
number of attribute value pairs.
We will revisit this in module 3
when we discuss graphing the models.
Similarly, at edge of a graph, we have
an edge type, also called an edge label.
Also just like a node,
an edge may have an edge schema
consisting of attribute value pierce.
Here, Interaction Type is
an attribute in our biological
network that describes the modality of
interaction between a pair of genes.
For the specific edge we have highlighted,
the genes interact through
biochemical activity.
Because they are party to
some biochemical process.
Clearly, there are different kinds
of interaction between these
genes or proteins.
That means an attribute called
interaction type can have a set of
possible values like physical,
genetic and so on.
This set of possible values is
called the domain of the attribute.
Putting these elements back
into our mathematical model,
we get a more concrete specification of
what a real live graph would contain.
We have already discussed edge types
as well as node and edge properties.
Take a minute to look through this again.
Whenever you consider an application that
needs graph analytics, the first task
should be to determine the informational
model of the graph your application needs.
It's always a good exercise to
document the information model,
in terms of the elements
described on the slide.
Let's see a little more on
the topic of edge properties.
Many application encode different
kids of numeric knowledge
into edges of a graph in
the form of edge points.
If we do not put weights
in an adjacency metrics,
an edge is just represented by
placing a one in the appropriate cell.
However, if we do use a weight,
the weight value can be placed in
the adjacency matrix to facilitate
down stream computation as
we'll show in the next lesson.
What do the weights mean?
That depends on the application.
Let's see some examples.
The most obvious example is a road map
where the nodes are road intersections and
the edges represent
stretches of the street or
highway between these intersections.
The edge weight can represent the distance
of a particular segment of the road.
In a personal communication network,
for example an email network,
we can count the average number of emails
per week sent from John to Jill and
use it as a proxy for
the strength of their connection.
So more emails means
a stronger connection.
In a biological network, one often has
to assess whether an interaction that
can occur is actually likely to occur
given the concentration of the reactants,
the chemical environment at the site
of the reaction and so forth.
This is represented as a weight that
designates the likelihood of interaction.
Finally, consider a knowledge network
where nodes represent entities
like people, places and events.
And edges represent relationships
like a person visited a place or
movie actor Tom is dating
movie actress Kim.
Now this kind of information may
be important for some news media.
However, if the information does
not come from an authentic source,
itself, it is more prudent to
put a certainty value on it.
This certainty value may be
treated as a weight on the edge.
Moving on from the information
model of the graph,
the structure of the graph often
contains valuable insights to a graph.
Many of the graph analytic techniques
we will discuss in this section
will consider these structural
properties of graphs.
One such structure is a loop,
which is an edge from a node to itself.
In the example here,
you can see that a protein can interact
with another protein of the same kind.
Many other examples abound.
People send emails to themselves.
A road segment circles back
to the same intersection.
A website has a link to its own URL.
The existence of loops and the nodes that
have such loops can be very informative
in some applications and
can be problematic for other applications.
Another structure property of a graph
is the occurrence of multiple
edges between the same node pair.
The graphs with this feature
are called multi-graphs.
In this example, the two map kinase
genes have five edges between them.
Why multiple edges?
It's because each edge has
a different information content.
In this case,
these two genes can have five different
types of interactions between them.
Where each interaction has a different
value for the attribute interaction type.
We see this all the time
in human networks too.
A person can be my spouse,
a co-performer in music and
my financial adviser,
all at the same time.
Many analytics algorithms
are not natively designed for
multigraphs, and often need a little
customization to handle them.
We will mention some of these
customizations as we go forward and walk
through the different kinds of analytics
applications preformed on graphs.
So we talked about local properties.
In this lecture,
we'll cover a global property based
method of [INAUDIBLE] finding.
The specific property we focus on,
is called modularity.
It tries to estimate
the quality of clusters of
communities in the [INAUDIBLE].
The intuition is as follows.
If we consider the edges in a group and
try to see whether it's different
from what you'd see if the edges
were assigned randomly with
some probability distribution.
If there is a community, there will be
more edges than would happen at random.
If there is no community in some part
of the graph, the number of edges in
that part will either be close to
the random case or even lower than that.
The modularity measure thus estimates
the quality of the clusters in
the graph by evaluating this difference of
the actual minus the random edge fraction.
So this is the mathematical
formulation of what I just described.
The adjacency matrix, A,
gives us the actual edges.
The Pij provides a probability
of a random edge.
The m in the denominator gives
us the fractional edges.
And the delta function's
task is to evaluate if i and
j should be in the same cluster.
If they are,
the contribution will be added to Q,
the quality metric,
which is multi-layered.
Well, we have not defined what
the probability model looks like.
There are many ways to figure
out what Pij should look like.
One simple model says, that the chance
that there is an edge between nodes i and
j, is proportional to the degree of
node i times the degree of node j.
That means if nodes i and
j are already well connected, there is
a high chance that they share an edge.
So if you're a mathematical person,
you might be thinking, okay,
let's find clusters in the graph so
that Q is maximum and then we're done.
Well sadly, maximizing Q is very hard.
So we need to find
an approximate solution.
So we will illustrate a very
popular method of finding this
modularity based community detection.
Well, the best way to describe
this is through a YouTube video.
That's the URL.
Now, the next slide and
the following slide,
describes it, but
I think it's better to explain the method
through screenshots off
the video as it happens.
We will show you some
snapshots of this video.
There are 309 nodes in this graph.
Initially, they all have different colors.
That is,
they belong to different communities.
This screenshot shows the graph at
iteration 144 of the algorithm.
The number of communities now is 286.
The chart on the right side plots time on
the x-axis and modularity on the y-axis.
As you see,
the modularity's on the rights.
Roughly, at each iteration,
the system is trying to change the color
of a node to that of its neighbors.
But it actually changes the color
only if the modularity value of
the whole graph changes as
a result of that color change.
After a few more iterations,
the number of communities has become 241.
The three arrows show some parts of the
graph where the nodes have changed colors.
Modularity is on the rise.
After 1,437 iterations, the modularity
of the graph is still going up.
Now, there are 113 communities.
The errors show some new areas where
the neighboring nodes have the same color.
At 1,842 iterations,
the modulary gains slows down.
Meanwhile, the number of
communities have reduced to 75.
At 4,179 iterations, the modularity
growth has started becoming flat.
But in the meantime, the number of colors,
that is communities, has reduced to 48.
At around 5,196 iterations, the algorithm
decides that there is not enough
reduction in the number of communities,
which is reduced to only 45 in
the last 1,000 iterations or so.
Now it collapses each community that
is clustered to a single node, and
creates a cluster to cluster edges.
The orange box,
an arrow shows this contraction.
Now compared to the previous slide,
this collapsing or
contraction of the plastic creates
a skeleton of the original draft.
Now the algorithm starts again
with this reduced graph.
You will find many graph
analysis software,
where you can run the Louvain
method of community detection.
[INAUDIBLE].
I took my Linked-in network,
which has me at the center, and
all my connections as nodes.
If two of my contacts are also
connected in Linked-in,
there is an edge between them.
This kind of mean-centric network
is often called an ego network.
When I [INAUDIBLE] the community direction
algorithm here, I found six communities,
with one set of parameters and
seven communities with another.
I could clearly see my
connections in San Diego.
My connections in my professional network,
my friends in India, and so forth.
There's always one false community,
which stands for
others, nodes that do not clearly
belong to any specific group.
Perhaps more interesting and
important than the static
analysis of communities is to track
communities over a length of time.
And determine how they evolve and why.
There are six large
categories of evolution steps
that can happen within a community.
A community like a new
Facebook group can be born.
A community, like a group of
people who gathered for an event,
would dissolve because the event and
the mutual interest around it has ended.
A community can grow because the members
rally around a common cause.
Typically, new cross-community
edges start getting
formed before the communities
actually merge.
The communities can
shrink like my book club.
Where do you see this in real life?
Well, how about company mergers?
Surely enough, the [INAUDIBLE] results
will happen when a community splits.
Going along with the previous example,
a closely working group in a company may
at some point create their own product and
form a new company with very
little ties to the old company.
One standard symptom of a group splitting
is that the nodes in the subgroup
show an increase in the number of
edges just amongst themselves.