Next, we'll look at a data model
that has been successfully used to
retrieve data from large
collections of text and images.
Let's stay with text for now.
Text is often thought of
as unstructured data.
Primarily because it doesn't really
have attributes and relationships.
Instead, it is a sequence of strings
punctuated by line and parent of breaks.
So one is to think of a different
way to find and analyze text data.
In this video, we'll describe that
finding text from a huge collection of
text data is a little different from
the data modules we have seen so far.
To find text,
we not only need the text data itself, but
we need a different structure that
is computed from the text data.
To create the structure,
we'll introduce the notion of the document
vector model which we call a vector model.
Further you will see
that finding a document
is not really an exact search problem.
Here, we'll give a query document and
ask the system to find all
documents that are similar to it.
After this video,
you'll be able to describe
how the similarity is computed and
how it is used to search documents.
Finally, you will see that search engines
use some form of vector models and
similarity search to locate text data.
And you will see that the same principle
can be use for finding similar images.
Let us describe the concept
of a document to an example.
So lets consider three types
of document shown here.
Now we'll create a matrix.
The rows of the matrix stand for
the documents and columns represent
the words in the documents.
We put the number of occurrences
of returning the document in
the appropriate cell of the matrix.
In this case, the count of each term
in each document happens to be one.
This is called the term frequency matrix.
So now that we have created
the term frequency matrix,
which we call tf for short.
We'll create a new vector called the
inverse document frequency for each term.
We'll explain why we need this
vector on the next slide.
First, let's see how it's computed.
The number of documents n here is 3.
The term new occurs
twice in the collection.
So the inverse document frequency or
IDF of the term new
is log to the base 2,
n divided by term count.
That is, log to the base 2,
3 divided by 2, which is 0.584.
We'll show the ideal score for
all six terms here.
Now some of you may wonder why we use
log to the base 2 instead of let's
say log to the base 10.
There is no deep scientific reason for it.
It's more of a convention in
many areas of Computer Science
when many important
numbers are powers of two.
In reality,
log to the base two of x is the same
number as log to the base ten of x
times log to the base two of ten.
The second number, that is log to
the base two of ten is a constant.
So the relative score of IDF does not
change regardless of the base we use.
Now let's understand this
number one more time.
The document frequency of a term is
the count of that term in the whole
collection divided by
the number of documents.
Here, we take the inverse of
the document frequency, so
that n, the number of documents,
is in the numerator.
Now before we continue, let's understand
the intuition behind the IDF vector.
Now suppose you have 100
random newspaper articles and
let's say 10 of them cover elections.
Which means all the others
cover all other subjects.
Now in this article, let's say we'll find
the term election 50 times in total.
How often do you think you'll find
the term is as in the verb is?
You can imagine that it will
occur in all hundred of them and
that too, multiple times.
We can safely assume that
the number of occurrences of is
will be 300 at the very least.
Thus the document frequency of is is six
times the document frequency of election.
But that doesn't sound right, does it?
Is is such a common word that it's
prevalence has a negative impact
on its informativeness.
So, now if you want to
compute the IDF of is and
election, the IDF of is will be far lower.
So, IDF acts like a penalty factor for
terms which are too widely used
to be considered informative.
Now that we have understood
that IDF is a penalty factor,
we will multiply the tf numbers through
the IDF numbers giving us this.
This is a column-wise multiplication
of the tf numbers with the IDF
numbers giving us what we
call the tf-idf matrix.
Therefore for each document, we have
a vector represented here as a row.
So that row represents the relative
importance of each term in the vocabulary.
Vocabulary means the collection of all
words that appear in this collection.
If the vocabulary has 3 million entries,
then this vector can get quite long.
Also, if the number of document
grows let's just say to 1 billion,
then it becomes a big data problem.
Now the last column after
each document of vector here
is the length of the document vector.
Which is really the square root of the sum
of squares of the individual term scores
as shown in the formula.
To perform a search in the vector space,
we write a query just like
we type terms in Google.
Here, the number of terms is three.
Out of which the term
new appears two times.
In fact, this is the maximum frequency
out of all terms in the query.
So we take the document vector of
the query and multiply each term
by the number of occurrences divided by
two which is the maximum term frequency.
Now in this case,
it gives us two non-zero terms.
0.584 and
0.292 for new and york.
Then we compute the length of
the query vector just like we did for
the document vectors
on the previous slide.
Next, we will compute the similarity
between the query vector and each document
with the idea that we'll measure how far
the query vector is from each document.
Now there are many similar functions
defined and used for different things.
A popular similarity measure
is the cosine function,
which measures the cosine function of
the angle between these two vectors.
The mathematical formula for
computing the function is given here.
The intuition is that if
the vectors are identical,
then the angle between them is zero.
And therefore,
the cosine function evaluates to one.
As the angle increases,
the value of the cosine function
decreases to make them more dissimilar.
The way to compute the function is to
multiply the corresponding elements of
the two vectors.
That is the first element
of one with the first
element of the second one and so forth.
And then sum of these products.
Here, the only contributing
terms are from new and
york because, these are the only two
non-zero terms in the query vector.
This sum is then divided by
the product of the document length and
the query length that we
have computed earlier.
Look at the result of the distance
function and you will notice that
the document 1 is much more similar
to the query than the other two.
So while similarity scoring and document
ranking process working effectively,
the method is a little cotton dry.
More often than not users would
like a little more control
over the ranking of terms.
One way of accomplishing this is to put
different weights on each query term.
And in this example, the query term
york has a default weight of one,
times has a weight of two.
And post has a weight of five
as specified by the user.
So relatively speaking,
york has a weight of 1 divided
by 1 + 5 + 2 is equal to 0.125.
Times has a weight of 0.25 and
post has a weight of 0.625.
Now the scoring method we showed
before will change a bit.
The query of vector and its length
were exactly as computed before.
However, now each term in the query
vector is further multiplied by these
relative weights.
In our case,
the term york now has a much higher rate.
So as expected, this will change
the ranking of the documents and
new york post will have the highest rank.
Now similarity search is often used for
images using a vector space model.
One can compute futures from images.
And one common feature
is a scatter histogram.
Consider the image here.
One can create the histogram of the red,
green and
blue channels where histogram is the count
of pixels having a certain density value.
This picture is mostly bright, so the
count of dark pixels is relatively small.
Now one can think of
histograms like a vector.
Very often the pixel values will
be bend before creating a vector.
The table shown is a feature vector
where the numbers for each row have been
normalized with the size of the image
to make the row sum equal to one.
Similar vectors can be computed of
the image texture, shapes of objects and
any other properties.
Thus making a vector space model
significant for unstructured data.
In our experience as educators
we have observed that
learners often make the assumption
that the format of the data
is the same as the logical model of the
data in the way that you operate on it.
The goal of this very
short lecture is to ensure
that we can clearly
distinguish between the two.
So, after watching this video you will be
able to explain the difference between
format, which is a serialized
representation of the data, as opposed to
data model which we have discussed
at length in the previous months.
Perhaps the simplest example of a data
format is a csv file, so here is
a snippet of a csv file from the global
terrorism database we discussed earlier.
We know that CSV or
common separative values means
that the term between two commas
is the value of an attribute.
But what is this value?
The common notion is that it's
a content of a single relation
where each line is a record
that's a tuple and
the iod value in the CSV corresponds
to the iod attribute as shown here.
Now that might very well be true but
let's look at a different example.
Let's say this snippet
here is my CSV file.
There is no difference between
the previous file and this one.
However, here is how I
like to see the data.
As you can see this is a graph,
and the data model is the same
although the format is still CSV.
This is the second hands on exercise for
sensor data.
In the first we looked at
static data in a text file.
In this one we'll be looking at
real-time streaming measurements.
First, we will open a terminal window, and
cd into the directory containing
the data and the scripts.
Next we'll connect to
the weather station and
look at the real-time
data as it streams in.
After that, we will look at the key to
remind ourselves what the fields mean.
And finally, we will plot the data
streaming from the weather station.
Let's begin.
First, open a terminal window,
by clicking on the terminal icon.
Top of the toolbar.
[NOISE] Let's run cd
Downloads/big-data-2/sensor.
You can run ls to see
the name of the scripts.
Let's run stream-data.py
to see the real-time data.
This shows us the real-time measurements
coming from the weather station.
By looking at the time stamps,
we can see that each measurement arrives
about one second after the previous one.
Additionally, we can see
that R1 comes fairly often,
whereas other measurements,
such as R2, are not as often.
We can open another terminal and
look at the key to remind ourselves
what these measurements mean.
The key is in wxt-520-format.txt.
We could run more
wxt-520-format.txt to view it.
If we go back to our live data,
we can see that the 19th
measurement here says Ta
was 22.5 degrees Celsius.
And look up here,
see that Ta is the air temperature.
The next measure we can see
that Dn was equal to 255D.
According to our key,
Dn is the wind direction minimum, and
the units are degrees.
We can also plot specific measurements
streaming live from the weather station.
Let's plot the wind speed average.
If we look at our key,
we see that the wind speed average is Sm.
So we can plot this by running
stream-plot-data.py sm.
This plots the data as the weather
station sends it to us.
If we look at the x-axis,
we can see that one measurement
comes in about every second.
We can plot other measurements by
choosing different fields from the key.
For example, we can plot the air pressure
by running stream-plot-data.py Pa.
Since Pa is the air pressure.
First thing we notice is that there's
only one measurement so far in the graph.
This means that the air pressure
measurements are not coming as
fast as the wind measurements.
In fact, we only got one.
In this hands-on activity,
we'll be looking at real time
data streaming from Twitter.
First, we'll open a terminal window and
cd into the directory containing
Python scripts to access this data.
Next, we'll look at the contents
of tweets streaming from Twitter
containing specific words.
Finally, we will plot the frequency
of these streaming tweets.
Let's begin.
First, click on the terminal
icon at the top of the toolbar.
Let cd into the directory containing
the python scripts to access the real time
data from Twitter.
We'll run CD downloads big-data-2 json.
We can run ls to see
the files in this directory.
The file auth should be created containing
your Twitter authentication information.
You could see the separate reading for
how to setup the Twitter app and
how to create this file.
Next, let's run the script live tweets
to view tweets in real time containing
a specific word.
Let's run LiveTweets.py president.
This will show the real time tweets
containing the word president.
[INAUDIBLE] Runs, in the first column,
you can see the time stamp of the tweet.
In the second column,
you can see the text.
When you're done, hit Ctrl + C.
Let's run LiveTweet again using
a different keyword that appear more
frequently.
Let's use the word time,
we'll run LiveTweet time
When we're done, hit Ctrl + C.
We can plot the frequency of these Tweets
by running the script plot Tweets.
Let's run plot, tweet, president to see
the frequency for the word president.
As this runs, we could see
the frequency changes over time.
I can see that the maximum was one.
And a few times,
there were just one tweet in that second.
When you're done looking at the graph,
click in the terminal window and
hit Enter.
Now, let's plot the frequency for
the word time.
Run PlotTweets.py time.
This plot shows that the word time appears
a lot more frequently than president.
We can see spikes in the frequency
of 40 and a maximum of around 65.
When you're done looking at the graph,
click on the terminal window and
press enter to quit.
With big data streaming from different
sources in varying formats, models, and
speeds it is no surprise that we
need to be able to ingest this data
into a fast and scalable storage system
that is flexible enough to serve many
current and future analytical processes.
This is when traditional data warehouses
with strict data models and data
formats don't fit the big data challenges
for streaming and batch applications.
The concept of a data lake was created in
response of these data big storage and
processing challenges.
After this video you
will be able to describe
how data lakes enable batch
processing of streaming data.
Explain the difference between
schema on write and schema on read.
Organize data streams and data lakes and
data warehouses on a spectrum of
big data management and storage.
What is a data lake?
Simply speaking, a data lake is
a part of a big data infrastructure
that many streams can flow into and
get stored for
processing in their original form.
We can think of it as a massive
storage depository with huge
processing power and ability to handle
a very large number of concurrence,
data management and analytical tasks.
In 2010,
the Pentaho Corporation's CTO James Dixon
defined a data link as follows.
If you think of a datamart as a store
of bottled water, cleansed and
packaged and structured for
easy consumption,
the data lake is a large body of
water in a more natural state.
The contents of the data lake stream
in from a source to fill the lake,
and various users of the lake can come
to examine it, dive in, or take samples.
A data lake works as follows.
The data gets loaded from its source,
stored in its native
format until it is needed
at which time the applications can freely
read the data and add structure to it.
This is what we call schema on read.
In a traditional data warehouse,
the data is loaded into the warehouse
after transforming it into a well
defined and structured format.
This is what we call schema on write.
Any application using the data needs to
know this format in order to retrieve and
use the data.
In this approach,
data is not loaded into the warehouse
unless there is a use for it.
However, schema on read
approach of data lakes ensures
all data is stored for
a potentially unknown use at a later time.
So how is a data lake
from a data warehouse?
A traditional data warehouse
stores data in a hierarchical file
system with a well-defined structure.
However, a data lake stores data as
flat files with a unique identifier.
This often gets referred to as
object storage in big data systems.
In data lakes each data is stored
as a binary large object or
BLOB and is assigned a unique identifier.
In addition, each data object is
tagged with a number of metadata tags.
The data can be searched
using these metadata tags
to retrieve it when there
is a need to access it.
From a users perspective,
metadata is stored is not a problem as
long as it is accessible when needed.
In Hadoop data architectures,
data is loaded into HDFS and processed
using the appropriate data management and
analytical systems on commodity clusters.
The selection of the tools is based on the
nature of the problem being solved, and
the data format being accessed.
We will talk more about
the processing of data streams and
data lakes in the next course
in this specialization.
To summarize a data lake is
a storage architecture for
big data collection and processing.
It enables collection of
all data suitable for
analysis today and
potentially in the future.
Regardless of the data source,
structure, and
format it supports storage of data and
transforms it only when it is needed.
A data lake ideally supports all parts
of the user base to benefit from
this architecture, including business,
storage, analytics and computing experts.
Finally, And perhaps most importantly,
data lakes are infrastructure components
within a big data architecture
that can evolve over time based
on application-specific needs.