The third component of
a data model is constraints.
A constraint is a logical statement.
That means one can compute and test
whether the statement is true or false.
Constraints are part of the data model
because they can specify something about
the semantics, that is,
the meaning of the data.
For example,
the constraint that a week has seven and
only seven days is something that a data
system would not know unless this
knowledge is passed on to it
in the form of a constraint.
Another constraint, shown here,
Tells the system that the number of
titles for a movie is restricted to one.
Different data models,
as we'll see in the next module,
will have different kinds of constraints.
There may be many different
kinds of constraints.
A value constraint is a logical
statement about data values.
On a previous slide we have said,
that the age, that is,
the value of data elements representing
the age of an entity can not be negative.
We also saw an example of
uniqueness constraint when we said
every movie can have only one title.
In the words of logic,
there should exist no data object that's
a movie and has more than one title.
It's easy to see that enforcing
these constraints requires us
to count the number of titles and
then verify that it's one.
Now, one can generalize this to count
the number of values associated with
each object and check whether it lies
between an upper and lower bound.
This is often called a cardinality
constraint of data property.
In a medical example here,
the constraint has a lower limit of 0 and
an upper limit of 3.
A different kind of value constraint can
be enforced by restricting the type of
the data allowed in a field.
If we do not have such a constraint we
can put any type of data in the field.
For example, you can have -99 as
the value of the last name of a person,
of course that would be wrong.
To ensure that this does not happen,
we can enforce the type of the last name
to be a non-numeric alphabetic string.
This example shows a logical
expression for this constraint.
A type constraint is a special
kind of domain constraint.
The domain of a data property or
attribute is the possible set of values
that are allowed for that attribute.
For example, the possible values for
the day part of the date field
can be between 1 and 31.
While a month may have
the value between 1 and 12.
Or, alternately, a value from the set
January, February, ect till December.
Now, one can devise a more complex
constraint, where the value of the date
for April, June, and September and
November, are restricted between 1 and 30.
And if you think about it,
all three constraints that we have
described in the last slide
are value constraints.
So they only state how to restrict
the values of some data property.
In sharp contrast, structural properties
restrict the structure of the data.
We'll choose a more complex example for
this.
Suppose we are a matrix,
as shown in the example, and
we've restricted to be a square matrix.
So the number of columns is exactly
equal to the number of rows.
We have not put any restriction
on the number of rows or columns.
But just that they have to be the same.
Now this constrains
the structure of the matrix and
implies that the number of entries in
the structure will be a squared number.
If we convert this matrix to a three
column table as shown, and impose
the same squareness constraint, it will
translate to a more complex condition.
That the number of data
rows will be the square of
the number of unique values
in column one of the table.
We'll encounter some more structural
constraints in the next module.
The second component of a data model is
a set of operations that can be performed
on the data.
And in this module,
we'll discuss the operations without
considering the bigness aspect.
In course three,
we'll come back to the issue of performing
these operations when the data is large.
Now,operations specified
the methods to manipulate the data.
SInce different data models are typically
associated with different structures,
the operations on them will be different.
But some types of operations are usually
performed across all data models.
We'll describe a few of them here.
One common operation extract a part of
a collection based on the condition.
In the example here,
we have a set of records and
we're looking for a sub set that
satisfies the condition that
the fifth field has a value
greater than 100,000.
The only one record
satisfies this requirement.
Note that we called this operation
subsetting rather loosely.
Depending on the context,
it's also called selection or filtering.
The next common operation is retrieving
a part of a structure that is specified.
In this case,
we specify that we are interested
in just the first two fields
of a collection off records.
But this produces a new collection of
records which has only these fields.
This operation like before has many names.
The most dominant name is projection.
In the next module, we'll see several
versions of this operation for
different data models.
The next two operations are about
combining two collections
into a larger one.
The term combine may be
interpreted in various ways.
The most straightforward
of them is said union.
The assumption behind the union operation
is that the two collections
involved have the same structure.
In other words, if one collection has
four fields and another has 14 fields, or
if one has four fields on people and
the dates of birth, and the other has four
things about countries and their capitols,
they cannot be combined through union.
In the example here,
their two collections have three and
two records, respectively, with one
record that's common between them.
The green one.
The result collection has four record,
because duplicates are disallowed
because it's a set operation.
There is indeed another version of
union where duplicates are allowed and
will produce five records instead of four.
The second kind of combining,
called a Join, can be done when
the two collections have different data
content but have some common elements.
In the example shown,
the first field is the common element
between the two collections on the left.
In this kind of data combination
there are two stages.
First, for each data item think
of a record of collection one,
one finds a set of matching
data items in collection two.
Thus, the first records of
the two collections match
based on the first field.
In the second phase of the operation,
all fields of the matching
record pairs are put together.
In the first record of the result
collection shown on the right,
one gets the first four fields
on the first collection and
the remaining two fields
from the second collection.
Now in this one example, we found one pair
of matching records from the collections.
In general, one would find more
than one matching record pairs.
As you can see,
this operation is more complex and
can be very expensive when the size
of the true collections are large.
In the big data world, we often hear the
term structured data, that is, data having
a structure which is quite different
from the so-called unstructured data.
But what is a structure?
Let's consider file 1.
It's a typical CSV file that has
three lines with different content.
But the file content is uniform
in the sense that each line,
call it a record,
has exactly three fields,
which we sometimes call data properties or
attributes.
Further, the first two of these fields
are strings and the third one is a date.
We can add more records, that's
lines with the same pattern of data,
to the file in the same fashion.
The content will grow, but the pattern of
data organization will remain identical.
This repeatable pattern of data
organization makes the file structured.
Now let's look at file 2,
which is four records of five fields each,
except that the third record seems
to be missing the last entry.
Is this file structured?
We argue that it is, because the missing
value makes the third record incomplete,
but it does not break the structure or
the pattern of the data organization.
Let's looks at these
two files side by side.
Clearly file 2 has more fields, and hence
is sort of wider than the first file.
Would you say that they
have the same structure?
Well, on the face of it they don't.
But if you think more broadly,
you would notice that they
are both collection of k fields.
The size of the collection,
respectively three and four, differs.
And k is 3 in the first case and
5 in the second.
But we can think of 3 and 5 as parameters.
In that case, we will say that these
files have been generated by a similar
organizational structure, and
hence they have the same data model.
Now in contrast, consider this file.
Just looking at it, it's impossible to
figure out how the data is organized and
how to identify subparts of the data.
We would call this data unstructured.
Often, compressed data like JPEG images,
MP3 audio files,
MPEG3 video files, encrypted data,
are usually unstructured.
In module two, we'll elaborate on data
models that are not fully structured or
are structured differently.
This is the first of two
hands-on exercises involving
sensor data from a weather station.
In this one, we will look at
static data in a text file.
The next one we will look at live data
streaming from the weather station
in real time.
In this exercise, we will begin
by opening a terminal window and
changing into the directory
containing the station measurements.
We will look at these measurements in
a text file and then look at the key for
these measurements so
we can understand what the values mean.
Finally, we will plot the measurements.
Let's begin.
First, we will open a terminal window by
clicking on the Terminal icon on the top
of the toolbar.
Next, we'll cd into the directory
containing the sensor data.
We'll run cd
Downloads/big-data-two/sensor.
We can write ls to see
the contents of this directory.
The data from the weather station is
in a text file called wx-data.txt.
We can run more wx-data.txt to
see the contents of this file.
Each line of this file is
a separate set of measurements.
There are two columns in this file,
the first column is a time stamp and
it's separated by
a second column by a tab.
The second column itself has separate
columns and these are separated by commas.
The time stamp is the number
of seconds since 1970.
You'll notice that it increases for
each time stamp.
each measurement.
But sometimes measurements
come in at the same time.
For example this one at 006.
The measurements,
we see that the prefix is 0R1 for
most of them but some have 0R2.
If we look at the other measurements,
we see that all the 0R1 measurements
start with Dn, Dm, Dx, and so on.
Whereas R2 begins with Ta, Ua, and Pa.
If we scroll down in the text
file by hitting the space bar,
we'll see there are other
measurements besides R1 and R2.
For example, there's R5 that has Th,
Vh, Vs and so on.
And there's R0 which has
all the measurements.
So Dn, Dm, Dx, Ta, Ua, Pa.
And the remaining ones.
Next we'll open another internal
window and look at the key to this
measurements click on the tool
bar to open the terminal window.
cd into downloads big data two sensor
And the key to these measurements is
in a file called wxt520format.txt.
We can run more wxt520format.txt
to see this file.
This file says where each
of the prefix is mean, for
example Sn is the wind speed minimum.
Sm is the wind speed average.
And Ta is the air temperature.
So if we go back to our sensor file,
we see here Ta equals 13.9c.
That means the air temperature at this
time was 13.9 degrees celsius.
We can also create a plot of
the data in this text file
by running plot-data.py wx-data.txt Ta.
This says to plot the data in
the wx-data file and the measure that we
want to apply is Ta, which according
to our key, is the air temperature.
When we run it, it displays a plot of the
air temperature found in the text file.
In this hands-on exercise,
we will be looking at an image file,
which uses an array data model.
First, we will open a terminal window and
display an image file on the screen.
Next, we will examine the structure
of the image, and finally,
extract pixel values from
various locations in the image.
Let's begin.
First, we'll open a terminal window by
clicking on the terminal icon at the top
of the toolbar.
Next, we'll CDN2 the directory
containing the image,
cdn2downloads/bigdata2/image.
We can run ls to see the image
in different scripts.
The file, Australia.jpg,
is an image that we want to view,
we can use eog to view it.
Run eog Australia.jpg Eog is
a common image viewer on Linux.
Australia.jpg is a satellite image
of the Australian continent.
Now let's look at the structure
of this image file.
If we go back to our terminal window,
we can run the image
viewer in the background by
hitting CTRL+Z, and then bg.
We can view the dimensions or
structure of the array data model of this
image by running
dimensions.py Australia.jpg.
This says that the image has
5250 columns and 4320 rows.
So it is a two-dimensional image.
Additionally, each cell or
pixel within this image is
composed of three 8-bit pixels.
These pixels are composed of three
elements, red, green, and blue.
We can extract or
view the individual pixel elements
at a specific location in the image
by using the pixel.py script.
We can run pixel.py Australia.jpg 0
0 to see the value at one location.
The 0 0 location is
the corner of the image.
If we go back to the image, the corners
are all the ocean, so they're dark blue.
If we look at the value that was
extracted, we see that blue has a high
value of 50, whereas red and
green are low with 11 and 10.
If we view it at another corner,
by looking at 5000 0,
we'll see the same value.
If we go back to the image, the middle
of the image, which is the land,
is orange or yellow.
It's definitely not blue, so
let's take a look at a pixel value there.
Okay, run pixel.py
Australia.jpg 2000 2000.
This says that the red has a value of 118,
green is 89, and the blue is 57.
So the red and green are higher than blue,
so it's not ocean.