A very important part of data preparation
is to assess the quality of your data.
We will look at some common data
quality issues in this lecture.
After this video, you will be able to
describe three data quality issues,
name three reasons for
poor data quality and
explain why data quality
issues need to be addressed.
Real world data is often very messy, so
it's a given fact that you will need
to clean your data by identifying and
addressing many issues that
affect the quality of your data.
Let's take a closer look at what
these data quality issues are.
A very common data quality
issue is missing data.
Recall that a sample in your dataset
typically contains several variables or
features like name, age and income.
For some samples, some of these
variables may not have a value.
These are referred to as
missing values in the data.
Missing values are also referred
to as N/A for not available.
So you will see N/A and
missing values used interchangeably.
You may have missing values in your data
if you have an optional field in your
data set.
For example, the field age is often
an optional field on a survey.
Also many people may choose not
to provide a response for income.
And so you will end up with missing values
for the variable income in your data set.
In some cases, a variable may
not be applicable to all cases.
For example, income may not be
applicable to people who are retired or
unemployed or to children.
So you will not have an entry for
income in all of your samples.
You can also have missing values, due to a
data collecting device that malfunctions,
a network problem that affects
how the data was transmitted, or
something else that goes wrong during
the data collection process itself, or
the process of transmitting the data or
storing the data.
Duplicate data occurs when your data set
has data objects that are duplicates or
new duplicates of one another.
An example of this is when there
are two different records for
the same customer with
different addresses.
This can come about, for example,
if a customer's address has changed,
but the second address was simply
added to this customer's records instead
of used to update the first address.
Duplicate data can occur when
merging data from multiple sources.
Invalid or
inconsistent data occurs when you have
an impossible value for a variable.
Some common examples are when you have
a six digit zip code, the letters AB for
state abbreviations, or
a negative numbers for age.
These invalid data values can
come about when there is a data
entry error during data collection.
For example, if you allow people
to type in their zip code and
someone accidentally includes an extra
digit to their five digit zip code,
then you will end up with
an invalid six digit zipcode.
Noise refers to anything
that can distort your data.
Noise can be introduced during
the data collection process or
data transmission process.
An example is buzzing in the background
when an audio message is recorded
due to background noise or
a faulty microphone.
Another example is an overly bright
image due to an incorrect light
exposure setting.
An Outlier is a data sample with
values that are considerably different
than the rest of the other
data samples in a data set.
An example scenario, that can create
Outliers is when there's a sense of
failure that causes values being recorded
to be much higher or lower than normal.
In this case, you want to remove
the Outliers from your data.
In other applications however,
such as fraud detection,
outliers are the important samples
that should be examined more closely.
So depending on the application,
outliers may need to be removed or
be kept for further analysis.
If you simply ignore these
data quality issues,
any analysis that is performed
will produce misleading results.
In addition, some implementations
of analysis techniques
cannot handle some of these
problems such as missing values.
So, problems that we've discussed
in this lecture need to be
addressed before any meaningful
analysis can be performed.
We will discuss some techniques for
handling data quality
issues in the next lecture.
If you have been in a conversation
on machine learning,
you have probably heard terms like
feature, sample, and variable.
We will be defining some of
those terms in this lecture.
After this video, you will be able
to describe what a feature is, and
how it relates to a sample.
Name some alternative terms for feature.
Summarize how a categorical feature
differs from a numerical feature.
Before we delve into the methods for
processing and
analyzing data, let's first start with
defining some term used to describe data,
starting with sample and variable.
A sample is an instance or
example of an entity in your data.
This is typically a row in your dataset.
This figure shows part of a dataset
of values related to weather.
Each row is a sample representing
weather data for particular day.
The table in the figure shows four samples
of weather data, each for different day.
In this table, each sample has
five values associated with it.
These values are different
information pieces about the sample
such as the sample ID, sample date,
minimum temperature, maximum temperature,
and rainfall on that day.
We call these different values
variables of the sample.
There are many names for
sample and variable.
Some other terms for sample that you
might hear in a machine learning
context include record, example,
row, instance and observation.
It is helpful to realize that all of
these terms mean the same thing in
machine learning.
That is, they all refer to a specific
example of an entity in your dataset.
There are also many names for the term
variable, such as feature, column,
dimension, attribute, and field.
All of these terms refer to
specific characteristics for
each sample in your dataset.
An important point to emphasize
about variable is that,
they are additional
values with a data type.
Each variable has a data
type associated with it.
The most common data types are numeric and
categorical.
There are other data types as
well such as string and date but
we will focus on two of the more common
data types, numeric and categorical.
As the name implies, numeric variables
are variables that take on number values.
Numeric variables can be measured, and
their values can be sorted in some way.
Note that a numeric variable can
take on just integer values or
be continuous valued.
It can also have just positive numbers,
negative numbers or both.
Let's go over some examples
of various numeric variables.
A person's height is a positive,
continuous valued number.
The score in an exam is a positive number
that range between zero and a 100%.
The number of transactions per
hour is a positive integer,
whereas the change in a stock price
can be either positive or negative.
A variable with labels,
names, or categories for
values instead of numbers
are called categorical variables.
For example a variable that describes
the color of an item, such as the color of
a car, can have values such as red,
silver, blue, white and black.
These are non-numeric values
that describes some quality or
characteristic of an entity.
These values can be thought of as names or
labels that can be sorted into categories.
Therefore, categorical variables are also
referred to as qualitative variables, or
nominal variables.
Some examples of categorical
variables are gender, marital status,
type of customer, for example,
teenager, adult, senior.
Product categories, for example,
electronics, kitchen, bathroom and
color of an item.
To summarize, a sample is an instance or
example of an entity in your data.
A variable captures a specific
characteristic of each entity.
So a sample has many
variables to describe it.
Data from real applications
are often multidimensional,
meaning that there are many dimensions or
variables describing each sample.
Each variable has a data
type associated with it,
the most common data types are numeric and
categorical.
Note that there are many terms to
describe these data related concepts.
The data used in machine learning
processes often have many variables.
This is what we call
highly dimensional data.
Most of these dimensions may or may not
matter in the context of our application
with the questions we are asking.
Reducing such high dimensions to
a more manageable set of related and
useful variables improves the performance
and accuracy of our analysis.
After this video, you will be able to
explain what dimensionality reduction is,
discuss the benefits of
dimensionality reduction, and
describe how PCA transforms your data.
The number of features or variables
you have in your data set determines
the number of dimensions or
dimensionality of your data.
If your dataset has two features,
than it is two dimensional data.
If it has three features than
it has three features and so on.
You want to use as many features as
possible to capture the characteristics of
your data, but
you also don't want the dimension
audio of your data to be too high.
As the dimensionality increases, the
problem spaces you're looking at increases
requiring substantially more instances
to adequately sample of that space.
So as the dimensionality increases,
the space that you are looking
at grows exponentially.
As the space grows data
becomes increasingly sparse.
In this diagram we see how
the problem space grows as
the dimensionality
increases from 1 to 2 to 3.
In the left plot, we have a one
dimensional space partitioned into four
regions each with size of 5 units.
The middle plot shows a two
dimensional space with 5x5 regions.
The number of regions has
now going from 4 to 16.
In the third plot, the problem space is
three dimensional with 5x5x5 regions.
The number of regions
increased even more to 64.
We see that as the number of dimensions
increases, the number of regions
increases exponentially and
the data becomes increasingly sparse.
With a small dataset relative to the
problem space, analysis results degrade.
In addition, certain calculations used in
analysis become much more difficult to
define and calculate effectively.
For example, distances between samples
are harder to compare since all samples
are far away from each other.
All of these challenges represent
the difficulty of dealing with high
dimensional data and as referred
to as the curse of dimensionality.
To avoid the curse of dimensionality,
you want to reduce
the dimensionality of your data.
This means finding a smaller subset of
features that can effectively capture
the characteristics of your data.
Recall from the lecture on feature
selection part of data preparation is to
select the features to use.
For example, you can a feature that is
very correlated with another feature.
Using feature selection
techniques to select assessitive
features is one approach to
dimensionality reduction.
Another approach to dimensionality
reduction is to mathematically determine
the most important dimension to keep and
ignore the rest.
The idea is to find a smallest
subset of dimensions that
capture the most variation in your data.
This reduces the dimensions of the data
while eliminating the relevant features
making the subsequent analysis simple.
A technique commonly use to find
the subset of most important dimensions is
called principal component analysis,
or PCA for short.
The goal of PCA is to map the data from
the original high dimensional space
to a lower dimensional space that
captures as much of the variation in
the data as possible.
In other words,
PCA aims to find the most useful subset
of dimensions to summarize the data.
This plot illustrates the idea behind PCA.
Here, we have data samples in a two
dimensional space that is defined
by the x axis and the y axis.
You can see that most of the variation in
the data lies along the red diagonal line.
This means that the dat samples are best
differentiated along this dimension
because they're spread out,
not clumped together along this dimension.
This dimension indicated by the red
line is the first principle component
labelled as PC1 in the part.
It captures the large amount of variance
along a single dimension in data.
PC1, indicated by the red line does
not correspond to either axis.
The next principle component is determined
by looking in the direction that is
orthogonal, in other words perpendicular,
to the first principle component which
captures the next largest
amount of variance in the data.
This is the second
principal component PC2 and
it's indicated by
the green line in the plot.
This process can be repeated to find as
many principal components as desired.
Note that the principal components do
not align with either the x-axis or
the y-axis.
And that they are orthogonal, in other
words, perpendicular to each other.
This is what PCA does.
It finds the underlined dimensions,
the principal
components that capture as much of
the variation in the data as possible.
These principal components form a new
coordinates system to transform
the data to, instead of the conventional
dimensions like X, Y, and Z.
So how does PCA help with
dimensionality reduction?
Let's look again in this plot with
the first principle component.
Since the first principle component
captures most of the variations in
the data, the original data sample can
be mapped to this dimension indicated by
the red line with minimum
loss of information.
In this case then,
we map a two-dimensional dataset to
a one-dimensional space while keeping
as much information as possible.
Here are some main points about
principal components analysis.
PCA finds a new coordinate system for
your data,
such that the first coordinate
defined by the first principal
component Captures the greatest
variance in your data.
The second coordinate defined by
the second principal component captures
the second greatest variance in a data,
etc..
The first few principle components that
capture most of the variance in a data
can be used to define
a lower-dimensional space for your data.
PCA can be a very useful technique for
dimensionality reduction,
especially when working
with high-dimensional data.
While PCA is a useful technique for
reducing the dimensionality of your
data which can help with
the downstream analysis,
it can also make the resulting analysis
models more difficult to interpret.
The original features in your data set
have specific meanings such as income,
age and occupation.
By mapping the data to a new coordinate
system defined by principal components,
the dimensions in your transformed
data no longer have natural meanings.
This should be kept in mind when using
PCA for dimensionality reduction.
In this activity, we will use KNIME to
perform data exploration of weather data.
First, we will create
a new KNIME workflow.
We'll then input the weather data.
Next, we will create
a histogram of air temperature.
Create a scatter plot
between two variables.
Create a bar chart to show the
distribution of a categorical variable.
And finally, create a box plot to
compare two different distributions.
Let's begin.
First, we will create
a new workflow in KNIME.
To do this we go to the File menu.
Select new, select new KNIME workflow and
click on next.
Then we type the name of
the workflow we want to create.
We'll call this one plots.
Click on finish.
Next we want to load
weather data into KNIME.
To do this we'll use a file reader node.
To add this node,
go to the bottom left node repository.
And in the box type in file reader.
Drag File Reader to the canvas.
Next, double click on File Reader to
configure it with the weather data.
Click on the Browse button.
We'll choose the weather file.
That's daily_weather.csv.
We can see preview of
the data at the bottom half
of the file reader configure dialog.
You can see values for
each column in the CSV file.
Click OK to close the dialog.
Next, we want to create
a histogram of air temperature.
We'll add the histogram
node to the workflow.
Again, we go to the node repository and
type in histogram.
We'll drag and
drop histogram to the workflow and
we'll connect File Reader to histogram.
We'll click and
hold on output to File Reader and
drag to the input of histogram and
release.
Before we configure the histogram node,
we need to run the file reader node.
We can do that by selecting
the file reader and
either clicking on the green
arrow at the top or
right clicking and choosing execute here.
Once we've done that,
double-click on histogram.
We'll select error_temp_9AM
as the biding column and
also add error_temp_9AM to
the aggregation column.
We'll leave the default
number of bins as ten.
Click on OK.
Now we'll run the workflow.
You can click on the two arrow green
button at the top to run all the nodes.
Now let's view the histogram.
Right click on the histogram node.
And choose View, Histogram View.
The x-axis shows the value for
each bin in the histogram.
And the y-axis is the count, or frequency.
We can see the most frequent
values are between 60 and 73.
On the right, we also see that
there's some with missing values.
Next close the window.
Now let's create a scatter plot to show
the relationship between two variables.
First, we will add the scatter
plot node to the work flow.
We'll connect the the output of
File Reader to the input of Scatter Plot.
Execute the workflow, right-click on
Scatter Plot and choose View Scatter Plot.
We'll click on the Column Selection and
choose air_temp_9am for the X Column.
And for the Y Column,
choose relative humidity 9 AM.
In this plot,
we can see a negative correlation
between temperature and humidity.
As the temperature increases,
the humidity goes down.
We'll close this window.
Next, we'll create a bar chart to show the
distribution of a categorical variable.
We'll visualize the wind
direction at 9 AM.
We will begin by creating the categorical
variable by using the numeric binner node.
Let's add numeric binner to the work flow.
We'll connect the output of file
reader to the input of numeric binner.
Double-click on Numeric Binner
to configure it.
Select max_wind_direction_9am and
click on add five times to add five bins.
Now let's give a name for
each of these bins.
Select a bin and now choose a name.
The first will be for the North direction.
So we'll call that 1-N.
Next, 2-E for East, 3-S for
South, 4-W for West and
finally 1-N for north again.
Now we need to specify the values for
each of these bins.
We'll select the first one and
set the endpoint to be 45 degrees.
Next, choose east and
set that maximum to be 135.
Select the third one and
choose the max to be 225.
Finally, select the fourth one and
select the max to be 315.
Next, click on a pin new column.
Set the name for categorical variable to
be categorical underscore max underscore.
Wind_direction_9AM.
Click OK.
Now add a histogram note to the work flow.
Connect the output of
Numeric Binner to histogram.
Double-click on Histogram to configure it.
Make sure they binning column is
categorical_max_wind_direction_9AM.
And also there are no aggregation columns.
Click OK and execute the work flow.
Let's view the chart.
Right click on Histogram and
choose View, Histogram View.
This tells us that most of the wind
comes from the east and the south.
And not many measurements from the north.
Next, close this.
Now lets create a box plot to
compare two different distributions.
We w'll examine the distribution,
air pressure for
low humidity days versus normal or
high humidity days.
To do this, we'll first need to creat
a categorical variable for humidity.
Lets add another numeric
binner actor to the workflow.
Connect the output,
a file reader to this actor.
Double click to configure.
Select relative humidity, 9 AM.
And click on add twice to add two bins.
Select the first bin and
we'll call that humidity_low.
Select the second bin and
we'll call that humidity_not_low.
Select the first bin, and
we'll set the maximum value to 25.
Check append new column.
And set the name to low_humidity_day,
click on OK.
Next, add the conditional box
plot node to the workflow.
Right click on conditional
box plot to configure it.
Make sure the nominal column
is low_humidity_day and
the numeric column is air_pressure_9am.
Click OK.
Run the workflow.
Right click on conditional box plot and
choose few additional box plot.
And the x axis, we see the two values or
a categorical variable, humidity low and
humidity not low.
The y axis shows the air pressure values.
I can see that on average,
lower humidity means higher air pressure.
Close this.
Finally, save the workflow when
we're done by clicking on the disk
at the top left of the toolbar.
In addition to cleaning your data
to address data quality issues,
data preparation also includes
selecting features to use for analysis.
After this video, you will be able to
explain what feature selection involves,
discuss the goal of feature selection,
and list three approaches for
selecting features.
Feature selection refers to
choosing the set of features to
use that is appropriate for
the subsequent analysis.
The goal of feature selection is to come
up with the smallest set of features
that best captures the characteristics
of the problem being addressed.
The smaller the number of features used,
the simpler the analysis will be.
But of course,
the set of features used must include
all features relevant to the problem.
So, there must be a balance
between expressiveness and
compactness of the feature set.
There are several methods to
consider in selecting features.
New features can be added,
some features can be removed, features can
be re-coded or features can be combined.
All these operations affect the final
set of features that will be used for
analysis.
Of course some features
can be kept as is as well.
New features can be derived
from existing features.
For example, a new feature to specify
whether a student is in state or
out of state can be added based on
the student's state of residence.
For an application such
as college admissions,
this new feature represents an important
aspect of an application and so
would be very helpful
as a separate feature.
Another example is adding a feature
to indicate the color of a vehicle,
which can play an important role
in an auto insurance application.
Features can also be removed,
candidates for
removal are features
that are very correlated.
During data exploration,
you may have discovered that
two features are very correlated,
that is they change in very similar ways.
For example,
the purchase price of a product and
the amount of sales tax paid
are likely to be very correlated.
The higher the purchase price
the higher the sales tax.
In this case, you might want
to drop one of these features,
since these features have
essentially duplicate information.
And keeping both features makes
the feature set larger and
the analysis unnecessarily more complex.
Features with a high percentage of
missing values may also be good
candidates for removal.
The validity and
usefulness of features with a lot
of missing values are in question.
So removing may not result
in any loss of information.
Again these features would have
been discovered during the data
exploration step.
Irrelevant features should also
be removed from the data set.
Irrelevant features are those that
contain no information that is useful for
the analysis task.
An example of this is employee
ID in predicting income.
Other fields used simply for
identification such as row number,
person's ID, etc.,
are good candidates for removal.
Features can also be combined if the new
feature presents important information
that is not represented by looking at
the original features individually.
For example, BMI, which is body
mass index is an indicator of
whether a person is underweight,
average weight, or overweight.
This is an important feature to have for
a weight loss application.
It represents information about how much
a person weighs relative to their height
that is not available by looking at just
the person's height or weight alone.
A feature can be re-coded as
appropriate for the application.
A common example of this is when you
want to turn a continuous feature in to
a categorical one.
For example for a marketing application
you might want to re-code customer's age
into customer categories such as teenager,
young adult, adult and senior citizen.
So you would map ages 13 to 19 to
teenager, ages 20 to 25 to young adult,
26 to 55 as adult and over 55 as senior.
For some applications you may want
to make use of finery features.
As an example, you might want a feature to
capture whether a customer tends to buy
expensive items or not.
In this case, you would want a feature
that maps to one for a customer with
an average purchase price over a certain
amount and maps to zero otherwise.
Re-coding features can also
result in breaking one feature
into multiple features.
A common example of this is to
separate an address feature
into its constituent parts street address,
city, state and zip code.
This way you can more easily
group records by state, for
example, to provide
a state by state analysis.
Future selection aims to select
the smallest set of features to best
capture the characteristics of
the data for your application.
Know from the examples represented
that domain knowledge once again place
a key role in choosing
the appropriate features to use.
Good understanding of the application is
essential in deciding which features to
add, drop or modify.
It should also be noted that feature
selection can be referred to as feature
engineering, since what you're doing here
is to engineer the best feature set for
your application.