This activity we'll be exploring
weather data in Spark.
First, we will load weather data from
a CSV file into a Spark DataFrame.
Next, we will examine the columns and
schema of the DataFrame.
We will then view the summary statistics
and drop rows with missing values.
Finally, we will compute
the correlation between two columns.
Let's begin.
First, we'll create a new
Jupyter Python notebook.
You do this by clicking on New and
choosing Python 3.
Next, we'll import SQL context.
This is done by entering from
pyspark.sql import SQLContext.
Next, we'll create an instance
of the SQLContext.
We'll enter sqlContext = SQLContext(sc).
Now let's read our weather
data into a DataFrame.
We'll call the DataFrame df and
we'll read it using the sqlContext.
We'll enter sqlContext.read.load.
The first argument is the URL of the file.
That's
file:///home/cloudera/Downloads/big-data--
4/daily_weather.csv.
The second argument specifies
the format of how to read the file.
In this case, we're going to use the
Spark CSV package from Databricks to load
the CSV directly into the DataFrame.
We need to use this because
the Cloudera image only has Spark 1.
In Spark 2 and later,
this package is included so
we don't have to use this argument.
We'll enter ,format= and
the name of the package is
com.databricks.spark.csv.
The next argument specifies that the first
line in the CSV file is the header,
header='true'.
The last argument tells Spark
to try to infer the schema
from the CSV header, inferSchema='true'.
Run this.
Now let's look at our DataFrame.
We can run a df.columns to see
the names of all the columns.
We can also run df.printSchema to
see the schema of the DataFrame.
Next, let's look at the summary
statistics for the data.
We can do this using the describe method.
We'll run df.describe().show().
This shows summary statistics for
all the columns in the DataFrame.
There's a lot of information here,
so lets just choose one column.
Let's look at air pressure at 9 AM.
We can see the summary statistics for
air pressure 9 AM by running
df.describe('air_pressure_9am').show().
There are five statistics in this output,
the count, the number of rows,
the mean, the standard deviation,
and the min and max values.
We can see the total number of columns in
the DataFrame by running len(df.columns).
We can also see the total number of rows
in the DataFrame by writing df.count.
This says that there are 1,095
rows in the DataFrame.
However, the summary statistics for
air_pressure_9am,
we see the count is 1,092.
Summary statistics do not
include rows of missing values.
This means that there are three rows in
the air_pressure_9am column that have
missing values.
We can drop these missing values.
Let's create a new DataFrame where
we've dropped these missing values.
We'll call the new DataFrame df2.
To drop the missing values, we'll enter
df.na.drop(subset=['air_pressure_9am']).
We can then count the total number of
rows in the new DataFrame, df2.count.
We see this value agrees with
our earlier value of 1092.
Next, let's compute the correlation
between two columns in the DataFrame.
We'll compute the correlation between
rain accumulation and rain duration.
To do this, we'll enter df2.stat.corr and
then the names of the two columns,
rain_accumulation_9am and
rain_duration_9am.
Visualizing your data is a very
effective way to explore your data.
We'll look at different ways to
visualize your data in this lecture.
After this video,
you will be able to discuss how plots
can be useful in exploring data,
describe how you would use a scatter plot,
and summarize what a boxplot shows.
Visualizing data,
that is looking at data graphically,
is a great way to explore your data set.
Data visualization is a nice complement
to using summary statistics for
exploring data.
We will cover several ways to
visualize your data in this lecture.
There are several types of plots that
you can use to visualize your data.
We will go over histogram, line plot,
scatter plot, bar plot, and box plot.
These are the most commonly used plots,
but there are many others as well.
A histogram is used to display
the distribution of a variable.
The range of values for the variable
is divided into the number of bins, and
the number of values that fall
into each bin is counted.
Which determines the height of each bin.
A histogram can reveal many things
about a variable in your data, for
example, you can usually determine
the central tendency of a variable,
that is where the majority
of the values lie.
You can also see the most frequent
value of values for that variable.
A histogram also shows whether the values
for that variable are skewed and
whether the skewness is to
the left towards smaller values or
to the right towards larger values.
You can also pick outliers in
the histogram as shown on the bottom plot.
A line plot shows how data
values change over time.
The values of a variable or
variables are shown on the Y axis and
the X axis shows the motion of time.
The resulting line displays
the data values over time.
A line plot can show
patterns in your variables.
For example, a cyclical pattern
can be detected as in this plot,
where the values start high,
then decrease and go back up again.
Trends can also be detected as
shown in the upper-right plot
where the values fluctuate but
show a general upward trend over time.
It is also easy to compare how multiple
variables change over time on a single
line plot as displayed in
the center bottom plot.
A scatter plot is a great way to visualize
the relationship between two variables.
One variable is on the x axis.
The other variable is on
the y axis Each sample is
a product using the values of the 2
variables aspects and Y coordinates.
The resulting plot shows how one variable
changes as the other is changed.
A scatter plot can be used to display
the correlation between 2 variables.
For example, 2 variables such as
the high temperature of the day, and
the low temperature of the day,
can have a positive correlation
as shown in this plot.
A positive correlation means that as
the value of one variable increases,
the value of the other variable
also increases by a similar amount.
The upper right scatter plot shows
a negative correlation between two
variables.
This means that as the value
of one variable increases,
there is a corresponding decrease in
the other variable, two variables
can also have a non-linear correlation
as shown in the lower left plot.
This means that a change
in one variable will not
always correspond to the same
change in the other variable.
This is indicated by the curve in
the scatter plot as opposed to something
closer to a straight line for
linear correlation.
There can also be no correlation
between two variables.
In this case, you will see something
like randomly placed dots as
displayed in the lower right plot,
indicating no
relationship between how the two variables
change with respect to each other.
A bar plot is used to show
the distribution of categorical variables.
Recall that a histogram is also used to
look at the distribution of the values
of the variable.
The difference is that in general,
a histogram is used for
numeric variables whereas a bar plot
is used for categorical variables.
In a bar chart, the different categories
of a categorical variable is shown along
the x-axis, and the count of instances for
each category is displayed on the y-axis.
This is an effective way to
compare the different categories.
For example, the most frequent
category can be easily determined.
A bar plot is also a great way to
compare two categorical variables.
For example, this plot compares
two categorical variables.
One in blue and the other in orange,
each with three different categories.
Here you can see that for
the first category,
the blue variable has the higher count,
while the orange variable has a higher
count for the second and third category.
This type of Bar Plot is
called a Grouped Bar Chart.
And the different variables
of products side by side.
A different kind of comparison can be
performed using a Stacked Bar chart
as seen in a lower right quad.
Here, the accounts for the two variables
are stacked on top of each other for
each category.
With this bar chart, you can
determine that the combined count for
the first category is about equal to
the combine count for the second category,
while the compliant count for
the third category is much larger.
A box plot is another plot that shows
the distribution of a numeric variable,
it shows the distribution in a different
format than the histogram, however.
This is how a box plot displays
the distribution of values for
a variable, the gray portion
in the figure is the box part.
The lower and upper boundaries of
the box represent the 25th and
75th percentiles respectively.
This means that the box represents
the middle 50% of the data,
the median is the 50th percentile,
meaning that 50% of
the data is greater than its value and
50% of the data is less than this value.
The top and bottom lines are the Whiskers
and represent the 10th and
90th percentiles respectively.
So, 80% of the data are in the region
indicated by the upper extreme and
lower extreme.
Any data values outside of
this region are outliers and
are indicated as single
point on the box plot.
Note that there are different
variations of the box plot,
with the whiskers representing
different types of extreme values.
Box plots provide a compact way to
show how variables are distributed, so
they are often used to compare variables.
The box plot on the left for
example compares the base salary for
two different roles.
This plot can quickly provide information
regarding the median value, the range and
the spread of the two different variables.
We can quickly see that
the median salary for
the marketing role is higher
than the research role.
We can also see that the variation or
spread of the values for
marketing is greater than for research,
due to the larger area of the purple box.
A box plot can also show you if
the distribution of the data values is
symmetrical, positively skewed or
negatively skewed.
Here we see that a box plot can
also be displayed on its side.
A symmetric distribution is
indicated if the line in the box
which specifies the median,
is in the center of the box.
A negative skew is indicated
when the median is to the right
of the center of the box.
This means that there are more
values that are less than the median
than there are values
greater than the median.
Similarly, a positive skew is indicated
when the median is to the left
of the center of the box.
To summarize,
data visualization provides a quick and
intuitive way to examine your data.
Data visualization should be
used in conjunction with summary
statistics that we discussed in
the last lecture to explore data.
The different types of plots that we have
covered in this lecture will also be very
helpful in communicating your results
throughout your machine learning project.
Let's look at how we can use summary
statistics to explore data in more detail.
After this video you will be able to
define what a summary statistic is,
list three common summary statistics and
explain how summary statistics
are useful in exploring data.
Summary statistics are quantities
that describe a set of data values.
Summary statistics provide a simple and
quick way to summarize a dataset.
We will discuss three main
categories of summary statistics.
Measures of location or centrality,
measures of spread, and measures of shape.
Measures of location are summary
statistics that describe the central or
typical value in your dataset.
These statistics give a sense of
the middle or center of the dataset.
Examples of these are mean,
median and mode.
The mean is just the average
of the values in a dataset.
The median is the value in the middle if
you sorted the values in your dataset.
In a sorted list, half of the values
will be less than the median and
half will be greater than the median.
If the number of data values is even,
then the median is the mean
of the two middle values.
The mode is a value that is repeated
more often than any other value.
In this example we have
a dataset with ten values.
For this dataset,
the mean is 51.1 which is the number
of all the values divided by 10.
The median is 46, if you sort these
numbers, the middle numbers are 42 and 50.
The average of these two numbers is 46.
There are two modes for
the this dataset, 42 and 78,
since each occurs twice,
more than any other value in the dataset.
Measures of spread describe how
dispersed or varied your dataset is.
Common measures of spread are minimum,
maximum, range,
standard deviation and variance.
Minimum and
maximum are of course the smallest and
largest values in your
dataset respectively.
The range is simply the difference
between the maximum and minimum and
tells you how spread out your data is.
Standard deviation describes the amount
of variation in your dataset.
A low standard deviation value means
that the samples in your dataset
tend to be close to the mean.
And a high standard deviation value means
that the data samples are spread out.
Variance is closely related
to standard deviation.
In fact the variance is the square
of the standard deviation.
So it also indicates how spread out
the data samples are from the mean.
For the same dataset, the range is 66
which is a difference between the largest
number which is 87 and
the smallest number which is 21.
The variance is 548.767,
you can calculate this using
a calculator or a spreadsheet.
And the standard deviation is 23.426
which is the square root of the variance.
Measures of shape describe the shape
of the distribution of a set of values.
Common members of shape are skewness and
kurtosis.
Skewness indicates whether the data
values are asymmetrically distributed.
A skewness value of around zero
indicates that the data distribution
is approximately normal, as shown in
the middle figure in the top diagram.
A negative skewness value indicates that
the distribution is skewed to the left,
as indicated in the left
figure in the top diagram.
A positive skewness
value on the other hand
indicates that the data distribution
is skewed to the right.
Kurtosis measures the tailedness
of the data distribution or
how heavy or
fat the tails of the distribution are.
A high kurtosis value describes a
distribution with longer and fatter tails
and a higher and sharper central peak,
indicating the presence of outliers.
A low kurtosis value on the other hand,
describes a distribution with shorter and
lighter tails and lower and
broader central peak,
suggesting the lack of outliers.
In our age example, the skewness is about
0.3 indicating a slight positive skew.
And the kurtosis is -1.2 indicating
a distribution with a low and
broad central peak and
shorter and lighter tails.
Measures of dependence determine if any
relationship exists between variables.
Pairwise correlation is a commonly
used measure of dependence.
This is a table that shows pairwise
correlation for a set of variables.
Note that correlation applies
only to numerical variables.
Correlations is between zero and one,
with zero indicating no correlation,
and one indicating a one
to one correlation.
So a correlation of
0.89 is very strong and
this is expected since a person's height
and weight should be very correlated.
The summary statistics we just covered
are useful for numerical variables.
For categorical variables, we want to look
at statistics that describe the number of
categories and
the frequency of each category.
This is done using a contingency table.
Here's an example that shows
a distribution of people's pets and
their colors.
We can see the most common pet is
a dog and least common's a fish.
Similarly, black is the most common
color and orange the least common.
The contingency table also shows
the distribution between the categories.
For example, only fish are orange
while most of the brown pets are dogs.
In addition to looking at
the traditional summary statistics for
numerical variables, and
category count for categorical variables.
For machine learning problems,
we also want to examine some additional
statistics to quickly validate the data.
One of the first things to
check is the number of rows and
the number of columns in your dataset.
Does the number of rows match
the expected number of samples?
Does the number of columns match
the expected number of variables?
These should be very quick and
easy checks.
Another easy data validation check is
to look at the values in the first and
last few samples in your dataset
to see if they're reasonable.
For example, do the temperature values
looks to be in the right units of measure.
Do the values for rainfall look correct or
are there some values
that look out of place?
Are the data types for
your variables correct, for example,
is the date field captured as dates or
timestamp.
Or is it capture as a string or
numerical value?
These will have consequences in how
these fields should be processed.
Another important step is to check for
missing values.
You need to determine the number
of samples with missing values.
You also need to determine
if there are any variables
with a high percentage of missing values.
Handling missing values is a very
important step in data preparation
which we will cover in the next module.
Having this information will be very
helpful in determining how missing values
should be handled in data preparation.
We covered several types of summary
statistics useful for exploring data and
machine learning.
The statistics provide useful information
about your dataset and should be
thoroughly examine if you want to get
a better understanding of your data.
Now that we are familiar with some
commonly use terms to describe data,
let's look at what data exploration is and
why it's important.
After this video,
you will be able to explain why data
exploration is necessary, articulate
the objectives of data exploration,
list the categories of techniques for
exploring data.
Data exploration means
doing some preliminary
investigation of your data set.
The goal is to gain a better understanding
of the data that you have to work with.
If you understand the characteristics of
your data, you can make optimal use of it
in whatever subsequent processing and
analysis you do with the data.
Note that data exploration is also
called exploratory data analysis, or
EDA for short.
How do you go about exploring data?
There are two main categories of
techniques to explore your data,
one based on summary statistics and
the other based on visualization methods.
Summary statistics provide important
information that summarizes a set
of data values.
There are many such statistics.
Many of them you have
probably heard of before,
such as mean, median,
and standard deviation.
These are some very commonly
used summary statistics.
A summary statistic provides a single
quantity that summarizes some aspects of
the dataset.
For example, the mean, is a single
value that describes the average value
of the dataset,
no matter how large that dataset is.
You can think of the mean as an indicator
of where your dataset is centrally located
on a number line, thus summary
statistics provide a simple and
quick way to summarize a dataset.
Data visualization techniques allow
you to look at your data, graphically.
There are several types of plots that
you can use to visualize your data.
Some examples are histogram,
line plot, and scatter plot.
Each type of plot serves a different
purpose, we will cover the use of plots to
visualize your data in
an upcoming lecture.
What should you look for
when exploring your data?
You use statistics and
visual methods to summarize and
describe your dataset, and
some of the things you'll want to look for
are correlations,
general trends and outliers.
Correlations provide information
about the relation took between
variables in your data.
By looking at correlations,
you may be able to determine that
two variables are very correlated.
This means they provide the same or
similar information about your data.
Since this contain redundant information,
this suggest that you may want to
remove one of the variables
to make the analysis simpler.
Trends in your data will reveal
characteristics in your data.
For example, you can see where
the majority of the data values lie,
whether your data is skilled or
not, what the most frequent value or
values are in a date set, etc.
Looking at trends in your data can also
reveal that a variable is moving in
a certain direction, such as sales revenue
increasing or decreasing over the years.
Calculating the minimum, the maximum and
range of the data values are basic
steps in exploring your data.
Determining outliers is
a also very important.
Outliers indicate potential
problems with the data and
may need to be eliminated
in some applications.
In other applications,
outliers represent interesting data points
that should be looked at more closely.
In either case, outliers usually
require further examination.
In summary, what you get by exploring
your data is a better understanding of
the complexity of the data so
you can work with it more effectively.
Better understanding in turn will
guide the rest of the process and
lead to more informed analysis.
Summary statistics and
visualization techniques
are essential in exploring your data.
This should be used together
to examined a dataset.
In the next two lectures,
we will look at a specific methods that
you can apply to explore your data.
In this lesson you will learn how
to prepare data for analysis.
After this video, you will be able
to articulate the importance of data
preparation, define the objectives
of data preparation, and
list some activities in preparing data.
The raw data that you get directly from
your sources is rarely in the format
that you can use to perform analysis on.
The goal of data preparation is to create
the data that will be used for analysis.
This means cleaning the data, and putting
the data in the right format for analysis.
The latter generally involves selecting
the appropriate features to use and
transforming the data as needed.
The data that you've acquired
will likely have many problems.
An important part of data preparation is
to clean the data that you have to work
with to address what are referred
to as data quality issues.
There are many types of
data quality issues,
including missing values, duplicate data,
inconsistent or invalid data,
noise, and outliers.
The problems listed here can negatively
affect the quality of the data and
compromise the analysis process and
results.
So it is very important to detect and
address these data quality issues.
Some techniques to address data quality
issues include removing data records
with missing values,
merging duplicate records,
generating a best, or at most reasonable,
estimate for invalid values.
We will discuss these techniques in
more detail in the next lecture.
Since the goal of the step of data
preparation is cleaning the data,
it is referred to as Data Cleaning or
Data Cleansing.
After the data has been cleaned,
another goal of data preparation is to
get the data into the format needed for
the analysis.
This step is referred to by many names,
Data Munching, Data Wrangling and
Data Preprocessing.
The two broad categories of data
wrangling are feature selection and
feature transformation.
Feature selection involves
deciding on which features
to use from the existing
ones available in your data.
Features can be removed,
added or combined.
Feature transformation involves
changing the format of the data
in some way to reduce noise or variability
or make the data easier to analyze.
Two common feature transformations
are scaling the data so
that all features have the same value
range and reducing the dimensionality,
which is effectively the number
of features of the data.
We will discuss these techniques
later in this lesson.
Data preparation is a very important
part of the machine learning process.
It can be a tedious process,
but it is a crucial step.
If you do not spend the time and
effort to create good data for
the analysis,
you will not get good results,
no matter how sophisticated the analysis
technique you are using is.
Always remember, garbage in, garbage out.
So take the time to prepare your data
if you want good analysis results.