Now that we went through an overview
of the Spark ecosystem and
the components of the Spark stack, it is
time for us to start learning more about
its architecture and run our first
Spark program in the cloud VM.
After this video you will be
able to describe how Spark
does in-memory processing using the
Resilient Distributed Dataset abstraction,
explain the inner workings of
the Spark architecture, and
summarize how Spark manages and
executes code on Clusters.
I mentioned a few times that
Spark is efficient because it
uses an abstraction called RDDs for
in memory processing.
What this means might not be
clear to some of you yet.
Let's remember the alternative.
In Hadoop MapReduce,
each step, also pipeline,
reads from disk to memory,
performs the computations and
writes back its output from
the memory to the disk.
However, writing data to disk
is a costly operation and
this cost becomes even more
with large volumes of data.
Here is an interesting fact.
Memory operations can
be up to 100,000 times
faster than disk operations in some cases.
Spark instead takes advantage of this and
allows for
immediate results of transformations
in different stages of the pipeline and
memory, like MAP and REDUCE here.
Here, we see that the outputs
of MAP operations
are shared with reduce operations
without being written to the disk.
The containers where the data
gets stored in memory
are called resilient distributed
datasets or RDDs for short.
RDDs are how Spark distributes data and
computations across
the nodes of a commodity cluster,
preferably with large memory.
Thanks to this abstraction,
Spark has proven to be 100 times
faster for some applications.
Let's define all the words
in this interesting name
beginning with the last one, datasets.
Datasets that RDD distributes comes
from a batch data storage like HDFS,
no SQL databases, text files or streaming
data ingestion systems like Cafco.
It can even conveniently read and
distribute the data from your local disc
like text files into Spark, or
even a hierarchy of folders.
When Spark reads data from these sources,
it generates RDDs for them.
The Spark operations can transform RDDs
into other RDDs like any other data.
Here it's important to mention
that RDDs are immutable.
This means that you cannot
change them partially.
However, you can create new RDDs by
a series of one or many transformations.
Next, let's look at what distributed
means in the RDD context.
As I mentioned before, RDDs distribute
partitioned data collections and
computations on clusters even
across a number of machines.
For example, running on the Amazon Cloud.
The complexity of this operation is
hidden by this very simple interface.
Computations are a diverse set of
transformations of RDDs like map,
filter and join.
And also actions on the RDDs like counting
and saving them persistently on disk.
The partitioning of data can be changed
dynamically to optimize Spark's
performance.
The last element is resilient, and
it's very important because in a large
scale computing environment it is
pretty common to have node failures.
It's very important to be
able to recover from these
situations without losing
any work already done.
For full tolerance in such situations,
Spark tracks the history of each
partition, keeping a lineage
over RDDs over time,
so every point in your calculations,
Spark knows which are the partitions
needed to recreate the partition
in case it gets lost.
And if that happens,
then Spark automatically figures out
where it can start the recompute from and
optimizes the amount of processing
needed to recover from the failure.
Before we create our first Spark program
using RDDs in Pi Spark in the cloud
layer VM,
let's review Spark's architecture.
From a bird's eye view,
Spark has two main components,
a driver program and worker nodes.
The driver program is where
your application starts.
It distributes RDDs on your
computational cluster and
makes sure the transformations and
actions on these RDDs are performed.
Driver programs create
a connection to a Spark cluster or
your local Spark through
a Spark context object.
The default Spark context
in the Spark shell is
an object called SC for Spark context.
For example, in the upcoming reading for
creating word counts in Spark,
we will use SC as the context to
generate RDDs for a text file
using the line of code shown here.
The driver program manages a potentially
large number of nodes called worker nodes.
On a local computer, we can assume
that there's only one worker node and
it is where the Spark operations execute.
A worker node in Spark keeps
a running Java virtual machine,
called JVM commonly, called the executor.
Depending on the illustration,
executor can execute task
related to mapping stages or
reducing stages or
other Spark specific pipelines.
This Java virtual machine is the core
that all the computation is executed,
and this is the interface also to the rest
of the Big Data storage systems and tools.
For example, if we ever had the Hadoop
file system, HTFS, as the storage system,
then on each worker node,
some of the data will be stored locally.
As you know, the most important point
of this computing framework is to bring
the computation to data.
So Spark will send some
computational jobs to be executed
on the data that are already available
on the machine thanks to HDFS.
Data will be read from HDFS and
get processed in memory,
the results will be stored as one RDD.
The actual computation is running
straight in the executor,
that is the JVM that runs your Scala or
Java codes.
Instead, if you are using PySpark
then there will be several Python
processes generally, one for task but
you can configure it depending
on your application.
In a real Big Data scenario, we have many
worker nodes running tasks internally.
It is important to have a system that can
automatically manage provisioning and
restarting of these nodes.
The cluster manager in
Spark has this capability.
Spark currently supports mainly three
interfaces for cluster management,
namely Spark's standalone cluster manager,
the Apache Mesos, and Hadoop YARN.
Standalone means that there's a special
Spark process that takes care of
restarting nodes that are failing or
starting nodes at the beginning
of the computation.
YARN and Mesos are two external research
measures that can be used also for
these purposes.
Choosing a cluster manager
to fit your application and
infrastructure can be quite confusing.
Here, we give you a good
article as a starting point on
how to pick the right cluster manager for
your organization.
To summarize, the Spark architecture
includes a driver program.
The driver program communicates
with the cluster manager for
monitoring and
provisioning of resources and
communicates directly with worker
nodes to submit and execute tasks.
RDDs get created and passed within
transformations running in the executable.
Finally, let's see how this
setup works on the Cloudera VM.
In the Cloudera VM,
we are using Spark in standalone mode and
everything is running locally.
So it's a single machine and on the same
machine we have our driver program,
the executor JVM and
our single PySpark process.
With that, we are ready to start with
our first reading to install Spark and
then running our word count program
using the Spark environment.
After a brief overview of some
of the processing systems
in the Big Data Landscape, it is time for
us to dive deeper into Spark.
Spark was initiated at
UC Berkeley in 2009 and
was transferred to
Apache Software Foundation in 2013.
Since then, Spark has become a top
level project with many users and
contributors worldwide.
After this video, you will be able
to list the main motivations for
the development of Spark,
draw the Spark stack as a layer diagram,
And explain the functionality of
the components in the Spark stack.
As we have discussed in our earlier
discussions, while Hadoop is great for
batch processing using
the MapReduce programming module,
it has shortcomings in a number of ways.
First of all, since it is limited to
Map and Reduce based transformations,
one has to restrict their big data
pipeline to map and reduce steps.
But the number of applications
can be implemented using Map and
Reduce, it's not always possible and
it is often not the most efficient
way to express a big data pipeline.
For example, you might want to do a join
operation between different data sets or
you might want to filter or
sample your data.
Or you might have a more
complicated data pipeline with
several steps including joins and
group byes.
It might have a Map and Reduce face,
but maybe another map face after that.
These types of operations are hard or
impossible to express using MapReduce and
cannot be accommodated by
the MapReduce framework in Hadoop.
Another important bottleneck in
Hadoop MapReduce that is critical for
performance, is that MapReduce relies
heavily on reading data from disc.
This is especially a problem for iterative
algorithms that require taking several
passes through the data using
a number of transformations.
Since each transformation will need
to read its inputs from the disk,
this will end up in a performance
bottleneck due to IO.
Most machine learning pipelines
are in this category,
making Hadoop MapReduce not ideal for
machine learning.
And as I mentioned in the system overview,
the only programming language
that MapReduce provides
a native interface for is Java.
Although, it's possible to run Python code
to implementation for it is more complex
and not very efficient especially when
you are running not with text data, but
with floating point numbers.
The programming language issue
also affects how interactive
the environment is.
Most data scientist
prefer to use scripting
languages due to their
interactive shell capabilities.
Not having such an interface in Hadoop
really makes it difficult to use and
adapt my many in the field.
In addition in the big data
era having support for
streaming data processing is a key for
being able to run similar analysis on
both real time and historical data.
Spark came out of the need to
extend the MapReduce framework
to overcome this shortcomings and
provide an expressive cluster computing
environment that can provide interactive
querying, efficient iterative analytics
and streaming data processing.
So, how does Apache Spark provide
solutions for these problems?
Spark provides a very rich and
expressive programming module that
gives you more than 20 highly efficient
distributed operations or transformations.
Pipe-lining any of these steps in Spark
simply takes a few lines of code.
Another important feature of Spark is
the ability to run these computations
in memory.
It's ability to cache and
process data in memory,
makes it significantly faster for
iterative applications.
This is proven to provide a factor
of ten or even 100 speed-up
in the performance of some algorithms,
especially using large data sets.
Additionally, Spark provides support for
batch and streaming workloads at once.
Last but not least,
Spark provides simple APIs for Python,
Scala, Java and SQL programming
through an interactive shell to
accomplish analytical tasks through both
external and its built-in libraries.
The Spark layer diagram,
also called Stack,
consists of components that build on
top of the Spark computational engine.
This engine distributes and monitors tasks
across the nodes of a commodity cluster.
The components built on top of this
engine are designed to interact and
communicate through this common engine.
Any improvements to
the underlying engine becomes
an improvement in the other components,
thanks to such close interaction.
This also enables building applications
that's span across these different
components like querying data using
Spark SQL and applying machine learning
algorithms, the query results using Sparks
machine learning library and MLlib.
The Spark Core is where
the core capability is
of the Spark Framework are implemented.
This includes support for
distributed scheduling,
memory management and full tolerance.
Interaction with different schedulers,
like YARN and Mesos and
various NoSQL storage systems like
HBase also happen through Spark Core.
A very important part of
Spark Core is the APIs for
defining resilient distributed data sets,
or RDDs for short.
RDDs are the main programming
abstraction in Spark,
which carry data across many computing
nodes in parallel, and transform it.
Spark SQL is the component of Spark
that provides querying structured and
unstructured data through
a common query language.
It can connect to many data sources and
provide APIs to convert
query results to RDDs in Python,
Scala and Java programs.
Spark Streaming is where data
manipulations take place in Spark.
Although, not a native real-time interface
to datastreams, Spark streaming enables
creating small aggregates of data coming
from streaming data ingestion systems.
These aggregate datasets
are called micro-batches and
they can be converted into RDBs in
Spark Streaming for processing.
MLlib is Sparks native library for
machine learning algorithms
as well as model evaluation.
All of the functionality is potentially
ported to any programming language Sparks
supports and
is designed to scale out using Spark.
GraphX is the graph analytics
library of Spark and
enables the Vertex edge data model of
graphs to be converted into RDDs as
well as providing scalable implementations
of graph processing algorithms.
To summarize, through these
layers Spark provides diverse,
scalable interactive management and
analyses of big data.
The interactive shell enables data
scientists to conduct exploratory
analysis and create big data pipelines,
while also enabling the big
data system integration engineers
to scale these analytical pipelines
across commodity computing clusters and
cloud environments.
There are many big data
processing systems, but
how do we make sense of them in order to
take full advantage of these systems?
In this video,
we will review some of them, and
a way to categorize big data processing
systems as we go through our review.
After this video, you will be able
to recall the Hadoop ecosystem,
draw a layer diagram with three layers for
data storage, data processing and
workflow management.
Summarize an evaluation criteria for
big data processing systems and
explain the properties of Hadoop,
Spark, Flink,
Beam, and Storm as major big
data processing systems.
In our introduction to big data course,
we talked about a version of
the layer diagram for the tools
in the Hadoop ecosystem organized
vertically based on the interface.
Lower level interface is the storage and
scheduling on the bottom and
higher level languages and
interactivity at the top.
Most of the tools in the Hadoop ecosystem
are initially built to complement
the capabilities of Hadoop for distributed
filesystem management using HDFS.
Data processing using the MapReduce
engine, and resource scheduling and
negotiation using the YARN engine.
Over time,
a number of new projects were built
either to add to these
complimentary tools or to handle
additional types of big data management
and processing not available in Hadoop.
Arguably, the most important
change to Hadoop over time
was the separation of YARN from
the MapReduce programming model
to solely handle resource
management concerns.
This allowed for Hadoop to be extensible
to different programming models.
And enabled the development of
a number of processing engines for
batch and stream processing.
Another way to look at the vast number of
tools that have been added to the Hadoop
ecosystem, is from the point of view of
their functionality in the big
data processing pipeline.
Simply put, these associate to three
distinct layers for data management and
storage, data processing, and resource
coordination and workflow management.
In our second course,
we talked about the bottom layer
in this diagram in detail,
namely the data management and storage.
While this layer includs Hadoop's HDFS
there are a number of other systems that
rely on HDFS as a file system or implement
their own no SQL storage options.
As big data can have a variety of
structure, semi structured and
unstructured formats, and
gets analyzed through a variety of tools,
many tools were introduced to
fit this variety of needs.
We call these big data management systems.
We reviewed redis and
Aerospike as key value stores,
where each data item is
identified with a unique key.
We got some practical
experience with Lucene and
Gephi as vector and
graph data stores, respectively.
We also talked about Vertica
as a column store database,
where information is stored
in columns rather than rows.
Cassandra and
Hbase are also in this category.
Finally, we introduce Solr and
Asterisk DB for managing unstructured and
semi-structured text, and
mongoDB as a document store.
The processing layer is where these
different varieties of data gets
retrieved, integrated, and analyzed,
which is the primary focus of this class.
In the integration and processing layer
we roughly refer to the tools that
are built on top of the HDFS and YARN,
although some of them work with
other storage and file systems.
YARN is a significant enabler of many of
these tools making a number of batch and
stream processing engines like Storm,
Spark, Flink and being possible.
We will revisit these processing
engines and explain why we have so
many later in this lecture.
This layer also includes tools like Hive,
or Spark SQL, for
bringing a query interface
on top of the storage layer.
Pig, for scripting simple big data
pipelines using the MapReduce framework.
And a number of specialized analytical
libraries for machine learning and
graph analytics, like Giraph as GraphX of
Spark are examples of such libraries for
graph processing.
And Mahout on top of the Hadoop stack and
MLlib of Spark are two options for
machine learning.
Although we have a basic overview of
graph processing and machine learning for
big data analytics later in this course,
we won't go into the details here.
Instead, we will have a dedicated
course on each of them
later in this specialization.
The third and top layer in our diagram is
the coordination and management layer.
This is where integration,
scheduling, coordination, and
monitoring of applications across many
tools in the bottom two layers take place.
This layer is also where the results of
the big data analysis gets communicated to
other programs, websites, visualization
tools, and business intelligence tools.
Workflow management systems help to
develop automated solutions that can
manage and coordinate the process of
combining data management and analytical
tests in a big data pipeline, as
a configurable, structured set of steps.
The workflow driven thinking also
matches this basic process of data
science that we overviewed before.
Oozie is an example of a workflow
scheduler that can interact with
many of the tools in the integration and
processing layer.
Zookeeper is the resource coordination and
monitoring tool and
manages and coordinates all these tools
and middleware named after animals.
Although virtual management is
my personal research area and
I talk more about it in other venues,
in this specialization we focus mainly
on big data integration and processing.
And we will not have a specific
lecture on this layer in this course.
We give you a reading on big data
workflows after this video as
further information and
a starting point for the subject.
In data integration and
processing pipelines,
data goes through a number of operations,
which can apply
a specific function to it, can work
the data from one format to another,
join data with other data sets, or
filter some values out of a data set.
We generally refer to these as
transformations, some of which can also
be specially named aggregations as you
have seen in Amarnath's earlier lectures.
In this video we will reveal some common
transformation operations that we see
in these pipelines, some of which,
we refer to as data parallel patterns.
After this video you will
be able to list common data
transformations within big data pipelines,
and design
a conceptual data processing pipeline
using the basic data transformations.
Simply speaking, transformations
are higher order functions or
tools to convert your data from
one form to another, just like
we would use tools at the wood shop
to transform logs into furniture.
When we look at big data
pipelines used today,
map is probably the most
common transformation we find.
The map operation is one of the basic
building blocks of the big data pipeline.
When you want to apply a process
to each member of a collection,
such as adding 10% bonus to each
person's salary on a given month a map
operation comes in very handy.
It takes your process and
understand that it is required to perform
the same operation or
process to each member of the set.
The figure on the left
here shows the application
of a map function to data
depicted in grey color.
Here colors red, blue, and
yellow are keys to identify each data set.
As you see, each data set is executed
separately even for the same colored key.
The reduce operation helps you then
to collectively apply the same
process to objects of similar nature.
For example, when you want to add your
monthly spending in different categories,
like grocery, fuel, and dining out,
the reduce operation is very useful.
In our figure here on the top left,
we see that data sets in
grey with the same color
are keys grouped together
using a reduced function.
Reds together, blues together,
and yellows together.
It would be a good idea to check out
the Spark word count hands-on to see
how map and reduce can be used
effectively for getting things done.
Map and reduce are types of
transformations that work on a single
list of key and data pairings just
like we see on the left of our figure.
Now let's consider a scenario where
we have two data sets identified
by the same keys just like the two
sets and colors in our diagram.
Many operations have such needs where
we have to look at all the pairings of
all key value pairs,
just like crossing two matrices.
For a practical example
Imagine you have two teams,
a sales team with two people, and
an operations team with four people.
In an event you would want each
person to meet every other person.
In this case, a cross product, or
a cartesian product, becomes a good
choice for organizing the event and
sharing each pairs' meeting location and
travel time to them.
In a cross or cartesian product operation,
each data partition gets
paired with all other data partitions,
regardless of its key.
This sometimes gets
referred to as all pairs.
Now add to the cross product by
just grouping together the data
partitions with the same key,
just like the red data.
And the yellow data partitions here.
This is a typical match or join operation.
As we see in the figure here, match
is very similar to the cross product,
except that it is more
selective in forming pairs.
Every pair must have something in common.
This something in common is
usually referred to as a key.
For example,
each person in your operations team and
sales team is assigned
to a different product.
You only want those people to meet
who are working on the same product.
In this case your key is product.
And you can perform and
match operation and
send e-mails to those people
who share a common product.
The number of e-mails is likely to be less
than when you performed a cartesian or
a cross product, therefore reducing
the cost of the operation.
In a match operation, only the keys
with data in both sets get joined,
and become a part of the final
output of the transformation.
Now let's consider listing
the data sets with all the keys,
even if they don't exist in both sets.
Consider a scenario where you
want to do brainstorming sessions
of people from operations and sales, and
get people who work on the same
products in the same rooms.
A co-group operation will do this for you.
You give it a product name
as they key to work with and
the two tables, the sales team and
operations team.
The co-group will create groups
which contain team members
working on common products even if a
product doesn't exist in one of the sets.
The last operation we will
see is the filter operation.
Filter works much like a test
where only elements that pass
a test are shown in the output.
Consider as a set that contains teams and
a number of members in their teams.
If your game requires people to pair up,
you may want to select teams which
have an even number of members.
In this case, you can create a test
that only passes the teams which have
an even number of team members shown as
divided by 2 with 0 in the remainder.
The real effectiveness of the basic
transformation we saw here
is in pipelining them in a way that
helps you to solve your specific
problem just as you would perform
a series of tasks on a real block
of wood to make a fine piece of
woodwork that you can use to steer your
ship, which in this case is
your business or research.
Now that we revealed all three layers,
we are ready to come back to
the Integration and Processing layer.
Just a simple Google search for
Big Data Processing Pipelines
will bring a vast number of pipelines
with large number of technologies
that support scalable data cleaning,
preparation, and analysis.
How do we make sense of it all to
make sure we use the right tools for
our application?
We will continue our lecture to review
a set of evaluation criteria for
these systems and some of the big data
processing systems based on this criteria.
Depending on the resources we have access
to and characteristics of our application,
we apply several
considerations to evaluate and
pick a software stack for big data.
Of these, first one we consider
is the Execution Model,
and the expressivity of it to support for
various transformations of batch or
streaming data, or
sometimes interactive computing.
Semantics of streaming,
including exactly once or
at least one processing for each event, or
being able to keep the state of the data,
is an important concern for
this execution model.
Latency is another important criteria,
depending on the application.
Having a low latency system
is very important for
applications like online gaming and
hazards management.
Whereas most applications
are less time critical,
like search engine indexing, and would
be fine with a batch processing ability.
Scalability for both small and
large datasets and different
analytical methods and algorithms,
is also an important evaluation criteria.
As well as support for
different programming language
of the libraries used by the analytical
tools that we have access to.
Finally, while all big data
tools provide fault tolerance,
the mechanics of how the fault tolerance is
handled is an important issue to consider.
Let's review five of
the big data processing
engines supported by the Apache Foundation
using this evaluation criteria.
The MapReduce implementation of
Hadoop provides a batch execution
model where the data from HDFS gets
loaded into mappers before processing.
There is no in-memory processing support,
meaning the mappers write the data on
files before the reducers can read it,
resulting in a high-latency and
less scalable execution.
This also hinders
the performance of iterative and
interactive applications that require many
steps of transformations using MapReduce.
Although the only native
programming interface for
MapReduce is in Java, other programming
languages like Python provide modules or
libraries for Hadoop MapReduce
programming, however with less efficiency.
Data replication is the primary
method of fault tolerance,
which in turn affects the scalability and
execution speed further.
Spark was built to support iterative and
interactive big data processing
pipelines efficiently using an in-memory
structure called Resilient Distributed
Datasets, or shortly, RDDs.
In addition to map and reduce operations,
it provides support for
a range of transformation
operations like join and filter.
Any pipeline of transformations can
be applied to these RDD's in-memory,
making Spark's performance very high for
iterative processing.
The RDD extraction is also designed
to handle fault tolerance with
less impact on performance.
In addition to HDFS,
Spark can read data from many storage
platforms and it provides support for
streaming data applications using
a technique called micro-batching.
Its latency can be on the order of
seconds depending on the batch size,
which is relatively slower compared
to native streaming platforms.
Spark has support for a number of
programming languages, including Scala and
Python as the most popular ones,
as well as built-in libraries for
graph processing and machine learning.
Although Flink has very
similar transformations and
in-memory data extractions with Spark,
it provides direct support for
streaming data,
making it a lower-latency framework.
It provides connection interfaces to
streaming data ingestion engines like
Kafka and Flume.
Flink supports application
programming interfaces in Java and
Scala just like Spark.
Starting with it's original
version called Stratosphere,
Flink had it's own execution engine
called Nephele, and had an ability
to run both on Hadoop and also separately
in its own execution environment.
In addition to map and reduce,
Flink provides abstractions for
other data parallel database
patterns like join and group by.
One of the biggest advantage of using
Flink comes from it's optimizer
to pick and apply the best pattern and
execution strategy.
There has been experiments comparing
fault tolerance features of Flink
to those of Sparks, which conclude
that Sparks slightly better for Spark.
The Beam system, from Google,
is a relatively new system for
batch and stream processing with
a data flow programming model.
It initially used Google's own Cloud data
flow as an execution environment, but
Spark and Flink backends for
it have been implemented recently.
It's a low-latency environment with
high reviews on fault tolerance.
It currently provides application
programming interfaces in Java and
Scala, and a Python SDK is in the works.
SDK means software development kit.
Beam provides a very strong streaming and
windowing framework for streaming data.
And it is highly scalable and reliable,
allowing it to make trade-off
decisions between accuracy,
speed, and cost of processing.
Storm has been designed for
stream processing in real
time with very low-latency.
It defined input stream interface
abstractions called spouts, and
computation abstractions called bolts.
Spouts and bolts can be pipelined
together using a data flow approach.
That data gets queued until
the computation acknowledges
the receipt of it.
A master node tracks running jobs and
ensures all data is processed
by the computations on workers.
Nathan Mars, the lead developer for
Storm, built the Lambda Architecture
using Storm for stream processing and
Hadoop MapReduce for batch processing.
The Lambda Architecture
originally used Storm for
speed layer and Hadoop and
HBase for batch and
serving layers, as seen in this diagram.
However, it was later used as a more
general framework that can combine
the results of stream and batch processing
executed in multiple big data systems.
This diagram shows a generalized Lambda
Architecture containing some of the tools
we discussed earlier, including using
Spark for both batch and speed layers.
In this course, we picked Spark
as a big data integration and
processing environment since it supports
most of our evaluation criteria.
And this hybrid data processing
architecture using built-in data querying,
streaming, and analytical libraries.
We will continue our discussion with
Spark and hands-on exercises in Spark.