Open XC is an open source hardware-software platform.
We wanted to see what correlations we could actually create within this model dashboards.
It plugs into your car, and it gives you all the data that you can possibly want.
What we're interested in is looking at how you
can make the car much more modular and customizable,
getting a lot of this data and afford cars
out and letting developers do whatever they want with it.
You could kind of like update technology as technology progresses.
So what we're really trying to do is like catch up with
the consumer electronics design cycle not the automotive design cycle types.
The clock hasn't started yet.
One of the tests that we did was a gas car versus an electric car.
So we're trying to see which is faster,
which is expecting the most energy,
which is the most cost efficient.
And we wanted to
measure doesn't electric car driver drive different than a gas car driver.
So actually by using the Open XC data,
and by splunking that creating links in
dashboards will give it to match ups and correlations.
It all comes down to how much are they mashing the gas.
We've been internally calling that dashboard the "Lead Foot Dashboard".
Who's the most efficient driver?
There's one of our drivers actually going low and
slow and actually using into the brakes not really gnashing on the gas,
and driving more like a normal person would.
When you drive an electric car, it's a lot quicker off the line than a gas powered car.
So, we find people kind of smashing
on the gas pedal but sort of easing up on the electric pedal.
So I've got some data for you here.
We see. What's this I'm doing?
It says you're doing.
There we go.
Battery car is high. There you go.
Hurry up.
There we go. We don't even need because Open XC, We just cut it.
These are basically all of
the sensor readings that are being broadcast from that Firefly box.
It's plugged into the diagnostics port of the car.
It's about how much power can we kind of give
away in order to incentivize a community of makers.
We want to be able to actually harness that and create
an environment where they can much more quickly,
experiment with our ideas,
enrich the platform in general,
make our vehicles in that sense more valuable.
In this hands on activity,
we will be performing queries in Splunk.
First, we will open a browser and
login to Splunk.
Next, we will import a CSV file and
search its contents.
We will see how to filter fields for
specific values and
also perform statistical
calculations on the data.
Let's begin.
First, open a web browser and
navigate to the Splunk web page.
We'll enter localhost:8000.
Next we'll log in to Splunk using
admin and the default password.
Next, we'll import a CSV file into Splunk.
We'll click on Add Data.
Upload We'll click on Select File.
And we'll choose the census.csv
file that we downloaded.
Click Next.
On the left,
it should say source type csv.
If it does not, click on the button and
go down to Structured and select csv.
In this table,
we see a preview of the data.
You should see the column names
of the CSV file at the top.
Click on Next.
Review.
And Submit.
Now that the file has been imported
successfully, click on Start Searching.
In the search box,
it fills in the default query,
source="cencus.csv" the host name and
sourcetype="csv"
We could change these fields
to search other files or
other data types if we
imported those into Splunk.
Now let's search census.csv for
particular values in the fields.
Let's search for all the data
where the state is California.
We'll enter STNAME="California".
You'll see the results down here.
You could search for
other states by using or.
For example, we can add OR
STNAME="Alaska".
This will search for
state names equal to California or Alaska.
We can add conditions
to our query as well.
Let's search for state equals California
whose population was over one million.
We'll do this by saying
STNAME = "California"
CENSUS2010POP > 1000000.
Can limit the results to one or
more columns.
You do this by adding pipe table
CTYNAME to the end of our query.
In Spunk queries, the pipe command is used
to send the outputs from the first part of
the query into the next.
You can also show more than
one column from the output.
If we add a comma CENSUS2010POP
to the end of this,
we'll see both the city name and
the population.
You can also see a visualization of this
data by clicking on the Visualization tab.
At the bottom, on the x-axis,
we see the county names, and
the y values are the population numbers.
Now let's perform some
statistics on this data.
We'll begin by counting the number of
records where the state is California.
You can do this by saying
STNAME="California" pipe stats count.
Now switch back to the statistics tab,
see the result here
Now let's see the total population for
California.
You can replace count
with sum(CENUS2010POP)
You can also calculate
the average population.
We'll replace sum with mean.
Hello, My name is Mitch Fleichmann,
senior instructor here at Splunk.
Today we are going to
install Splunk on Linux.
I'm using one of
the Splunk Education Linux servers.
Let's examine the environment.
First of all,
notice I'm logged in as the user splunker.
As a best practice,
do not install Splunk as the root user.
I'm currently in the /opt directory,
where I've already downloaded
the tarball from splunk.com/download for
this platform.
As a final check, let's check the system
to make sure we have the correct operating
system and kernel.
This is indeed a Linux machine, let's
get confirmation that it is also 64 bit.
So we are good to go.
The next step is to unzip and
untar the installer and
that we can do with the gunzip and
tar commands.
When everything untucks, you'll notice
a new sub directory created named splunk.
And we can navigate to the splunk/bin
directory to start up Splunk.
Couple of ways to start
Splunk with no switches.
On the first startup, you'll be prompted
to read and agree to the software license.
Or as a shortcut, you can start
up Splunk and accept the license.
And notice a couple of port numbers
being grabbed, port 8000 for
splunk web and port 8089 for
splunk management.
The splunk daemon has started.
Splunk is generating its own keys.
And we can see the splunk web interface,
the URL.
As a best practice,
you may also want to consider automating
splunk to start when the machine boots.
That you can do as the root user.
By issuing the splunk enable command,
enable boot-start as the -user splunker,
the same user that we
just consult splunk with.
So lets log in to splunk web and
see how the system looks.
And for that we'll go back to the browser.
Go to the appropriate URL.
And we can see upon first login,
you are prompted to login with
the credentials admin, password changeme.
Since this is the first login,
you also coach to change your
password to something more secure.
And it's highly recommended to
follow this best practice as well.
And also on first connection,
you'll also see a splash screen
showing you what's new in version 6.
In this case, Powerful Analytics.
Some changes to the UI to
make it more intuitive.
Simplified component management for
cluster management,
folder management and so on.
Also a richer developer experience.
Close down this window and
you can explore the navigation options.
And notice in the left side,
you see a panel showing you
the apps to navigate to and manage.
And on the right side, you see some
panel showing you data in the system and
various links for help.
Let's go to the search and
reporting app by clicking here.
And you can see the search far up top,
some tips on how to search and
then data to search.
Since this is a fresh install,
there is no data to search, so
the next step is to index data and
begin searching.
Good luck.
[SOUND] Hello, this is Chris Busheers,
part of the Splunk education team.
In this video, I'll show you how
install Splunk onto a Window's server.
First we need to get the software
from the splunk.com download page.
We will need to select that
the platform is 32 or 64-bit.
If you aren't sure if your system is 32 or
64-bit, you can check
your system properties.
As you can see, this server is 64-bit,
so we can install that version.
If we saw a system type of 32-bit,
we would download the 32-bit version.
We run the installer by
double clicking on it.
There is button to view the license
agreement, and a check box to accept it.
At this point we can either install
Splunk with the defaults, or
customize our installation.
Let's click on the customize options
to see what settings can be selected.
The first option is to change
the installation location of Splunk.
We are fine with this location,
so we click Next.
Now we must choose what account type
to install Splunk as, Local System or
Domain Account.
A Local System account will allow
Splunk to access all data on, or
forwarded, to this machine.
A Domain Account will allow
you to collect logs and
metrics from remote machines as
well as local and forwarded data.
You are required to provide a Domain
Account with the proper domain rights
to use this type.
Local System works well for
us, so we click Next.
We can select to have a shortcut to Splunk
added, and click Install to continue.
[MUSIC]
Once installed, we can select to have
Splunk launch, and click Finish.
This Splunk web interface
opens in our default browser.
We enter the default user name of admin,
and a password of change made.
A dialog box appears asking
us to change our password.
It is always best practice to do this.
Once logged in, we are taken to
the Splunk launcher homepage.
And that's all it takes to get
Splunk installed on Windows.
Now dig in, and start exploring.
[SOUND]
Our third and
final case is applicable to most companies
that create customer-focused products.
They want to understand how their
customers are responding to the products,
how the product marketing
efforts are performing,
what kind of problems customers
are encountering, and what new features or
feature improvements the customers
are seeking, and so forth.
But how does the company
get this information?
What kind of data sources
would carry this information?
The figure show some of these sources.
They are in focused user surveys,
emails sent by the customers, in blogs and
product review forums, specialized
groups on social media and user forums.
In short, they are on the Internet or
in material received through the Internet.
Now, how many sources are there?
Two.
The number would vary.
A new sites, a new postings, and
new discussion threads
would come up all the time.
In all of these,
the goal is to identify information that
truly relates to the companies product,
its features and its utility.
To cast this as a type
of big data problem,
we look at a task that computer
scientists called Data Fusion.
Consider a set of data sources, S,
as we mentioned on the last slide and
a set of data items, D.
A data item represents a particular
aspect of a real world entity
which in our case is
a product of the company.
For each data item, a source can, but
not necessarily will, provide a value.
For example,
the usability of an ergonomically
split keyboard can have a value good.
The value can be atomic,
like good, or a set, or a list or
sometimes embedded in the string.
For example, the cursor sometimes
freezes when using the touchpad,
is a string which has
a value about the touchpad.
The goal of Data Fusion is to find
the values of Data Items from a source.
In many cases, the system would find
a unique true value of an item.
For example, the launch data of a product
in Europe should be the same true value
regardless of the data
source one looks at.
In other cases, we could find
a value distribution of an item.
For example, the usability of our
keyboard may have a value distribution.
That's with Data Fusion, we should be
able to collect the values of real world
items from a subset of data sources.
It is a subset because
not all Data Sources
will have relevant information
about the Data Item.
There are some other versions
of what a Data Fusion is but for
our purposes we'll stick with
this general description.
Now one obvious problem with the Internet
is that there are too many data
sources at any time,
these lead to many difficulties.
First, it is to be understood
that with too many data sources
there will be many values for
the same item.
Often these will differ and
sometimes they will conflict.
A standard technique in this case
is to use a voting mechanism.
However, even a voting
mechanism can be complex
due to problems with the data source.
One of the problems is to estimate
the trustworthiness of the source.
For each data source,
we need to evaluate whether it's reporting
some basic or known facts correctly.
If a source mentions details
about a rainbow colored iPhone,
which does not exist,
it's trustworthiness reduces
because of the falsity of
the provided value of this data item.
Accordingly, a higher vote count can be
assigned to a more trustworthy source.
And then, this can be used in voting.
The second aspect is Copy Detection.
Detecting weather once was has copied
information from another can be very
important for
detail fusion task in customer analytics.
If a source has copied information,
it's such that discounted vote count
can be assigned to a copy value and
voting that means the copy in
source will have less weight.
Now this is especially relevant when we
compute value distributions, because if we
treat copies as genuine information, we
will statistically bias the distribution.
Now here is active research on how to
detect copies, how to determine bias and
then arrive at a statistically sound
estimation of value distribution.
But to our knowledge, these methods are
yet to be applied to existing software for
big data integration.
It should be very clear by now but
there are two kinds of big data
situations when it comes to information.
The first two uses cases that we
saw requires an integration system
to consider all sources because
the application demand so.
In contrast, problems where data comes
from too many redundant, potentially
unreliable sources like the Internet, the
best results can be obtained if we have
a way of evaluating the worthiness of
sources before information integration.
But this problem is
called Source Selection.
The picture on the right shows the result
of a cost benefit analysis for
data fusion.
The x-axis indicates the number
of sources used, and
the y-axis measures the proportion
of true results that were returned.
We can clearly see that the plot peaks
around six-to-eight sources, and
that the efficiency falls
as more sources are added.
In a cost benefit analysis,
the cost must include both the human and
the computational costs,
while the benefit is a function of
the accuracy of the fusion result.
The technique for
solving this problem comes from economics.
Assuming that cost and
benefits are measure in the same unit, for
example, dollars.
They proposed to continue
selecting sources
until the marginal benefit is
less than the marginal cost.
Now recent techniques were performing
this computation at quite scalable.
In one setting,
selecting the most beneficial sources
from a total of one million
sources took less than one hour.
This completes our coverage of
the big data integration problems.