So we have seen how to compute
degree histograms of a graph.
While degree histograms are useful
to characterize a graph,
it is usually a means to an end.
It's a known practice in statistics to
compute a mathematical expression for
a statistical distribution
Using histograms.
For graphs, we often look for a function
to describe the degree distribution.
But this is expressed as
a distribution of the probability
that a random vertex will
have exactly k neighbors.
Now, this problem has been
investigated by many.
One popular, well known model,
is a Power Law.
A graph follows a Power Law if,
the best probability is given by k,
erased to a negative
exponent called alpha.
The value of alpha, for many practical
networks, is between two and three.
More recently,
people have suggested other distributions
that look like the power law graph.
One of them is a log-normal graph.
Here, the logarithm of k has
a Gaussian distribution.
So this log-normal distribution
seems to have the better fit to
natural graphs that are observed.
So, why are power law graphs important?
Interestingly, many very,
very different real life graphs in
the world seem to follow the power law.
If a graph does follow the power law, it
would have one large connected component
with a very high proportion of notes
connected to it In a power law graph,
most nodes have a low degree and
some nodes will be disconnected.
The low degree nodes belong to
a very dense sub graphs and
those sub graphs are connected
to each other through hubs.
In the center of the graph
has a high density,
power law graphs can be
difficult to compute with.
For example, the shortest path
algorithm operating in the dense part
will possibly be very inefficient, not
because of the size of the network, but
because there are too many paths to
explore inside the denser pieces.
The more interesting reason why
people study power-law graphs
is because power-law graphs
are supposed to be robust.
So in nature, all biological networks
show power-law graphs because
It gives you a high rate of redundancy
against failure and attacks.
The most primitive path analytics
question one can ask is to find the best
path from node one to node two.
What does best mean?
Well, that depends on the actual
needs of the application.
But in general, to specify the best path,
we need to define when one
path is better than another.
This is usually expressed in
terms of an optimization problem.
Where we need to minimize and maximize
our subfunction subject to constraints.
What kind of constraints?
Two common criteria for graphs are,
inclusion and exclusion conditions.
Inclusion criteria may specify which
nodes we have to include in the path.
And exclusion criteria
specifies which nodes and
edges should be excluded from the path.
In addition,
one specify a preference criteria
that act as a softer or
less strict constraint.
For example, we would like to
minimize highways on my trip.
Or avoid condition.
These are soft because although
the users would like to have them
enforced completely, it is all right
if they are not fully enforced.
A good practical use case occurs when I'm
trying to drive to work in the morning.
Ideally, I would like to take a path
having the shortest distance from my home.
For example, node I, to my workplace,
which is node B in the graph.
But I have to drop off my son at school.
So my path must include his school,
the J here.
However, I would like to avoid roads
around the new construction that's
happening about five miles from my
workplace, like the node E in the graph.
Because there is usually a huge traffic
delay around that construction site.
I could also add
a preference criteria like
I don't prefer to drive on the highway.
But for this discussion,
we'll skip the preference idea.
Too complicated?
Okay, let's start with a simpler problem.
To start with, let's drop the constraints
and look at the problem with just
the optimization part of the problem,
having a single variable.
In our case, that variable is the sum
of edge weights from the source,
that is the starting node I,
to the target, which is B.
This problem is handled by all mapping and
road direction software.
Here is a Google map screenshot,
in which I am trying to go from my home
in North San Diego,
to a collision center in a nearby city.
Google Maps shows three different routes,
and
highlights one as a preferred solution.
You should readily see that the real
shortest path of 26.6 miles
will take the longest time at the time of
the day when I was looking at the map.
So this means the weights here are not
raw distances but estimated travel time.
You should also notice the blue, red, and
orange segments in the preferred
path are presented by Google.
The orange and red street segments
clearly represent congestion areas and
therefore have higher weight
than the blue segments.
Therefore, the weights of the street
segments are not really static but
change with many other factors,
like weather or the time of the day.
This is why the least weight path problem
is an important problem to solve for
the benefit of the commuter.
A widely applied algorithm
that is applied for
shortest path problems is
called Dijkstra's algorithm.
Originally, Dijkstra considered a variant
of the problem where the task is
to find the shortest path from a single
source node to all other nodes.
We'll go through the algorithm here.
However, there are many good online
resources including tutorials and
YouTube videos describing the algorithm.
For our discussion, we'll confine
ourselves to the case where both
the source and
the target nodes are known in advance.
As you probably already know, Cypher is
the scripting language used in Neo4j and
it's what we have been using
already in the previous lectures.
In this lecture, we're going to go through
a series of basic queries using Cypher
with the focus on the data sets
that we've already been using.
Here's a listing of the basic queries
we will go through step by step.
So let's get started.
To keep things simple we will be using a
text file containing the basic queries and
we'll make this file available for
download as a reading in the module.
I will briefly review the queries and
then we'll toggle to the browser to view
the results of the queries in Neo4j.
Neo4j has a very nice feature which
allows us to retain individual queries
in multiple panels as we're going through
the process of exploring each query.
So for the first few queries we'll be
using the simple road network data set
that we used in previous demonstrations.
And here we've already loaded
the data set into Neo4j.
So let's look at our first query.
Our first query is a very a simple one,
in which we're counting the number
of nodes in the network.
So the first line of code simply matches
all of the nodes with the label MyNode and
it returns a count of those nodes.
So let's look at the results.
The results are very simple,
the value of eleven.
And we can visually confirm this
by inspecting the graph itself and
see it has 11 nodes and
we can see that up here.
The next query is almost as simple,
we want to count the number of edges.
Now, first thing to keep in mind
is in order to count edges,
we also need to declare nodes that
are associated with those edges.
So this first line of codes
includes a declaration
of the nodes associated with the edges.
Here we're identifying
with thevariable r and
then we're returning
a count of those edges.
So let's take a look in Neo4j and the
results of this query are a value of 14.
And once again we can confirm this
visually by looking at our network and
counting the number of edges.
The next query involves finding all
of the leaf nodes in the network.
Now as you may remember
from a previous lecture,
leaf nodes are defined as those
nodes which have no outgoing edges.
Notice that we're returning the node
represented by the variable M,
which is the target node in this query.
So here we're matching all nodes
associated with edges having the label two
and we want to place
a constraint on those nodes,
such that they have no outgoing edges.
And then we return all those nodes.
So let's take a look at the results.
We're going to see a single node returned,
the node with the label p.
And if we inspect our graph, we can
see over here on the right the node p,
and sure enough it has no outgoing edges,
only one incoming edge.
The next query is also similar,
we're looking for
root nodes instead of leaf notes.
And as you may also remember,
root nodes are defined as a node
which has no incoming edges.
You may notice that this segment of
the first line of code is sort of a mirror
image of the same segment in the first
line of code from the previous query.
We also want to place the constraint
on the nodes that we want to return
by specifying that they can
have no incoming edges.
And then, we return all of those nodes
When we look at our results in Neo4j.
Once again,
we see we only get a single node
return it's the node with the label H.
And if we inspect our graph,
we see over here the node H and
sure enough it has no incoming edges.
Only a single outgoing edge which
means it's a root node of the network.
The next query can be described
as a pattern matching query.
We're looking for a pattern that
we're describing as triangles.
This is a pattern that's
a bit more complex than
the patterns we've been looking for
in our previous queries.
A triangle can also be described as a
three cycle, consisting of three nodes and
three edges where the beginning and
end node are the same.
So here we're matching a node A which
goes through an edge to node B
which goes through a second
edge to a second node C and
through a third edge back
to the original node A.
And then we return all of those notes.
Let's look at our results.
And here we see we have five
distinct nodes returned.
And we have two triangles or
two three cycles.
From D to E to G and from D to C to B.
Finally the last query we're going
to execute with this data set,
is going to explore the neighborhood
of a particular node.
In this case, the node with the label d.
And we're going to be looking for
what we're calling second neighbors of D.
This means nodes that
are two nodes away from d.
So the first line of code matches
all nodes that are two nodes away
from a specific node.
And then the second line of codes
specifies the actual node that we
we want to consider by constraining
its name to have the label d,
and then we return those nodes.
And here we're using the command distinct
because we want to make sure that we
don't return any duplicate nodes.
All of our nodes must be unique.
So let's look at the results.
And here we have a network that
consists of nine nodes and 11 edges and
we can see that each node is
two nodes away from the node D.
Some nodes appear to be only one
node away from the node D but
we can get to those nodes indirectly
through another node, which means that
they're not only a first neighbor but
they're also a second neighbor.
So we encourage you to play
around with these queries,
and make minor changes with them,
and see what the results might be.
For our next three queries,
we're going to switch to the terrorist
data set that we had used in
our previous demonstration.
Our first query involves finding
the types of a particular node.
So, as you may recall in the terrorist
data set there were node types
corresponding to a country.
So, in this case we
want to match all nodes,
where the name is equal to Afghanistan.
And we will return the labels for
that particular match.
And the results for
this query are relatively simple.
The label for the node named Afghanistan
is country, as you might expect.
Next, we're going to do something
similar but with an edge.
In this case, we want to find the label
of a edge associated with
a node named Afghanistan.
And also, if you can recall from that
particular network, the label for
an edge associated with a country named
Afghanistan would be an IS_FROM label.
And the final query, we would like to
demonstrate with this terrorist data set,
involves finding all of
the properties of a node.
Now, based on how we defined
our data import script,
we defined all of our
nodes to be of type Actor.
So in this query, we're going to
search for all nodes of type Actor and
then, we're going to return all of the
properties associated with those nodes.
But, since there are thousands of nodes,
we're going to limit
the results to the first 20.
So, let's go ahead and submit our query.
And here are the results.
Each node represents a terrorist and
if we look at the rows data
behind the scenes we can see the various
properties associated with each node.
Each node has a name.
Each node has aliases,
one or more aliases.
And they have a type property.
Now, depending on how we defined our
import script in the first place,
these nodes could have
different types of properties.
In this case, we only defined them
to have three different properties.
For our next two queries,
we're going to use a different data set,
it's a biological data set consisting
of genetics data representing
interactions between genes.
We will be providing the data for
you to download.
In fact, there are two separate data sets.
One is a complete data set
consisting of 250,000 rows,
and the other data set consists
of the first 50,000 rows,
and that's what we'll be using for
this demonstration.
So, let's take a look at
a small sample of the data.
Here you see a graph network
in which each node is a gene.
And each edge represents
the association between genes.
To load this data set, this is the smaller
data set, required 1446 seconds,
and it consists of 9656 labels and
46621 relationships.
So, the first query involves finding
loops in the data which represent genes
that have associations
with there own types.
So, it's a very simple query
in which the source node and
the target node are the same and we'll
be returning those along the edges and
we'll limit our results to the first ten.
So, here are the results of our query.
We can see a few different loops.
If we look at the rows, our query returned
not only the node but the edge type.
So, on the left we see the particular
gene and on the right,
we see the type of association.
And there are a range of different types.
So, this data set also
contains multigraphs.
If you recall from a previous lecture,
the definition of a multigraph
is any two nodes which have two or
more edges between them.
So in this case, we'll be matching
two separate node edge relationships.
And we'll apply a constraint in which
the edges must be different for
the same pairs of nodes.
And then we will return those nodes and
those edges.
We'll limit our results to the first ten.
And here's the results.
Here we see a set of four genes, and
there are two pairs that have three
edges between them and another pair
that has four edges between them.
Our final query addresses something that
is not necessarily been fully covered
in previous lectures, but
it is useful enough to address here and
you'll get an understanding of it by
going through this query example.
We're going to essentially
extract a subset of nodes and
edges from the graph that
we've been working with.
And this is called an induced subgraph.
In which, if we provide a set of nodes,
we want to return
the network that consists only of those
nodes and their associated edges.
So, my first line of code is very
familiar, we're matching nodes and
edges, it's a very basic node and
edge match.
The second line of code is where
the constraints are explicitly stated.
A resulting network must consist
of edges in which the source node
must be constrained to this
subset of node labels.
And the target node must also be
constrained to be a part of the subset of
nodes with just these labels.
And then we return the nodes and
the edges.
So, let's see the resulting graph.
And here it is.
So, as we would expect,
we're seeing the five nodes that were
defined in our query constraints.
And the edges corresponding to them,
retain the network structure.
So, this concludes our review of
some of the basic queries you can do
with Neo4j using the cipher
scripting language.
Next, we will talk about
connectivity analytics with Cypher.
If you remember in module two,
we talked about connectivity analytics
in terms of network robustness.
In other words, a measure of how resistant
a graph network is to being disconnected.
Specifically, we used
two kinds of methods.
One computed the eigenvalues, and the
second computed the degree distribution.
For these examples, we're going to use
the second one, degree distributions.
And we will use the same graph
network we've used previously.
A simple graph representing
a road network.
And here's a listing of the query examples
we're going to be applying to our network.
My first query example finds all
of the outdegrees of all nodes.
Now, if you'll notice, this query consists
of two parts, because there's a specific
type of node, a leaf node, which does not
conform to this particular constraint.
So our first match statement finds
all nodes with outgoing edges,
as you can see here,
this is a directed edge.
And then,
we returns the names of the nodes and
the count as the variable outdegree.
And for convenience,
we order by outdegree.
And we need to combine that with
a specific query dealing with leaf nodes.
We're familiar with how to
do that from past examples.
And so, we'll match all leaf nodes and
return the name and
the value zero for its outdegree.
So when we submit this query we
get this listing right here.
The node P has 0 for its outdegree and
all of the other nodes are as we might
expect and they're ordered
by their value of outdegree.
Our next query finds
the indegree of all nodes,
which is very similar to
our previous example.
But, in this case, as you might expect,
we're going to take into account
root nodes instead of leaf nodes.
And so, our match involves incoming edges.
Indegree is a measure of all nodes
connected to a specific node with
incoming edges.
And we return similar results and
we union that with the specific query
commands to find all of the root nodes,
and then we return those names and
0 as the value of indegree.
So when we submit this query,
here's our results as we might expect.
In this case, H is our only root node.
So it has a value of 0 for indegree, and
all the other nodes
are as we might expect.
And our third query example
finds the degree of all nodes,
which is a combination of outdegree and
indegree.
So in this case we're not including any
specific direction in our match statement.
And we're returning the name and
the count for all of our edges.
But we're using the distinct statement,
otherwise we would be
counting some nodes twice.
And then, for convenience,
we order this by the value of degree.
And when we submit this query,
we get the results as shown here.
We have 1 column with the name and
the other column with the degree and
the values are as we would expect, we have
a leaf node P with the degree of 1 and
a root node H with a degree of 1.
Our next query example generates a degree
histogram of the graph since we're able to
calculate the degree of each node, we can
sort those into actual values of degree.
So if we look at the distribution
of degree among our nodes,
we see there's 2 nodes with the degree 1,
there's 3 nodes with degree 2,
there's 4 nodes with degree 3, and
there's 2 nodes with degree 4.
So we're going to group those
in the form of a histogram.
So when we submit this query,
we get this table.
The first column list the degree
value in ascending order and
the second column list the counts of
the nodes that have that degree value.
So for those of you who are familiar with
SQL you might recognize this as similar
to the group by command,
it performs a similar function
Our next query example saves the degree
of the node as a new node property.
This provides an added convenience so that
we don't have to calculate the degree of
a node every time we're
performing some sort of analysis.
So we match all nodes with edges, and
there's no direction in this
particular edge definition.
And then, we return distinct
counts of each node's degree, and
then we create a new property, called deg,
and assign the value of degree to it.
Then, we return the names and
the degree values, and so
when we submit this query,
we see this distribution right here,
with the names in the left column, and
the values of degree in the right column.
And we can verify that if we issue a
command to return all of the properties of
the specific node.
So in this case I issued a command
to match the node named D and
return all of its properties.
And sure enough we see that it has
a property name and a property degree.
Before we go to the last two examples,
there's a philosophical issue that we
need to remember with all databases.
Every database will allow you some
analytical computation and the remainder
of the analytical computations must
be done outside of the database.
However, it is always a judicious
idea to get the database to
achieve an intermediate result formatted
in a way that you would need for
the next computation.
And then, you use that intermediate result
as the input to the next computation.
We've seen that a number of
computations in graph analytics
start with the adjacency matrix.
So we should be able to force Cypher
to produce an adjacency matrix.
And this is what we're doing here.
So think of a Matrix as a three column
table, in which, here's one column,
here's another column, and the third
column will be the values that we
are calculating when we determine whether
two nodes have an edge between them.
And we're introducing a new
construct in Cypher called case.
This allows us to evaluate conditions and
return one result, or
a different result
depending on the condition.
Here, we're specifying that when
there is an edge between nodes n and
m, then we return a value of 1,
otherwise return a value of 0.
And we'll output those results as a value.
And so, when we submit this query,
we get our three column table in which
the first column is
the name of our first node.
The second column is the name of our
second node and the value is either a 1 or
a 1 depending on whether the nodes
have an edge between them.
So in this case we see node A and
C have an edge,
A and L have an edge and
so on as we would expect.
So if we can calculate the adjacency
matrix then we can calculate any matrix.
You might remember from our
module two lecture where we
learned about this complex structure
called the Normalized Laplacian Matrix.
So let's go ahead and calculate that.
We'll perform something very similar
to what we did in the previous example.
We'll match all nodes for
the first column, and all nodes for
the second column.
We'll return the names of those nodes and
then we'll use the case structure again
to compare the names of each node and
determine whether we have the same node.
If we do have the same node then
that is a diagonal of the matrix and
should get a value of 1.
If they are different nodes and
contain an edge between them,
then we calculate the normalized
Laplacian with this equation here.
And you'll also want to notice that here
we're using the actual degree property
that we assigned to the nodes
in a previous example.
This is an example of how that
can become a convenient option.
So when the calculation is performed,
the value would be returned.
If there's no edge between the 2 nodes,
then the value of 0 will be returned.
And these values will end
up in the value column.
So when we submit this query,
here's the table that get returned.
This is the first column
with the source node.
The second column with the target node and
the values.
So in the first row, the first node
is P and the second node is P, so
it's identical, which means it's
on the diagonal of the matrix.
Likewise, for A in this row down here.
And then the first value of the Laplacian
is calculated between nodes A and
C, and so on.
So that concludes our examples of how
to perform connectivity analytics
in Neo4j with Cypher.