In the first example
of graph analytics for
big data, we'll consider
the social media called Twitter.
And graphs representing tweets.
What types of objects and
relationships does a tweet have?
Well, in fact, tweets consist
of many of the same elements and
relationships as the Facebook posts.
Tweets have users, they contain text,
tweets can point to one another or
to URL's, they have hashtags, they can
include reference to various other types
of media, but what about relationships?
Well much like Facebook, relationships and
tweets are more reflective of
what the users do with tweets.
For example, people create tweets,
they respond to tweets,
they mention other users, and so forth.
Let's look at these
relationships in detail.
In this graph, all of the light
blue notes are tweets, and
all of the purple notes are users.
When a specific user
creates a specific tweet,
an entity is created in
the graph as a result.
We'll come back to this graph
in the next few slides.
So what we want to do with it?
Well to be very specific,
this graph was created from tweets
of a bunch of online gamers.
In this case, we were monitoring
the tweets of all people
who played particular online video game.
Typically, gamers are very
excited about their video games.
They're exited about their characters
of the video games and they want to
discuss the video games they're excited
about, when new versions are released.
So what are the data
science questions here?
People who look at these things, such as
behavioral psychologists, want to know.
If you are a war game user or
if you play any other violent game, where
there is a lot of fighting online, do
these people also show violent behavior?
Maybe they do, maybe they don't.
They also want to know whether as a result
of looking at somebody's tweets and
following them over time they can tell if
the person is addicted to the game or not.
So why use graphs for that?
One of the things you could
do is what we showed here,
from the graphs you can extract
certain elements like conversations.
If you look at it, you will see all of
them have somebody posting something.
Somebody responding to the post, and the
first person responding to the response.
They are retweeting, and
they are responding, and so forth.
You would see a conversation chain
going on which can be short or long,
like you see, and
other people would join in.
We don't know if it's violent or not, but
at least there is a lively
conversation going on about something.
Using graphs, we could find some
meaningful parts of a graph
that we can further analyze using
techniques like text analytics.
Another kind of thing people
would like to identify,
is which players are interacting
with which other players?
Who are these people?
Do they form a close community?
Can anybody join in?
Are there groups, what are the groups?
If you find a group,
who are the most influential users?
Who are the people that everybody
refers to, listens to and so on?
Graph analytics is used to answer all
these questions about a conversation
that's going on live in
social media stream.
Let's look at our next example.
Our second use case is about biology.
Interactions arise naturally in biology.
Genes produce proteins, proteins regulate
the functions of other proteins,
cells transmit signals to other cells.
These functional genes lead to
pathological conditions that
present themselves as
observable phenotypes.
Some of these interactions that are
observed and measured by experiment lists.
Another class of graph relations
represent human knowledge.
For example, an edge may denote
an anatomical association, such as
the nucleuses inside a cell, part of
the cerebral cortex is part of the brain.
Similarly, one can encode different
classifications of entities like
both humans and dogs and mammals.
Researchers also find these
relationships from literature
or by computational techniques
like bioinformatics algorithms.
There are many bioinformatics algorithms
that find statistical correlations between
genes and proteins.
Many biological networks are created by
creating edges between entities because
they are strongly correlated based on
measurements like gene expression level.
Yet, a third category of
computed relationships
associates terms by mining
scientific literature.
If two entities are co-mentioned
in scientific articles very often,
then there is a likelihood that
these two entities are related.
In this case, the edge between them does
not depict a specific relationship, but
the fact they are associated.
All these interactions can be assembled
into networks of graphs where the nodes
are biological entities and
edges represent different categories of
molecular interactions,
associations between diseases and.
Now there are two issues I
would like you to understand.
First, graphs like the one
we saw are assembled.
That is, integrated from many data sources
produced by many independent science
groups who have different research goals,
use different scientific techniques,
but the underlying biological entities
are common across many groups.
It is the commonality that helps us
stitch together these logic graphs.
Second, as more results get linked and
integrated, the size of the networks grow,
leading to big data problems and
the need for big data technology.
Now let's ask the same question.
Why graphs?
In bio medicine people are always
trying to discover new science, for
instance, they want to discover
unknown relationships.
For example, they can take two diseases,
very different diseases, colorectal
cancer and Alzheimers disease, and
they might want to ask are they related?
If so, can you connect the dots and
find out what the intervening
network between them is?
It turns out, as you can see,
there are several genes that directly or
indirectly connect these two diseases.
Thus, we can use path finding techniques
like this to discover previously
unknown connections in a network.
In addition,
researchers sometimes think to explore the
networks to help their discovery process.
I have collaborated with a group that
is using graph exploration techniques
to figure out how phenotypes of
undiagnosed diseases all fit together.
Our third use case is about
the human information network.
That means a personal information network.
The graphic you see there
is my LinkedIn network.
Everybody who is on my LinkedIn is a node.
And if they know each other,
there's an edge between them.
You can possibly see some groups or
clusters there.
One analytical question
we'll explore in module two
is how to discover these
groups automatically.
Now of course with LinkedIn we only
have professional information.
But it is prudent to ask whether
one can integrate the professional network
with other forms of personal information.
This would be other social media data like
my friendship network from Facebook or
Google, or it could be information
like my Outlook email network.
One can add even more information and
put that interpersonal relationships.
For example, Professor Norman who is
on my contact list is my director.
And if we add my calendar to this,
one can find events that I'll be attending
and people that I will be meeting.
Taking it even further, for
special applications you might
actually include financial and
business transactions, or
performance in activities,
or fitness information, or
the location from my GPS.
Now, if you add all of these questions, we
should ask what we do with these things?
Let's see.
One use of this kind of
information is matching.
For example, matching people with jobs
is not just a matter of screening
series based on job descriptions or
evaluating their job experience.
To recruit for high level positions,
like the board of directors of a company,
you need to evaluate the network of the
candidate to determine their relationships
with important organizations,
groups, and individuals.
For some tasks like choosing a surgeon,
you might also want inspect
their social media ratings.
In other classic applications,
we might want to look for
people who can influence a human network.
Suppose, we are in an election
campaign team, and
need our message to get to as many
people as possible in a city.
We can not go door to door ourselves,
we need to go to some people, and
these people will reach
others on our behalf.
Graph analytic techniques may help
identify the fewest number of people
who will have maximal reach into most
of the potential voters in the city.
A third category of application
is threat detection.
This network is created
by groups who study news.
For example,
they collect information about all
the militant groups in different countries
and all the reported acts of terrorism.
This creates a network as you can see.
We show only a part of the network.
In this graph view,
the green notes are groups and
the pink notes are deemed individuals.
It should be clear that some
of these individuals and
groups are more closely
associated than others.
Discovering and tracking these groups,
their current activities,
together with an analysis of details of
the events they're associated with might
help analysts to get deeper
insight into the networks and
perhaps anticipate their
future activities.
Our fourth and
last use case has to do with smart cities.
Now, a city is a geographically
bounded space, and
contains many different networks
operating within the same spatial domain.
What kind of networks?
Let's see.
It has transportation networks.
Water and sewage networks,
power transmission networks,
your IP broadband networks.
Some of these networks have
multiple subtypes, for
example transportation networks include
the bus networks, the subway network,
the surface street network, and
the railway network, and so on.
These networks form a physical
infrastructure and therefore
can be represented as graphs where
each node has a geographic coordinate.
But some of these networks can also be
thought of as a commodity flow network.
People flow through
transportation networks.
Sewage material flows through
a sewage network and so on.
For many of these networks,
a city planner would like to make
sure that they cover the entire city,
that commute time is optimized,
traffic congestions are well planned.
To accomplish this, they would need to
create what's called a network model.
For example, urban planners develop
city traffic model servicing.
A traffic model will use both
the geographic layout and
connectivity of the network along
with the flow parameters like
the number of commuters getting
on board at any station.
Well, if we're planning
to create a smart hub,
we need to make sure that all the right
things happen at the same place.
People who come out of a metro
station find nearby businesses.
They find nearby facilities.
Those facilities should
have broadband network for
people who are going to go
on their mobile phones.
The same places need to have
a water supply network, and
you have to plan it in such
a way that all these networks
who exist within a certain
distance of each other.
And all the facilities can
be planned accordingly.
Beyond normal operations,
we also need to model what would
happen if the network gets disrupted.
What are the kinds of congestion or
traffic that might disturb the network?
Therefore these graphs are no longer just
structures, but they represent things like
congestions, things like people's behavior
and materials behavior over the network.
One should also compute
energy use patterns for
the busy parts of the network in order to
figure out how the network structure or
the network flow can be altered to
enable energy optimal operations.
As we saw in these four examples,
what graphs are used for
are kind of different but
they all show different view points from
which you can use graphs for analysis.
So this course focuses on Graph Analytics.
I would like to briefly
recap what the term means.
Analytics is the ability to
discover meaningful patterns and
interesting insights into data using
mathematical properties of data.
It covers a process of computing
with mathematical properties and
accessing the data itself efficiently.
Further, it involves
the ability to represent and
work with domain knowledge as we
saw in use case two with biology.
Finally, analytics often involves
statistical modeling techniques for
drawing inferences and
making predictions on data.
With analytics, we should be able
to achieve the goals shown here.
Therefore, Graph Analytics
is a special piece of
analytics where the underlying data
can be modeled as a set of graphs.
In the previous video,
we learned what a graph is.
We gained insight into both
the mathematician's view and
the computer scientist's view.
Now we want to look at the big
picture of graph analytics.
Why are we doing what we are doing, and
why do I need a graph
representation on graph analytics?
Let's start with a graph network which you
may already be familiar with, Facebook.
Here is my Facebook page.
Let's look at it and
consider some of the elements it contains.
There is a primary user, and that's me.
There are my friends.
And typically there are some posts,
some of which may have media in them,
such as video.
What else does it have?
Well, let's consider what's inside a post.
The post contains text.
It has tags.
I tag some people,
some people comment on my post.
If somebody's commenting,
then that means there must be a commenter
who is also a user in the Facebook.
Other people like my post or
they like a comment and
they also respond to some of the comments.
Many posts have locations
associated with them as well.
When we consider all of these together,
do you see the graph?
Well if not, we'll show you.
Here, we see very much the same types of
information but now they're in a graph.
First, notice me on the far left.
If you look carefully at this graph you'll
also notice there are relations labeled
Friend-of and Created_post and parts
of the post and everything that you saw
before that are now organized in terms of
objects and relationship speaking objects.
The objects here on the post, comments on
the post, replies to the comments and so
forth, and the relationships also
include tagged in or refers to.
So this is sort of the big picture, right?
Next we will look at 4 specific
Use Cases in four different disciplines.
The first one will be on Social Media.
The second one will be on biology,
where we'll look at genes and diseases.
The third one will be Human Information
Network, which means personal information.
And the fourth one will
be on smart cities.
Let's go through these
examples one by one.