Welcome back to the fourth and
final module of the course.
In this module, we'll cover the underlying
principles of large scale graph processing
and the software infrastructure
that supports it.
So, in this module,
you'll learn a programming model for
graph computation and
systems that implement this model.
After this model, you'll be able to
formulate graph analytics computations
in terms of the programming model.
This module will consist of three lessons.
The first lesson, will revisit
the concept of the programming model and
introduce a programming model
called Bulk Synchronous Parallel or
BSP that is designed specifically for
graph oriented computation.
I will discuss two well known versions of
the central idea, Pregel from Google, and
Graphlab from Carnegie Mellon University.
The second lesson,
we'll discuss two software systems,
Giraph that operates on Hadoop,
and GraphX that operates on Spark.
We'll compare the basic architecture
of these two systems and
point out their differences.
The final lesson will show example
computations, using graphics platform.
Since graphics come with Spark,
we've created these examples on the
virtual machine, which you have access to.
The code and
some data sets are available for
those who wish to play with the system.
Now we are going to
introduce you to Graphx,
which we'll primarily cover
as a hands-on presentation.
Graphx was developed by the Amp
lab at UC Berkeley, and
has now become an Apache product.
In this brief introduction, we are using
a few slides from Amp lab presentations.
Like [INAUDIBLE] graphic
uses a property graph model.
That means both nodes and
edges can have attributes and values.
In Graphx, the node properties
are stored in a Vertex Table.
And edge properties
are stored in an Edge Table.
The connectivity information, that is
which edge connects to which nodes,
is stored separately from the nodes and
edge properties.
Since Graphx is based on spark,
whose central information representation
is based on resilient data sets or RDDs.
You may recall that RDDs are typically
in memory information objects.
These objects can be used to perform
an action, which returns a value.
Or they can perform a transformation,
which can produce another RDD.
Graphx is built on special RDDs for
vertices and edges.
Note that VertexIDs are defined
to be unique by design.
VertexRDD A represents a set of vertices
all of which have an attribute called A.
The Edge class is an object with a source
vertex, a destination vertex, and
edge attribute.
The EdgeRDD extends this
basic edge by storing
edges in a columnar format on
each partition of performance.
Very often, it's easier to operate
on a data structure that has both
node properties and edge properties.
If you are familiar with this schema, you
will readily see that this is a three-way
join operation between the node set,
the edge set and the second node set.
Finally, GraphX implements
it's own version of BSP.
This implementation,
not surprisingly, is called Pregel.
It allows a user to write a vertex
program, a send message routine,
and a message combiner routine,
just like BSP.
However, this implementation also performs
vertex partitioning like
we saw in graph lab.
Also, similarly to graph lab,
it enables the message sending computation
to reach the attributes of both vertices.
The code limit shown here
is written in Scala.
The hands on code after this you'll
see are all certain in scatter.
Will have a notice here in no scatter.
We would like to show you
here an example which uses
the Pregel runtime object in GraphX
to implement the simple BSP desk.
We would like to show here how Pregel
runtime objects in Graphx works.
We point out all the functions
that are defined by users
in running the Pregel operation.
The vprogf function,
which takes a vertex and a message and
returns a new attribute value for
that vertex.
The sendMsgr function, which computes
the new message along each edge.
The Option[M] construct says that it is
optional for a vertex to send the message.
That is,
the system should not show an error
if your message is not sent for
the vertex.
The combinef function is
a message combiner that we
mention in passive for graph.
Finally, the user can also specify
the number of reiterations that
the GraphX BSP process will run for.
In 2010, Google
published a paper outlining a system
that they had been working on.
This publication about a system called
Pregel, has been one of the most
influential publications on
large scale graph computing.
The Pregel system essentially implemented
the BSB model that we covered in
the last lecture.
To show how the Pregel
system is programmed,
we present the published code of Google's
most famous algorithm, the PageRank.
Recall that PageRank's task is
to compute note centrality.
The basic philosophy of PageRank is
that a note that is connected to an more
important note gains more importance.
In the filler on the right, B is a very
important node with a high page rank
because a lot of other nodes directly or
indirectly point to it.
So C being his direct neighbor
that receives an edge from B,
also has a high page rank.
All the C itself,
there's not have too many incident edges.
On the left side we have
Google's published C++ code
that implements PageRank method
on the Pregel infrastructure.
You don't have to know C++ to understand
the basic essence of the code.
We will explain the basic elements of
the Vertex program in the next few slides.
Remember from the last lecture
that the VSP technique considers
a vertex to be a process.
Every vertex implements
a method called compute.
This method, implements the logic of what
a vertex should do during the super steps.
The program starts by creating a special
kind of vertex called the PageRank vertex
for which this compute
method is specified.
You will notice that the compute
method starts by saying what happens
when the super step is one or more.
But what happens in super step zero?
Usually, superstep 0 is used for
initialization.
Every vertex, initialization
PageRank value to a same number
which is one divided by the total
number of vertices in the graph.
Computationally, a PageRank of a vertex is
a number calculated by adding two terms.
The first term, depends on the total
number of vertices in the graph, and
is therefore the same every time.
And the second term depends on the page
rank of the neighbors of the vertex.
How does the vertex
compute the second term?
It gets the PageRank values of
the neighbors in its messages,
and adds them up.
As we saw for SSSP,
after a vertex computes its value,
it goes to the propagate step and
sends a message to its outgoing edges.
For PageRank, the message it sends out
is just computed value divided
by the number of outgoing edges.
When this is done, the node halts for
the next superstep, and waits for
some other node to wake it up.
At this point, we have seen two
examples of graph analytic operations
executed on the BSB programming model.
Now, we'll look at the same problem
from a slightly different viewpoint.
GraphLab, originally a project from
Carnegie Mellon University, now turned
into a company called Dato, took a similar
yet different approach to the problem.
In GraphLab, any kind of data can be
associated with a vertex or an edge.
This information is stored in
what is called a data graph.
Let's look at the same
page like I already did.
The syntax is a bit different but
the logical blocks are identical.
These are the same blocks
that we highlighted before.
GraphLab breaks up these blocks into
three different user specified functions
called Gather, Apply,
Scatter, or GAS, for short.
Okay, so what's different?
Let's mention a few important differences.
First, let's consider gather.
Rather than adopting a message passing or
data flow model like Pregel,
GraphLab allows the user defined update
function complete freedom to read and
modify any of the data on
adjacent vertices edges.
In GraphLab, a receiving vertex has
access to the data on adjacent vertices
even if the adjacent vertices did
not schedule the current update.
In contrast, for Pregel the control
is with descending nodes.
An update can happen only when
a node sends out messages.
For some graph analytics operations
like a dynamic version of PageRank,
this is very important.
Further, if vertex can update
its value asynchronously.
That is, as soon as it receives
an update without having to wait for
all nodes like we do in VSP.
This often helps some intuitive algorithms
like page rank converge faster.
When the graph is large and
must be split across machines,
BSP cuts the graph along edges,
as we see on this slide.
So every cut edge results in
a machine to machine communication.
If we increase the number
of across machine edges,
we increase communication cost.
This has an interesting
practical consequence.
As we have mentioned,
many graph applications have communities.
And central nodes that have high degree.
Many young people today have
over 500 Facebook friends.
So when an analytical
operation like Page Rank,
that goes through multiple
iterations until convergence, for
these graphs, the communication
cost can become very high.
In the cluster graph shown here, every
color represents a different machine.
Let's look at that red vertex.
What would happen if we
split it like this instead?
The red node gets split.
And different vertices of different
machines work with their own copy
of the red vertex.
In the diagram,
the primary red vertex is marked zero and
copies are marked one through five.
Now the gather phase happens for
each copy.
Followed by a second operation from
the copies to the primary red vertex.
And this is followed by new user
defined operation called merge
that combines the partial results from
the copies to the primary vertex.
So for PageRank, the merge operation
boils down to computing the total
summation of the partial summation
of the edges computed at the copies.
Thus in this lesson,
we have seen two of the most influential
paradigms of large scale graph
computation when the number of nodes and
edges run into tens of millions and more.