Let's now discuss what
feature transformation is.
After this video you will be able
to articulate the purpose of
feature transformation, list three
feature transformation operations, and
discuss when scaling is important.
In addition to feature selection,
data pre-processing can also
include feature transformation.
Feature transformation involves
mapping a set of values for
the feature to a new set of values to
make the representation of the data more
suitable or easier to process for
the downstream analysis.
A common feature transformation
operation is scaling.
This involves changing
the range of values for
a feature of features to
another specified range.
This is done to avoid allowing
features with large values to
dominate the analysis results.
For example, if your dataset has
both width and height as features,
the magnitude of the weight values,
which are in pounds, will be much
larger than the magnitude of the height
values which are in feet and inches.
So scaling both features
to a common value range
will make the contributions from
both weight and height equal.
One way to perform scaling is to map all
values of a feature to a specific range
such as between zero and one.
For example,
let's say you have a feature for
income that ranges from 30,000 to 100,000.
And you have another feature for years
of employment that ranges from 0 to 50.
These features have very different scales.
If you want both features to have equal
weighting when you compare the data
samples, then you can scale the range
of both features to be between 0 and 1.
That way the income feature which is
on much largest scale than the years
of employment feature will not
dominate the compares result.
Alternatively, scaling can be perform
by transforming the features such that
the results have zero mean,
and unit standard deviation.
The steps to perform the scaling
is to first calculate the mean and
standard deviation values for
the feature to be scaled.
Then for each value, for this feature,
subtract the mean value from that value,
and divide by the standard deviation.
The transformed feature will end
up with a mean value of zero, and
standard deviation of one.
This effectively removes
the units of the features and
converts each future value to number
of standard deviations from the mean.
This scaling method is used when
the min and max values are known.
This is also useful when there are
outliers which will skew the calculation
for the range as the max value is
determined by the furthest outlier.
This scaling operation is often
referred to as zero-normalization or
as standardization.
Filtering is another feature
transformation operation.
This is commonly applied to time series
data, such as speech or audio signals.
A low pass filter can be
used to filter out noise.
Which usually manifests as the high
frequency component in the signal.
A low pass filter removes components
above a certain frequency
allowing the rest to
pass through unaltered.
Filtering can also be used
to remove noise in images.
Noise in an image is random variation
in intensity or color in the pixels.
For example, a noise can cause
an image to appear grainy.
A mean or median filter can be used to
replace the pixel value with the mean or
median value of its neighboring pixels.
This has the effect of
smoothing out the image,
removing the noise that causes
the graininess in the image.
Aggregation combines values for
a feature in order to summarize data or
reduce variability.
Aggregation combines values for a feature
in order to summarize the data or
to reduce variability.
Aggregation is done by summing or
averaging data values at a higher level.
For example, hourly values can be
aggregated to the daily level.
Or values within a city region can
be aggregated to a state level.
These plots show
the results of aggregation.
The left plot shows the wind
speed values in miles per hour
averaged every 10 minutes
over a period of seven days.
Notice that there's a lot of variability,
that is the values fluctuate a lot.
The right plot shows wind speed
values averaged every hour so
every 60 minutes instead
of every 10 minutes.
Notice that the line is much smoother
here because the values are aggregated at
a higher time scale level.
So aggregation can have
the effect of removing noise
to provide a clear representation
of the structure of your data.
Another example is tracking stock prices.
Hourly deviations of a stock
may be difficult to track but,
aggregated daily changes may better reveal
any upward or downward trend of the stock.
In summary, feature transformation
involves mapping the set of values for
a feature to a new set of values to
make the representation of the data
more suitable for the downstream analysis.
Feature transformation should be used with
cautions since they change the nature of
the data and unintentionally remove some
important characteristics of the data.
So it's important to look at the effects
of the transformation you're applying
to your data to make certain that
it has the intended consequences.
In this activity we will be using
KNIME to handle missing data.
First, we will create new workflow and
import our weather data.
Next, we will remove missing values for
specific measurement in the data.
We will then impute missing
values with the mean.
And finally,
remove all the rows with missing values.
Let's begin, first,
let's create a new workflow in KNIME.
We'll name it, Handling Missing Values.
Next, let's import the weather
data using the File Reader node.
We'll add the File Reader
node to the canvas.
We'll configure File Reader
to read daily_weather.csv.
Next, we'll connect the Histogram
node to File Reader.
Before we configure the Histogram node,
we need to run the File Reader node.
We can do this by clicking on File Reader,
and
clicking on the green
arrow in the toolbar.
Next, double-click on
Histogram to configure it.
We'll set both the binning column and
aggregation columns to air_temp_9am.
Next, we'll add a missing value node.
We'll connect this to
the file reader node.
Double click on missing
value to configuring it.
Go to column settings,
select air_temp_9am, and click on Add.
We'll then choose remove row.
This will remove the measurements of
air_temp_9am that had missing values.
Click OK.
Next, we'll add another histogram
node to the output of missing value.
We can do this easily by copying and
pasting the existing histogram node.
Now let's run the workflow by
clicking on the double green arrows.
Let's view the output in
the histogram nodes before and
after we remove missing values.
In this histogram view,
we can see that there are missing values.
If we go and
look at the second histogram node,
the one after we removed
the missing values.
We can see that there are no
missing values in this chart.
Next, instead of removing missing values,
let's impute the values to the mean.
We could do this by configuring
the missing value node.
And instead of remove row,
change that to mean.
Click OK, and rerun the work flow.
We could see the difference by comparing
the graphs and the two histogram nodes.
If we go to visualization settings.
And change labels to all elements, we'll
see the number of elements in each band.
In the histogram,
before we removed the missing values,
we can see the fifth column
has 216 measurements in it.
Where as the fifth column after we imputed
the missing values has 221 values in it.
Let's close these.
Next, let's remove all the rows that
have missing values in the data.
We can do this by double
clicking on missing value.
Removing air_temp_ 9am.
Clicking on the default tab.
Changing this to remove row.
I'll click OK, now we rerun the workflow.
Again, we'll look at the histograms before
and after we remove the missing values.
Again, we'll go to visualization settings
and change the labels to all elements so
we can see the number of
elements in each bin.
We can see the number of elements in
each bin in the different histograms
has changed.
In this activity we will see how
to handle missing values in Spark.
First, we will load weather
data into a Spark DataFrame.
We'll then examine the summary
statistics for air temperature, remove
the rows with missing values, and finally
impute missing values with the mean.
Let's begin.
First, we'll open the notebook
called handling missing values.
The first cell creates an SQLContext and
then loads the weather data
csv into a data frame.
Let's execute this,
we can view the summary statistics for
the DataFrame by running
df.describe().show().
Let's just look at the summary
statistics for the air temperature.
We'll run
df.describe(['air_score_9am']) .show.
This says that there are 1090 rows.
This does not include the rows of
missing values for the air temperature.
We can count the total number of rows
in the DataFrame by running df.count.()
Since there are 1095 total
rows in the DataFrame, but
only 1090 in the air_temp column,
that means there are five rows in
air_temp that have missing values.
Next, let's remove all the rows in
the DataFrame that have missing values.
We'll put these in a new data
frame called removeAllDF.
To drop the missing values
we'll run df.na.drop.
Let's look at the summary statistics for
air_temp 9AM with
the missing values dropped.
We'll run removeAllDF .describe([
air_temp_9am]) show.()
We can see that the mean and
standard deviation values
are close to the original values before
we removed the rows with missing values.
Additionally, the count of
the number of rows is 1064.
We can verify that this is the total
number of rows in the new DataFrame by
running removeAllDF.count.
Next, let's impute the missing
values with the mean,
instead of removing them
from the DataFrame.
First, we'll need to load
the average function from pyspark.
We'll do this by running from
pyspark.sql.functions import avg.
Next, we'll create a copy of the DataFrame
in which we will input the missing values.
We'll call the new DataFrame imputeDF.
To impute the missing values we'll
iterate through each column of
the original DataFrame, first computing
the mean value for that column and
then replacing the missing values
in that column with the mean value.
To move through the columns
in the data frame,
we'll enter for
x in imputeDF.columns: next,
we'll compute the mean value for
that column.
We'll use the data frame in which
we removed all the missing values,
we'll call the agg function
to compute an aggregate.
And the argument that we give it is avg.
The argument avg is x, which is the column
we are trying to compute the average of.
The agg function returns to DataFrame and
we want to get the first
row of that data frame.
We can do this by calling .first and
then you get the first value in
this row or say [0].
Next let's print the column
name in mean value.
print(x, meanValue)
Now let's update our new DataFrame,
replacing the missing
values with the mean value.
imputeDF = imputeDF.na.fill(meanValue,
[x]).
Let's run this.
We can see that the mean value for
air_temp 9am matches the mean value
computed in the summary statistics of
the data frame where the missing
values were removed.
Finally, let's print the imputed
data summary statistics.
First we'll show the summary
statistics for the original DataFrame.
And then the summary statistics for
the imputed DataFrame.
We'll enter df.describe([
air_temp_ 9am]) .show () and
imputeDF.describe(['air_temp_9am']).sho-
w().
Run this.
We can see that the number of rows
in the imputed DataFrame is larger
than the number of rows in
the original DataFrame.
There were five rows in the original
DataFrame with missing values.
And these have now been
replaced with the mean.
Let's talk about what it means to
build a classification model and
how building a model differs
from applying a model.
After this video,
you will be able to discuss what
building a classification model means.
Explain the difference between
building and applying a model.
And summarize why the parameters
of a model needs to be adjusted.
A machine learning model
is a mathematical model.
In the general sense, this means that
the model has parameters and uses
equations to determine the relationship
between its inputs and outputs.
The parameters are used by the model to
modify the inputs to generate the outputs.
The model adjusts its parameters
in order to correct or
refine this input, output relationship.
Here's an example of a simple model.
This mathematical model represents a line.
y is the output, x is the input,
m determines the slope of the line and
b determines the y-intercept or
where the line crosses the y-axis.
m and b are the model's parameters.
Given a specific value for
x, the model uses as parameters
along with x to determine y.
By adjusting the values for
the parameters m and b,
the model can adjust how the input
x matched to the output y.
Here we see how the output y changes for
the same value of input x,
when parameter b changes.
Recall that b is the y-intercept, or
where the line crosses the y-axis.
The value of b is +1 for
the red line and -1 for the blue line.
For the input x=1, the value of y is 3 for
the red line,
as indicated by the red arrow.
For the blue line, when the parameter
b changes from +1 to -1,
for x=1, the value of y is 1,
as indicated by the blue arrow.
So we see that with just a simple
change in one model parameter,
the input to output mapping changes.
A machine learning model
works in a similar way.
It maps input values to output values.
And it adjusts the parameters
in order to correct or
refine this input-output mapping.
The parameters of a machine
learning model are adjusted or
estimated from the data
using a learning algorithm.
This, in essence,
is what is involved in building a model.
This process is referred to by many terms,
such as model building,
model creation,
model training and model fitting.
In building a model,
we want to adjust the parameters in
order to reduce the model's error.
In the case of supervised tasks,
such as classification, this means getting
the model's outputs to match the targets
or desired outputs as much as possible.
Since the classification task is
to predict the correct category or
class, given the input variables,
you can think of the classification
problem visually as carving out the input
space as regions corresponding
to the different class labels.
In this diagram for example,
the classification model needs to form
the boundaries to define the regions
separating red triangles
from blue diamonds, from green circles,
from yellow squares.
In this example, if a sample falls within
the region in the upper right corner,
it will be classified as a blue diamond.
Classification decisions are based on
these regions, and the regions are defined
by the boundaries, as indicated by
the dashed lines in the diagram.
So these boundaries are referred
to as decision boundaries.
Building a classification then means using
the data to adjust the model's parameters
in order to form decision boundaries
to separate the target classes.
Note that the term classifier is often
used to mean classification model.
In general,
building a classification model,
as well as other machine learning models,
involves two phases.
The first is the training phase,
in which the model is constructed and
its parameters adjusted using as
what referred to as training data.
Training data is the data set
used to train or create a model.
The second is the testing phase.
This is where the learned
model is applied to new data.
That is,
data not used in training the model.
Here's another way to
look at the two phases.
In a training phase, the learning
algorithm uses the training data
to adjust the model's
parameters to minimize errors.
At the end of the training phase,
you get the trained model.
In the testing phase,
the trained model is applied to test data.
Test data is separate from training data
and is previously unseen by the model.
The model is then evaluated on
how it performs on the test data.
The goal in building a classifier
model is to have the model
perform well on training,
as well as test data.
We will discuss in more detail
the use of training and
test data sets in the next module,
when we discuss model evaluation.
To adjust a model's parameters,
we need to apply a learning algorithm.
We will discuss the specific algorithms
to build a classification model in
the next few lectures.
In this video, we will outline
some commonly used algorithms for
building a classification model.
After this video,
you will be able to describe the goal of
a classification algorithm and name some
common algorithms for classification.
Recall that a classification task is
to predict the category from the input
variables.
A classification model processes the input
data it receives and provides an output.
Since classification is a supervised task,
a target or
desired output is provided for
each sample.
The goal is to get the model outputs to
match the targets as much as possible.
A classification model
adjusts its parameters
to get its outputs to match the targets.
To adjust a model's parameters,
a learning algorithm is applied.
This occurs in a training phase
when the model is constructed.
There are many algorithms to
build a classification model.
In this course,
we will cover the algorithms listed here,
kNN or k Nearest Neighbors,
decision tree, and naive Bayes.
kNN stands for k Nearest Neighbors.
This technique relies on the notion that
samples with similar characteristics,
that is samples with similar values for
input, likely belong to the same class.
So classification of a sample is dependent
on the target values of
the neighboring points.
Another classification technique
is referred to as decision tree.
A decision tree is a classification
model that uses a treelike structure
to represent multiple decision paths.
Traversing each path leads to a different
way to classify an input sample.
A naive Bayes model uses a probabilistic
approach to classification.
Baye's Theorem is used to capture the
relationship between the input data and
the output class.
Simply put, the Baye's Theorem
compares the probability of an event
in the presence of another event.
We see here the probability
of A if B is present.
For example, probability of having
a fire if the weather is hot.
You can imagine event B depending
on more than one variable.
For example, weather is hot and windy.
We will cover kNN, decision tree and naive
Bayes in detail in the next few lectures.
There are many other classification
techniques, but we will focus on these
since they are fundamental algorithms
that are commonly used and
form the basis of other algorithms for
classification.