the sixth v value
in this module
we described the five ways which are considered to be dimensions of big data
each way presented a challenging dimension of big data namely
size complexity speed quality and connectedness
although we can list some other rays base on the context we prefer to list these
five s fundamental dimensions that this big data specialization helps you work on
however at the heart of the big data challenge
is turning all of the other dimensions into truly useful business value
the idea behind processing all this big data in the first place
is to bring value to the problem at hand
in week two we will explore how to take the first steps into
starting to generate value out of big data
now that we saw all the ways let focus on an example of a big data challenge
let imagine now that you are part of a company called eglence inc
one of the products of eglence inc is a highly popular mobile game
called catch the pink flamingo
it a multi - user game where the users have to catch special types
of pink flamingos that randomly pop up on the world map on their
screens based on the mission that gets updated randomly
the game is played by millions of people online throughout the world
one of the goals of the game is to form a network of players to collectively
cover the world map with pink flamingo sightings and compete other groups
users can pick their groups based on player stats
the game website sends free cool stuff to registered users
registration requires users to enter demographic information such gender
year of birth city highest education and things like that
however most of the users enter inaccurate information about themselves
just like most of us do
to help improve the game the game collects realtime usage activity
data from each player and feeds them to it data servers
the players of this game are enthusiastically active on social media
and have strong associations with the game
a popular twitter hashtag for this game is catchthepinkflamingo
which gets more than 200 000 mentions worldwide per day
there are strong communities of users who meet via social media and
get together to play the game
now imagine yourself as the big data solutions architect for fun games inc
there are definitely examples of all three types of data sources in this example
the mobile app generates data for the analysis of user activity
twitter conversations of players form a rich source of unstructured data from
people
and the customer and
game records are examples of data that this organization collects
this is a challenging big data example
where all characteristics of big data are represented
there are high volumes of player game and
twitter data which also speaks to the variety of data
the data streams from the mobile app website and
social media in real - time which can be defined as high velocity data
the quality of demographic data users enter is not clear and
there are networks of players which are related to the balance of big data
cloud computing : an important big data enabler
in our first lecture in this course we mentioned the cloud as one of
the two influences of the launch of the big data era
we called it on - demand computing and
we said that it enables us to compute any time any anywhere
simply whenever we demand it
in this video
we will see how we deploy the cloud to our benefit in our big data applications
the main idea behind cloud computing
is to transform computing infrastructure into a commodity
so application developers can focus on solving application - specific challenges
instead of trying to build infrastructure to run on
so how does this happen
we can simply define a cloud computing service
as a rental service for computing
you rent what you want and return upon usage
think about this you would not buy or
even build a truck every time you have to move a piece of furniture
you would simply rent
why build a computing cluster when you can rent
especially if you are not using it all the time
similarly you can rent a car or a bike when you are on vacation
so you can bike anytime anywhere
let dig into this question
what factors do you consider when you are developing a solution for your yourself or
your client
should you build a hardware and software resources yourself
or should you rent these resources from the cloud
let look at in - house hardware and software resource building first
if you choose to develop in - house capabilities you have to hire people and
buy hardware that suits your requirements
these includes but not limited to buying networking hardware
storage disks upgrading hardware when it becomes obsolete and so on
not to forget the real estate cost of keeping the hardware
how do you estimate the size of your hardware needs
do you make a five year estimate or ten year
in today fast changing world
it is becoming harder to estimate future demands
getting the software that fits your needs is equally challenging
most software installations require a lot of tweaking and
manual intervention that require a lot of skills
you will need your engineers to do this
compatibility issues bring problems that are hard to foresee
most software is updated on a daily basis
you must ensure you are updated
this insures you avoid security risks and get the best
over all building your own data center or computing power house can be expensive
and it can be time consuming maintaining it is a task by itself
this requires high initial capital investments and
efficient operation of several departments in your business
which you might not have if you are a startup company
most people forget to include the cost of disposing old hardware
now lets see what the cloud can do for us
cloud benefits are similar to what you would get from a rental car company
you pay for what you use which means a low capital investment
you do not need to go to the dealership do a negotiation get a bank loan
get insurance
that means quick implementation of your projects
just like you do not need to buy a car if you only need a car for
a limited use deploying your application on a server that is geographically
closer to your client can give you fast service and happy customers
for startup and small business it can be challenging to do so
cloud lets you do this with a click
you can be sitting at a coffeeshop or your home and starting your internet business
without a huge capital investment thanks to the cloud
and you do not need to have a five or ten year resource estimation plan
adapt to your requirements faster if your business is growing faster than you
thought
cloud lets you forget about the resource management problems and
lets you focus on your business products or domain expertise with minimal cost
just as you can rent a truck or a convertible at a rental car company
you can build your own custom machine on cloud
with a custom machine we mean a commodity cluster
made out of the right type of computing nodes for your application
you pick not only a cpu or a gpu but
pick from a whole menu of compute memory and storage choices
it a buffet on the cloud
design machines to suit your application requirements data size and analytics
get what you want and pay for what you use
compare this with buying and
maintaining all combinations of hardware that you possibly would use
that is so costly and not possible at all times
thanks to all these advantages there are many cloud server providers today
and the numbers are growing
here we list some of the players in the cloud computing market
take a moment to look at them
you will probably recognize some big names and
some others you have not even heard of before
as a summary cloud does the heavy lifting so your team can extract
value from data with getting bogged down in the infrastructure details
cloud provides convenient and
viable solutions for scaling your prototype to a full fledged application
you can leverage the experts to handle security
robustness and let them handle the technical issues
your team can work on utilizing your strengths
to solve your domain specific problem
cloud service models : exploration of choices
there are many levels of services that you can get from cloud providers
any cloud computing discussion will involve terms like application
as a service platform as a service and infrastructure as a service
all of these refer to business models around using the cloud
with different levels of engagement and servicing similar to rental agreements
iaas infrastructure as a service can be defined as a bare minimum rental service
this is like renting a truck from a company that you can assume has hardware
and you do the packing of your furniture and drive to your new house
you as the user of the service install and maintain an operating system
and other applications in the infrastructure as a service model
the amazon ec2 cloud is a good example for this model
paas platform as a service
is the model where a user is provided with an entire computing platform
this could include the operating system and programming languages that you need
it could extend to include the database of your choice or even a web server
you can develop and
run your own application software on top of these layers
the google app engine and microsoft azure are two examples of this model
saas the software as a service model is the model
in which the cloud service provider takes the responsibilities for the hardware and
software environment such as the operating system and the application software
this means you can work on using the application to solve your problem
dropbox is a very popular software as a service platform
ultimately the decision of which service you want to explore is a function of
several variables
it depends on the skill level of your team to handle computing environment
development and maintenance
it also depends on how you might need to use the service
you need to pick the right service model that
best fits you in terms of long term goals
finally when you are deploying a cloud service you also have to understand
all the security risks since your data resides on third party service
security is a very important aspect in today world of growing
digitization of information
you must make your client data safety a top priority
and hence this should be an important criteria in your decision
all the security risks must be understood and
evaluated as your data resides on third party servers
we are seeing other forms of services being added
to the family of cloud services
the logic of infrastructure platform and
software as a service is getting extended further
xaas is an umbrella term that signifies
even finer - grain control over computing resources that you want to rent
for example storage as a service communication as a service
marketing as a service and so on
as a summary infrastructure as a service platform as a service and application
as a service are three main class service models that are being used with success
picking one will depend on the number of variables which are company goals
these three models have inspired many similar models
to emerge around cloud computing
in this lecture we will be learning about the basic file manipulation commands for
the hadoop file system or hdfs
we will first start by downloading a text file of words
we will use this text file to copy to and from the local file system in hdfs and
later on we will use it to run word count on
after we download the text file we will open a terminal shell and
copy the text file from the local file system to hdfs
next we will copy the file within hdfs and
also see how to copy file from hdfs to the local file system
finally we will see how to delete a file in hdfs
let start
we are going to download text file to copy into hdfs
it does not matter what the contents of the text file is so we will download
the complete works of shakespeare since it contains interesting text
first click on the icon here to launch a web browser
now we will search google for the complete works of shakespeare
i am going to be using this first link here
and we will provide this link in the reading section
so this is the complete works of shakespeare and
we will save it to a text file in the local file system by clicking on the icon here
the open menu and selecting save page
so we will call it words txt
and the save in folder it going to save it into the downloads directory
once that completes we will open a terminal window by clicking on the icon here
so if we go into the downloads ddrectory by typing a cd downloads and
running ls we can see that words txt was successfully downloaded
moving on let copy words txt from the local file system to the hdfs file system
the command to do this is hadoop fs - copyfromlocal words txt
when i run this it will copy it from the local directory and
local file system to hdfs
we can see that the file was copied by running hadoop fs - ls
you can see that the file was successfully copied
next we can copy this file to another file within hdfs
we can do this by running hadoop fs - cp words txt words2 txt
the first words txt is the file that already exists in hdfs
the second words 2 txt
is the new file that we are going to create when we run this command
let run it and again we are can run
hadoopfs - ls to see the files in hdfs
we can see the original file words txt and the copy that was made words2 txt
let copy words2 txt from hdfs to the local filesystem
we can do this by running hadoop fs - copytolocal words2 txt
after i run this command i can call ls to see the contents of the local file system
so now we have the new file words2 txt which we have just copied from hdfs
the last step in this lecture is to delete a file in hdfs
we can delete words2 txt by running hadoop fs
but is rn words2 txt
as you can see it printed that it deleted the file
we can also run hadoop fs - ls to verify that the file is deleted
you can see that there only the original words txt and words2 txt was deleted
getting started
why do we worry about foundations
starting next week you will start diving into the details of the hadoop
framework for big data
before you start taking a little bit of time to understand some core
concepts will help you to digest the information on hadoop better and faster
imagine yourself attending a chemistry lab
before you start hearing about the tubes and mixtures you really need
to understand the chemistry or theory of the practical concepts in the lab
similarly learning these concepts now will help
you with your understanding of the practical concepts in the hadoop lectures
in addition we want to prepare you to understand the tools beyond hadoop
any big data system that you find will be built on these core concepts
so these foundations will help you beyond this course
now let get started