the hadoop distributed file system a storage system for big data
as a storage layer the hadoop distributed file system or the way we call it hdfs
serves as the foundation for most tools in the hadoop ecosystem
it provides two capabilities that are essential for managing big data
scalability to large data sets
and reliability to cope with hardware failures
hdfs allows you to store and access large datasets
according to hortonworks a leading vendor of hadoop services
hdfs has shown production scalability up to 200 petabytes and
a single cluster of 4 500 servers
with close to a billion files and blocks
if you run out of space you can simply add more nodes to increase the space
hdfs achieves scalability by partitioning or
splitting large files across multiple computers
this allows parallel access to very large files since the computations run in
parallel on each node where the data is stored
typical file size is gigabytes to terabytes
the default chunk size the size of each piece of a file is 64 megabytes
but you can configure this to any size
by spreading the file across many nodes
the chances are increased that a node storing one of the blocks will fail
what happens next
do we lose the information stored in block c
hdfs is designed for full tolerance in such case
hdfs replicates or
makes a copy of file blocks on different nodes to prevent data loss
in this example the node that crashed stored block c
but block c was replicated on two other nodes in the cluster
by default hdfs maintains three copies of every block
this is the default replication factor
but you can change it globally for every file or
on a per file basis
hdfs is also designed to handle a variety of data types aligned with
big data variety
to read a file in hdfs you must specify the input file format
similarly to write the file you must provide the output file format
hdfs provides a set of formats for common data types
but this is extensible and you can provide custom formats for your data types
for example text files can be read
line by line or a word at a time
geospatial data can be read as vectors or rasters
data formats specific to geospatial data or
other domain specific data formats
like fasta or fastq formats for sequence data genomics
hdfs is comprised of two components
namenode and datanode
these operate using a master slave relationship
where the namenode issues comments to datanodes across the cluster
the namenode is responsible for metadata
and datanodes provide block storage
there is usually one namenode per cluster
a datanode however runs on each node in the cluster
in some sense the namenode is the administrator or
the coordinator of the hdfs cluster
when the file is created the namenode records the name
location in the directory hierarchy and other metadata
the namenode also decides which data nodes to store the contents of the file and
remembers this mapping
the datanode runs on each node in the cluster
and is responsible for storing the file blocks
the data node listens to commands from the name node for block creation
deletion and replication
replication provides two key capabilities
fault tolerance and data locality
as discussed earlier when a machine in the cluster has a hardware failure there
are two other copies of each block that are stored on that node
so no data is lost
replication also means that the same block will be stored on different nodes on
the system which are in different geographical locations
a location may mean a specific rack or a data center in a different town
the location is important since we want to move computation to data and
not the other way around
we will talk about what moving computation to data means later in this module
as i mentioned earlier the default replication factor is three but
you can change this
a high replication factor means more protection against hardware failures
and better chances for data locality
but it also means increased storage space is used
as a summary hdfs provides
scalable big data storage by partitioning files over multiple nodes
this helps to scale big data analytics to large data volumes
the application protects against hardware failures and
provides data locality when we move analytical complications to data
the hadoop ecosystem : so much free stuff !
how did the big data open - source movement begin
in 2004 google published a paper about their
in - house processing framework they called mapreduce
the next year yahoo released an open - source
implementation based on this framework called hadoop
in the following years other frameworks and
tools were released to the community as open - source projects
these frameworks provided new capabilities missing in hadoop
such as sql like querying or high level scripting
today there are over 100 open - source projects for
big data and this number continues to grow
many rely on hadoop but some are independent
with so many frameworks and tools available how do we learn what they do
we can organize them with a layer diagram to understand their capabilities
sometimes we also used the term stack instead of a layer diagram
in a layer diagram a component uses the functionality or
capabilities of the components in the layer below it
usually components at the same layer do not communicate
and a component never assumes a specific tool or component is above it
in this example component a is in the bottom layer
which components b and c use
component d uses b but not c
and d does not directly use a
let look at one set of tools in the hadoop ecosystem as a layer diagram
this layer diagram is organized vertically based on the interface
low level interfaces so storage and scheduling on the bottom
and high level languages and interactivity at the top
the hadoop distributed file system or hdfs is the foundation for
many big data frameworks since it provides scaleable and reliable storage
as the size of your data increases you can add commodity hardware
to hdfs to increase storage capacity so
it enables scaling out of your resources
hadoop yarn provides flexible scheduling and
resource management over the hdfs storage
yarn is used at yahoo to schedule jobs across 40 000 servers
mapreduce is a programming model that simplifies parallel computing
instead of dealing with the complexities of synchronization and scheduling you
only need to give mapreduce two functions map and reduce as you heard before
this programming model is so
powerful that google previously used it for indexing websites
mapreduce only assume a limited model to express data
hive and pig are two additional programming models on
top of mapreduce to augment data modeling of mapreduce
with relational algebra and data flow modeling respectively
hive was created at facebook to issue sql - like
queries using mapreduce on their data in hdfs
pig was created at yahoo to model data flow based programs using mapreduce
thanks to yarn stability to manage resources
not just for mapreduce but other programming models as well
giraph was built for processing large - scale graphs efficiently
for example facebook uses giraph to analyze the social graphs of its users
similarly storm spark and flink were built for
real time and in memory processing of big data on
top of the yarn resource scheduler and hdfs
in - memory processing is a powerful way of running big data applications even faster
achieving 100x better performance for some tasks
sometimes your data or processing tasks are not easily or
efficiently represented using the file and directory model of storage
examples of this include collections of key - values or large sparse tables
nosql projects such as cassandra mongodb and hbase handle these cases
cassandra was created at facebook but facebook also used hbase for
its messaging platform
finally running all of these tools requires a centralized management system
for synchronization configuration and to ensure high availability
zookeeper performs these duties
it was created by yahoo to wrangle services named after animals
a major benefit of the hadoop ecosystem
is that all these tools are open - source projects
you can download and use them for free
each project has a community of users and developers that
answer questions fix bugs and implement new features
you can mix and match to get only the tools you need to achieve your goals
alternatively there are several pre - built stacks of these tools
offered by companies such as cloudera mapr and hortonworks
these companies provide the core software stacks for free and
offer commercial support for production environments
as a summary the hadoop ecosystem
consists of a growing number of open - source tools
providing opportunities to pick the right tool for
the right tasks for better performance and lower costs
we will reveal some of these tools in further detail and
provide an analysis of when to use which in the next set of lectures
generating value from hadoop and
pre - built hadoop images that come as off the shelf products
assembling your own software stack from scratch can be messy and
a lot of work for beginners
the task of setting up the whole stack could consume a lot of project time and
man power reducing time to deployment
getting pre - built images is similar to buying pre - assembled furniture
you can obtain a ready to go software stack which contains a pre - installed
operating system required libraries and application software
it saves you from the trouble of putting the different
parts together in the right orientation
you can start using the furniture right away
packaging of these pre - built software images is enabled
by virtual machines using virtualization software
without going into too much detail one of the benefits of virtualization
software is that it lets you run a ready made software stack within minutes
your software stack comes as a large file
virtualization software provides a platform where your stack can run
many companies provide images for their version of the hadoop platform
including a number of tools of their choice
hortonworks is one of the companies that provides a pre - built software stack for
both mac and windows platforms
cloudera is another company that provides pre - installed and
assembled software stack images
cloudera image is what we will be working with in this course
many other companies provide similar images
additionally lots of online tutorials for beginners are on vendors websites for
self - training of users working with these images and
the open source tools they include
once you choose the vendor you can check out their website for
tutorials on how to get started quickly
there are plenty of resources online for that
you can deploy pre - built images over the cloud
this would further accelerate your application deployment process
it is always best to evaluate which approach is most cost effective for
your business model and organization
companies such as cloudera hortonworks and others
provide step - by - step guides on how to set up pre - built images on the cloud
as a summary using pre - built software packages have a number of benefits and
can significantly accelerate your big data projects
even small teams can quickly prototype deploy and validate their project ideas
the developed analytical solutions can be scaled to larger volumes and
increase velocities of data in a matter of hours
these companies also provide enterprise level solutions for large
full - fledged applications
an added benefit is that there are plenty of companies which provide
ready - made solutions
that means lots of choices for you to pick the one most suited to your project
what is a distributed file system
most of us have file cabinets in our offices or
homes that help us store our printed documents
everyone has their own method of organizing files
including the way we bin similar documents into one file or
the way we sort them in alphabetical or date order
when computers first came out the information and
programs were stored in punch cards
these punch cards were stored in file cabinets
just like the physical file cabinets today
this is where the name file system comes from
the need to store information in files comes from a larger need
to store information in the long - term
this way the information lives after the computer program or
what we call process that produced it terminates
if we do not have files our access to such information would not be possible
once a program using or producing it
even during the process we might need to store large amounts of information
that we cannot store within the program components or computer memory
in addition once the data is in a file
multiple processes can access the same information if needed
for all these reasons we store information in files on a hard disk
there are many of these files and
they get managed by your operating system like windows or linux
how the operating system manages files is called a file system
how this information is stored on disk drives has high impact
on the efficiency and speed of access to data especially in the big data case
while the files have exact addresses for their locations in the drive referring
to the data units of sequence of these blocks that called the flat structure
or hierarchy construction of index records that called the database
they also have human readable symbolic names generally followed by an extension
extensions tell what kind of file it is in general
programs and users can access files with their names
the contents of a file can be numeric alphabetic alphanumeric
or binary executables
most computer users work on personal laptops or
desktop computers with a single hard drive
in this model the user is limited to the capacity of their hard drive
the capacity of different devices vary
for example while your phone or
tablet might have a storage capacity in the order of gigabytes your
laptop computer might have a terabyte of storage but what if you have more data
some of you probably had issues in the past with
running out of space on your hard drive
a way to solve this is to have an external hard drive and
store your files there or you can buy a bigger disk
both options are a bit of a hassle to copy the data to a new disk are not they
they might not even be an option sometimes
now imagine you having two computers and
storing some of your data in one and the rest of your data in another
how you organize and partition your data between these computers is up to you
you might want to store your work data in one computer and
your personal data in another
distributing data on multiple computers might be an option but
it raises new issues
in this situation you need to know where to find the files you need
depending on what you re doing
you can find it manageable if it s just your data
but now imagine having thousands of computers
to store your data with big volumes and variety
would not it be good to have a system that can handle the data access and
do this for you
this is a case that can be handled by a distributive file system
now let assume that there are racks of these computers
often even distributed across the local or
wide area network because such file systems distributed file systems
data sets or parts of a data set
can be replicated across the nodes of a distributed file system
since data is already on these nodes then analysis of parts of the data
is needed in a data parallel fashion computation can be moved to these nodes
additionally distributed file systems replicate the data
between the racks and also computers distributed across geographical regions
data replication makes the system more fault tolerant
that means if some nodes or a rack goes down
there are other parts of the system the same data can be found and analyzed
data replication also helps with scaling the access to this data by many users
often if the data is popular many reader processes will want access to it
in a highly parallelized replication
each reader can get their own node to access to and analyze data
this increases overall system performance
note that a problem with having such a distributive replication is
that it is hard to make changes to data over time
however in most big data systems the data is written once and
the updates to data is maintained as additional data sets over time
as a summary a file system is responsible from the organization of
the long term information storage in a computer
when many storage computers are connected through the network
we call it a distributed file system
distributed file systems provide data scalability fault tolerance and
high concurrency through partitioning and replication of data on many nodes
when to reconsider hadoop
the hadoop ecosystem is growing at a fast pace
this means a lot of stuff that was difficult or
not supportive is becoming possible
in this lecture
we will look at some aspects that clearly make a good match for hadoop
we will also look at several aspects that might motivate you
to evaluate hadoop at a deeper level
and does hadoop really make sense for your specific problem
first let look at the key features that make a problem hadoop friendly
if you see a large scale growth in amount of data you will tackle
probably it makes sense to use hadoop
when you want quick access to your old data which would otherwise go on tape
drives for archival storage hadoop might provide a good alternative
other hadoop friendly features include
scenarios when you want to use multiple applications over the same data store
high volume or high variety are also great indicators for
hadoop as a platform choice
small data set processing should raise your eyebrows
do you really need hadoop for that
dig deeper and find out exactly why you want to use hadoop before going ahead
hadoop is good for data parallelism
as you know data parallelism is the simultaneous execution of the same
function on multiple nodes across the elements of a dataset
on the other hand task parallelism as you see in this graph
is the simultaneous execution of many different functions
on multiple nodes across the same or different data sets
if your problem has task - level parallelism you must do further
analysis as to which tools you plan to deploy from the hadoop ecosystem
what are the precise benefits that these tools provide
proceed with caution
not all algorithms are scalable in hadoop or
reducible to one of the programming models supported by yarn
hence if you are looking to deploy highly coupled data processing algorithms
proceed with caution
do a thorough analysis before using hadoop
are you thinking of
throwing away your existing database solutions and replacing them with hadoop
think again
hadoop may be a good platform where your diverse data sets can land and
get processed into a form digestible with your database
hadoop may not be the best data store solution for your business case
evaluate and proceed with caution
hdfs stores data in blocks of 64 megabytes or larger
so you may have to read an entire file just to pick one data entry
that makes it a bit harder to perform random data access
the hadoop ecosystem is growing at a faster pace than ever
this slide shows some of the moving targets in the hadoop ecosystem and
the additional needs which must be addressed by new tools
to the hadoop ecosystem
mainly advanced analytical queries
latency sensitive tasks and cyber security of sensitive data
here we give pointers to tools you might want to look into further
to understand the challenges these need tools address
as a summary although hadoop is good with scalability of many algorithms it is just
one model and does not solve all issues in managing and processing big data
although it would be possible to find counterexamples we can generally say
that the hadoop framework is not the best for working with small data sets
advanced algorithms that require a specific hardware type
task level parallelism infrastructure replacement or random data access