yarn the resource manager for hadoop
yarn is a resource manage layer that sits just above the storage layer hdfs
yarn interacts with applications and schedules resources for their use
yarn enables running multiple applications over hdfc increases
resource efficiency and let you go beyond the map reduce or
even beyond the data parallel programming model
when hadoop was first created this was not the case
in fact the original hadoop stack had no resource manager
these two stacked diagrams show some of it evolution over the last ten years
one of the biggest limitations of hadoop one point zero
was it inability to support non - mapreduce applications
it had several terrible resource utilization
this meant that for advanced applications such as graph analysis that
required different ways of modelling and
looking at data you would need to move your data to another platform
that a lot of work if your data is big
adding yarn in between hdfs and the applications enabled
new systems to be built focusing on different types of big data applications
such as giraph for graph data analysis storm for
streaming data analysis and spark for in - memory analysis
yarn does so by providing a standard framework
that supports customized application development in the hadoop ecosystem
yarn lets you extract maximum benefits from your data sets
by letting you use the tools you think are best for your big data
let take a peek into the architecture of yarn without getting too technical
in this picture notice the resource manager in the center and
the node managers on each of the three nodes on the right
the resource manager controls all the resources and decides who gets what
node manager operates at machine level and is in charge of a single machine
together the resource manager and
the node manager form the data computation framework
each application gets an application master
it negotiates resource from the resource manager and
it talks to node manager to get its tasks completed
notice the ovals labeled container the container
is an abstract notions that signifies a resource that is
a collection of cpu memory disk network and
other resources within the compute note to simplify and
be less precise you can think of a container and the machine
we looked at the essential gears of the yarn
engine to give you an idea of the key components of yarn
now when you hear terms like resource manager node manager and
container you will have an understanding of what tasks they are responsible for
here is a real life example to show the strength hadoop 2 0 over 1 0
yahoo was able to run almost
twice as many jobs per day with yarn than with hadoop 1 0
they also experienced a substantial increase in cpu utilization
yahoo !
even claimed that upgrading to yarn was equal into
adding 1000 machines to their 2500 machine cluster
that big
yarn success is evident from an explosive growth of
different application that the hadoop ecosystem now has
new to yarn
you can use the tool of your choice over your big data without any hassle
compare this with hadoop 1 0 which was limited to mapreduce alone
let review a summary of the key take - aways about yarn
yarn gives you many ways for applications to extract value from data
it lets you run many distributed applications over the same hadoop cluster
in addition yarn reduces the need to move data around and
supports higher resource utilization resulting in lower costs
it a scalable platform that has enabled growth of several applications
over the hdfs enriching the hadoop ecosystem
at this point you hopefully have a good general idea of what big data means and
why big data is important
so now we need to focus on what to do
when we have an application that uses big data
in this video we focus on the problem of managing big data
so at the end of the video
you should be able to describe what data management means in general and then
specifically recognize the issues that are involved in the management of big data
first let see what data management means in general
instead of giving you definitions of data management
let think of some questions that must be asked and
answered well if you are to manage a reasonable amount of data
now we can not possibly cover all questions one should ask for
a data - centric application but here are some important ones which range from how
we get the data to how we work with it to how we secure it from malicious users
we will visit these issues one at a time
ingestion means the process of getting the data
into the data system that we are building or using
now you might think why is it worth talking about
we will just read the data from somewhere like a file
and then using some command place it into the data system
or we will have have some kind of a web form or
other visual interface and just fill it in so that the data goes into the system
both of these ways of data ingestion are valid
in fact they are valid for
some big data systems like your airline reservation system
however when you think of a large scale system
you wold like to have more automation in the data ingestion processes
and data ingestion then becomes a part of the big data management infrastructure
so here are some questions you might want to ask when you automate data ingestion
now take a minute to read the questions
we will look at two examples to explore them in greater detail
the first example is that of a hospital information system that we discussed in
course one in the context of precision medicine
we said that hospitals collect terabytes of medical record
from different departments and be considered big data systems
the second example is a cloud based data store where many people upload their
messages chats pictures videos music and so fourth
the cloud storage also supports active communication between the members and
store their communication in real time
so let think of a hypothetical hospital information information and
the answer to depressions that we are putting there
now do not take the numbers to be very accurate
they are just examples
but it illustrates some important points
one note that there are two kinds of likeness associated with data
some data like medical images are large data objects by themselves
secondly the records themselves are quite small but
the size of the total collection of records is very high
two while there is a lot of patient data the number of data sources that is
the different departmental systems contributing to the total information
system does not change very much over time
three the rate of data ingestion is not enormous and is often proportional
to the number of patient activities that takes place at the hospital
four the system contains medical records so
data can never be discarded even when there are errors in the data
the errors in this specific case are flagged but the data is retained
now this is the kind of rule called an error handling policy
which might be different for different application problems
an air handling policy is part of a larger scheme of policies called
ingestion policies
another kind of ingestion policy involves decisions regarding what the system should
do if the data rate suddenly increases or becomes suspiciously low
in this example we have deliberately decided not to include it in the design
now compare the previous case with the case of the online store of
personal information
again this is just an imaginary example
so do not think of all the parameters to be exact
now in this case one the store will have a fast growing membership
each member will use multiple devices to capture and ingest their data
two over all members together the site will be updated at a really fast rate
making this a large volume data store with a fast ingest rate
three in this system our primary challenge is to keep up with the data
rate and hence erroneous data will be discarded after just one edit to reinvest
four now there is an actual policy for handling data overflow
which essentially says keep the excess data in a site store
and ingest them when the data rate becomes slower
but if the site store starts getting full
start dropping some incoming data at a rate of 0 1 at a time
now we should see why data ingestion together with it
policies should be an integral part of a big data system
especially when it involves storing fast data
a very significant aspect of data management is to document define
implement and test the set of operations that are required for
a specific application
as we will see later in the specialization some operations are independent of
the type of data and some others would require us to know the nature of the data
because the operations make use of a particular data model
that is the way that it is structured
in general there are two broad divisions of operations
those that work on a singular object and
those that work on collections of data objects
in the first case an operation that crops an image
that means extracts a sub area from an area of pixels
is a single object operation because we consider the image as a single object
one can think of many subclasses of the second category
where the operations are on data collections
we briefly referred to three very common operations that can be done
regardless of the nature of the data
the first is to take a collection and filter out a subset of that collection
the most obvious case is selecting a subset from a set
in this example we select circles whose number is greater than three
a second case is merging two collections together to form a larger collection
in the example shown
two three structure data items are merged by fusing the node with a common property
that is two
in the last case we compute a function on a collection and
return the value of the function
so in this example the function is a simple count
in the real world this kind of aggregate function can be very complicated
we will come back to this issue when we talk more about map readings but
in this course we will talk about many different data operations
every operator must be efficient
that means every operator must perform its task as fast as possible
by taking up as little memory or our disk as possible
obviously the time to perform an operation
will depend on the size of the input and the size of the output
so if there is an opportunity to use concurrency where the operator can split
its data and have different threads operate on the pieces at the same time
it should definitely do so
we present a simple example of an operator we saw on the previous slide
so this operator called selection
refers to choosing a subset of a set based on some conditions
here we are choosing a subset of circles whose numbers are even
to make it more efficient we can take the input data and
partition it randomly into two groups
now for each group
we can concurrently run the subset algorithm and get the partial results
for this operation the partial results can be directly sent to the output
without any additional processing step
okay we in essence store the data efficiently
but is it any good
are there ways of knowing if the data is potentially error free and useful for
the intended purpose
this is the issue of data quality
there are many reasons why any data application
especially larger applications need to be mindful of data quality
here are three reasons of course there are more that we do not mention
the first reason emphasizes that the ultimate use of big data
is its ability to give us actionable insight
poor quality data leads to poor analysis and hence to poor decisions
the second related data in regulated industries in areas like clinical
trials for pharmaceutical companies or financial data like from banks
errors in data in these industries can regulate regulations leading to
legal complications
the third factor is different than the first two
it says if your big data should be used by other people or
a third party software it very important for
the data to give good quality to gain trust as a leader provider
a class of big data applications is scientific where large
integrated collections of data are created by human experts to
understand scientific questions
ensuring accuracy of data will lead to correct human engagement and
interaction with the data system
gartner the well known technology research and
advising company created a 2015 industry report on big data qualities
in this report they identify the approaches to meeting
the data quality requirements in the industry
this methods include the adherence to standards where applicable
it also refers to the need to create the rules in the data system
that can be use to check if the data passes a set of correct this qualities
like is even employed above 18
it also includes methods to clean the data if it found to have errors or
inconsistencies
further the data quality management should include a well define work flow on how
low quality data could be corrected to bring it back to a high level of quality