in this video we will provide a quick summary of the main points from our
first course on introduction to big data
if you have just completed our first course and
do not need a refresher you may now skip to the next lecture
after this video you will be able to recall
what started the big data era and the three main big data sources
summarize the volume variety velocity and
veracity issues related to each source
explain the five step data science process to gain value from big data
remember the main elements of the hadoop stack
we began our first course with an explanation of how a lead torrent of
big data combined with cloud computing capabilities to process data anytime and
anywhere has been at the core of the launch of the big data era
this big torrent of big data is often boil down to a few varieties of data
generated by machines people and
organizations with machine generated data
we refer to the data generated from real time sensors and industrial machinery or
vehicles
web logs that track user behavior online
environmental sensors
personal health trackers among many other sense data sources
with human generated data we really refer to the vast amount of social media data
status updates tweets photos and videos
with organization generated data we refer to more traditional types of data
including transaction information data bases and
structure data often stored in data warehouses
note that big data can be structured semi - structured and unstructured
which is a topic we will talk about more and in depth later in this course
whatever your big data application is and the types of big data you are using
the real value will come from integrating different types of data sources and
analyzing them at scale
overall by modeling managing and
integrating diverse streams to improve our business and
add value to our big data even before we start analyzing it
as a part of modeling and
managing big data is focusing on the dimensions of scale availability and
considering the challenges associated with this dimensions to pick the right tools
volume variety and velocity are the main dimensions which
we characterized big data and describe its challenges
we have huge amounts of data in different formats and
varying quality which must be processed quickly
veracity refers to the biases noise and abnormality in data
or the unmeasurable certainty is in the truthfulness and trustworthiness of data
and valence refers to the connectedness of big data
such as in the form of graph networks
each v presents a challenging dimension of big data mainly of size
complexity speed quality and consecutiveness
although we can list some other v based on the context
we prefer to list these five as fundamental dimensions which
this big data specialization helps you work on
moreover we must be sure to never forget the sixth v : value
at the heart of the big data challenge is turning
all of the other dimensions into truly useful business value
how will big data benefit you and your organization
the idea behind processing all this big data in the first place
is to bring value to the problem at hand
we need to take steps into big data engineering and
scalable data science to generate value out of big data
we have all heard it
data signs turns big data into insides or even actions
but what does that really mean
data signs can be taught of as the basis for empirical research
like data is used to induce information on the observations
these observations are mainly data
in our case big data related to a business or scientific use case
inside is a term we use to refer to the data products of data science
it is extracted from a diverse amount of data
through a combination of exploratory data analysis and modeling
the questions are sometimes less specific and it can require looking
carefully at the data for patterns in it to come up with a specific question
another important point to recognize is that data science is not static
one time analysis
it involves a process where models where you generate give us insights
are constantly improve to a further and prequel evidence and iterations
there are many ways to look at this process
one way of looking at it as two distinct activities
mainly big data engineering and big data analytics
or computational big data science as i like to call it
since more than simple analytics are being performed
a more detailed way of looking at the process reveals five listing steps or
activities of the data science process
namely acquire prepare analyze report and act
we can simply say that data science happens at the boundary of all the steps
ideally this process should support experimental work
which is constantly iterated and leads to more scientific exploration
as well as producing actionable results during these explorations
using dynamic scalability on big data and cloud platforms
this five step process can be used in alternative ways in real life big data
applications if we add the dependencies of different tools to each other
the influence of big data pushes for
alternative scalability approaches at each step of the process
acquire includes anything that helps us retrieve data
including finding accessing acquiring and moving data
it includes identification of and authenticated access to all related data
as well as transportation of data from sources to destinations
it includes ways to subset and match the data to regions or
times of interest which we sometimes refer to as geospatial querying
we divide the prepare data step into two sub - steps
based on the nature of the activity
the first step in data preparation involves exploring the data
to understand its nature what it means its quality and format
it often takes a preliminary analysis of data or
samples of data to understand it
this is why this primary step is called prepare
once we know more about the data through exploratory analysis
the next step is pre - processing of data for analysis
it includes cleaning data subsetting or filtering data and
creating data which programs can read and understand by modelling raw data
into a more defined data model or packaging it using a specific data format
we will learn more about data models and data formats later in this course
if there are multiple data sets involved
this step also includes integration of different data sources or
streams which is a topic we will explore in our course three
the prepared data then would be passed on to the analysis step
which involves selection of analytical techniques to use
building a model of the data and analyzing results
this step can take a couple of iterations on its own or
might require a data scientist to go back to steps 1 and
2 to get more data or package data in a different way
so exploration never ends
step 4 for communicating results includes evaluation of analytical results
presenting them in a visual way creating reports that include
an assessment of results with respect to success criteria
activities in this step can often be referred to with terms like interpret
summarize visualize and post - process
the last step brings us back to the very first reason we do data science
for a purpose
reporting insights from analysis and determining actions from insights based
on the purpose you initially defined is what we refer to as the act step
we have now seen all of the steps in a typical data science process
please note that this is an iterative process and findings from
one step may require previous steps to be repeated but need information
leading for further exploration and application of these steps
scalability of this process to big data analysis requires the use of
big data platforms like hadoop
the hadoop ecosystem frameworks and applications
provide such functionality through several overarching themes and goals
first they provide scalability to store large volumes of data
on commodity hardware
as the number of systems increase so
does the chance for crashes and hardware failures
they handle fault tolerance to gracefully recover from these problems
in addition they are designed to handle big data capacity and compressing text
files graphs of social networks streaming sensor data and raster images
we can add more data types to this variety
for any given data type
you can find several projects in the ecosystem that support it
finally they facilitate a shared environment
allow multiple jobs to execute simultaneously
additionally the hadoop ecosystem includes a wide range of open source
projects backed by a large and active community
these projects are free to use and easy to find support for
today there are over 100 big data open source projects
and this continues to grow many rely on hadoop but some are independent
here is one way of looking at a subset of tools in the hadoop ecosystem
this layer diagram is organized vertically based on the interface
lower level interfaces to storage and scheduling on the bottom and
high level languages and interactivity at the top
the hadoop distributed file system or hdfs is the foundation for
many big data frameworks since it provides scalable and reliable storage
as the size of your data increases you can add commodity
hardware to hdfs to increase storage capacity
so it enables what we call scaling out of your resources
hadoop yarn provide flexible scheduling and
resource management over the htfs storage
yarn is use at yahoo to schedule jobs across 40 000 servers
mapreduce is a programming model that simplifies parallel computing
instead of dealing with the complexities of synchronization and scheduling you only
need to give mapreduce two functions map and reduce
this programming model is so
powerful that google previously used it for indexing websites
mapreduce only assumes a limited model to express data
hive and pig are two additional programming models
on top of mapreduce to augment data modeling of mapreduce
with relational algebra and data flow modeling respectively
hive was created at facebook to issue sql - like queries using
mapreduce on their data in hdfs
pig was created at yahoo to model dataflow based programs using mapreduce
thanks to yarns ability to manage resources not just for
mapreduce but other programming models
giraph was built for processing large scale graphs efficiently
for example facebook uses giraph to analyze the social graphs of its users
similarly storm spark and flink were built for
real time and in - memory processing of big data
on top of the yarn resource scheduler and hdfs
in - memory processing is a powerful way of running big data applications
even faster achieving 100x better performance for some tasks
sometimes your data processing or tasks are not easily or
efficiently represented using the file and directory model of storage
examples of this include collections of key values or large sparse tables
nosql projects such as cassandra mongodb and
hbase handle all these cases
cassandra was created at facebook and facebook also use hbase for
its messaging platform
finally running all this tools requires a centralized management system for
synchronization configuration and to ensure high availability
zookeeper created by yahoo to wrangle services named after animals
performs these duties
just looking at the small number of hadoop stack components
we can already see that most of them are dedicated to data modeling
management and efficient processing of the data
in the rest of this course we will give you fundamental knowledge and
some practical skills on how to start modeling and managing your data and
picking the right tools for this activity from a plethora of big data tools
welcome to course two of the big data specialization
i am amarnath gupta
and i am ilkay altintas
we are really excited to work with you in this course
to develop your understanding and skills in big data modeling and management
you might have just finished our first course and see the potential and
challenges of big data
if you have not it not required but for
those with less background in the area you might find it valuable
let explain what we mean by big data modeling and management
suppose you have an application where the data is big in a sense and
it has a large volume or has high speed or comes with a lot of variations
even before you think of how to handle the bigness
you need to have a sense of what the data looks like
the goal of data modeling is to formally explore the nature of data so
that you can figure out what kind of storage you need and
what kind of processing you can do on it
the goal of data management is to figure out
what kind of infrastructure support you would need for the data
for example does your environment need to keep multiple replicas of the data
do you need to do statistical computation with the data
once these operational requirements you will
be able to choose the right system that will let you perform these operations
we will also introduce management of big data as it is
streaming from data sources and talk about storage architectures for big data
for example how can high velocity data get ingested
managed stored in order to enable real time analytical capabilities
or what is the difference between data at rest and data in motion
and how can a data system enable both
once you have understood the basic concepts of data modeling
data management and streaming data we will introduce you
to the characteristics of large volume data and how to think about that
thus we will transition from classical database management systems
that is dbmss to big data management systems or bdmss
we will present brief overviews of several big data management systems
available in the marketplace today
we are so excited to show you examples of archived and streaming big data sets
our goal is to provide you with simple hands on exercises that require
no programming but show you what big data looks like and why various
big data management systems are suitable for specific kinds of big data
in the end you will be able to design a simple
big data information system using this knowledge
we wish you a fun time learning and
hope to hear from you in the discussion forums and learner stories
happy learning and think big data
this is the second course in the 2016 version of our big data specialization
after listening to learners like you we have changed some of the content and
ordering in the specialization
this course takes you on the first step of any big data project
its modeling and management
we hope that this background on what big data looks like and
how it is modeled and managed in a large scale system will make you feel
more prepared to take steps towards retrieving and processing big data and
perform big data analytics which are topics coming up in the next courses