data science
getting value out of big data
we have all heard data science turned data into insights or even actions
but what does that really mean
data science can be thought of as a basis for
empirical research where data is used to induce information for observations
these observations are mainly data in our case
big data related to a business or scientific case
insight is a term
we use to refer to the data products of data science
it is extracted from a diverse amount of data through a combination of
exploratory data analysis and modeling
the questions are sometimes more specific and sometimes it requires
looking at the data and patterns in it to come up with the specific question
another important point to recognize is that data science is not static
it is not one time analysis
it involves a process where models generated to lead to insights
are constantly improved through further empirical evidence or simply data
for example a book retailer like amazon com can constantly improve
the model of a customer book preferences using the customer demographic
his or her previous purchases and the book reviews of the customer
the book retailer can also uses information to predict
which customers are likely to like any book
and take action to market the book to those customers
this is where we see insights being turned into action
as we have seen in the book marketing example using data science and analysis
of the past and current information data science generates actions
this is not just an analysis of the past but
rather generation of actionable information for the future
this is what we can call a prediction like the weather forecast
when you decide what to wear for the day based on the forecast of the day
you are taking action based on insight delivered to you
just like this business leaders and decision makers
take action based on the evidence provided by their data science teams
we set data science teams
this comes from the breadth of information and skill that it takes to make it happen
you have probably seen diagrams like this one that describe data science
data science happens at the intersection of computer science
mathematics and business expertise
if we zoom deeper into this diagram and
open the sets of expertise we will see a variation of this figure
even at this level all of these circles require deeper knowledge and skills
in areas like domain expertise data engineering statistics and computing
an even deeper analysis of these skills will lead you to skills like
machine learning statistical modeling relational algebra
business passion problem solving and data visualization
that a lot of skills to have for a single person
these wide range of skills and definitions of data scientists having them
all led to discussions like are data scientists unicorns
meaning they do not exist
there are data science experts who have expertise in more than one of these
skills for sure
but they are relatively rare and
still would probably need help from an expert on some of these areas
so in reality data scientists are teams of people who act like one
they are passionate about the story and the meaning behind data
they understand they problem they are trying to solve and
aim to find the right analytical methods to solve this problem
and they all have an interest in engineering solutions to solve problems
they also have curiosity about each others work and have communication
skills to interact with the team and present their ideas and results to others
as a summary a data science team often comes together to analyze situations
business or scientific cases which none of the individuals can solve on their own
there are lots of moving parts to the solution
but in the end all these parts should come together to provide
actionable insight based on big data
being able to use evidence - based insight in business decisions is more
important now than ever
data scientists have a combination of technical business and
soft skills to make this happen
getting started characteristics of big data
by now you have seen that big data is a blanket term that is used to refer to any
collection of data so large and complex that it exceeds the processing
capability of conventional data management systems and techniques
the applications of big data are endless
every part of business and society are changing in front our eyes due to that
fact that we now have so much more data and the ability for analyzing
but how can we characterize big data
you can say i know it when i see it
but there are easier ways to do it
big data is commonly characterized using a number of v
the first three are volume velocity and variety
volume refers to the vast amounts of data that is generated every second
minutes hour and day in our digitized world
variety refers to the ever increasing different forms that data can come in
such as text images voice and geospatial data
velocity refers to the speed at which data is being generated and
the pace at which data moves from one point to the next
volume variety and
velocity are the three main dimensions that characterize big data
and describe its challenges
we have huge amounts of data in different formats and
varying quality which must be processed quickly
more vs have been introduced to the big data community
as we discover new challenges and ways to define big data
veracity and valence are two of these additional v we
will pay special attention to as a part of this specialization
veracity refers to the biases noise and abnormality in data
or better yet it refers to the often unmeasurable uncertainties and
truthfulness and trustworthiness of data
valence refers to the connectedness of big data in the form of graphs
just like atoms
moreover we must be sure to never forget our sixth v value
how do big data benefit you and your organization
without a clear strategy and
an objective with the value they are getting from big data
it is easy to imagine that organizations will be sidetracked by all these
challenges of big data and not be able to turn them into opportunities
now let start looking into the first five of these v in detail
how does data science happen
five p of data science
now that we identified what data science is and how companies can strategize around
big data to start building a purpose let come back to using data science
to get value out of big data around the purpose or questions they defined
our experience with building and
observing successful data science projects led to a method around the craft with
five distinct components that can be defined as components of data science
here we define data science as a multi - disciplinary
craft that combines people teaming up around
application - specific purpose that can be achieved through a process
big data computing platforms and programmability
all of these should lead to products where the focus really
is on the questions or purpose that are defined by your big data strategy ideas
there are many technology data and analytical research and
development related activities around the questions
but in the end everything we do in this phase is to reach to that
final product based on our purposes
so it makes sense to start with it and
build a process around how we make this product happen
remember the wild fire prediction project i described
one of the products we described there was the rate of spread and
direction of an ongoing fire
we have identified questions and
the process that led us to the product in the end to solve it
we brought together experts around the table for fire modeling
data management time series analysis scalable computing
geographical information systems and emergency response
i asked them let not dive into the techniques yet
what is the problem at large
how do we see ourselves solving it
a typical conversation around the process starts with this question
then from then on drilling down to many areas of expertise
often we blur lines between the steps
my wildfire team would start listing things like we do not have an integrated
system or we do not have real - time access to data programmatically
so we cannot analyze fires on the fly
or they can say i cannot integrate sensor data with satellite data
all of this leads me to challenges i can then use to define problems
there are many dimensions of data science to think about within this discussion
let start with the obvious ones people and purpose
people refers to a data science team or the projects stakeholders
as you know by now they are expert in data and
analytics business computing science or big data management
like all the set of experts i listed in my wildfire scenario
the purpose refers to the challenge or set of challenges defined by your
big data strategy like solving the question related to the rate of spread and
direction of the fire perimeter in the wildfire case
since there a predefined team with a purpose a great place for
this team to start with is a process they could iterate on
we can simply say people with purpose will define a process to collaborate and
communicate around
the process is conceptual in the beginning and
defines the set of steps an how everyone can contribute to it
there are many ways to look at the process
one way of looking at it is as two distinct activities
mainly big data engineering and
big data analytics or computational big data science
as i like to call it as more than simple analytics is being performed here
a more detailed way of looking at the process reveals five distinct steps or
activities of this data science process
namely acquire prepare
analyze report and act
we can simply say that data science happens
at the boundary of all these steps
ideally this process should support experimental work and
dynamic scalability on the big data and computing platforms
this five step process can be used in alternative ways in real life big data
applications if we add the dependencies of different tools to each other
the influence of big data pushes for
alternative scalability approaches at each step of the process
just like you would scale each step on its own
you can scale the whole process as a whole in the end
one can simply say all of these steps have reporting needs in different forms
or there is a need to draw all these activities as an iterating process
including build explore and scale for big data as steps
big data analysis needs alternative data management techniques and
systems as well as analytical tools and methods
multiple modes of scalability is needed based on dynamic data and computing loads
in addition change in physical infrastructure
streaming data specific urgencies arising from special events
can also require multiple modes of scalability
in this intro course for simplicity
we will refer to the process as a set of five sequential activities that iterate
however we will touch on scalability as needed in our example applications
as a part of building your big data process
it important to simply mention two other p
the first one is big data platforms like the ones in the hadoop framework
or other computing platforms to scale different steps
the scalability should be in the mind of all team members and
get communicated as an expectation
in addition the scalable process should be programmable through
utilization of reusable and reproducible programming interfaces
to libraries like systems middleware analytical tools
visualization environments and end user reporting environments
thinking of big data applications as a process
including a set of activities that the team members can collaborate over
also helps to build metrics for accountability to be built into it
this way expectations on cost time
optimization of deliverables and time lines can be discussed
between the the members starting with the beginning of the data science process
sometimes we may not be able to do this in one step
and joint explorations like statistical evaluations of intermediate results or
accuracy of sample data sets become important
as a summary data science can be defined as a craft of using the five p
identified in this lecture leading to a sixth p the data product
having a process within the more business - driven ps like people and
purpose and the more technically driven p like platforms and
programmability leads to a streamlined approach that starts and
ends with the product team accountability and collaboration in mind
data science process provides guidelines for
implementing big data solution as it helps to organize efforts and
ensures all critical steps taken conforms to pre - define and agreed upon metrics
step one acquiring data
the first step in the data science process is to acquire the data
you need to obtain the source material before analyzing or acting on it
the first step in acquiring data is to determine what data is available
leave no stone unturned when it comes to finding the right data sources
you want to identify suitable data related to your problem and
make use of all data that is relevant to your problem for analysis
leaving out even a small amount of important data
can lead to incorrect conclusions
data comes from many places local and
remote in many varieties structured and un - structured
and with different velocities
there are many techniques and technologies to access these different types of data
let discuss a few examples
a lot of data exists in conventional relational databases
like structure big data from organizations
the tool of choice to access data from databases is structured query language or
sql which is supported by all relational databases management systems
additionally most data base systems come with a graphical application
environment that allows you to query and explore the data sets in the database
data can also exist in files such as text files and excel spreadsheets
scripting languages are generally used to get data from files
a scripting language is a high level programming language
that can be either general purpose or specialized for specific functions
common scripting languages with support for processing files are java script
python php perl r and matlab and are many others
an increasingly popular way to get data is from websites
web pages are written using a set of standards approved by
a world wide web consortium or shortly w3c
this includes a variety of formats and services
one common format is the extensible markup language or xml
which uses markup symbols or tabs to describe the contents on a webpage
many websites also host web services which produce program access to their data
there are several types of web services
the most popular is rest because it so easy to use
rest stand for representational state transfer
and it is an approach to implementing web services with performance
scalability and maintainability in mind
web socket services are also becoming more popular
since they allow real time modifications from web sites
nosql storage systems are increasingly used to manage a variety of data
types in big data
these data stores are databases that do not represent data
in a table format with columns and rows as with conventional relational databases
examples of these data stores include cassandra mongodb and hbase
nosql data stores provide apis to allow users to access data
these apis can be used directly or in an application that needs to access the data
additionally most nosql systems provide data access
via a web service interface such a rest
now let discuss our wildfire case study
as a real project that acquires data using several different mechanisms
the wifire project stores sensor data from weather stations in a relational database
we use sql to retrieve this data from the database to create
models to identify weather patterns associated with santa anna conditions
to determine whether a particular weather station is currently experiencing
santa anna conditions we access real time data using a web socket service
once we start listening to this service
we receive weather station measurements as they occur
this data is then processed and compared to patterns found by our models
to determine if a weather station is experiencing santa ana conditions
at the same time tweets are retrieved
using hashtags related to any fire that is occurring in the region
the tweet messages are retrieves using the twitter rest service
the idea is to determine the sentiment of these tweets to see if people
are expressing fear anger or are simply nonchalant about the nearby fire
the combination of sensor data and tweet sentiments helps
to give us a sense of the urgency of the fire situation
as a summary big data comes from many places
finding and evaluating data
useful to your big data analytics is important before you start acquiring data
depending on the source and
structure of data there are alternative ways to access it
step 2 - a : exploring data
after you have put together the data that you need for your application
you might be tempted to immediately build models to analyze the data
resist this temptation
the first step after getting your data is to explore it
exploring data is a part of the two - step data preparation process
you want to do some preliminary investigation
in order to gain a better understanding of the specific characteristics of your data
in this step you will be looking for
things like correlations general trends and outliers
without this step you will not be able to use the data effectively
correlation graphs can be used to explore the dependencies
between different variables in the data
graphing the general trends of variables will show you if there is
a consistent direction in which the values of these variables are moving towards
like sales prices going up or down
in statistics an outlier is a data point that distant from other data points
plotting outliers will help you double check for
errors in the data due to measurements
in some cases outliers that are not errors might make you find a rare event
additionally summary statistics provide numerical values to describe your data
summary statistics are quantities that capture various characteristics
of a set of values with a single number or a small set of numbers
some basic summary statistics that you should compute for
your data set are mean median range and standard deviation
mean and median are measures of the location of a set of values
mode is the value that occurs most frequently in your data set
and range and standard deviation are measures of spread in your data
looking at these measures will give you an idea of the nature of your data
they can tell you if there something wrong with your data
for example if the range of the values for age in your data includes
negative numbers or a number much greater than 100
there something suspicious in the data that needs to be examined
visualization techniques also provide a quick and effective and
overall a very useful way to look at data in this preliminary analysis step
a heat map such as the one shown here
can quickly give you the idea of where the hotspots are
many other different types of graphs can be used
histograms show that the distribution of the data and
can show skewness or unusual dispersion
boxplots are another type of plot for showing data distribution
line graphs are useful for seeing how values in your data change over time
spikes in the data are also easy to spot
scatter plots can show you correlation between two variables
overall there are many types of graph to visualize data
they are very useful in helping you understand the data you have
in summary what you get by exploring your data is a better
understanding of the complexity of the data you have to work with
this in turn will guide the rest of your process