helped Danone using sentiment analysis.
Meltwater is a company
that helps other companies
analyze what people are saying about
them and manage their online reputation.
One of the case studies on their
website is about Danone baby nutrition.
Meltwater helped Danone to monitor
the opinions through social media for
one of their marketing campaigns.
They were able to measure what
was impactful and what was not,
through such monitoring.
Meltwater also helped Danone manage
a potential reputation issue.
When a crisis occurred
related to horse DNA
being in some meat products across Europe.
While Danone was confident that they
didn't have an issue with their products,
having the information a couple of
hours before news hit the UK press.
Allowed them to check and
reassure their customers that their
products were safe to consume.
You can imagine millions of mothers
having been reassured and happy for
Danone's efforts on this.
This is an excellent story about how
big data helped manage public opinion.
And I'm sure Meltwater was able to help
them to measure the opinion impact through
social media as well.
Big data is now being
generated all around us.
So what?
It's the applications.
It is the way in which big data can
serve human needs that makes it valued.
Let's look at a few examples of the
applications big data is allowing us to
imagine and build.
Big data allows us to build better models,
which produce higher precision results.
We are witnessing hugely innovative
approaches in how companies
market themselves and sell products.
How human resources are managed.
How disasters are responded to.
And many other applications that
evidenced based data is being
used to influence decisions.
What exactly does that mean?
Here is one example.
Many of you might have experienced it,
I do.
Data, Amazon keeps some
things I've been looking at
allows them to personalize
what they show me.
Which hopefully helps narrow down
the huge raft of options I might get
than just searching on dinner plates.
Now, businesses can leverage technology
to make better informed decisions
that are actually based on signals
generated by actual consumers, like me.
Big data enables you to hear
the voice of each consumer as
opposed to consumers at large.
Now, many companies,
including Walmart and Target,
use this information to personalize their
communications with their costumers, which
in turns leads to better met consumer
expectations and happier customers.
Which basically is to say, big data
has enabled personalized marketing.
Consumers are copiously generating
publicly accessible data through
social media sites,
like Twitter or Facebook.
Through such data, the companies
are able to see their purchase history,
what they searched for, what they watched,
where they have been, and
what they're interested in
through their likes and shares.
Let's look at some examples of how
companies are putting this information to
build better marketing campaigns and
reach the right customers.
One area we are all familiar with
are the recommendation engines.
These engines leverage user patterns and
product features
to predict best match product for
enriching the user experience.
If you ever shopped on Amazon,
you know you get recommendations
based on your purchase.
Similarly, Netflix would
recommend you to watch
new shows based on your viewing history.
Another technique that companies use is
sentiment analysis, or in simple terms,
analysis of the feelings around events and
products.
Remember the blue plates I
purchased on Amazon.com?
I not only can read the reviews
before purchasing them,
I can also write a product
review once I receive my plates.
This way, other customers can be informed.
But more importantly, Amazon can keep
a watch on the product reviews and
trends for a particular product.
In this case, blue plates.
For example, they can judge if a product
review is positive or negative.
In this case,
while the first review is negative,
the next two reviews are positive.
Since these reviews are written in
English using a technique called natural
language processing, and
other analytical methods,
Amazon can analyze the general opinion of
a person or public about such a product.
This is why sentiment analysis often
gets referred to as opinion mining.
News channels are filled with
Twitter feed analysis every time
an event of importance occurs,
such as elections.
Brands utilize sentiment analysis
to understand how customers
relate to their product,
positively, negatively, neutral.
This depends heavily on use of
natural language processing.
Mobile devices are ubiquitous and
people almost always carry
their cellphones with them.
Mobile advertising is a huge market for
businesses.
Platforms utilize the sensors
in mobile devices,
such as GPS, and
provide real time location based ads,
offer discounts,
based on this deluge of data.
This time, let's imagine that
I bought a new house and
I happen to be in a few
miles range of a Home Depot.
Sending me mobile coupons about paint,
shelves, and
other new home related purchases
would remind me of Home Depot.
There's a big chance I
would stop by Home Depot.
Bingo!
Now I would like to take a moment to
analyze what kinds of big data are needed
to make this happen.
There's definitely the integration
of my consumer information and
the online and offline databases
that include my recent purchases.
But more importantly,
the geolocation data that falls under
a larger type of big data,
spacial big data.
We will talk about spacial
data later in this class.
Let's now talk about how the global
consumer behavior can be used for
product growth.
We are now moving from
personalize marketing
to the consumer behavior as a whole.
Every business wants to understand
their consumer’s collective
behavior in order to capture
the ever-changing landscape.
Several big data products enable this
by developing models to capture user
behavior and allow businesses to target
the right audience for their product.
Or, develop new products for
uncharted territories.
Let's look at this example.
After an analysis of their sales for
weekdays,
an airline company might notice that their
morning flights are always sold out,
while their afternoon
flights run below capacity.
This company might decide to add more
morning flights based on such analysis.
Notice that they are not using
individual consumer choices, but
using all the flights purchased without
consideration to who purchased them.
They might, however,
decide to pay closer attention to
the demographic of these consumers
using big data to also add similar
flights in other geographical regions.
With rapid advances in genome
sequencing technology,
the life sciences industry is experiencing
an enormous draw in biomedical big data.
This biomedical data is being used
by many applications in research and
personalized medicine.
Did you know genomics data is one of
the largest growing big data types?
Between 100 million and 2 billion human
genomes could be sequenced by year 2025.
Impressive.
This [INAUDIBLE] sequence data demands for
between 2 exabytes and
40 exabytes in data storage.
In comparison, all of YouTube only
requires 1 to 2 exabytes a year.
An exabyte is 10 to the power 18 bites.
That is, 18 zeros after 40.
Of course, analysis of such massive
volumes of sequence data is expensive.
It could take up to 10,000
trillion CPU hours.
One of the biomedical applications
that this much data is enabling
is personalized medicine.
Before personalized medicine,
most patients without a specific type and
stage of cancer received
the same treatment,
which worked better for
some than the others.
Research in this area is enabling
development of methods to analyze
large scale data to develop solutions
that tailor to each individual,
and hence hypothesize
to be more effective.
A person with cancer may now still receive
a treatment plan that is standard,
such as surgery to remove a tumor.
However, the doctor may
also be able to recommend
some type of personalized
cancer treatment.
A big challenge in biomedical big data
applications, like many other fields,
is how we can integrate many types of data
sources to gain further insight problem.
In one of our future lectures,
my colleagues here at
the Supercomputer Center,
will explain how he and his colleague have
used big data from a variety of sources
for personalized patient interventions.
Another application of big data comes
from interconnected mesh of large
number of sensors implanted
across smart cities.
Analysis of data generated
from sensors in real time
allows cities to deliver better
service quality to inhabitants.
And reduce unwanted affect such
as pollution, traffic congestion,
higher than optimal cost on
delivering urban services.
Let's take our city, San Diego.
San Diego generates a huge volumes
of data from many sources.
Traffic sensors, satellites,
camera networks, and more.
What if we could integrate and
synthesize these data streams to
do even more for our community?
Using such big data,
we can work toward making San Diego
the prototype digital city.
Not only for life-threatening hazards, but
making our daily lives better, such as
managing traffic flow more efficiently or
maximizing energy savings,
even as we'll see next, wildfires.
If you want to read more,
here's a link to the AT Kearney report,
where they talk about other
areas using big data.
As a summary,
big data has a huge potential
to enable models with higher
precision in many application areas.
And these highly precise models
are influencing and transforming business.
Big Data Generated By People,
how is it being used?
We listed a number of challenges for
using unstructured data
generated by human activities.
Now let's look at some of the emerging
technologies to tackle these challenges.
And see some examples that turn
unstructured data into valuable insights.
Although unstructured data specially
the kind generated by people has
a number of challenges.
The good news is that the business
culture of today is shifting
to tackle these challenges and
take full advantage of such data.
As it is often said,
a challenge is a perfect opportunity.
This is certainly the case for
big data and
these challenges have created
a tech industry of it's own.
This industry is mostly centered or
as we would say, layered or
stacked, around a few fundamental
open source big data frameworks.
Need big data tools
are designed from scratch
to manage unstructured information and
analyze it.
A majority of these tools
are based on an open source
big data framework called Hadoop.
Hadoop is designed to support
the processing of large data sets
in a distributed computing environment.
This definition would already give you a
hint that it tackles the first challenge.
Namely, the volume of
unstructured information.
Hadoop can handle big batches
of distributed information but
most often there's a need for
a real time processing of people generated
data like Twitter or Facebook updates.
Financial compliance monitoring is another
area of our central time processing is
needed, in particular
to reduce market data.
Social media and market data are two
types of what we call high velocity data.
Storm and
Spark are two other open source frameworks
that handle such real time
data generated at a fast rate.
Both Storm and
Spark can integrate data with any
database or data storage technology.
As we have emphasized
before unstructured data
does not have a relational data model so
it doesn't generally
fit into the traditional data warehouse
model based on relational databases.
Data warehouses are central repositories
of integrated data from one or
more sources.
The data that gets stored in warehouses,
gets extracted from multiple sources.
It gets transformed into
a common structured form and
it can slow that into
the central database for
use by workers creating analytical
reports throughout an enterprise.
This Exact Transform Load
process is commonly called ETL.
This approach was fairly standard in
enterprise data systems until recently.
As you probably noticed,
it is fairly static and
does not fit well with today's
dynamic big data world.
So how do today's businesses
get around this problem?
Many businesses today are using a hybrid
approach in which their smaller
structured data remains in
their relational databases, and
large unstructured datasets get stored
in NoSQL databases in the cloud.
NoSQL Data technologies are based
on non-relational concepts and
provide data storage options
typically on computing clouds
beyond the traditional relational
databases centered rate houses.
The main advantage of using
NoSQL solutions is their ability
to organize the data for
scalable access to fit the problem and
objectives pertaining to
how the data will be used.
For example, if the data will be used
in an analysis to find connections
between data sets, then the best
solution is a graph database.
Neo4j is an example of a graph database.
Graph networks is a topic that
the graph analytics course
later in this specialization,
we'll explain in depth.
If the data will be best accessed using
key value pairs like a search engine
scenario, the best solution is probably
a dedicated key value paired database.
Cassandra is an example
of a key value database.
These, and
many other types of NoSQL systems will
be explained further in course two.
So we are now confident that there
are emerging technologies for
individual challenges to manage
people generated unstructured data.
But how does one take advantage
of these to generate value?
As we saw big data must pass through a
series of steps before it generates value.
Namely data access, storage,
cleaning, and analysis.
One approach to solve this problem is
to run each stage as a different layer.
And use tools available to
fit the problem at hand, and
scale analytical solutions to big data.
In coming lectures, we will see
important tools that you can use
to solve your big data problems in
addition to the ones you have seen today.
Now let's take a step back and remind
ourselves what some of the value was.
Remember how companies can listen to the
real voice of customers using big data?
It is this type of generated
data that enabled it.
Sentiment analysis analyzes social
media and other data to find
whether people associate positively or
negatively with you business.
Organizations are utilizing
processing of personal data to
understand the true
preferences of their customers.
Now let's take a fun quiz to guess how
much Twitter data companies analyze
every day to measure sentiment
around their product.
The answer is 12 terabytes a day.
For comparison,
you would need to listen continuously for
two years to finish listening
to 1 terabyte of music.
Another example application area for
people generated data is customer
behavior modeling and prediction.
Amazon, Netflix and
a lot of other organizations,
use analytics to analyze
preferences of their customers.
Based on consumer behavior, organizations
suggest better products to customers,
and in turn have happier customers and
higher profits.
Another application area where the value
comes in the form of societal impact and
social welfare, is disaster management.
As you have seen in my wildfire example,
there are many types of big data that
can help with disaster response.
Data in the form of pictures and
tweets, helps facilitate
a collective response to disaster
situations, such as evacuations through
the safest route based on community
feedback through social media.
There are also networks that
turn crowd sourcing and
big data analytics into collective
disaster response tools.
The International Network
of Crisis Mappers,
also called Crisis Mappers Net,
is the largest of such networks and
includes an active international
community of volunteers.
Crisis Mappers use big data in the form
of aerial and satellite imagery,
participatory maps and
live Twitter updates to analyze
the data using geospatial platforms,
advanced visualization,
live simulation and computational and
statistical models.
Once analyzed the results get reported to
rapid response and humanitarian agencies
in the form of mobile and
web applications.
In 2015, right after the Nepal earthquake
Crises Mappers crowd source the analysis
of tweets and mainstream media to
rapidly access disaster damage and
needs and to identify where
humanitarian help is needed.
This example is amazing and shows how
big data can have huge impacts for
social welfare in times of need.
You can learn more about this
story at the following link.
As a summary, although there are
challenges in working with unstructured
people generated data at a scale and
speed that applications demand.
There are also emerging technologies and
solutions that are being
used by many applications to generate
value from the rich source of information.
Big Data Generated By People,
The Unstructured Challenge.
People are generating massive amounts of
data every day through their activities on
various social media networking sites
like Facebook, Twitter, and LinkedIn.
Or online photo sharing sites like
Instagram, Flickr, or Picasa.
And video sharing websites like YouTube.
In addition an enormous amount of
information gets generated via
blogging and commenting,
internet searches, more via text messages,
email, and through personal documents.
Most of this data is text-heavy and
unstructured,
that is non-conforming to
a well-defined data model.
We can also consider this
data to be content with
occasionally some
description attached to it.
This much activity Leads
to a huge growth in data.
Did you know that in a single day,
Facebook users produce
more data than combined US
academic research libraries?
Let's look at some similar
daily data volume numbers
from some of the biggest online platforms.
It is amazing that some of these
numbers are in the petabyte range for
daily activity.
A petabyte is a thousand terabytes.
The sheer size of mostly unstructured
data generated by humans
brings a lot of challenges.
Unstructured data refers to data that does
not conform to a predefined data model.
So no relation model and no SQL.
It is mostly anything that we
don't store in a traditional
Relational database management system.
Consider a sales receipt that
you get from a grocery store.
It has a section for a date, a section for
store name, and
a section for total amount.
This is an example of structure.
Humans generate a lot of
unstructured data in form of text.
There's no given format to that.
Look at all the documents that you
have written with your hand so far.
Collectively, it is a bank of unstructured
data you have personally generated.
In fact, 80 to 90% of all data in
the world is unstructured and
this number is rapidly growing.
Examples of unstructured data generated
by people includes texts, images,
videos, audio,
internet searches, and emails.
In addition to it's rapid growth
major challenges of unstructured data
include multiple data formats,
like webpages, images, PDFs,
power point, XML, and other formats that
were mainly built for human consumption.
Think of it, although I can sort my
email with date, sender and subject.
It would be really difficult
to write a program,
to categorize all my email messages
based on their content and
organize them for me accordingly another
challenge of human generated data
is the volume and fast generation of data,
which is what we call velocity.
Just take a moment to study this info
graphic, and observe what happens in one
minute on the internet, and
consider how much to contribute to it.
Moreover, confirmation of unstructured
data is often time consuming and costly.
The costs and
time of the process of acquiring, storing,
cleaning, retrieving, and processing
unstructured data can add up to quite and
investment before we can start
reaping value from this process.
It can be pretty hard
to find the tools and
people to implement such a process and
reap value in the end.
As a summary,
although there is an enormous amount of
data generated by people,
most of this data is unstructured.
The challenges of working with
unstructured data should not
be taken lightly.
Next, we'll look at how businesses are
tackling these challenges to gain insight.
And thus, value out of working
with people generated data.
As we have already seen, there are many
different exciting applications
that are being enabled
by the Big Data era.
As part of my core research here at
the San Diego Supercomputer Center,
I work on building methodologies and
tools to make Big Data useful to dynamic
data driven scientific applications.
My colleagues and I work on many grand
challenge data science applications,
in all areas of science and engineering,
including genomics, geoinformatics,
metro science, energy management,
biomedicine, and personalized health.
What is common to all these applications
is their unique way of bringing
together new modes of data and
computing research.
Let me tell you the one I'm passionate
about, Wildfire Analytics,
which breaks up into two components,
prediction and response.
Why is this so important?
On May 2014, in San Diego County where
the instructors of this
specialization live and work,
there were 14 fires burning,
as many as nine at one time,
which burned a total of 26,000 acres,
11,000 hectares,
an area just less than the size
of the City of San Francisco.
Six people were injured and
one person died.
And these wildfires
resulted in a total cost of
over $60 million US in damage and
firefighting.
These wildfires can become so severe
that we actually call them firestorms.
Although we cannot
control such fire storms,
something we can do is to get ahead
of them by predicting their behavior.
This is why disaster management
of ongoing wildfires relies
heavily on understanding their
direction and rate of spread.
As these fires are a part of our lives,
we wanted to see if we can use Big Data to
monitor, predict and manage a firestorm.
Why can Big Data help?
As we will see in this video,
indeed, wildfire prevention and
response can benefit from many
streams in our data torrent.
Some streams are generated by
people through devices they carry.
A lot come from sensors and satellites,
things that measure environmental factors.
And some come from organizational data,
including area maps,
better service updates and field content
databases, which archive how much
registers vegetation and other types of
fuel are in the way of a potential fire.
What makes this a Big Data problem?
Because novel approaches and
responses can be taken if
we can integrate this many
diverse data streams.
Many such data sources have already
existed for quite some time.
But what is lacking in disaster
management today is a dynamic system
integration of real time sensor networks,
satellite imagery,
near real time data management tools,
wildfire simulation tools,
connectivity to emergency command centers,
and
all these before, during,
and after a firestorm.
As you will see,
the integration of diverse streams and
novel ways is really what's driving
our ability to see new things and
develop predictive analytics,
which may help improve our world.
What are these diverse sources?
One of the most important data sources
is sensor data streaming in from weather
stations and satellites,
such sensed data include temperature,
humidity, air pressure.
We can also include image
data streaming from
mountaintop cameras and
satellites in this category.
Another important data source
comes from institutions
such as
the San Diego Supercomputer Center,
which generate data related
to wildfire modeling.
These include past and current fire
perimeter maps put together by
the authorities and fuel maps that
tell us about the vegetation,
and other types of fuel in a fire's path.
These types of data sources are often
static or updated at a slow rate,
but they provide valuable data
that is well-curated and verified.
A huge part of data on fires is
actually generated by the public
on social media sites such as Twitter,
which support photo sharing resources.
These are the hardest data sources to
streamline during an existing fire, but
they can be very valuable once
integrated with other data sources.
Imagine synthesizing all the pictures
on Twitter about an ongoing fire or
checking the public sentiment
around the boundaries of a fire.
Once you have access to such
information at your fingertips,
there are many things you
can do with such data.
You can simply monitor it, or
maybe you can visualize it.
But it's not until you bring all these
different types of data sources together
and integrate them with real time analysis
and predictive modeling that you can
really make contributions in predicting
and responding to wildfire emergencies.
So now,
I will like you to take a moment and
imagine how Big Data might help
with firefighting in the future.
All these streams of data will come
together in 3D displays that can show
all the related information along
with weather and fire predictions,
just like the way tornadoes
are managed today.
Let's look at a 2nd example where big data
can have a big impact on saving lives.
I mean,
literally saving lives one life at a time.
I collaborated with a number of
world-class researchers in San Diego, and
an industrial group who are dedicated to
improving human health through research
and practice of precision medicine.
What is precision medicine?
It is an emerging area of medicine
targeted toward an individual person.
Analysing her genetics, her environment,
her daily activities so
that one can detect or
predict a health problem early,
help prevent disease and
in case of illness provide the right drug
at the right dose that is
suitable just for her.
Very recently the White House and
the National Institute of Health here
in the U.S. have declared it to be
a top priority area for research and
development for the next decade.
The expected learning
outcome of this video is for
you to give example of sensor,
organizational and
people-generated data used
in precision medicine.
And, explain why the integration of
different kinds of data is critical
in advancing healthcare.
For any technology to
succeed in real life we need
not only a certain level of maturity of
the technology itself, but a number of
enabling factors including social
economic environment, market demands,
consumer readiness, cost effectiveness,
all of which must work together.
Why is big data for
precision medicine important now?
Let's see.
An important aspect of precision
medicine is to utilize
an individual's genetic profile for
his or her own diagnoses and treatment.
Analyzing the human genome,
which holds the key to human health
is rapidly becoming more affordable.
Today's cost to sequence a genome is less
than 10% of what it
cost just back in 2008.
But, human genomic data is big.
How big?
In a perfect world, just the three
billion letters of your genome
would require about 700
megabytes to store.
In the real world, meaning the kind of
data generated from genome sequencing
machines, we need 200GB to store a genome.
And it takes now about
a day to sequence a genome.
We are finally beginning to create more
electronic records that can be stored and
manipulated in digital media.
Most doctors offices and hospitals now
use electronic health record systems
which contain all details of
a patient's visit and lab test.
How big is this data?
As a quick example The Samaritan Medical
Center Watertown New York at 294 that
Community Hospital reported
120 terabytes as of 2013.
The data value more than double
in just the last two years.
So clearly just in a past two years
dramatic changes have prepared the health
care industry to produce and analyze
larger mounts of complex patient data.
To summarize what we have seen so far
the key components of these changes are:
Reduced cost of data generation and
analysis, increased availability of cheap
large data storage, and they increased
digitization of previously paper records.
But we need one more capability to advance
toward the promised land of individualized
health care practices.
We need to combine various types of
data produce by different groups in
a meaningful way.
Let's look at this issue from
the same point of view as Ilka did.
With her discussion of how big data
can help with wildfire analytics.
The key is the integration of
multiple types of data sources.
Data from sensors,
organizations and people.
In the next few slides,
we look at each of these, and
then I'll share a story about some of the
new and really exciting ways people data
especially has the potential to
change healthcare big data landscape.
Let's start with sensor data.
Sure, digital hospital equipment
have been producing sensor data for
years, but it was unlikely that
the data was ever stored or
shared, let alone
analyzed retrospectively.
These were intended for
real-time use, to inform healthcare
professionals, and then got discarded.
Now we have many more sensors and
deployment.
And many more places
that are capturing and
explicitly gathering information
to be stored and analyzed.
Let's just take a new kind of data
that's increasingly becoming
common in our daily lives.
Fitness devices are everywhere now
their sales have skyrocketed
in the last few years.
They are in wristbands, watches, shoes and
vests, directly communicating with your
personal mobile device, tracking several
activity variables like blood pressure,
different types of activities,
blood glucose levels, etc at every moment.
Their goal is to improve wellness.
By having you monitor
your daily status and
hopefully improve your
lifestyle to stay healthy.
But the data they generate can be
very useful medical information
because this data is about what
happens in your normal life and
not just when you go to the doctor.
How much data do they generate?
The device called FitBit can
produce several gigabytes a day.
Could this data be used to save healthcare
costs, effect a healthier lifestyle?
That's a question mark.
It's safe to guess that this data
alone wouldn't drive the dream of
precision medicine.
But what if we consider integrating
it with other sources of data
like electronic health records or
a genomic profile?
This remains an open question.
This is an open arena for research that
my colleagues at scripts are doing.
It's also a potentially significant area
for product and business development.
Let's look at some examples of health
related data being generated by
organizations.
Many public databases
including those curated and
managed by NCBI, the National Center for
Biotechnology Information,
had been created to capture the basic
scientific data and knowledge for
humans and other model organisms at
the different building blocks of life.
These databases carry both experimental
and computed data that are necessary to
observations for
unconquered diseases like cancer.
In addition,
many have created knoweledge-bases
like the Geneontology and
The Unified Medical Language System
to assemble human knowledge in
a machine processable form.
These are just a few examples of
organizational data sources and
governmental data gathered by health
care systems around the world
could also be used as a massive
source of information.
But really some of
the most interesting and
novel opportunities seem likely to come
from the area of people generated data.
Mobile healths apps is an area
that is growing significantly.
There are apps now to monitor heart rates,
blood pressure, and
test oxygen saturation levels.
Apps, we might say,
record data from sensors but
are also obviously generated from people.
But there is more people generated
data that's interesting beyond censure
measurements.
In 2015 the Webby People's Voice Award
went to an app which supports
meditation and mindfulness.
Rather than an electronic sensing device,
a human would indicate how many
minutes per day they spent meditating.
If they interact with the app
which reminds them to be mindful,
then we have human generated behavior
that we couldn't get from a sensor.
There are well over 100,000 health apps
today in either iTunes or Google Play.
And by some estimates
the Mobile Health App market
may be worth 27 billion dollars by 2017.
So really we are just seen the beginning
of what data might be generated here
from what's being called human sensors,
but to really understand where the power
of people generated data might take us
in the era of big data for healthcare.
Let's imagine how things stand now.
In general,
a patient goes to see their doctor and
maybe their doctor asks if they have had
any side effects from their medications.
The accuracy and
hence the quality of data patients provide
in this kind of setting is very low.
Not that it's really the patients fault.
It might have been days or
weeks ago that they experienced something.
They may be unsure whether something
they experienced was actually a reaction
to then report it.
And there might be details about exactly
when they took a medication that
are meaningful, but
they've forgotten it after the fact.
Today, people are self reporting reactions
and experiences they are having.
We're on Twitter, on blog sites,
online support groups,
online data sharing services: these
are sources of data that we've
never had before that can be used to
understand in a far more detailed and
personal rate the impact of drug
integrations are responses to certain
If applications were designed
to integrate doctor and
hospital records with information
on when drugs were taken and
then to further mine social media or
collect self reports from patients.
Who knows what kinds of questions
we will be able to answer?
Or new questions we may be able to ask?
Where does big data come from?
The first thing I would like to
say before talking about big data
is that it is not new.
Most of the big data sources existed
before, but the scale we use and
apply them today has changed.
Just look at this image of open
link data on the Internet.
I thought this image was so cool.
It shows not only there are so
many sources of data, but
they're also connected.
If you want to check it out yourself,
we'll give you the link
at the end of this video.
Big data is often boiled down to a few
varieties of data generated by machines,
people, and organizations.
With machine generated data we refer to
data generated from real time sensors in
industrial machinery or vehicles that
logs that track user behavior online,
environmental sensors or
personal health trackers, and
many other sense data resources.
The Large Hadron Collider
generates 40 terabytes of data
every second during experiments.
But human generated data, we refer to
the vast amount of social media data,
status updates, tweets,
photos, and medias.
With organizational generated data we
refer to more traditional types of data,
including transaction
information in databases and
structured data open
stored in data warehouses.
Note that big data can be either
structured, semi-structured, or
unstructured, which is a topic we will
talk about more later in this course.
In most business use cases, any single
source of data on its own is not useful.
Real value often comes from combining
these streams of big data sources
with each other and
analyzing them to generate new insights,
which then goes back into
being big data themselves.
Once you have such insights,
it then enables what we call data
enabled decisions and actions.
Let's now look into these different
types of big data in more detail.
Why is Big Data generated
by machines useful?
Let's go back for
a second to our first example for
machine generated big data planes.
What is producing all
that data on the plane?
If you look at some of
the sensors that contribute
to the half terabyte of
data generated on a plane,
we will find that some of it comes from
accelerometers that measure turbulence.
There are also sensors built into
the engines for temperature, pressure,
many other measurable factors
to detect engine malfunctions.
Constant real-time analysis of all
the data collected provides help
monitoring and
problem detection at 40,000 feet.
That's approximately 12,000
meters above ground.
We call this type of
analytical processing in-situ.
Previously, in traditional relational
database management systems,
data was often moved to
computational space for processing.
In Big Data space In-Situ
means bringing the computation
to where data is located or,
in this case, generated.
A key feature of these types
of real-time notifications is
that they enable real-time actions.
However, using such a capability
would require you to approach your
application and your work differently.
If you are using an activity tracker, you
should probably come up with a strategy
for how you will incorporate the usage of
these useful gadgets into your lifestyle.
Just like that, if you're planning to
incorporate Big Data driven insights into
your organization, you need to define
a new strategy, and a new way of working.
Most Big Data centric businesses have
updated their culture to be more real-time
action oriented, refining real-time
processes to handle anything from customer
relations and fraud detection,
to system monitoring and control.
In addition, such volumes of real-time
data and analytical operations that need
to take place requires an increased
use of scalable computing systems,
which need to be a part of the planning
for an organizational Big Data strategy.
They see affects of such
changes also in SCADA system.
SCADA stands for Supervisory Control and
Data Acquisition.
SCADA is a type of industrial control
system for remote monitoring and
control of industrial processes
that exists in the physical world,
potentially including multiple sites,
many types of sensors.
In addition to monitoring and control,
SCADA system can be used to define
actions for reduced waste and improved
efficiency in industrial processes,
including those of manufacturing and
power generation, public or
private infrastructure processes,
including water treatment, oil, and
gas pipelines, and
electrical power transmission, and
facility processes including buildings,
airports, ships, and space stations.
They can even be used in smart
building applications to monitor and
control heating, ventilation,
air conditioning systems like HVAC,
access, and energy consumption.
Again, the management of these processes
once the trends, patterns, and
anomalies are identified in real-time
needs to be decided in the Big Data case.
As a summary, as the largest and fastest
type of Big Data, machine generated
data can uniquely enable real-time
actions in many systems and processes.
However, a culture shift is needed for
its computing and real-time action.
Big data generated by machines.
It's everywhere and there's a lot.
Do big planes require big data?
Absolutely!
Did you know that a Boeing 787 produces
half a terabyte of data
every time it flies?
Really, almost every part of
the plane updates both the flight and
the ground team about
its status constantly.
Where's all this data coming from?
This is an example of machine-generated
data coming from sensors.
If you look at all sources of big data,
machine data is the largest
source of big data.
Additionally, it is very complex.
In general, we call machines that provide
some type of sensing capability smart.
Have you ever wondered why you
call your cell phone a smartphone?
Because it gives you a way
to track many things,
including your geolocation, and
connect you to other things.
So what makes a smart device smart, smart?
Generally speaking, There are three
main properties of smart devices
based on what they do with sensors and
things they encapsulate.
They can connect to other devices or
networks, they can execute services and
collect data autonomously,
that means on their own, they have
some knowledge of the environment.
The widespread availability of the smart
devices and their interconnectivity
led to a new term being coined,
The Internet of Things.
Think of a world of smart devices at home,
in your car, in the office,
city, remote rural areas,
the sky, even the ocean,
all connected and all generating data.
Let's look at an example of a device
that has some of these things in it.
An activity tracker is a device or
application for monitoring and
tracking fitness-related metrics
such as distance walked or run,
calorie consumption, and in some cases,
heartbeat and quality of sleep.
What if everyone in New York City
wore an activity tracker?
What if everyone wore several?
I personally have three activity
trackers that I use on a daily basis.
One to track my sleep, another one
to track my physical activity, and
a third, my smartphone,
that goes everywhere with me.
So it is not that unusual to imagine that
this will be the case for many people.
As you have already heard from in
a previous lecture on personalized data,
such activity trackers
have enabled a new way
of doing patient intervention
via personalized medicine.
Similarly, the sensors in planes have
generated a new way of looking at
fleet management and flight safety.
As a summary,
machines collect data 24/7 via
their built-in sensors,
both at personal and industrial scales.
And thus, they are the largest
of all the big data sources.
Organization-Generated Data.
Benefits come from combining
with other data types.
How are some organizations
benefiting from big data?
Let's look at real world examples to
see the advantages these organizations
are getting out of big data.
One of these companies is UPS.
UPS delivers 16 million shipments per day.
They get around 40 million
tracking requests.
That's huge.
An estimate of how much data UPS has
on its operations is 16 petabytes.
Can you guess how much money UPS can
save by reducing each driver's route
by just one mile?
If they can reduce distance traveled
by each truck by even one mile,
UPS can save a whopping $50 million U.S.
per year.
This is where big data steps in.
Utilizing complex optimization
over large datasets
can lead to route optimizations that were
previously not visible to the company.
Big data, together with smart processing,
enables UPS to manage thousands
of route optimizations.
Let's travel from package
delivery to the retail domain.
An organization from
the retail shopping domain
that heavily utilizes big data is Walmart.
Walmart is a big organization that gets
250 million customers in 10,000 stores.
Did you know they collect 2.5
petabytes of data per hour?
They collect data on Twitter tweets,
local events, local weather,
in-store purchases, online clicks and
many other sales, customer and
product related data.
They use this data to find patterns
such as which products are frequently
purchased together, and what is the best
new product to introduce in their stores,
to predict demand at
the particular location,
and to customize customer recommendations.
Overall, by leveraging big data and
analytics, Walmart has maintained
its position as a top retailer.
UPS and Walmart examples were just two out
of a number of companies using big data.
Big data is producing results for
companies in all sectors.
Studies forecast spending on
big data technologies to go up
drastically in the next five years.
A study by Bane and Company
suggests that early adopters of big
data analytics have gained a significant
lead over the rest of the corporate world.
For graphics referenced here,
we see that companies that use
analytics are twice as likely
to be in the top quartile of financial
performance within their industries.
Five times as likely to make decisions
much faster than market peers.
Three times as likely to
execute decisions as intended.
And twice as likely to use data very
frequently when making decisions.
This points to the growth and
demand of people and
technology centered around or
specializing in big data applications.
As a summary, organizations are gaining
significant benefit from integrating
big data practices into their culture and
breaking their silos.
Some major benefits to organizations are
operational efficiency, improved marketing
outcomes, higher profits, and
improved customer satisfaction.
Big data, generated by organizations,
structured but often siloed.
The last type of big data we will discuss
is big data generated by organizations.
This type of data is the closest to
what most businesses currently have.
But it's considered a bit out of fashion,
or
traditional, compared to
other types of big data.
However, it is at least as important
as other types of big data.
So how do organizations produce data?
The answer to how
an organization generates data
is very unique to the organization and
context.
Each organization has distinct
operation practices and
business models, which result in
a variety of data generation platforms.
For example, the type and source of data
that a bank gets is very different from
what a hardware equipment
manufacturer gets.
Some common types of organizational big
data come from commercial transactions,
credit cards, government institutions,
e-commerce, banking or
stock records, medical records, sensors,
transactions, clicks and so on.
Almost every event can
be potentially stored.
Organizations store this data for
current and
future use, as well as for
analysis of the past.
Let's say you're an organization
that collects sales transactions.
You can use this data for pattern
recognition to detect correlated products,
to estimate demand for
products likely to go up in sales, and
capture fraudulent activity.
Moreover, when you know your
sales record and can correlate it
with your marketing records, you can find
which campaigns really made an impact.
You are already becoming
a data savvy organization.
Now think of bringing your
sales data together with other
external open public data,
such as major world events in the news.
You can ask, was it savvy marketing or
a consequence of external events
that triggered your sales?
Using proper analytics,
you can now build inventories to match
your predicted growth and demand.
In addition, organizations build and
apply processes to record and
monitor business events of interest,
such as registering a customer,
manufacturing a product or
taking an order.
These processes collect
highly structured data
that include transactions,
reference tables, and
relationships, as well as
the metadata that sets its context.
Usually, structured data is stored in
relational database management systems.
However, we call any data
that is in the form of
a record located in a fixed field or
file structured data.
This definition also
includes spreadsheets.
As I have mentioned before,
traditionally this type of
highly structured data is the vast
majority of what IT managed and
processed in both operational and
business intelligence systems.
Let's look at the sales transaction
data in our previous example.
If you look at the data in
the relational table on the right.
As the name structured suggests,
the table is organized to store data using
a structure defined by a model.
Each column is tagged to tell us what
data that column intends to store.
This is what we call a data model.
A data model defines
each of these columns and
fields in the table, and
defines relationships between them.
If you look at the product ID column,
you will see that it includes only
identifiers that can potentially be linked
to another table defining these products.
The ability to define such relationships,
easily make structured data,
or in this case relational databases,
highly adopted by many organizations.
There are commonly used
languages like SQL,
the Structured Query Language, to extract
data of interest from such tables.
This is referred to as querying the data.
However, it could even be a challenge
to integrate such structured data.
This image shows us a continuum
of technologies to model,
collect and query unstructured
data coming from software and
hardware components
within an organization.
In the past, such challenges
led to information being stored
in what we call silos,
even within an organization.
Many organizations have traditionally
captured data at the department level,
without proper infrastructure and
policy to share and integrate this data.
This has hindered the growth of
scalable pattern recognition
to the benefits of
the entire organization.
Because no one system has access to
all data that the organization owns.
Each data set is compartmentalized.
If such silos are left untouched,
organizations risk having outdated,
unsynchronized, and
even invisible data sets.
Organizations are realizing
the detrimental outcomes of this rigid
structure.
And changing policies and infrastructure
to enable integrated processing of
all data to the entire
organization's benefit.
Cloud-based solutions
are seen as agile and
low capital intensive
solutions in this area.
As a summary, while highly structured
organizational data is very useful and
trustworthy, and
thus a valuable source of information,
organizations must pay special
attention to breaking up
the silos of information to
make full use of its potential.
The key, integrating diverse data.
Whatever your big data application is, and
the types of big data you are using
the real value will come from integrating
different types of data sources,
and analyzing them at scale.
So how do we start getting this value?
Sometimes, all it takes,
is looking at the data you already
collect in a different way.
And it can mean a big difference
in your return on investment.
This new story from June 2015
mentions that Carnival Cruises
is using structured and unstructured
data from a variety of sources.
Carnival turns it into profit
using price optimization
techniques on the integrated data.
For you to achieve such a success story,
you will need to include data
integration into your big data practice.
However, there are some unique challenges
when attempting to integrate these
diverse data sources and
scaling the solutions.
Course Two on on the specialization,
we'll teach you more about these issues.
But let's take a moment to define why
effect of data integration is useful?
Data integration means bringing
together data from diverse sources and
turning them into coherent and
more useful information.
We also call this knowledge.
The main objective here is taming or
more technically managing data and
turning it into something you can
make use of programmatically.
A data integration process
involves many parts.
It starts with discovering,
accessing, and monitoring data and
continues with modeling and transforming
data from a variety of sources.
But why do we need data
integration in the first place?
Let's start by focusing on
differences between big data sets
coming from different sources.
You might have flat file formatted data,
relational database data,
data encoded in XML or JSON,
both common for internet generated data.
These different formats and
models are useful
because they are designed to express
different data in unique ways.
In a way, different data formats and
models make big data more useful and
more challenging all at the same time.
When you integrate data in different
formats, you make the final
product richer in the number of
features you describe the data with.
For example,
by integrating environmental sensor and
camera data with geographical
information system data, such as in
my wildfire prediction application,
I can use the spacial data capabilities
with non-spacial data to more
accurately run fire simulations.
In the past, although we were able
to see the images of the fire
from mountain top cameras,
just like this image, we were still
not able to tell what the exact
location of the fire is automatically.
Now, when a fire is detected
from a mountain top camera,
viewsheds are used to estimate
the location of the fire.
This location information can
be fed into the fire simulator
as early as it's detected
to predict the size and
location of the fire in the next
hour more accurately and faster.
Similarly, I can use real time
data with eye curve data sets, and
use them all together.
Additionally, by bringing
the data together, and
providing programmable access to it, I'm
now making each data set more accessible.
Moreover, integration of
diverse datasets significantly
reduces the overall data complexity
in my data-driven product.
The data becomes more available for
use and unified as a system of its own.
One advantage of such an integration
is not often mentioned.
Such a streamlined and
integrated data system
can increase the collaboration between
different parts of your data systems.
Each part can now clearly see
how their data is integrated
into the overall system.
Including the user scenarios and the
security and privacy processes around it.
Overall by integrating diverse data
streams you add value to your big data and
improve your business even
before you start analyzing it.
Next, we will focus on the dimensions
of the scalability and
discuss how we can start tackling
some of these challenges.
What launched the big data era?
In this video, you will learn about
two new opportunities that have
contributed to the launch
of the big data era.
Opportunities are often
a signal of changing times.
In 2013, an influential report by
a company called McKinsey claimed that
the area of data science will be the
number one catalyst for economic growth.
McKinsey identified one of our new
opportunities that contributed to
the launch of the big data era.
A growing torrent of data.
This refers to the idea that data seems to
be coming continuously and at a fast rate.
Think about this,
today you can buy a hard drive to store
all the music in the world for only $600.
That's an amazing storage capability over
any previous forms of music storage.
In 2010 there were 5 billion
mobile phones in use.
You can be sure that
there are more today and
as I'm sure you will understand,
these phones and
the apps we install on them
are a big source of big data,
which all the time, every day,
contributes to our core.
And Facebook, which recently just set
a record of having one billion
people login in a single day,
has more that 30 billion pieces
of content shared every month.
Well, that number's from 2013.
So I'm sure that it's much
higher than that now.
Does it make you think how many
Facebook share's you made last month?
All this leads to projections
of serious growth.
40% in global data per year,
and 5% in global IT spending.
This much data has sure
pushed the data science field
to start remaining itself and
the business world of today.
But, there's something else contributing
to the catalyzing power of data science.
It is called cloud computing.
We call this on demand computing.
Cloud computing is one of
the ways in which computing
has now become something that
we ca do anytime, and anywhere.
You may be surprised to know
that some of your favorite
apps are from businesses
being run from coffee shops.
This new ability,
combined with our torrent of data,
gives us the opportunity to perform novel,
dynamic and scalable data analysis,
to tell us new things about our world and
ourself.
To summarize, a new torrent of big data
combined with computing capability
anytime, anywhere has been at the core
of the launch of the big data era.
Asking the Right Questions.
The first step in any process is to define
what it is you are trying to tackle.
What is the problem that
needs to be addressed, or
the opportunity that
needs to be ascertained.
Without this,
you won't have a clear goal in mind, or
know when you've solved your problem.
An example question is,
how can sales figures and
call center logs be combined
to evaluate a new product,
or in a manufacturing process,
how can data from multiple
sensors in an instrument be used
to detect instrument failure?
How can we understand our customers and
market better to achieve
effective target marketing?
Next you need to assess the situation
with respect to the problem or
the opportunity you have defined.
This is a step where you need to
exercise caution analyzing risks,
costs, benefits, contingencies,
regulations, resources and
requirements of the situation.
What are the requirements of the problem?
What are the assumptions and constraints?
What resources are available?
This is in terms of both personnel and
capital,
such as computer systems, instruments etc.
What are the main costs
associated with this project?
What are the potential benefits?
What risks are there in
pursuing the project?
What are the contingencies to
potential risks, and so on?
Answers to these questions will help you
get a better overview of the situation.
And better understanding of
what the project involves.
Then you need to define your goals and
objectives,
based on the answers to these questions.
Defining success criteria
is also very important.
What do you hope to achieve
by the end of this project?
Having clear goals and and
success criteria will help you to assess
the project throughout its life cycle.
Once you know the problem you want to
address and understand the constraints and
goals, then you can formulate
the plan to come up with the answer,
that is the solution to
your business problem.
As a summary, defining the questions
you're looking to find answers for
is a huge factor contributing to
the success of a data science project.
By following the explained set of steps,
you can formulate better questions
to solve using analytical skills and
link them to business value.
Building a Big Data Strategy.
Before we focus on big data strategy,
let's look at what strategy means.
Although it is associated
with a military term,
a dictionary search on strategy shows
the meaning as a plan of action or
policy designed to achieve a major or
overall aim.
This definition calls out the four major
parts that need to be in any strategy.
Namely, aim, policy, plan, and action.
Now, we are talking about
a big data strategy.
So what do these four terms mean for us?
When building our big data strategy,
we look at what we have,
what high level goals we want to achieve,
what we need to do to get there,
and what are the policies around
data from the beginning to the end.
A big data strategy starts
with big objectives.
Notice that I didn't say it
starts with collecting data
because in this activity we
are really trying to identify what
data is useful and
why by focusing on what data to collect.
Every organization or team is unique.
Different projects have
different objectives.
Hence, it's important to first
define what your team's goals are.
Have you ever had the scenario where you
see the temperature on the weather report
and someone else highlights
the humidity instead?
To find problems relevant to solve and
data related to it, it might be
useful to start with your objectives.
Once you define these objectives, or
more generally speaking, questions to turn
big data into advantage for your business,
you can look at what you have and
analyze the gaps and actions to get there.
It is important to focus
on both short term and
long term objectives in this activity.
These objectives should also be linked
to big data analytics with business
objectives.
To make the best use of big data,
each company needs to evaluate how
data science or big data analytics would
add value to their business objectives.
Once you have established that
analytics can help your business,
you need to create
a culture to embrace it.
The first and foremost ingredient for
a successful data science program
is organizational buy-in.
A big data strategy must
have commitment and
sponsorship from the company's leadership.
Goals for using big data analytics should
be developed with all stakeholders and
clearly communicated to
everyone in the organization.
So that its value is understood and
appreciated by all.
The next step is to build
your data science team.
A diverse team with data scientists,
information technologists,
application developers, and business
owners is necessary to be effective.
As well as the mentality that everyone
works together as partners with
common goals.
Remember, one for all.
No one is a customer or
service provider of another.
Rather, everyone works together and
delivers as a team.
Since big data is a team game,
and multi-disciplinary,
a big part of a big data
strategy is constant training
of team members on new big data tools and
analytics.
As well as business practices and
objectives.
This becomes even more critical if your
business depends on deep expertise
on one or more subject areas with subject
matter experts working on problems,
utilizing big data.
Such businesses might have subject matter
experts who can be trained to add big
data skills, and provide more value added
support than a newcomer would have.
Similarly, any project member would
be trained to understand what
the business objectives and
products are, and how he or
she can utilize big data to improve those
objectives using his or her skills.
Many organizations might benefit by having
a small data science team whose main job
is do data experiments and test new ideas
before they get deployed at full scale.
They might come up with
a new idea themselves
based on the analysis they perform.
They take more research level role.
However, their findings can drastically
shape your business strategy
almost on a daily basis.
The impact of such teams
becomes evident over time
as other parts of your organization starts
to see the results of their finding and
analysis affecting their strategies.
They become strategic partners of
all verticals in your business.
Once you see that something works,
you can start collecting more data to see
similar results at organizational scale.
Since data is key to any big
data initiative, it is essential
that data across the organization
is easily accessed and integrated.
Data silos as you know, are like
a death knell on effective analytics.
So barriers to data
access must be removed.
Opening up the silos must be encouraged
and supported from the organization's
leaders in order to promote a data
sharing mindset for the company.
Another aspect of defining
your big data strategy
is defining the policies around big data.
Although it has an amazing amount
of potential for your business,
using big data should also raise some
concerns in long term planning for data.
Although this is a very complex issue,
here are some questions you should
think of addressing around policy.
What are the privacy concerns?
Who should have access to,
or control data?
What is the lifetime of data,
which is sometimes defined as volatility,
anatomy of big data?
How does data get curated and cleaned up?
What ensures data quality
in the long term?
How do different parts of your
organization communicate or
interoperate using this data?
Are there any legal and
regulatory standards in place?
Cultivating an analytics
driven culture is crucial
to the success of a big data strategy.
The mindset that you want to
establish is that analytics
is an integral part of doing business,
not a separate afterthought.
Analytics activities must be tied
to your business objectives, and
you must be willing to use analytics
in driving business decisions.
Analytics and business together bring
about exciting opportunities and
growth to your big data strategy.
Finally, one size does not fit all.
Hence, big data technologies and
analytics is growing rapidly as your
business is an evolving entity.
You have to iterate your strategy to
take advantage of new advances and
also make your business more
dynamic in the face of change.
As a summary,
when building a big data strategy,
it is important to integrate big data
analytics with business objectives.
Communicate goals and
provide organizational buy-in for
analytics projects.
Build teams with diverse talents,
and establish a teamwork mindset.
Remove barriers to data access and
integration.
Finally, these activities need to be
iterated to respond to new business
goals and technological advances.
In this video, we'll talk about a new
that is usually not covered much.
It's called valence.
Simply put Valence
refers to Connectedness.
The more connected data is,
the higher it's valences.
The term valence comes from chemistry.
In chemistry, we talk about core electrons
and valence electrons of an atom.
Valence electrons are in the outer most
shell, have the highest energy level and
are responsible for
bonding with other atoms.
That higher valence results in greater
boding, that is greater connectedness.
This idea is carried over into our
definition of the term valence
in the context of big data.
Data items are often directly
connected to one another.
A city is connected to
the country it belongs to.
Two Facebook users are connected
because they are friends.
An employee is connected
to his work place.
Data could also be indirectly connected.
Two scientists are connected,
because they are both physicists.
For a data collection valence measures
the ratio of actually connected data items
to the possible number of connections
that could occur within the collection.
The most important aspect of valence
is that the data connectivity
increases over time.
The series of network graphs comes from
a social experiment where scientists
attending a conference were asked to meet
other scientists they did not know before.
After several rounds of meetings,
they found new connections
shown by their red edges.
Increase in valence can lead to emergent
group behavior in people networks,
like creation of new groups and coalitions
that have shared values and goals.
A high valence data set is denser.
This makes many regular,
analytic critiques very inefficient.
More complex analytical methods
must be adopted to account for
the increasing density.
More interesting challenges arise due
to the dynamic behavior of the data.
Now there is a need to model and
predict how valence of a connected data
set may change with time and volume.
The dynamic behavior also leads to
the problem of event detection,
such as bursts in the local
cohesion in parts of the data.
And emergent behavior
in the whole data set,
such as increased
polarization in a community.
Now we'll talk about a form of
scalability called variety.
In this case, scale does not
refer to the largeness of data.
It refers to increased diversity.
Here is an important mantra
you need to think about.
When we, as data scientists, think of
data variety, we think of the additional
complexity that results from more kinds
of data that we need to store, process,
and combine.
Now, many years ago when I
started studying data management,
we always thought of data as tables.
These tables could be in spreadsheets or
databases or just files, but somehow
they will be modeled and manipulated
as rows and columns of of tables.
Now, tables are still really important and
dominant, however today a much wider
variety of data are collected, stored, and
analyzed to solve real world problems.
Image data, text data, network data,
geographic maps, computer
generated simulations are only a few of
the types of data we encounter everyday.
The heterogeneity of data can be
characterized along several dimensions.
We mentioned four such axes here.
Structural variety refers
to the difference in
the representation of the data.
For example, an EKG signal is very
different from a newspaper article.
A satellite image of wildfires from
NASA is very different from tweets
sent out by people who
are seeing the fire spread.
Media variety refers to the medium
in which the data gets delivered.
The audio of a speech versus
the transcript of the speech
may represent the same information
in two different media.
Data objects like news video
may have multiple media.
An image sequence, an audio,
and closed captioned text,
all time synchronized to each other.
Semantic variety is best
described two examples.
We often use different units for
quantities we measure.
Sometimes we also use qualitative
versus quantitative measures.
For example, age can be a number or
we represent it by terms like infant,
juvenile, or adult.
Another kind of semantic
variety comes from different
assumptions of conditions on the data.
For example, if we conduct two income
surveys on two different groups of people,
we may not be able to compare or
combine them without knowing more
about the populations themselves.
The variation and
availability takes many forms.
For one, data can be available real time,
like sensor data, or it can be stored,
like patient records.
Similarly data can be
accessible continuously, for
example from a traffic cam.
Versus intermittently, for
example, only when the satellite
is over the region of interest.
This makes a difference between what
operations one can do with data,
especially if the volume
of the data is large.
We'll cover this in more
detail in course two
when we explore the different genres
of data and how we model them.
We should not think that
a single data object, or
a collection of similar data objects,
will be all uniform in themselves.
Emails, for example, is a hybrid entity.
Some of this information can be a table,
like shown here.
Now, the body of the email
usually has text in it.
However, some of the text may
have ornaments around them.
For example,
the part highlighted in yellow represents
something called a markup on text.
We'll get to markups later in the course.
Emails contain attachments.
These are files, or embedded images,
or other multimedia objects
that the mailer allows.
This screenshot from my Outlook
shows the image of a scanned image
of a handwritten note.
When you take a collection of
all emails from your mailbox, or
that from an organization,
you will see that senders and
receivers form a communication network.
In 2001, there was a famous scandal around
a company called Enron that engaged in
fraudulent financial reporting practices.
Their email network, partly shown here,
has been studied by data scientist to find
usual and unusual patterns of connections
among the people in the organization.
An email collection can also
have it's own semantics.
For example, an email cannot refer to,
that means cannot copy or
forward, a previous email.
Finally, an email server
is a real-time data source.
But an email repository is not.
Does email, and email collections,
demonstrate significant
internal variation in structure,
media, semantics, and availability?
Characteristics of Big Data- Velocity.
Velocity refers to the increasing
speed at which big data is created and
the increasing speed at which the data
needs to be stored and analyzed.
Processing of data in real-time to match
its production rate as it gets generated
is a particular goal
of big data analytics.
For example,
this type of capability allows for
personalization of advertisement
on the web pages you visit
based on your recent search,
viewing, and purchase history.
If a business cannot take advantage
of the data as it gets generated, or
at the speed analysis of it is needed,
they often miss opportunities.
In order to build a case for the
importance of this dimension of big data,
let's imagine we are taking a road trip.
You're looking for
some better information to start packing.
In this case, the newer the information,
the higher its relevance
in deciding what to pack.
Would you use last month's
weather information or
data from last year at this time?
Or, would you use the weather
information from this week, yesterday or
better, today?
It makes sense to obtain the latest
information about weather and
process it in a way that
makes your decisions easier.
If the information is old,
it doesn't matter how accurate it is.
Being able to catch up with
the velocity of big data and
analyzing it as it gets generated can
even impact the quality of human life.
Sensors and smart devices monitoring
the human body can detect abnormalities
in real time and trigger immediate action,
potentially saving lives.
This type of processing is what
we call real time processing.
Real-time processing is quite
different from its remote relative,
batch processing.
Batch processing was the norm
until a couple of years ago.
Large amounts of data would be
fed into large machines and
processed for days at a time.
While this type of processing is still
very common today, decisions based on
information that is even few days old
can be catastrophic to some businesses.
Organizations which make
decisions on latest data
are more likely to hit the target.
For this reason it's important
to match the speed of processing
with the speed of information generation,
and get real time decision making power.
In addition, today's sensor-powered
socioeconomic climate
requires faster decisions.
Hence, we can not wait for
all the data to be first produced,
then fed into a machine.
There are many applications where
new information is streaming and
needs to be integrated
with existing data to
produce decisions such as emergency
response planning in a tornado, or
deciding trading strategies in real time,
or getting estimates in advertising.
We have to digest chunks of data as they
are produced and give meaningful results.
As more data comes in,
your results will need to adapt to
reflect this change in the input.
Decisions based on processing of already
acquired data such as batch processing,
may give an incomplete picture.
And hence, the applications need real
time status of the context at hand.
That is, streaming analysis.
Fortunately, with the event
of cheap sensors technology,
mobile phones, and social media,
we can obtain the latest information
at a much rapid rate and
in real time in comparison with the past.
So how do you make sure we match
the velocity of the expectations
to gain insights from big data?
With the velocity of the big data.
Rate of generation, retrieval,
or processing of data is
application specific.
The need for real time data-driven
actions within a business case is
what in the end dictates the velocity
of analytics over big data.
Sometimes precision of a minute is needed.
Sometimes half a day.
Let's look at these four paths and
discuss when to pick the right one for
your analysis.
The dollar signs next to the numbers
in this example indicate how costly
the operation is.
The more dollars, the higher the cost.
When the timeliness of processed
information plays no role in decision
making, the speed at which data
is generated becomes irrelevant.
In other words, you can wait for
as long as it takes to process data.
Days, months, weeks.
And once processing is over,
you will look at the results and
probably share them with someone.
When timeliness is not an issue,
you can choose any of the four paths.
You will likely pick the cheapest one.
When timeliness of end result is an issue
deciding which of the four paths
to choose is not so simple.
You will have to make a decision
based on cost of hardware,
time sensitivity of information,
future scenarios.
In other words,
this becomes a business driven question.
For example, if speed is really important
at all costs, you will pick path four.
As a summary, we need to pay attention
to the velocity of big data.
Streaming data gives information
on what's going on right now.
Streaming data has velocity, meaning
it gets generated at various rates.
And analysis of such data in
real time gives agility and
adaptability to maximize
benefits you want to extract.
Characteristics of Big Data, Veracity.
Veracity of Big Data refers
to the quality of the data.
It sometimes gets referred
to as validity or
volatility referring to
the lifetime of the data.
Veracity is very important for
making big data operational.
Because big data can be noisy and
uncertain.
It can be full of biases,
abnormalities and it can be imprecise.
Data is of no value if it's not accurate,
the results of big data analysis are only
as good as the data being analyzed.
This is often described in analytics
as junk in equals junk out.
So we can say although big data
provides many opportunities to make
data enabled decisions,
the evidence provided by data
is only valuable if the data
is of a satisfactory quality.
There are many different
ways to define data quality.
In the context of big data,
quality can be defined as a function
of a couple of different variables.
Accuracy of the data, the trustworthiness
or reliability of the data source.
And how the data was generated
are all important factors
that affect the quality of data.
Additionally how meaningful the data
is with respect to the program that
analyzes it, is an important factor, and
makes context a part of the quality.
In this chart from 2015,
we see the volumes of data increasing,
starting with small amounts
of enterprise data to larger,
people generated voice over IP and
social media data and
even larger machine generated sensor data.
We also see that the uncertainty of
the data increases as we go from
enterprise data to sensor data.
This is as we would expect it to be.
Traditional enterprise
data in warehouses have
standardized quality solutions
like master processes for extract,
transform and load of the data which
we referred to as before as ETL.
As enterprises started incorporating less
structured and unstructured people and
machine data into their
big data solutions,
the data become messier and
more uncertain.
There are many reasons for this.
First, unstructured data on the internet
is imprecise and uncertain.
In addition, high velocity big data
leaves very little or no time for
ETL, and in turn hindering the quality
assurance processes of the data.
Let's look at these product reviews for
a banana slicer on amazon.com.
One of the five star reviews say that
it saved her marriage and compared it
to the greatest inventions in history.
Another five star reviewer said
that his parole officer recommended
the slicer as he is not
allowed to be around knives.
These are obviously fake reviewers.
Now think of an automated product
assessment going through such
splendid reviews and estimating lots
of sales for the banana slicer and
in turn suggesting stocking more
of the slicer in the inventory.
Amazon will have problems.
For a more serious case let's look at
the Google flu trends case from 2013.
For January 2013,
the Google Friends actually
estimated almost twice as many
flu cases as was reported by CDC,
the Centers for
Disease Control and Prevention.
The primary reason behind this was that
Google Flu Trends used a big data on
the internet and did not account properly
for uncertainties about the data.
Maybe the news and social media
attention paid to the particularly
serious level of flu that
year effected the estimate.
And resulted in what we
call an over estimation.
This is a perfect example for
how inaccurate the results can be if
only big data is used in the analysis.
Imagine the economical impact of
making health care preparations for
twice the amount of flu cases.
That would be huge.
The Google flu trends example
also brings up the need for
being able to identify where exactly
the big data they used comes from.
What transformation did
big data go through up
until the moment it was used for
a estimate?
This is what we refer
to as data providence.
Just like we refer to
an artifacts provenance.
As a summary, the growing
torrents of big data pushes for
fast solutions to utilize
it in analytical solutions.
This creates challenges on
keeping track of data quality.
What has been collected,
where it came from, and
how it was analyzed prior to its use.
This is akin to an art artifact
having providence of everything
it has gone through.
But even more complicated to achieve
with large volumes of data coming
in varieties and velocities.
Characteristics of Big Data- Volume.
Volume is the big data dimension that
relates to the sheer size of big data.
This volume can come from
large datasets being shared or
many small data pieces and
events being collected over time.
Every minute 204 million emails are sent,
200,000 photos are uploaded, and 1.8
million likes are generated on Facebook.
On YouTube, 1.3 million videos are viewed
and 72 hours of video are uploaded.
But how much data are we talking about?
The size and the scale of storage for
big data can be massive.
You heard me say words that
start with peta, exa and
yotta, to define size, but
what does all that really mean?
For comparison, 100 megabytes will
hold a couple of encyclopedias.
A DVD is around 5 GBs, and
1 TB would hold around 300
hours of good quality video.
A data-oriented business currently
collects data in the order of terabytes,
but petabytes are becoming more
common to our daily lives.
CERN's large hadron collider
generates 15 petabytes a year.
According to predictions by an IDC report
sponsored by a big data company called
EMC, digital data, will grow by
a factor of 44 until the year 2020.
This is a growth from 0.8 zetabytes,
In 2009 to 35.2 zettabytes in 2020.
A zettabyte is 1 trillion gigabytes,
that's 10 to the power of 21.
The effects of it will be huge!
Think of all the time, cost,
energy that will be used to store and
make sense of such an amount of data.
The next era will be yottabytes.
Ten to the power of 24 and
brontobytes, ten to the power of 27.
Which is really hard to imagine for
most of us at this time.
This is also what we call data
at an astronomical scale.
The choice of putting the Milky Way Galaxy
in the middle of the circle
is not just for aesthetics.
This is what we would see if
we were to scale up 10 to
the 21 times into the universe.
Cool, isn't it?
Please refer to the reading
in this module called,
what does astronomical scale mean,
for a nice video on the powers of ten.
All of these point to an exponential
growth in data volume and storage.
What is the relevance of
this much data in our world?
Remember the planes collecting big data?
Our hope, as passengers,
is data means better flight safety.
The idea is to understand that businesses
and organizations are collecting and
leveraging large volumes of data
to improve their end products,
whether it is safety, reliability,
healthcare, or governance.
In general, in business the goal
is to turn this much data into
some form of business advantage.
The question is how do we
utilize larger volumes of data
to improve our end product's quality?
Despite a number of
challenges related to it.
There are a number of challenges related
to the massive volumes of big data.
The most obvious one is of course storage.
As the size of the data increases so
does the amount of storage space
required to store that data efficiently.
However, we also need to be able
to retrieve that large amount of
data fast enough, and
move it to processing units in a timely
fashion to get results when we need them.
This brings additional challenges
such as networking, bandwidth,
cost of storing data.
In-house versus cloud storage and
things like that.
Additional challenges arise during
processing of such large data.
Most existing analytical methods
won't scale to such sums of
data in terms of memory,
processing, or IO needs.
This means their performance will drop.
You might be able to get good performance
for data from hundreds of customers.
But how about scaling your solution
to 1,000 or 10,000 customers?
As the volume increases performance and
cost start becoming a challenge.
Businesses need a holistic
strategy to handle processing of
large scale data to their benefit
in the most cost effective manner.
Evaluating the options across
the dimensions mentioned here,
is the first step when it comes to
continuously increasing data size.
We will revisit this topic
later on in this course.
As a summary volume is the dimension
of big data related to its size and
its exponential growth.
The challenges with working with volumes
of big data include cost, scalability,
and performance related to their storage,
access, and processing.
Data Science.
Getting value out of big data.
We have all heard data science turned
data into insights or even actions.
But what does that really mean?
Data science can be
thought of as a basis for
empirical research where data is used
to induce information for observations.
These observations are mainly data,
in our case,
big data, related to a business or
scientific case.
Insight is a term
we use to refer to the data
products of data science.
It is extracted from a diverse amount
of data through a combination of
exploratory data analysis and modeling.
The questions are sometimes more specific,
and sometimes it requires
looking at the data and patterns in it
to come up with the specific question.
Another important point to recognize
is that data science is not static.
It is not one time analysis.
It involves a process where models
generated to lead to insights
are constantly improved through further
empirical evidence, or simply, data.
For example, a book retailer like
Amazon.com can constantly improve
the model of a customer's book preferences
using the customer demographic,
his or her previous purchases and
the book reviews of the customer.
The book retailer can also
uses information to predict
which customers are likely
to like any book,
and take action to market
the book to those customers.
This is where we see insights
being turned into action.
As we have seen in the book marketing
example, using data science and analysis
of the past and current information,
data science generates actions.
This is not just an analysis of the past,
but
rather generation of actionable
information for the future.
This is what we can call a prediction,
like the weather forecast.
When you decide what to wear for
the day based on the forecast of the day,
you are taking action based
on insight delivered to you.
Just like this, business leaders and
decision makers
take action based on the evidence
provided by their data science teams.
We set data science teams.
This comes from the breadth of information
and skill that it takes to make it happen.
You have probably seen diagrams like
this one that describe data science.
Data science happens at
the intersection of computer science,
mathematics and business expertise.
If we zoom deeper into this diagram and
open the sets of expertise we will
see a variation of this figure.
Even at this level, all of these circles
require deeper knowledge and skills
in areas like domain expertise, data
engineering, statistics and computing.
An even deeper analysis of these
skills will lead you to skills like
machine learning, statistical modeling,
relational algebra,
business passion, problem solving and
data visualization.
That's a lot of skills to have for
a single person.
These wide range of skills and
definitions of data scientists having them
all led to discussions like
are data scientists unicorns?
Meaning they don't exist.
There are data science experts who have
expertise in more than one of these
skills, for sure.
But they're relatively rare, and
still would probably need help from
an expert on some of these areas.
So, in reality, data scientists
are teams of people who act like one.
They are passionate about the story and
the meaning behind data.
They understand they problem
they are trying to solve, and
aim to find the right analytical
methods to solve this problem.
And they all have an interest in
engineering solutions to solve problems.
They also have curiosity about each
others work, and have communication
skills to interact with the team and
present their ideas and results to others.
As a summary, a data science team often
comes together to analyze situations,
business or scientific cases, which none
of the individuals can solve on their own.
There are lots of moving
parts to the solution.
But in the end, all these parts
should come together to provide
actionable insight based on big data.
Being able to use evidence-based
insight in business decisions is more
important now than ever.
Data scientists have a combination
of technical, business and
soft skills to make this happen.
Getting started,
characteristics of big data.
By now you have seen that big data is a
blanket term that is used to refer to any
collection of data so large and
complex that it exceeds the processing
capability of conventional data
management systems and techniques.
The applications of big data are endless.
Every part of business and society
are changing in front our eyes due to that
fact that we now have so much more
data and the ability for analyzing.
But how can we characterize big data?
You can say, I know it when i see it.
But there are easier ways to do it.
Big data is commonly characterized
using a number of V's.
The first three are volume,
velocity, and variety.
Volume refers to the vast amounts of
data that is generated every second,
mInutes, hour, and
day in our digitized world.
Variety refers to the ever increasing
different forms that data can come in
such as text, images,
voice, and geospatial data.
Velocity refers to the speed at
which data is being generated and
the pace at which data moves
from one point to the next.
Volume, variety, and
velocity are the three main dimensions
that characterize big data.
And describe its challenges.
We have huge amounts of data
in different formats, and
varying quality which must
be processed quickly.
More Vs have been introduced
to the big data community
as we discover new challenges and
ways to define big data.
Veracity and
valence are two of these additional V's we
will pay special attention to as
a part of this specialization.
Veracity refers to the biases,
noise, and abnormality in data.
Or, better yet, It refers to the often
unmeasurable uncertainties and
truthfulness and trustworthiness of data.
Valence refers to the connectedness
of big data in the form of graphs,
just like atoms.
Moreover, we must be sure to
never forget our sixth V, value.
How do big data benefit you and
your organization?
Without a clear strategy and
an objective with the value
they are getting from big data.
It is easy to imagine that organizations
will be sidetracked by all these
challenges of big data, and not be
able to turn them into opportunities.
Now let's start looking into the first
five of these V's in detail.
How does data science happen?
Five P's of data science.
Now that we identified what data science
is and how companies can strategize around
big data to start building a purpose,
let's come back to using data science
to get value out of big data around
the purpose or questions they defined.
Our experience with building and
observing successful data science projects
led to a method around the craft with
five distinct components that can be
defined as components of data science.
Here we define data science
as a multi-disciplinary
craft that combines
people teaming up around
application-specific purpose that
can be achieved through a process,
big data computing platforms,
and programmability.
All of these should lead to
products where the focus really
is on the questions or purpose that are
defined by your big data strategy ideas.
There are many technology,
data and analytical research, and
development related activities
around the questions.
But in the end, everything we do
in this phase is to reach to that
final product based on our purposes.
So, it makes sense to start with it and
build a process around how
we make this product happen.
Remember the wild fire
prediction project I described?
One of the products we described
there was the rate of spread and
direction of an ongoing fire.
We have identified questions and
the process that led us to
the product in the end to solve it.
We brought together experts around
the table for fire modeling,
data management, time series analysis,
scalable computing,
Geographical Information Systems,
and emergency response.
I asked them,
let's not dive into the techniques yet.
What is the problem at large?
How do we see ourselves solving it?
A typical conversation around
the process starts with this question.
Then from then on,
drilling down to many areas of expertise,
often we blur lines between the steps.
My wildfire team would start listing
things like, we don't have an integrated
system or we don't have real-time
access to data programmatically,
so we can't analyze fires on the fly.
Or they can say, I can't integrate
sensor data with satellite data.
All of this leads me to challenges
I can then use to define problems.
There are many dimensions of data science
to think about within this discussion.
Let's start with the obvious ones,
people and purpose.
People refers to a data science team or
the projects stakeholders.
As you know by now,
they're expert in data and
analytics, business, computing,
science, or big data management,
like all the set of experts I
listed in my wildfire scenario.
The purpose refers to the challenge or
set of challenges defined by your
big data strategy, like solving the
question related to the rate of spread and
direction of the fire perimeter
in the wildfire case.
Since there's a predefined team
with a purpose, a great place for
this team to start with is
a process they could iterate on.
We can simply say, people with purpose
will define a process to collaborate and
communicate around.
The process is conceptual
in the beginning and
defines the set of steps an how
everyone can contribute to it.
There are many ways to
look at the process.
One way of looking at it is
as two distinct activities,
mainly big data engineering and
big data analytics, or
computational big data science,
as I like to call it, as more than simple
analytics is being performed here.
A more detailed way of looking at
the process reveals five distinct steps or
activities of this data science process,
namely acquire, prepare,
analyze, report, and act.
We can simply say that
data science happens
at the boundary of all these steps.
Ideally, this process should
support experimental work and
dynamic scalability on the big data and
computing platforms.
This five step process can be used in
alternative ways in real life big data
applications, if we add the dependencies
of different tools to each other.
The influence of big data pushes for
alternative scalability approaches
at each step of the process.
Just like you would scale
each step on its own,
you can scale the whole
process as a whole in the end.
One can simply say, all of these steps
have reporting needs in different forms.
Or there is a need to draw all these
activities as an iterating process,
including build, explore, and
scale for big data as steps.
Big data analysis needs alternative
data management techniques and
systems, as well as analytical tools and
methods.
Multiple modes of scalability is needed
based on dynamic data and computing loads.
In addition,
change in physical infrastructure,
streaming data specific urgencies
arising from special events
can also require multiple
modes of scalability.
In this intro course, for simplicity,
we will refer to the process as a set of
five sequential activities that iterate.
However, we'll touch on scalability as
needed in our example applications.
As a part of building
your big data process,
it's important to simply
mention two other P's.
The first one is big data platforms,
like the ones in the Hadoop framework,
or other computing platforms
to scale different steps.
The scalability should be in
the mind of all team members and
get communicated as an expectation.
In addition, the scalable process
should be programmable through
utilization of reusable and
reproducible programming interfaces
to libraries, like systems middleware,
analytical tools,
visualization environments, and
end user reporting environments.
Thinking of big data
applications as a process,
including a set of activities that
the team members can collaborate over,
also helps to build metrics for
accountability to be built into it.
This way, expectations on cost, time,
optimization of deliverables,
and time lines can be discussed
between the the members starting with
the beginning of the data science process.
Sometimes we may not be able
to do this in one step.
And joint explorations like statistical
evaluations of intermediate results or
accuracy of sample data
sets become important.
As a summary, data science can be
defined as a craft of using the five P's
identified in this lecture,
leading to a sixth P, the data product.
Having a process within the more
business-driven Ps, like people and
purpose, and the more technically
driven P's, like platforms and
programmability, leads to
a streamlined approach that starts and
ends with the product, team
accountability, and collaboration in mind.
Data science process
provides guidelines for
implementing big data solution,
as it helps to organize efforts and
ensures all critical steps taken conforms
to pre-define and agreed upon metrics.
Step one, acquiring data.
The first step in the data science
process is to acquire the data.
You need to obtain the source material
before analyzing or acting on it.
The first step in acquiring data is
to determine what data is available.
Leave no stone unturned when it comes
to finding the right data sources.
You want to identify suitable
data related to your problem and
make use of all data that is relevant
to your problem for analysis.
Leaving out even a small
amount of important data
can lead to incorrect conclusions.
Data, comes from, many places, local and
remote, in many varieties,
structured and un-structured.
And, with different velocities.
There are many techniques and technologies
to access these different types of data.
Let's discuss a few examples.
A lot of data exists in
conventional relational databases,
like structure big data
from organizations.
The tool of choice to access data from
databases is structured query language or
SQL, which is supported by all
relational databases management systems.
Additionally, most data base systems
come with a graphical application
environment that allows you to query and
explore the data sets in the database.
Data can also exist in files such as
text files and Excel spreadsheets.
Scripting languages are generally
used to get data from files.
A scripting language is a high
level programming language
that can be either general purpose or
specialized for specific functions.
Common scripting languages with support
for processing files are Java Script,
Python, PHP, Perl, R, and
MATLAB, and are many others.
An increasingly popular way
to get data is from websites.
Web pages are written using
a set of standards approved by
a world wide web consortium or
shortly, W3C.
This includes a variety of formats and
services.
One common format is
the Extensible Markup Language, or XML,
which uses markup symbols or tabs to
describe the contents on a webpage.
Many websites also host web services which
produce program access to their data.
There are several types of web services.
The most popular is REST because it's so
easy to use.
REST stand for
Representational State Transfer.
And it is an approach to implementing
web services with performance,
scalability and maintainability in mind.
Web socket services are also
becoming more popular
since they allow real time
modifications from web sites.
NoSQL storage systems are increasingly
used to manage a variety of data
types in big data.
These data stores are databases
that do not represent data
in a table format with columns and rows as
with conventional relational databases.
Examples of these data stores include
Cassandra, MongoDB and HBASE.
NoSQL data stores provide APIs
to allow users to access data.
These APIs can be used directly or in an
application that needs to access the data.
Additionally, most NoSQL
systems provide data access
via a web service interface, such a REST.
Now, let's discuss our wildfire case study
as a real project that acquires data
using several different mechanisms.
The WIFIRE project stores sensor data from
weather stations in a relational database.
We use SQL to retrieve this data
from the database to create
models to identify weather patterns
associated with Santa Anna conditions.
To determine whether a particular weather
station is currently experiencing
Santa Anna conditions, we access real
time data using a web socket service.
Once we start listening to this service,
we receive weather station
measurements as they occur.
This data is then processed and
compared to patterns found by our models
to determine if a weather station is
experiencing Santa Ana conditions.
At the same time Tweets are retrieved
using hashtags related to any fire
that is occurring in the region.
The Tweet messages are retrieves
using the Twitter REST service.
The idea is to determine the sentiment
of these tweets to see if people
are expressing fear, anger or are simply
nonchalant about the nearby fire.
The combination of sensor data and
tweet sentiments helps
to give us a sense of the urgency
of the fire situation.
As a summary,
big data comes from many places.
Finding and evaluating data
useful to your big data analytics is
important before you start acquiring data.
Depending on the source and
structure of data,
there are alternative ways to access it.
Step 2-A: Exploring Data
After you've put together the data
that you need for your application,
you might be tempted to immediately
build models to analyze the data.
Resist this temptation.
The first step after getting
your data is to explore it.
Exploring data is a part of
the two-step data preparation process.
You want to do some
preliminary investigation
in order to gain a better understanding of
the specific characteristics of your data.
In this step, you'll be looking for
things like correlations,
general trends, and outliers.
Without this step, you will not be
able to use the data effectively.
Correlation graphs can be used
to explore the dependencies
between different variables in the data.
Graphing the general trends of
variables will show you if there is
a consistent direction in which the values
of these variables are moving towards,
like sales prices going up or down.
In statistics, an outlier is a data point
that's distant from other data points.
Plotting outliers will
help you double check for
errors in the data due to measurements.
In some cases, outliers that are not
errors might make you find a rare event.
Additionally, summary statistics provide
numerical values to describe your data.
Summary statistics are quantities
that capture various characteristics
of a set of values with a single number or
a small set of numbers.
Some basic summary statistics
that you should compute for
your data set are mean, median,
range, and standard deviation.
Mean and median are measures of
the location of a set of values.
Mode is the value that occurs
most frequently in your data set.
And range and standard deviation
are measures of spread in your data.
Looking at these measures will give you
an idea of the nature of your data.
They can tell you if there's
something wrong with your data.
For example, if the range of the values
for age in your data includes
negative numbers, or
a number much greater than 100,
there's something suspicious in
the data that needs to be examined.
Visualization techniques also
provide a quick and effective, and
overall a very useful way to look at
data in this preliminary analysis step.
A heat map, such as the one shown here,
can quickly give you the idea
of where the hotspots are.
Many other different types
of graphs can be used.
Histograms show that
the distribution of the data and
can show skewness or unusual dispersion.
Boxplots are another type of plot for
showing data distribution.
Line graphs are useful for seeing how
values in your data change over time.
Spikes in the data are also easy to spot.
Scatter plots can show you
correlation between two variables.
Overall, there are many types
of graph to visualize data.
They are very useful in helping
you understand the data you have.
In summary, what you get by
exploring your data is a better
understanding of the complexity of
the data you have to work with.
This, in turn,
will guide the rest of your process.
Step 2-B: Pre-processing Data
The raw data that you get directly from
your sources are never in the format that
you need to perform analysis on.
There are two main goals in
the data pre-processing step.
The first is to clean the data to
address data quality issues, and
the second is to transform the raw
data to make it suitable for analysis.
A very important part of data preparation
is to address quality
of issues in your data.
Real-world data is messy.
There are many examples of quality issues
with data from real applications including
inconsistent data like a customer with two
different addresses, duplicate customer
records, for example, customers address
recorded at two different sales locations.
And the two recordings don't agree.
Missing customer agent demographics or
studies.
Missing values like missing a customer
age in the demographic studies.
invalid data like an invalid zip code for
example, a six digit code.
And outliers like a sense of failure
causing values to be much higher or
lower than expected for a period of time.
Since we get the data downstream
we usually have little control
over how the data is collected.
Preventing data quality problems as
the data is being collected is not
often an option.
So we have the data that we get and
we have to address quality issues
by detecting and correcting them.
Here are some approaches we can take
to address this quality issues.
We can remove data records
with missing values.
We can merge duplicate records.
This will require a way to determine
how to resolve conflicting values.
Perhaps it makes sense to retain the newer
value whenever there's a conflict.
For invalid values, the best estimate for
a reasonable value can be
used as a replacement.
For example, for
a missing age value for an employee,
a reasonable value can be estimated based
on the employee's length of employment.
Outliers can also be removed if
they are not important to the task.
In order to address data
quality issues effectively,
knowledge about the application,
such as how the data was collected,
the user population, and the intended
uses of the application is important.
This domain knowledge is
essential to making informed
decisions on how to handle incomplete or
incorrect data.
The second part of preparing data
is to manipulate the clean data into
the format needed for analysis.
The step is known by many names.
Data manipulation,
data preprocessing, data wrangling,
and even data munging, some operations for
this type of operation I mean data
munging, wrangling, preprocessing,
include, scaling, transformation,
feature selection,
dimensionality reduction,
and data manipulation.
Scaling involves changing the range of
values to be between a specified range.
Such as from zero to one.
This is done to avoid having certain
features that large values from
dominating the results.
For example,
in analyzing data with height and weight.
To magnitude of weight values is much
greater than of the height values.
So scaling all values
to be between zero and
one will equalize contributions from
both height and weight features.
Various transformations can be performed
on the data to reduce noise and
variability.
One such transformation is aggregation.
Aggregate data generally results
in data with less variability,
which may help with your analysis.
For example, daily sales figures
may have many serious changes.
Aggregating values to weekly or monthly
sales figures will result in similar data.
Other filtering techniques can also be
used to remove variability in the data.
Of course, this comes at
the cost of less detailed data.
So these factors must be weighed for
the specific application.
Future selection can involve removing
redundant or irrelevant features,
combining features, and
creating new features.
During the exploring data step,
you might have discovered that
two features are correlated.
In that case one of these
features can be removed
without negatively affecting
the analysis results.
For example,
the purchase price of a product and
the amount of sales tax paid,
are likely to be correlated.
Eliminating the sales tax amount,
then will be beneficial.
Removing redundant or
irrelevant features will make
the subsequent analysis much simpler.
In other cases, you may want to combine
features or create new ones.
For example,
adding the applicant's education level
as a feature to a loan approval
application would make sense.
There are also algorithms to automatically
determine the most relevant features,
based on various mathematical properties.
Dimensionality reduction is useful when
the data set has a large number of
dimensions.
It involves finding a smaller
subset of dimensions that
captures most of
the variation in the data.
This reduces the dimensions of the data
while eliminating irrelevant features and
makes analysis simpler.
A technique commonly used for
dimensional reduction is called
principle component analysis or PCA.
Raw data often has to be manipulated to
be in the correct format for analysis.
For example, from samples recording
daily changes in stock prices,
we may want the capture price changes for
a particular market segments
like real estate or health care.
This would require determining which
stocks belong to which market segment.
Grouping them together, and
perhaps computing the mean, range,
standard deviation for each group.
In summary,
data preparation is a very important
part of the data science process.
In fact, this is where you will spend most
of your time on any data science effort.
It can be a tedious process,
but it is a crucial step.
Always remember, garbage in, garbage out.
If you don't spend the time and
effort to create good data for the
analysis, you will not get good results
no matter how sophisticated
the analysis technique you're using is.
Step 3: Analyzing Data.
Now that you have your
data nicely prepared,
the next step is to analyze the data.
Data analysis involves building
a model from your data,
which is called input data.
The input data is used by the analysis
technique to build a model.
What your model generates
is the output data.
There are different types of problems, and
so there are different types
of analysis techniques.
The main categories of analysis techniques
are classification, regression,
clustering, association analysis,
and graph analysis.
We will describe each one.
In classification, the goal is to
predict the category of the input data.
An example of this is predicting
the weather as being sunny,
rainy, windy, or cloudy in this case.
Another example is to classify
a tumor as either benign or malignant.
In this case, the classification is
referred to as binary classification,
since there are only two categories.
But you can have many categories as well,
as the weather prediction problem
shown here having four categories.
Another example is to identify
handwritten digits as
being in one of the ten
categories from zero to nine.
When your model has to predict
a numeric value instead of a category,
then the task becomes
a regression problem.
An example of regression is to
predict the price of a stock.
The stock price is a numeric value,
not a category.
So this is a regression task
instead of a classification task.
Other examples of regression
are estimating the weekly sales of a new
product and
predicting the score on a test.
In clustering, the goal is to
organize similar items into groups.
An example is grouping a company's
customer base into distinct segments for
more effective targeted marketing
like seniors, adults and
teenagers, as we see here.
Another such example is identifying
areas of similar topography,
like mountains, deserts,
plains for land use application.
Yet another example is determining
different groups of weather patterns,
like rainy, cold or snowy.
The goal in association analysis
is to come up with a set
of rules to capture associations
within items or events.
The rules are used to determine when
items or events occur together.
A common application of association
analysis is known as market
basket analysis, which is used to
understand customer purchasing behavior.
For example, association analysis
can reveal that banking customers
who have certificate of deposit accounts,
surety CDs, also
tend to be interested in other investment
vehicles, such as money market accounts.
This information can be used for
cross-selling.
If you advertise money market
accounts to your customers with CDs,
they're likely to open such an account.
According to data mining folklore,
a supermarket chain used association
analysis to discover a connection between
two seemingly unrelated products.
They discovered that many customers who go
to the supermarket late on Sunday night
to buy diapers also tend to buy beer,
who are likely to be fathers.
This information was then
used to place beer and
diapers close together and
they saw a jump in sales of both items.
This is the famous diaper beer connection.
When your data can be transformed into
a graph representation with nodes and
links, then you want to use graph
analytics to analyze your data.
This kind of data comes about when
you have a lot of entities and
connections between those entities,
like social networks.
Some examples where graph analytics can
be useful are exploring the spread of
a disease or epidemic by analyzing
hospitals' and doctors' records.
Identification of security threats
by monitoring social media,
email and text data.
And optimization of mobile
communications network traffic.
telecommunications network traffic,
to ensure call quality and
reduce dropped calls.
Modeling starts with selecting,
one of the techniques we listed
as the appropriate analysis technique,
depending on the type of problem you have.
Then you construct the model
using the data you've prepared.
To validate the model,
you apply it to new data samples.
This is to evaluate how well the model
does on data that was
used to construct it.
The common practice is to divide
the prepared data into a set of data for
constructing the model and
reserving some of the data for
evaluating the model after
it has been constructed.
You can also use new data prepared the
same way as with the data that was used to
construct model.
Evaluating the model depends on the type
of analysis techniques you used.
Let's briefly look at how
to evaluate each technique.
For classification and regression,
you will have the correct output for
each sample in your input data.
Comparing the correct output and
the output predicted by the model,
provides a way to evaluate the model.
For clustering,
the groups resulting from clustering
should be examined to see if they
make sense for your application.
For example, do the customer
segments reflect your customer base?
Are they helpful for
use in your targeted marketing campaigns?
For association analysis and
graph analysis, some investigation will be
needed to see if the results are correct.
For example, network traffic delays
need to be investigated to see what your
model predicts is actually happening.
And whether the sources of the delays
are where they are predicted
to be in the real system.
After you have evaluated your model to get
a sense of its performance on your data,
you will be able to
determine the next steps.
Some questions to consider are,
should the analysis be
performed with more data in order
to get a better model performance?
Would using different data types help?
For example, in your clustering results,
is it difficult to distinguish
customers from distinct regions?
Would adding zip code
to your input data help
to generate finer grained
customer segments?
Do the analysis results suggest
a more detailed look at
some aspect of the problem?
For example, predicting sunny
weather gives very good results,
but rainy weather
predictions are just so-so.
This means that you should take a closer
look at your examples for rainy weather.
Perhaps you just need more
samples of rainy weather, or
perhaps there are some
anomalies in those samples.
Or maybe there are some missing data
that needs to be included in order
to completely capture rainy weather.
The ideal situation would be that your
model platforms very well with respect to
the success criteria that were determined
when you defined the problem at
the beginning of the project.
In that case, you're ready to
move on to communicating and
acting on the results that you
obtained from your analysis.
As a summary, data analysis involves
selecting the appropriate technique for
your problem, building the model,
then evaluating the results.
As there are different types of problems,
there are also different
types of analysis techniques.
Step four, reporting insights.
The fourth step in our data science
process is reporting the insights gained
from our analysis.
This is a very important step
to communicate your insights and
make a case for
what actions should follow.
It can change shape based on your
audience and should not be taken lightly.
So how do you get started?
The first thing to do is to look
at your analysis results and
decide what to present or report as the
biggest value or biggest set of values.
In deciding what to present you
should ask yourself these questions.
What is the punchline?
In other words, what are the main results?
What added value do
these results provide or
how can the model add to the application?
How do the results compare to
the success criteria determined at
the beginning of the project?
Answers to these questions are the items
you need to include in your report or
presentation.
So make them the main topics and
gather facts to back them up.
Keep in mind that not all of
your results may be rosy.
Your analysis may show results that are
counter to what you were hoping to find,
or results that are inconclusive or
puzzling.
You need to show these results as well.
Domain experts may find some of
these results to be puzzling, and
inconclusive findings may
lead to additional analysis.
Remember the point of
reporting your findings
is to determine what
the next step should be.
All findings must be presented so
that informed decisions can be made.
Visualization is an important
tool in presenting your results.
The techniques that we discuss and
explore in data can be used here as well.
What were they?
Scatter plots, line graphs,
heat maps, and other types of graphs
are effective ways to present
your results visually.
This time you're not
plotting the input data, but
you're plotting the output
data with similar tools.
You should also have tables with
details from your analysis as backups,
if someone wants to take
a deeper dive into the results.
There are many visualization
tools that are available.
Some of the most popular open
source ones are listed here.
R is a software package for
general data analysis.
It has powerful visualization
capabilities as well.
Python is a general purpose
programming language
that also has a number of packages to
support data analysis and graphics.
D3 is a JavaScript library for
producing interactive web based
visualizations and data driven documents.
Leaflet is a lightweight mobile
friendly JavaScript library
to create interactive maps.
Tableau Public Allows you
to create visualizations,
in your public profile, and share them,
or put them, on a site, or blog.
Google Charts provides
cross-browser compatibility,
and closed platform portability
to iPhones and Android.
Timeline is a JavaScript library
that allows you to create timelines.
In summary, you want to report your
findings by presenting your results and
value add with graphs
using visualization tools.
Step 5, Act, turning insights into action.
Now that you have evaluated
the results from your analysis and
generated reports on the potential value
of the results, the next step is to
determine what action or actions should
be taken, based on the insights gained?
Remember why we started
bringing together the data and
analyzing it in the first place?
To find actionable insights
within all these data sets,
to answer questions, or for
improving business processes.
For example,
is there something in your process that
should change to remove bottle necks?
Is there data that should be added to your
application to make it more accurate?
Should you segment your population
into more well defined groups for
more effective targeted marketing?
This is the first step in
turning insights into action.
Now that you've determined
what action to take,
the next step is figuring out
how to implement the action.
What is necessary to add this action
into your process or application?
How should it be automated?
The stakeholders need to be identified and
become involved in this change.
Just as with any process improvement
changes, we need to monitor and
measure the impact of the action
on the process or application.
Assessing the impact
leads to an evaluation.
Evaluating results from the implemented
action will determine your next steps.
Is there additional analysis that need
to be performed in order to yield
even better results?
What data should be revisited?
Are there additional opportunities
that should be explored?
For example, let's not forget
what big data enables us to do.
Real-time actions based on high
velocity streaming information.
We need to define what part of our
business needs real-time action to be
able to influence the operations or
the interaction with the customer.
Once we define these real time actions,
we need to make sure that
there are automated systems, or
processes to perform such actions, and
provide failure recovery
in case of problems.
As a summary, big data and
data science are only useful if
the insights can be turned into action,
and if the actions are carefully
defined and evaluated.
Steps in the Data Science Process.
We have already seen a simple linear
form of data science process,
including five distinct activities
that depend on each other.
Let's summarize each activity further
before we go into the details of each.
Acquire includes anything that makes
us retrieve data including; finding,
accessing, acquiring, and moving data.
It includes identification of and
authenticated access to all related data.
And transportation of data from
sources to distributed files systems.
It includes way to subset and match
the data to regions or times of interest.
As we sometimes refer to
it as geo-spacial query.
The next activity is prepare data,
we divide the pre-data activity.
Into two steps based on
the nature of the activity.
Namely, explore data and pre-process data.
The first step in data preparation
involves literally looking
at the data to understand its nature,
what it means, its quality and format.
It often takes a preliminary
analysis of data, or
samples of data, to understand it.
This is why this step is called explore.
Once we know more about the data
through exploratory analysis,
the next step is pre-processing
of data for analysis.
Pre-processing includes cleaning data,
sub-setting or
filtering data, creating data,
which programs can read and
understand, such as modeling raw
data into a more defined data model,
or packaging it using
a specific data format.
If there are multiple data sets involved,
this step also includes integration
of multiple data sources, or streams.
The prepared data then would be
passed onto the analysis step,
which involves selection of
analytical techniques to use,
building a model of the data,
and analyzing results.
This step can take a couple
of iterations on its own or
might require data scientists
to go back to steps one and
two to get more data or
package data in a different way.
Step four for communicating results
includes evaluation of analytical results.
Presenting them in a visual way,
creating reports that include
an assessment of results with
respect to success criteria.
Activities in this step can often be
referred to with terms like interpret,
summarize, visualize, or post process.
The last step brings us back to the very
first reason we do data science,
the purpose.
Reporting insights from analysis and
determining actions from insights based
on the purpose you initially defined
is what we refer to as the act step.
We have now seen all the steps in
a typical data science process.
Please note that this is an iterative
process and findings from one step
may require the previous step to
be repeated with new information.
The Sixth V, Value.
In this module,
we described the five ways which are
considered to be dimensions of big data.
Each way presented a challenging
dimension of big data namely,
size, complexity, speed,
quality, and connectedness.
Although we can list some other rays base
on the context, we prefer to list these
five s fundamental dimensions that this
big data specialization helps you work on.
However, at the heart of
the big data challenge
is turning all of the other dimensions
into truly useful business value.
The idea behind processing all
this big data in the first place
is to bring value to the problem at hand.
In week two we will explore how
to take the first steps into
starting to generate
value out of big data.
Now that we saw all the ways, let's focus
on an example of a big data challenge.
Let's imagine now that you're part
of a company called Eglence Inc.
One of the products of Eglence Inc
is a highly popular mobile game
called Catch the Pink Flamingo.
It's a multi-user game where
the users have to catch special types
of pink flamingos that randomly
pop up on the world map on their
screens based on the mission
that gets updated randomly.
The game is played by millions of
people online throughout the world.
One of the goals of the game is to form
a network of players to collectively
cover the world map with pink flamingo
sightings and compete other groups.
Users can pick their groups
based on player stats.
The game's website sends free
cool stuff to registered users.
Registration requires users to enter
demographic information such gender,
year of birth, city, highest education,
and things like that.
However, most of the users enter
inaccurate information about themselves,
just like most of us do.
To help improve the game,
the game collects realtime usage activity
data from each player and
feeds them to it's data servers.
The players of this game are
enthusiastically active on social media,
and have strong
associations with the game.
A popular Twitter hashtag for
this game is, CatchThePinkFlamingo,
which gets more than 200,000
mentions worldwide per day.
There are strong communities of
users who meet via social media and
get together to play the game.
Now, imagine yourself as the big data
solutions architect for Fun Games Inc.
There are definitely examples of all three
types of data sources in this example.
The mobile app generates data for
the analysis of user activity.
Twitter conversations of players form
a rich source of unstructured data from
people.
And the customer and
game records are examples of data
that this organization collects.
This is a challenging big data example
where all characteristics of
big data are represented.
There are high volumes of player, game and
Twitter data,
which also speaks to the variety of data.
The data streams from the mobile app,
website, and
social media in real-time, which can
be defined as high velocity data.
The quality of demographic data
users enter is not clear, and
there are networks of players which
are related to the balance of big data.
Cloud Computing: An Important
Big Data Enabler.
In our first lecture in this course,
we mentioned the cloud as one of
the two influences of
the launch of the big data era.
We called it on-demand computing, and
we said that it enables us to
compute any time any anywhere.
Simply, whenever we demand it.
In this video,
we will see how we deploy the cloud to
our benefit in our big data applications.
The main idea behind cloud computing
is to transform computing
infrastructure into a commodity.
So application developers can focus on
solving application-specific challenges
instead of trying to build
infrastructure to run on.
So how does this happen?
We can simply define
a cloud computing service,
as a rental service for computing.
You rent what you want,
and return upon usage.
Think about this, you wouldn't buy, or
even build, a truck every time you
have to move a piece of furniture.
You would simply rent.
Why build a computing
cluster when you can rent?
Especially if you are not
using it all the time.
Similarly, you can rent a car or
a bike when you are on vacation.
So you can bike anytime, anywhere.
Let's dig into this question.
What factors do you consider when you're
developing a solution for your yourself or
your client?
Should you build a hardware and
software resources yourself?
Or should you rent these
resources from the cloud?
Let's look at in-house hardware and
software resource building first.
If you choose to develop in-house
capabilities, you have to hire people and
buy hardware that suits your requirements.
These includes, but not limited to,
buying networking hardware,
storage disks, upgrading hardware
when it becomes obsolete, and so on.
Not to forget, the real estate
cost of keeping the hardware.
How do you estimate the size
of your hardware needs?
Do you make a five year estimate,
or ten year?
In today's fast changing world,
it is becoming harder to
estimate future demands.
Getting the software that fits
your needs is equally challenging.
Most software installations
require a lot of tweaking and
manual intervention that
require a lot of skills.
You will need your engineers to do this.
Compatibility issues bring
problems that are hard to foresee.
Most software is updated on a daily basis.
You must ensure you're updated.
This insures you avoid security risks and
get the best.
Over all, building your own data center or
computing power house can be expensive.
And it can be time consuming,
maintaining it is a task by itself.
This requires high initial
capital investments and
efficient operation of several
departments in your business,
which you might not have if
you are a startup company.
Most people forget to include
the cost of disposing old hardware.
Now lets see what the cloud can do for us.
Cloud's benefits are similar to what you
would get from a rental car company.
You pay for what you use,
which means a low capital investment.
You don't need to go to the dealership,
do a negotiation, get a bank loan,
get insurance.
That means quick implementation
of your projects.
Just like you don't need to buy
a car if you only need a car for
a limited use, deploying your application
on a server that is geographically
closer to your client can give you
fast service and happy customers.
For startup and small business,
it can be challenging to do so.
Cloud lets you do this with a click.
You can be sitting at a coffeeshop or your
home and starting your Internet business,
without a huge capital investment,
thanks to the cloud.
And you don't need to have a five or
ten year resource estimation plan.
Adapt to your requirements faster if
your business is growing faster than you
thought.
Cloud lets you forget about
the resource management problems and
lets you focus on your business's products
or domain expertise with minimal cost.
Just as you can rent a truck or
a convertible at a rental car company,
you can build your own
custom machine on cloud.
With a custom machine,
we mean a commodity cluster
made out of the right type of
computing nodes for your application.
You pick not only a CPU or a GPU, but
pick from a whole menu of compute,
memory and storage choices.
It's a buffet on the cloud.
Design machines to suit your application
requirements, data size and analytics.
Get what you want, and
pay for what you use.
Compare this with buying and
maintaining all combinations of
hardware that you possibly would use.
That is so costly and
not possible at all times.
Thanks to all these advantages, there
are many cloud server providers today.
And the numbers are growing.
Here we list some of the players
in the cloud computing market.
Take a moment to look at them.
You will probably recognize
some big names and
some others you have not
even heard of before.
As a summary, cloud does the heavy
lifting, so your team can extract
value from data with getting bogged
down in the infrastructure details.
Cloud provides convenient and
viable solutions for scaling your
prototype to a full fledged application.
You can leverage the experts
to handle security,
robustness, and
let them handle the technical issues.
Your team can work on
utilizing your strengths
to solve your domain specific problem.
Cloud Service Models: Exploration
of Choices.
There are many levels of services that
you can get from cloud providers.
Any cloud computing discussion will
involve terms like application
as a service, platform as a service,
and infrastructure as a service.
All of these refer to business
models around using the cloud
with different levels of engagement and
servicing similar to rental agreements.
IaaS, infrastructure as a service, can be
defined as a bare minimum rental service.
This is like renting a truck from
a company that you can assume has hardware
and you do the packing of your furniture,
and drive to your new house.
You as the user of the service install and
maintain an operating system,
and other applications in
the infrastructure as a service model.
The Amazon EC2 cloud is a good example for
this model.
PaaS, platform as a service,
is the model where a user is provided
with an entire computing platform.
This could include the operating system
and programming languages that you need.
It could extend to include the database
of your choice, or even a web server.
You can develop, and
run your own application software,
on top of these layers.
The Google App engine and Microsoft Azure
are two examples of this model.
SaaS, the software as a service model,
is the model
in which the cloud service provider takes
the responsibilities for the hardware and
software environment such as the operating
system and the application software.
This means you can work on using
the application to solve your problem.
Dropbox is a very popular
software as a service platform.
Ultimately, the decision of which service
you want to explore is a function of
several variables.
It depends on the skill level of your
team to handle computing environment,
development and maintenance.
It also depends on how you
might need to use the service.
You need to pick the right
service model that
best fits you in terms of long term goals.
Finally, when you're deploying a cloud
service you also have to understand
all the security risks, since your
data resides on third party service.
Security is a very important
aspect in today's world of growing
digitization of information.
You must make your client's
data safety a top priority,
and hence this should be an important
criteria in your decision.
All the security risks
must be understood and
evaluated as your data resides
on third party servers.
We are seeing other forms
of services being added
to the family of cloud services.
The logic of infrastructure, platform, and
Software as a Service is
getting extended further.
XaaS is an umbrella term that signifies
even finer-grain control over computing
resources that you want to rent.
For example, storage as a service,
communication as a service,
marketing as a service, and so on.
As a summary, infrastructure as a service,
platform as a service, and application
as a service are three main class service
models that are being used with success.
Picking one will depend on the number
of variables which are company's goals.
These three models have
inspired many similar models
to emerge around cloud computing.
In this lecture we'll be learning about
the basic file manipulation commands for
the Hadoop File System or HDFS.
We'll first start by downloading
a text file of words.
We'll use this text file to copy to and
from the local file system in HDFS and
later on we'll use it
to run word count on.
After we download the text file,
we'll open a terminal shell and
copy the text file from
the local file system to HDFS.
Next, we'll copy the file within HDFS and
also see how to copy file from
HDFS to the local file system.
Finally, we'll see how to
delete a file in HDFS.
Let's start.
We're going to download text
file to copy into HDFS.
It doesn't matter what the contents of
the text file is, so we'll download
the complete works of Shakespeare
since it contains interesting text.
First, click on the icon here
to launch a web browser.
Now we'll search Google for
the complete works of Shakespeare.
I'm going to be using
this first link here.
And we'll provide this link
in the reading section.
So this is the complete
works of Shakespeare and
we'll save it to a text file in the local
file system by clicking on the icon here,
the Open Menu and selecting save page.
So we'll call it words.txt.
And the Save in folder, it's going to
save it into the Downloads directory.
Once that completes, we'll open a terminal
window by clicking on the icon here.
So if we go into the downloads
Ddrectory by typing a cd Downloads and
running ls, we can see that words.txt
was successfully downloaded.
Moving on, let's copy words.txt from the
local file system to the HDFS file system.
The command to do this is hadoop
fs- copyFromLocal words.txt.
When I run this,
it'll copy it from the local directory and
local file system to HDFS.
We can see that the file was
copied by running hadoop fs -ls.
You can see that the file
was successfully copied.
Next, we can copy this file
to another file within HDFS.
We can do this by running hadoop
fs -cp words.txt words2.txt.
The first words.txt is the file
that already exists in HDFS.
The second words 2.txt
is the new file that we're going to
create when we run this command.
Let's run it, and again we're can run
hadoopfs-ls to see the files in HDFS.
We can see the original file words.txt,
and the copy that was made, words2.txt.
Let's copy words2.txt from
HDFS to the local filesystem.
We can do this by running hadoop
fs -copyToLocal words2.txt.
After I run this command, I can call ls to
see the contents of the local file system.
So now we have the new file words2.txt
which we've just copied from HDFS.
The last step in this lecture
is to delete a file in HDFS.
We can delete words2.txt
by running hadoop fs,
but is rn words2.txt.
As you can see,
it printed that it deleted the file.
We can also run hadoop fs- ls,
to verify that the file is deleted.
You can see that there's only the original
words.txt, and words2.txt was deleted.
Getting started.
Why do we worry about foundations?
Starting next week you'll start
diving into the details of the Hadoop
framework for big data.
Before you start, taking a little
bit of time to understand some core
concepts will help you to digest the
information on Hadoop better and faster.
Imagine yourself attending
a chemistry lab.
Before you start hearing about
the tubes and mixtures, you really need
to understand the chemistry or theory
of the practical concepts in the lab.
Similarly, learning these
concepts now will help
you with your understanding of the
practical concepts in the Hadoop lectures.
In addition, we want to prepare you to
understand the tools beyond Hadoop.
Any big data system that you find
will be built on these core concepts.
So these foundations will
help you beyond this course.
Now, let's get started.
Getting started.
Why Hadoop?
We have all heard that Hadoop and
related projects in this
ecosystem are great for big data.
This module will answer the four Ws and
an H about why this statement is true.
Before we dive further into
the details of Hadoop,
let's take a moment to analyze the
characteristics of the Hadoop ecosystem.
What's in the ecosystem?
Why is it beneficial?
Where is it used?
Who uses it?
And how do these tools work?
The Hadoop ecosystem frameworks and
applications that we will describe in this
module have several overarching themes and
goals.
First, they provide scalability
to store large volumes of data
on commodity hardware.
As the number of systems increases,
so does the chance for crashes and
hardware failures.
A second goal, supported by most
frameworks in the Hadoop ecosystem,
is the ability to gracefully
recover from these problems.
In addition, as we have mentioned before,
big data comes in
a variety of flavors, such as text files,
graph of social networks,
streaming sensor data and raster images.
A third goal for
the Hadoop ecosystem then,
is the ability to handle these different
data types for any given type of data.
You can find several projects in
the ecosystem that support it.
A fourth goal of the Hadoop ecosystem
is the ability to facilitate
a shared environment.
Since even modest-sized
clusters can have many cores,
it is important to allow multiple
jobs to execute simultaneously.
Why buy servers only to let them sit idle?
Another goal of the Hadoop ecosystem
is providing value for your enterprise.
The ecosystem includes a wide
range of open source projects
backed by a large active community.
These projects are free to use and
easy to find support for.
In the following lectures in this module,
we will take a more detailed
look at the Hadoop ecosystem.
First, we will explore the kinds
of projects available and
the types of capabilities they provide.
Next we will take a deeper look at
the three main parts of Hadoop.
The Hadoop distributed file system,
or HDFS.
YARN, the scheduler and resource manager.
And MapReduce, a programming model for
processing big data.
We will then discuss cloud computing, and
the types of service models it provides.
We will also describe situations in
which Hadoop is not the best solution.
This module then concludes with
two readings involving hands-on
experience with HDFS and MapReduce.
So let's get started.
MapReduce, Simple Programming for
Big Results.
MapReduce is a programming model for
the Hadoop ecosystem.
It relies on YARN to schedule and
execute parallel processing over
the distributed file blocks in HDFS.
There are several tools that use the
MapReduce model to provide a higher level
interface to other programming models.
Hive has a SQL-like interface that
adds capabilities that help with
relational data modeling.
And Pig is a high level data flow language
that adds capabilities that
help with process map modeling.
Traditional parallel programming requires
expertise on a number of computing and
systems concepts.
For example, synchronization
mechanisms like locks, semaphores,
and monitors are essential.
And incorrectly using them can
either crash your program, or
severely impact performance.
This high learning curve
makes it difficult.
It is also error prone,
since your code can run on hundreds, or
thousands of nodes,
each having many cores.
And any problem related to
these parallel processes,
needs to be handled by
your parallel program.
The MapReduce programming model greatly
simplifies running code in parallel
since you don't have to deal
with any of these issues.
Instead, you only need to create and
map and reduce tasks, and you don't
have to worry about multiple threads,
synchronization, or concurrency issues.
So, what is a map and reduce?
Map and reduce are two concepts
based on functional programming
where the output the function
is based solely on the input.
Just like in a mathematical function,
f (x) = y, y depends on x.
You provide a function, or
operation for a map, and reduce.
And the runtime executes it over the data.
For map, the operation is
applied on each data element.
And in reduce, the operation
summarizes elements in some manner.
An example, using map and
reduce will make this concepts more clear.
Hello word is a traditional
first program you code
when you start to learning
programming languages.
The first program to learn, or hello
word of map reduce, is often WordCount.
WordCount reads one or
more text files, and
counts the number of occurrences
of each word in these files.
The output will be a text
file with a list of words and
their occurrence frequencies
in the input data.
Let's examine each step of WordCount.
For simplification we are assuming
we have one big file as an input.
Before WordCount runs,
the input file is stored in HDFS.
As you know now,
HDFS partitions the blocks across
multiple nodes in the cluster.
In this case, four partitions labeled,
A, B, C, and D.
The first step in MapReduce is to
run a map operation on each node.
As the input partitions are read
from HTFS, map is called for
each line in the input.
Let's look at the first lines
of the input partitions, A and
B, and start counting the words.
The first line,
in the partition on node A,
says, My apple is red and my rose is blue.
Similarly, the first line, on partition B,
says, You are the apple of my eye.
Let's now see what happens in
the first map node for partition A.
Map creates a key value for
each word on the line containing
the word as the key, and 1 as the value.
In this example, the word apple is
read from the line in partition A.
Map produces a key value of (apple, 1).
Similarly, the word my is seen
on the first line of A twice.
So, the key values of (my,
1), are created.
Note that map goes to each node
containing a data block for
the file,
instead of the data moving to map.
This is moving computation to data.
Let's now see what the same map
operation generates for partition B.
Since each word only
happens to occur once,
a list of all the words with one
key-value pairing each gets generated.
Please take a moment to
observe the outputs of map and
each key-value pair associated to a word.
Next, all the key-values that were output
from map are sorted based on their key.
And the key values, with the same word,
are moved, or shuffled, to the same node.
To simplify this figure, each node only
has a single word, in orange boxes.
But in general,
a node will have many different words.
Just like our example from the two
lines in A and B partitions.
Here we see that, you and apple,
are assigned to the first node.
The word is, to the second node.
And the words, rose and red, to the third.
Although, for simplicity, we drew four
map nodes and three shuffle nodes.
The number of nodes can be extended
as much as the application demands.
Next, the reduce operation
executes on these nodes to
add values for
key-value pairs with the same keys.
For example, (apple, 1), and
another (apple, 1), becomes (apple, 2).
The result of reduce is
a single key pair for
each word that was read in the input file.
The key is the word, and
the value is the number of occurrences.
If we look back at our WordCount example,
we see that there were
three distinct steps.
Namely, the map step, the shuffle and
sort step, and the reduce step.
Although, the WordCount
example is pretty simple,
it represents a large number of
applications to which these three steps
can be applied in order to achieve
data parallel scalability.
For example, now that you have
seen the WordCount application,
consider changing the WordCount
algorithm to index all
the URLs by words after a web crawl.
This means, instead of pointing to
a number, the keys would refer to URLs.
After the map, with this new function,
which by the way is called a user
defined function, the output of
shuffle and sort would look like this.
Now, when we reduce the URLs, all the URLs
that mention Apple would look like this.
This is, in fact, one of the ways
a search engine like Google works.
So now, if somebody came to the interface
built for this application,
to search for the word apple,
and entered apple,
it would be easy to get all
the URLs as the word itself.
No wonder the first MapReduce
paper was produced by Google.
We will give you a link to the original
Google paper on MapReduce from
2004 at the end of this lecture.
It is pretty technical, but
it gives you a simple overview without
the current system implementations.
We just saw how MapReduce can
be used in search engines
in addition to counting the words and
documents.
Although it's possible to add many
more applications, let's stop here for
a general discussion on how the points of
data parallelism can be used in
search in this three step pattern.
There is definitely parallelization
during the map step.
This parallelization is over the input,
as each partition gets
processed one line at a time.
To achieve this type of data
parallelism we must decide on
the data granularity of
each parallel competition.
In this case, it will be a line.
We also see parallel grouping of
data in the shuffle and sort phase.
This time, the parallelization is
over the intermediate products.
That is, the individual key-value pairs.
And after the grouping of
the intermediate products,
the reduce step gets parallelized
to construct one output file.
You have probably noticed
that the data gets reduced
to a smaller set at each step.
This overview gave us an idea of what
kinds of tasks that MapReduce is good for.
While MapReduce excels at independent
batch tasks similar to our applications,
there are certain kinds of tasks that
you would not want to use MapReduce for.
For example,
if your data is frequently changing,
MapReduce is slow since it reads
the entire input data set each time.
The MapReduce model requires that maps and
reduces execute
independently of each other.
This greatly simplifies
your job as a designer,
since you do not have to deal
with synchronization issues.
However, it means that computations
that do have dependencies,
cannot be expressed with MapReduce.
Finally, MapReduce does
not return any results
until the entire process is finished.
It must read the entire input data set.
This makes it unsuitable for interactive
applications where the results must be
presented to the user very quickly,
expecting a return from the user.
As a summary, MapReduce hides
complexities of parallel programming and
greatly simplifies building
parallel applications.
Many types of tasks suitable for
MapReduce include search engine
page ranking and topic mapping.
Please see the reading after
this lecture on making Pasta Sauce
with MapReduce for another fun application
using the MapReduce programming model.
Programming Models for Big Data.
We have seen that scalable computing
over the internet to achieve
data-parallel scalability for big data
applications is now a possibility.
Thanks to commodity clusters.
Cost-effective commodity clusters
together with advances in distributed
file systems to move computation to data,
provide a potential to conduct
scalable big data analytics.
The next thing we will
talk about is how to take
advantage of these
infrastructure advances.
What are the right programming models?
A programming model is an abstraction or
existing machinery or infrastructure.
It is a set of abstract
runtime libraries and
programming languages that
form a model of computation.
This abstraction level can be low-level
as in machine language in computers.
Or very high as in high-level programming
languages, for example, Java.
So we can say,
if the enabling infrastructure for
big data analysis is distributed
file systems as we mentioned,
then the programming model for
big data should enable the programmability
of the operations within
distributed file systems.
What we mean by this being able to
write computer programs that work
efficiently on top of distributed
file systems using big data and
making it easy to cope with
all the potential issues.
Based on everything we discussed so
far, let's describe the requirements for
big data programming models.
First of all, such a programming model for
big data should support
common big data operations like
splitting large volumes of data.
This means for partitioning and
placement of data in and
out of computer memory along with a model
to synchronize the datasets later on.
The access to data should
be achieved in a fast way.
It should allow fast distribution to nodes
within a rack and these are potentially,
the data nodes we moved
the computation to.
This means scheduling of
many parallel tasks at once.
It should also enable
reliability of the computing and
full tolerance from failures.
This means it should enable
programmable replications and
recovery of files when needed.
It should be easily scalable to
the distributed notes where the data gets
produced.
It should also enable adding new resources
to take advantage of distributive
computers and scale to more or
faster data without losing performance.
This is called scaling out if needed.
Since there are a variety
of different types of data,
such as documents, graphs,
tables, key values, etc.
A programming model should enable
operations over a particular set
of these types.
Not every type of data may be
supported by a particular model, but
the models should be optimized for
at least one type.
Is it getting a little complicated?
It doesn't have to have to be.
In fact, we apply similar models in
our daily lives for everyday tasks.
Let's look at the scenario where you
might unknowingly apply this model.
Imagine a peaceful Saturday afternoon.
You receive a phone call from a friend and
she says,
she they will be at your
house in an hour for dinner.
It seems like you completely forgot that
you had invited your friends for dinner.
So you say, you are looking forward
to it and head to the kitchen.
As a quick solution, you decide to
cook pasta with some tomato sauce.
You need to take advantage
of parallelization, so
that the dinner is ready by the time your
guest arrive, that's within an hour.
You call your spouse and your teenage
kids to action in the kitchen.
Now, you need to give them directions to
start dicing the ingredients for you.
But in the heat of the moment, you end up
mixing the onions, tomatoes and peppers.
Instead of sorting them first,
you give everyone a randomly mixed
batch of different types of vegetables.
They are required to use their computer
powers to chop the vegetables.
They need to ensure not mix
different types of veggies.
When everyone is done chopping, you want
to group the veggies by their types.
You ask each helper to collect items
of the same type, put them in a large
bowl and label this large bowl with
the sum of individual bowl weights
like tomatoes in one bowl, peppers in
another and the onions in the third bowl.
In the end,
you have nice large bowls with the total
weight of each vegetable labeled on it.
Your helpers are soon done with their work
while you're focused on coordinating their
actions and other dinner tasks in the
kitchen, you can start cooking your pasta.
What you have just seen is an excellent
example of big data modeling in action.
Only it is really the data
processed by human processors.
This scenario can be modeled by a common
programming model for big data.
Namely MapReduce.
MapReduce is a big data programming
model that supports all
the requirements of big
data modeling we mentioned.
It can model processing large data,
split complications into
different parallel tasks and
make efficient use of large commodity
clusters and distributed file systems.
In addition, it abstracts out
the details of parallelzation,
full tolerance, data distribution,
monitoring and load balancing.
As a programming model,
it has been implemented in a few
different big data frameworks.
Next week,
we will see more details on MapReduce and
how its Hadoop implementation works.
To summarize, programming models for
big data are abstractions over
distributed file systems.
The desired programming models for
big data should handle large volumes and
varieties of data.
Support full tolerance and
provide scale out functionality.
MapReduce is one of these models,
implemented in a variety of
frameworks including Hadoop.
We will summarize the inner workings
of the Hadoop implementation next week.
In this lecture we will use
Hadoop to run WordCount.
First we will open a terminal shell and
explore the Hadoop-provided MapReduce
programs.
Next we will verify the input
file exists in HDFS.
We will then run WordCount and
explore the WordCount output directory.
After that we will copy
the WordCount results
from HDFS to the local file system and
view them.
Let's begin.
First we'll open a terminal shell by
clicking on the icon at
top of the window here.
Next, we'll look at the map produced
programs that come with Hadoop.
We can do this by running Hadoop,
jars user jars, Hadoop examples .jar.
This command says we're going to use
the jar command to run a program
in Hadoop from a jar file.
And the jar file that we're running from
is in /usr/jars/hadoop-examples.jar.
Many programs written in Java
are distributed via jar files.
If we run this command We'll see a list of
different programs that come with Hadoop.
So for example, wordcount.
Count the words in a text file.
Wordmean, count the average
length of words.
And other programs, such as sorting and
calculating the length of pi.
In the previous lecture we downloaded
the Works of Shakespeare and
saved it into HDFS.
Let's make sure that file is still
there by running hadoop fs -ls.
We can see that the file is still there,
and it's called words.txt.
We can run wordcount by running hadoop jar
/usr/jars/hadoop-examples.jar wordcount.
This command says that
we're going to run a jar,
and this is the name of the jar
containing the program.
And the program we're
going to run is wordcount.
When we run it, we see that it
prints the command line usage for
how to run wordcount.
This says that wordcount takes one or
more input files and an output name.
Now, both the input and
the output are located in HDFS.
So we have the input file that we
just listed, words.txt, in HDFS.
We can run wordcount.
So we'll run hadoop
jar/usr/jars/hadoop-examples.jar
wordcount words.txt out.
This is saying we're going to run
the WordCount program using words.txt
as the input and
put the output in a directory called out.
So we'll run it.
As wordcount is running,
your prints progress to the screen.
It'll print the percentage of map and
reduce completed.
And when both of these reach 100%,
then the job is done.
Now that the job is complete,
let's look at the results.
We can run Hadoop fs
-ls to see the output.
This shows that out was created and
this is where our results are stored.
Notice that it's
a directory with a d here.
So hadoop word count created
the directory to contain the output.
Let's look inside that directory
by running Hadoop fs- ls out.
[BLANK AUDIO] We can see that there
are two files in this directory.
The first is _SUCCESS, this means that
the WordCount job completed successfully.
The other file part-r-00000 is a text file
containing the output from
the WordCount command
Now let's copy this text file to the local
file system from HDFS and then view it.
We could copy it by running
hadoop fs -copytolocal
out/part-r-00000 local.
And we'll say local.txt is the name.
You can view the results of this.
We're running more local.txt.
This will view the contents of the file.
We can hit spacebar to scroll down.
We see the results of
WordCount in this file.
Each line is a particular word and
the second column is the count
of how many words of this particular
word was found in the input file.
You can hit q to quit
Scalable computing over the internet.
Most computing is done on
a single compute node.
If the computation needs more than
a node or parallel processing,
like many scientific computing problems,
we use parallel computers.
Simply put, a parallel computer
is a very large number of
single computing nodes with specialized
capabilities connected to other network.
For example, the Gordon Supercomputer here
at The San Diego Supercomputer Center,
has 1,024 compute nodes with 16 cores each
equalling 16,384 compute cores in total.
This type of specialized
computer is pretty costly
compared to its most recent cousin,
the commodity cluster.
The term, commodity cluster,
is often heard in big data conversations.
Have you ever wondered
what it exactly means?
Commodity clusters are affordable
parallel computers
with an average number of computing nodes.
They are not as powerful as
traditional parallel computers and
are often built out of
less specialized nodes.
In fact,
the nodes in the commodity cluster
are more generic in their
computing capabilities.
The service-oriented computing community
over the internet have pushed for
computing to be done on commodity
clusters as distributed computations.
And in turn, reducing the cost
of computing over the Internet.
In commodity clusters,
the computing nodes are clustered in racks
connected to each other
via a fast network.
There might be many of such
racks in extensible amounts.
Computing in one or
more of these clusters across
a local area network or the internet
is called distributed computing.
Such architectures enable what
we call data-parallelism.
In data-parallelism many jobs
that share nothing can work on
different data sets or
parts of a data set.
This type of parallelism sometimes
gets called as job level parallelism.
But in this specialization,
we will refer to it as data-parallelism
in the context of Big-data computing.
Large volumes and varieties of big
data can be analyzed using this mode
of parallelism, achieving scalability,
performance and cost reduction.
As you can imagine, there are many
points of failure inside systems.
A node, or
an entire rack can fail at any given time.
The connectivity of a rack
to the network can stop or
the connections between
individual nodes can break.
It is not practical to restart everything
every time, if failure happens.
The ability to recover from such
failures is called Fault-tolerance.
For Fault-tolerance of such systems,
two neat solutions emerged.
Namely, Redundant data storage and
restart of failed
individual parallel jobs.
We will explain these two solutions next.
As a summary the commodity
clusters are a cost effective way
of achieving data parallel scalability for
big data applications.
These type of systems have a higher
potential for partial failures.
It is this type of distributed
computing that pushed for
a change towards cost
effective reliable and
Fault-tolerant systems for
management and analysis of big data.
The Hadoop Distributed File System,
a storage system for big data.
As a storage layer, the Hadoop distributed
file system, or the way we call it HDFS.
Serves as the foundation for
most tools in the Hadoop ecosystem.
It provides two capabilities that
are essential for managing big data.
Scalability to large data sets.
And reliability to cope
with hardware failures.
HDFS allows you to store and
access large datasets.
According to Hortonworks,
a leading vendor of Hadoop services,
HDFS has shown production
scalability up to 200 petabytes and
a single cluster of 4,500 servers.
With close to a billion files and blocks.
If you run out of space, you can simply
add more nodes to increase the space.
HDFS achieves scalability
by partitioning or
splitting large files
across multiple computers.
This allows parallel access to very large
files since the computations run in
parallel on each node
where the data is stored.
Typical file size is
gigabytes to terabytes.
The default chunk size, the size of
each piece of a file is 64 megabytes.
But you can configure this to any size.
By spreading the file across many nodes,
the chances are increased that a node
storing one of the blocks will fail.
What happens next?
Do we lose the information
stored in block C?
HDFS is designed for
full tolerance in such case.
HDFS replicates, or
makes a copy of, file blocks on
different nodes to prevent data loss.
In this example,
the node that crashed stored block C.
But block C was replicated on
two other nodes in the cluster.
By default, HDFS maintains
three copies of every block.
This is the default replication factor.
But you can change it globally for
every file, or
on a per file basis.
HDFS is also designed to handle
a variety of data types aligned with
big data variety.
To read a file in HDFS you must
specify the input file format.
Similarly to write the file you must
provide the output file format.
HDFS provides a set of formats for
common data types.
But this is extensible and you can provide
custom formats for your data types.
For example text files can be read.
Line by line or a word at a time.
Geospatial data can be read as vectors or
rasters.
Data formats specific to geospatial data,
or
other domain specific data formats.
Like FASTA, or FASTQ formats for
sequence data genomics.
HDFS is comprised of two components.
NameNode, and DataNode.
These operate using a master
slave relationship.
Where the NameNode issues comments
to DataNodes across the cluster.
The NameNode is responsible for metadata.
And DataNodes provide block storage.
There is usually one NameNode per cluster,
a DataNode however,
runs on each node in the cluster.
In some sense the NameNode
is the administrator or
the coordinator of the HDFS cluster.
When the file is created,
the NameNode records the name,
location in the directory hierarchy and
other metadata.
The NameNode also decides which data nodes
to store the contents of the file and
remembers this mapping.
The DataNode runs on
each node in the cluster.
And is responsible for
storing the file blocks.
The data node listens to commands from
the name node for block creation,
deletion, and replication.
Replication provides two key capabilities.
Fault tolerance and data locality.
As discussed earlier, when a machine in
the cluster has a hardware failure there
are two other copies of each block
that are stored on that node.
So no data is lost.
Replication also means that the same block
will be stored on different nodes on
the system which are in different
geographical locations.
A location may mean a specific rack or
a data center in a different town.
The location is important since we
want to move computation to data and
not the other way around.
We'll talk about what moving computation
to data means later in this module.
As I mentioned earlier, the default
replication factor is three, but
you can change this.
A high replication factor means more
protection against hardware failures,
and better chances for data locality.
But it also means increased
storage space is used.
As a summary HDFS provides
scalable big data storage by
partitioning files over multiple nodes.
This helps to scale big data
analytics to large data volumes.
The application protects
against hardware failures and
provides data locality when we move
analytical complications to data.
The Hadoop Ecosystem: So Much free Stuff!
How did the big data
open-source movement begin?
In 2004 Google published
a paper about their
in-house processing framework
they called MapReduce.
The next year,
Yahoo released an open-source
implementation based on this
framework called Hadoop.
In the following years,
other frameworks and
tools were released to the community
as open-source projects.
These frameworks provided new
capabilities missing in Hadoop,
such as SQL like querying or
high level scripting.
Today, there are over 100
open-source projects for
big data and
this number continues to grow.
Many rely on Hadoop, but
some are independent.
With so many frameworks and tools
available, how do we learn what they do?
We can organize them with a layer diagram
to understand their capabilities.
Sometimes we also used the term
stack instead of a layer diagram.
In a layer diagram,
a component uses the functionality or
capabilities of the components
in the layer below it.
Usually components at the same
layer do not communicate.
And a component never assumes a specific
tool or component is above it.
In this example,
component A is in the bottom layer,
which components B and C use.
Component D uses B, but not C.
And D does not directly use A.
Let's look at one set of tools in
the Hadoop ecosystem as a layer diagram.
This layer diagram is organized
vertically based on the interface.
Low level interfaces, so storage and
scheduling, on the bottom.
And high level languages and
interactivity at the top.
The Hadoop distributed file system,
or HDFS, is the foundation for
many big data frameworks, since it
provides scaleable and reliable storage.
As the size of your data increases,
you can add commodity hardware
to HDFS to increase storage capacity so
it enables scaling out of your resources.
Hadoop YARN provides
flexible scheduling and
resource management over the HDFS storage.
YARN is used at Yahoo to schedule
jobs across 40,000 servers.
MapReduce is a programming model
that simplifies parallel computing.
Instead of dealing with the complexities
of synchronization and scheduling, you
only need to give MapReduce two functions,
map and reduce, as you heard before.
This programming model is so
powerful that Google previously
used it for indexing websites.
MapReduce only assume a limited
model to express data.
Hive and Pig are two additional
programming models on
top of MapReduce to augment
data modeling of MapReduce
with relational algebra and
data flow modeling respectively.
Hive was created at
Facebook to issue SQL-like
queries using MapReduce
on their data in HDFS.
Pig was created at Yahoo to model data
flow based programs using MapReduce.
Thanks to YARN stability
to manage resources,
not just for MapReduce but
other programming models as well.
Giraph was built for
processing large-scale graphs efficiently.
For example, Facebook uses Giraph to
analyze the social graphs of its users.
Similarly, Storm, Spark,
and Flink were built for
real time and
in memory processing of big data on
top of the YARN resource scheduler and
HDFS.
In-memory processing is a powerful way of
running big data applications even faster,
achieving 100x's better performance for
some tasks.
Sometimes, your data or
processing tasks are not easily or
efficiently represented using the file and
directory model of storage.
Examples of this include collections
of key-values or large sparse tables.
NoSQL projects such as Cassandra,
MongoDB, and HBase handle these cases.
Cassandra was created at Facebook,
but Facebook also used HBase for
its messaging platform.
Finally, running all of these tools
requires a centralized management system
for synchronization, configuration and
to ensure high availability.
Zookeeper performs these duties.
It was created by Yahoo to wrangle
services named after animals.
A major benefit of the Hadoop ecosystem
is that all these tools
are open-source projects.
You can download and use them for free.
Each project has a community of users and
developers that
answer questions, fix bugs and
implement new features.
You can mix and match to get only
the tools you need to achieve your goals.
Alternatively, there are several
pre-built stacks of these tools
offered by companies such as Cloudera,
MAPR and Hortonworks.
These companies provide the core
software stacks for free and
offer commercial support for
production environments.
As a summary, the Hadoop ecosystem
consists of a growing number
of open-source tools.
Providing opportunities to
pick the right tool for
the right tasks for
better performance and lower costs.
We will reveal some of these
tools in further detail and
provide an analysis of when to use
which in the next set of lectures.
Generating value from Hadoop and
Pre-Built Hadoop Images that
come as off the shelf products.
Assembling your own software stack
from scratch can be messy and
a lot of work for beginners.
The task of setting up the whole stack
could consume a lot of project time and
man power, reducing time to deployment.
Getting pre-built images is similar
to buying pre-assembled furniture.
You can obtain a ready to go software
stack which contains a pre-installed
operating system, required libraries and
application software.
It saves you from the trouble
of putting the different
parts together in the right orientation.
You can start using
the furniture right away.
Packaging of these pre-built
software images is enabled
by virtual machines using
virtualization software.
Without going into too much detail,
one of the benefits of virtualization
software is that it lets you run a ready
made software stack within minutes.
Your software stack comes as a large file.
Virtualization software provides
a platform where your stack can run.
Many companies provide images for
their version of the Hadoop platform,
including a number of
tools of their choice.
Hortonworks is one of the companies that
provides a pre-built software stack for
both Mac and Windows platforms.
Cloudera is another company
that provides pre-installed and
assembled software stack images.
Cloudera image is what we will
be working with in this course.
Many other companies
provide similar images.
Additionally, lots of online tutorials for
beginners are on vendors websites for
self-training of users
working with these images and
the open source tools they include.
Once you choose the vendor,
you can check out their website for
tutorials on how to get started quickly.
There are plenty of resources online for
that.
You can deploy pre-built
images over the Cloud.
This would further accelerate your
application deployment process.
It is always best to evaluate which
approach is most cost effective for
your business model and organization.
Companies such as Cloudera,
Hortonworks and others,
provide step-by-step guides on how to
set up pre-built images on the Cloud.
As a summary, using pre-built software
packages have a number of benefits and
can significantly accelerate
your big data projects.
Even small teams can quickly prototype,
deploy and validate their project ideas.
The developed analytical solutions
can be scaled to larger volumes and
increase velocities of
data in a matter of hours.
These companies also provide
Enterprise level solutions for large,
full-fledged applications.
An added benefit is that there
are plenty of companies which provide
ready-made solutions.
That means lots of choices for you to
pick the one most suited to your project.
What is a Distributed File System?
Most of us have file
cabinets in our offices or
homes that help us store
our printed documents.
Everyone has their own
method of organizing files,
including the way we bin similar
documents into one file, or
the way we sort them in alphabetical or
date order.
When computers first came out,
the information and
programs were stored in punch cards.
These punch cards were
stored in file cabinets,
just like the physical
file cabinets today.
This is where the name,
file system, comes from.
The need to store information in
files comes from a larger need
to store information in the long-term.
This way the information lives
after the computer program, or
what we call process,
that produced it terminates.
If we don't have files, our access to
such information would not be possible
once a program using or producing it.
Even during the process, we might need
to store large amounts of information
that we cannot store within the program
components or computer memory.
In addition, once the data is in a file,
multiple processes can access
the same information if needed.
For all these reasons, we store
information in files on a hard disk.
There are many of these files, and
they get managed by your operating system,
like Windows or Linux.
How the operating system manages
files is called a file system.
How this information is stored
on disk drives has high impact
on the efficiency and speed of access to
data, especially in the big data case.
While the files have exact addresses for
their locations in the drive, referring
to the data units of sequence of these
blocks, that's called the flat structure,
or hierarchy construction of index
records, that's called the database.
They also have human readable symbolic
names, generally followed by an extension.
Extensions tell what kind of file it is,
in general.
Programs and
users can access files with their names.
The contents of a file can be numeric,
alphabetic, alphanumeric,
or binary executables.
Most computer users work
on personal laptops or
desktop computers with
a single hard drive.
In this model, the user is limited
to the capacity of their hard drive.
The capacity of different devices vary.
For example, while your phone or
tablet might have a storage capacity
in the order of gigabytes, your
laptop computer might have a terabyte of
storage, but what if you have more data?
Some of you probably had
issues in the past with
running out of space on your hard drive.
A way to solve this is to have
an external hard drive and
store your files there or,
you can buy a bigger disk.
Both options are a bit of a hassle, to
copy the data to a new disk, aren't they?
They might not even be
an option sometimes.
Now imagine, you having two computers and
storing some of your data in one and
the rest of your data in another.
How you organize and partition your data
between these computers is up to you.
You might want to store your
work data in one computer and
your personal data in another.
Distributing data on multiple
computers might be an option, but
it raises new issues.
In this situation, you need to know
where to find the files you need,
depending on what you’re doing.
You can find it manageable,
if it’s just your data.
But now imagine having
thousands of computers
to store your data with big volumes and
variety.
Wouldn't it be good to have a system
that can handle the data access and
do this for you?
This is a case that can be handled
by a distributive file system.
Now, let's assume that there
are racks of these computers,
often even distributed across the local or
wide area network, because such file
systems, distributed file systems.
Data sets, or parts of a data set,
can be replicated across the nodes
of a distributed file system.
Since data is already on these nodes,
then analysis of parts of the data
is needed in a data parallel fashion,
computation can be moved to these nodes.
Additionally, distributed file
systems replicate the data
between the racks, and also computers
distributed across geographical regions.
Data replication makes
the system more fault tolerant.
That means, if some nodes or
a rack goes down,
there are other parts of the system,
the same data can be found and analyzed.
Data replication also helps with scaling
the access to this data by many users.
Often, if the data is popular, many
reader processes will want access to it.
In a highly parallelized replication,
each reader can get their own node
to access to and analyze data.
This increases overall system performance.
Note that a problem with having
such a distributive replication is,
that it is hard to make
changes to data over time.
However, in most big data systems,
the data is written once and
the updates to data is maintained
as additional data sets over time.
As a summary, a file system is
responsible from the organization of
the long term information
storage in a computer.
When many storage computers
are connected through the network,
we call it a distributed file system.
Distributed file systems provide data
scalability, fault tolerance, and
high concurrency through partitioning and
replication of data on many nodes.
When to reconsider Hadoop?
The Hadoop ecosystem is
growing at a fast pace.
This means a lot of stuff
that was difficult, or
not supportive, is becoming possible.
In this lecture,
we will look at some aspects that
clearly make a good match for Hadoop.
We will also look at several
aspects that might motivate you
to evaluate Hadoop at a deeper level.
And does Hadoop really make sense for
your specific problem?
First let's look at the key features
that make a problem Hadoop friendly.
If you see a large scale growth in
amount of data you will tackle,
probably it makes sense to use Hadoop.
When you want quick access to your old
data which would otherwise go on tape
drives for archival storage,
Hadoop might provide a good alternative.
Other Hadoop friendly features include
scenarios when you want to use multiple
applications over the same data store.
High volume or
high variety are also great indicators for
Hadoop as a platform choice.
Small data set processing
should raise your eyebrows.
Do you really need Hadoop for that?
Dig deeper, and find out exactly why you
want to use Hadoop before going ahead.
Hadoop is good for data parallelism.
As you know, data parallelism is
the simultaneous execution of the same
function on multiple nodes across
the elements of a dataset.
On the other hand, task parallelism,
as you see in this graph,
is the simultaneous execution
of many different functions
on multiple nodes across the same or
different data sets.
If your problem has task-level
parallelism, you must do further
analysis as to which tools you plan
to deploy from the Hadoop ecosystem.
What are the precise benefits
that these tools provide?
Proceed with caution.
Not all algorithms are scalable in Hadoop,
or
reducible to one of the programming
models supported by YARN.
Hence, if you are looking to deploy
highly coupled data processing algorithms
proceed with caution.
Do a thorough analysis
before using Hadoop.
Are you thinking of
throwing away your existing database
solutions and replacing them with Hadoop?
Think again.
Hadoop may be a good platform where
your diverse data sets can land and
get processed into a form
digestible with your database.
Hadoop may not be the best data store
solution for your business case.
Evaluate, and proceed with caution.
HDFS stores data in blocks
of 64 megabytes or larger,
so you may have to read an entire
file just to pick one data entry.
That makes it a bit harder to
perform random data access.
The Hadoop ecosystem is growing
at a faster pace than ever.
This slide shows some of the moving
targets in the Hadoop ecosystem and
the additional needs which
must be addressed by new tools
to the Hadoop ecosystem.
Mainly, advanced analytical queries,
latency sensitive tasks, and
cyber security of sensitive data.
Here, we give pointers to tools you
might want to look into further
to understand the challenges
these need tools address.
As a summary, although Hadoop is good with
scalability of many algorithms, it is just
one model and does not solve all issues
in managing and processing big data.
Although it would be possible to find
counterexamples, we can generally say
that the Hadoop framework is not the best
for working with small data sets,
advanced algorithms that require
a specific hardware type,
task level parallelism, infrastructure
replacement, or random data access.
YARN, The Resource Manager for Hadoop.
YARN is a resource manage layer that
sits just above the storage layer HDFS.
YARN interacts with applications and
schedules resources for their use.
YARN enables running multiple
applications over HDFC increases
resource efficiency and
let's you go beyond the map reduce or
even beyond the data
parallel programming model.
When Hadoop was first created,
this wasn't the case.
In fact, the original Hadoop
stack had no resource manager.
These two stacked diagrams, show, some of
it's evolution over the last ten years.
One of the biggest limitations
of Hadoop one point zero,
was it's inability to support
non-mapreduce applications.
It had several terrible
resource utilization.
This meant that for advanced
applications such as graph analysis that
required different ways of modelling and
looking at data, you would need to
move your data to another platform.
That's a lot of work if your data is big.
Adding YARN in between HDFS and
the applications enabled
new systems to be built, focusing on
different types of big data applications
such as Giraph for
graph data analysis, Storm for
streaming data analysis, and
Spark for in-memory analysis.
YARN does so
by providing a standard framework
that supports customized application
development in the HADOOP ecosystem.
YARN lets you extract maximum
benefits from your data sets
by letting you use the tools you
think are best for your big data.
Let's take a peek into the architecture
of YARN without getting too technical.
In this picture, notice the resource
manager in the center, and
the node managers on each of
the three nodes on the right.
The resource manager controls all
the resources, and decides who gets what.
Node manager operates at machine level and
is in charge of a single machine.
Together the resource manager and
the node manager form the data
computation framework.
Each application gets
an application master.
It negotiates resource from
the Resource Manager and
it talks to Node Manager
to get its tasks completed.
Notice the ovals labeled
Container The container
is an abstract Notions that
signifies a resource that is
a collection of CPU
memory disk network and
other resources within
the compute note to simplify and
be less precise you can think
of a container and the Machine.
We looked at the essential
gears of the YARN
engine to give you an idea of
the key components of YARN.
Now when you hear terms like
Resource Manager, Node Manager and
Container, you will have an understanding
of what tasks they are responsible for.
Here is a real life example to show
the strength Hadoop 2.0 over 1.0.
Yahoo was able to run almost
twice as many jobs per day with
Yarn than with Hadoop 1.0.
They also experienced a substantial
increase in CPU utilization.
Yahoo!
even claimed that upgrading
to YARN was equal into
adding 1000 machines to
their 2500 machine cluster.
That's big.
YARN success is evident
from an explosive growth of
different application that
the Hadoop ecosystem now has.
New to yarn?
You can use the tool of your choice
over your big data without any hassle.
Compare this with Hadoop 1.0 which
was limited to MapReduce alone.
Let's review a summary of
the key take-aways about yarn.
Yarn gives you many ways for
applications to extract value from data.
It lets you run many distributed
applications over the same Hadoop cluster.
In addition, YARN reduces
the need to move data around and
supports higher resource utilization
resulting in lower costs.
It's a scalable platform that has
enabled growth of several applications
over the HDFS,
enriching the Hadoop ecosystem.
At this point, you hopefully have a good
general idea of what big data means and
why big data is important.
So now, we need to focus on what to do
when we have an application
that uses big data.
In this video, we focus on
the problem of managing big data.
So at the end of the video,
you should be able to describe what data
management means in general, and then
specifically recognize the issues that are
involved in the management of big data.
First, let's see what data
management means in general.
Instead of giving you
definitions of data management,
let's think of some questions
that must be asked and
answered well if you're to manage
a reasonable amount of data.
Now, we can not possibly cover
all questions one should ask for
a data-centric application, but here are
some important ones, which range from how
we get the data, to how we work with it,
to how we secure it from malicious users.
We'll visit these issues one at a time.
Ingestion means the process
of getting the data
into the data system that
we are building or using.
Now you might think,
why is it worth talking about?
We'll just read the data from somewhere,
like a file.
And then using some command,
place it into the data system.
Or we'll have have some
kind of a web form or
other visual interface and just fill it
in so that the data goes into the system.
Both of these ways of
data ingestion are valid.
In fact, they're valid for
some big data systems like your
airline reservation system.
However when you think
of a large scale system
you wold like to have more automation
in the data ingestion processes.
And data ingestion then becomes a part of
the big data management infrastructure.
So here are some questions you might want
to ask when you automate data ingestion.
Now take a minute to read the questions.
We'll look at two examples to
explore them in greater detail.
The first example is that of a hospital
information system that we discussed in
course one in the context
of precision medicine.
We said that hospitals collect
terabytes of medical record
from different departments and
be considered big data systems.
The second example is a cloud based data
store where many people upload their
messages, chats, pictures,
videos, music and so fourth.
The cloud storage also supports active
communication between the members and
store their communication in real time.
So let's think of a hypothetical
hospital information information and
the answer to depressions
that we are putting there.
Now, do not take the numbers
to be very accurate.
They are just examples.
But it illustrates some important points.
One, note that there are two kinds
of likeness associated with data.
Some data like medical images
are large data objects by themselves.
Secondly, the records
themselves are quite small but
the size of the total collection
of records is very high.
Two, while there is a lot of patient data,
the number of data sources that is
the different departmental systems
contributing to the total information
system does not change
very much over time.
Three, the rate of data ingestion is
not enormous and is often proportional
to the number of patient activities
that takes place at the hospital.
Four, the system contains
medical records so
data can never be discarded even
when there are errors in the data.
The errors in this specific case
are flagged but the data is retained.
Now this is the kind of rule
called an error handling policy.
Which might be different for
different application problems.
An air handling policy is part of
a larger scheme of policies called
ingestion policies.
Another kind of ingestion policy involves
decisions regarding what the system should
do if the data rate suddenly increases or
becomes suspiciously low.
In this example we have deliberately
decided not to include it in the design.
Now compare the previous case with
the case of the online store of
personal information.
Again this is just an imaginary example.
So don't think of all
the parameters to be exact.
Now in this case one, the store will
have a fast growing membership.
Each member will use multiple devices
to capture and ingest their data.
Two, over all members together, the site
will be updated at a really fast rate,
making this a large volume data
store with a fast ingest rate.
Three, in this system, our primary
challenge is to keep up with the data
rate, and hence, erroneous data will be
discarded after just one edit to reinvest.
Four, now there is an actual policy for
handling data overflow,
which essentially says,
keep the excess data in a site store.
And ingest them when the data
rate becomes slower.
But if the site store starts getting full
start dropping some incoming data
at a rate of 0.1% at a time.
Now we should see why data
ingestion together with it's
policies should be an integral
part of a big data system.
Especially when it involves
storing fast data.
A very significant aspect of data
management is to document, define,
implement, and test the set of
operations that are required for
a specific application.
As we'll see later in the specialization,
some operations are independent of
the type of data and some others would
require us to know the nature of the data
because the operations make use
of a particular data model.
That is the way that it is structured.
In general, there are two
broad divisions of operations.
Those that work on a singular object and
those that work on
collections of data objects.
In the first case,
an operation that crops an image,
that means extracts a sub
area from an area of pixels,
is a single object operation because we
consider the image as a single object.
One can think of many subclasses
of the second category
where the operations
are on data collections.
We briefly referred to three very
common operations that can be done
regardless of the nature of the data.
The first is to take a collection and
filter out a subset of that collection.
The most obvious case is
selecting a subset from a set.
In this example, we select circles
whose number is greater than three.
A second case is merging two collections
together to form a larger collection.
In the example shown,
two three structure data items are merged
by fusing the node with a common property.
That is two.
In the last case,
we compute a function on a collection and
return the value of the function.
So in this example,
the function is a simple count.
In the real world, this kind of aggregate
function can be very complicated.
We will come back to this issue when
we talk more about map readings, but
in this course, we'll talk about
many different data operations.
Every operator must be efficient.
That means every operator must
perform its task as fast as possible
by taking up as little memory,
or our disk, as possible.
Obviously, the time to
perform an operation
will depend on the size of the input and
the size of the output.
So, if there is an opportunity to use
concurrency where the operator can split
its data and have different threads
operate on the pieces at the same time,
it should definitely do so.
We present a simple example of
an operator we saw on the previous slide.
So this operator, called selection,
refers to choosing a subset of
a set based on some conditions.
Here we are choosing a subset of
circles whose numbers are even.
To make it more efficient,
we can take the input data and
partition it randomly into two groups.
Now, for each group,
we can concurrently run the subset
algorithm and get the partial results.
For this operation, the partial results
can be directly sent to the output
without any additional processing step.
Okay we in essence store
the data efficiently.
But is it any good?
Are there ways of knowing if the data is
potentially error free and useful for
the intended purpose?
This is the issue of data quality.
There are many reasons
why any data application,
especially larger applications need
to be mindful of data quality.
Here are three reasons, of course
there are more that we do not mention.
The first reason emphasizes that
the ultimate use of big data
is its ability to give
us actionable insight.
Poor quality data leads to poor
analysis and hence to poor decisions.
The second related data in regulated
industries in areas like clinical
trials for pharmaceutical companies or
financial data like from banks.
Errors in data in these industries
can regulate regulations leading to
legal complications.
The third factor is different
than the first two.
It says if your big data should
be used by other people or
a third party software
it's very important for
the data to give good quality to
gain trust as a leader provider.
A class of big data applications
is scientific, where large,
integrated collections of data
are created by human experts to
understand scientific questions.
Ensuring accuracy of data will lead
to correct human engagement and
interaction with the data system.
Gartner, the well known
technology research and
advising company created a 2015
industry report on big data qualities.
In this report,
they identify the approaches to meeting
the data quality requirements
in the industry.
This methods include the adherence
to standards where applicable.
It also refers to the need to
create the rules in the data system
that can be use to check if the data
passes a set of correct this qualities.
Like is even employed above 18.
It also includes methods to clean
the data if it's found to have errors or
inconsistencies.
Further the data quality management should
include a well define work flow on how
low quality data could be corrected to
bring it back to a high level of quality.
There are many ways of
looking at scalability.
And we'll consider them as
we go forward in the course.
One way is to consider scaling up and
scaling out.
Simply put,
it is a decision between making a machine
that makes a server more powerful
versus adding more machines.
The first choice will
involve adding more memory,
replacing processes with
process of more course and
adding more processes within a system with
a very fast internet connection speed.
The second choice will involve adding more
machines to a relatively slower network.
Now, there are no absolutes here.
In many cases, we'll choose the former
to get more performance for
large leader systems.
The general trend in the big data world,
however, is to target
the scale out option.
Most big data management systems today
are designed to operate over
a cluster up machines and
have the ability to adjust as more
machines are added and when machines fail.
Cluster management and management
of data operations over a cluster
is an important component in today's
big data management systems.
Now we'll briefly touch upon
the complex issue of data security.
It is obvious that having more sensitive
data implies the need for more security.
If the data is within
the walls of an organization,
we'll still need a security plan.
However, if a big data system
is deployed in the cloud,
over multiple machines, security of
data becomes an even bigger challenge.
So now we need to ensure the security for
not only the machines,
but also the network which will be
heavily used during data transfer
across different phases
of data operations.
For example, if the data store and
the data analysis are performed over
different sets of servers that
every analysis operation gets to
an additional overhead of encrypting the
data as the data gets to the network and
decrypting when it gets
to the processing server.
This effectively increases
operational cost.
As of today, while there are many
security products, the methods for
ensuring security and achieving data
processing efficiency at the same time
remains a research issue
in big data management.
Now the goal of a storage infrastructure,
obviously, is to store data.
There are two storage related
issues we consider here.
The first is the issue of capacity.
How much storage should we allocate?
That means, what should be the size
of the memory, how large and
how many disk units should we have,
and so forth.
There is also the issue of scalability.
Should the storage devices be
attached directly to the computers
to make the direct IO fast but
less scalable?
Or should the storage be
attached to the network
that connect the computers in the cluster?
This will make disk
access a bit slower but
allows one to add more
storage to the system easily.
Now these questions do
not have a simple answer.
If you're interested, you may look up
a website given on your reading list.
A different class of questions deals
with the speed of the IU operation.
This question is often addressed with
this kind of diagram here called a memory
hierarchy, or storage hierarchy, or
sometimes memory storage hierarchy.
The top of the pyramid structure shows
a part of memory called cache memory,
that lives inside the CPU and
is very fast.
There are different levels of cache,
called L1, L2, L3,
where L3 is the slowest but
still faster than what we call memory,
shown here in orange near the middle.
The figure shows their speed
in terms of response times.
Notice the memory streamed here
is 65 nanoseconds per access.
In contrast,
the speed of the traditional hard disk
is of the order of 10 milliseconds.
This gap has prompted the design
of many data structures and
algorithms.that use a hard disk but
tries to minimize the cost of
the IO operations between the fast
memory and the slower disk.
But more recently,
a newer kind of storage.
Very similar to the flash drives or
USBs that we regularly use have made
an entry as a new storage medium.
These devices are called SSDs or
Solid State Devices.
They are much faster
than spinning hard disks.
An even newer addition is
the method called NVMe,
NVM stands for non-volatile memory,
that makes data transfer between SSDs and
memory much faster.
What all this means in a big data system
is that now we have the choice of
architecting a storage infrastructure
by choosing how much of each type of
storage we need to have.
In my own research with large amounts
of data, I have found that using SSDs
speed up all look up operations in data by
at least a factor of ten over hard drives.
Of course the flip side of
this is the cost factor.
The components become increasingly more
expensive as we go from the lower layers
of the pyramid to the upper layers.
So ultimately, it becomes an issue
of cost-benefit tradeoff.
[SOUND] Let us consider
a real life application to
demonstrate the utility and
the challenges of big data.
Many industries naturally deal
with large amounts of data.
For our discussion, we consider
an energy company that provides gas and
electricity to its
consumers in an urban area.
In this news report, you can see
that Commonwealth Edison, or Con Ed,
the gas and electric provider of New York,
decided to place smart meters
all through its jurisdictions.
That comes to 4.7 million smart meters.
Now smart meters are smart because aside
from measuring energy consumption,
they have a two way communication
capability between the meter and
the central system at the gas and
electric company.
In other words, they generate real time
data from the meters to be stored and
processed at the central facility.
How much data?
According to this report,
the number of data received at
the center is 1.5 billion per day.
So the system will not only consume
this data, but process it and
produce output at 15-minute intervals,
and sometimes, 5 minute intervals.
Let's do the math.
That comes to ingesting and processing
about 10.5 million data
points per 15 minutes.
So what kind of computation must
take place within these 15 minutes?
Well, one obvious computation is billing,
where one needs to compute who, especially
in the commercial sector, who actually
owns the meter and should be billed?
This requires combining the meter data
with the data in the customer
database maintained by the company.
But let's just consider
computation related to analytics.
We can list at least four
different kinds of computations.
The first is computing the consumption
pattern per user, not per meter.
Per user, where the output is
a histogram of hourly usage.
So the x axis of the histogram
is hourly intervals And
the y-axis is a number of units consumed.
This leads to the computed both daily and
over larger time periods.
To determine the hourly requirements for
this consumer.
The second computation relates
to estimating the effects of
outdoor temperature on the electricity
consumption of each consumer.
For those you who
are statistically inclined,
this often involves fitting a piece-wise
linear progression model to the data.
The third task is to extract the daily
consumption trends that occur
regardless of the outdoor temperature.
This is again a statistical computation,
and may require something like
a periodic alter regression algorithm,
for time series theta.
The algorithm is not that important there.
What's more important is the ability to
make make good prediction has a direct
economic impact because the company
needs to buy energy from others.
For example, an under-prediction
implies they'll end up paying more for
buying energy at the last moment to
meet the consumer's requirements.
The fourth task is to find groups of
similar consumers based on their usage
pattern so that the company can determine
how many distinct groups of customers
there are and design targeted energy
saving campaigns for each group.
This requires finding similarities
over large number of time series data,
which is a complex computation.
Regardless of the number and
complexity of computation required,
the company's constrained by the fact that
it has only 15 minutes to process the data
before the next and
computation has to be performed.
That issue is not just
the bigness of the data, but
the strip and
strings of the arrival to output time.
The analytics has value, only if it can be
completed within the life-cycle deadline.
So if we were to design a big data system
for such a company, you would need to
understand how much are the computation
can be executed in parallel And
how many machines with what kind of
capability are required to handle the data
rate and the number and complexity of
the analytical computations needed?
Hi, my name is Chad Berkley.
I'm the CTO of FlightStats, and I'm here
today to talk to you a little bit about
our platform and
how we acquire and process data.
But first of all, I'd like to start by
just kind of introducing the company and
telling you a little bit
about what we're all about.
So FlightStats is a data company and
we basically are the leading provider
of global real-time flight status data.
We pull in data from over 500 sources and
we aggregate that data back together, and
we sell it out to our customers which our
other businesses as well as consumers.
So just to give you a little bit
of information about the scope and
scale of what we do.
Like I said,
we have over 500 sources of data.
And on a daily basis,
we process about 15 million flight events,
those that includes landings,
arrivals, departures.
Any time the status of the flight changes,
we got some sort of message on that.
We process about 260 million aircraft
positions per day, so we have an extensive
network that monitors graph positions for
realtime flight tracking applications.
And we also handle about One million PNRs,
or passenger name records,
which are the actual data type
of an itenerary any time you
book travel, a PNR is created for
you, for your travel.
And it includes all of the segments,
like air travel, ferries,
hotels, taxis, Anyhting that
can be scheduled on your trip.
And we basically take in all that data and
we aggregate it together and
we sell it back out.
And how most people kind of know us for
FlightStats.com, that's our
consumer site for business where we
handle about 2 million daily requests.
And we handle about 1
million mobile app requests.
That our b to b side, we cert out a lot
of data by APIs and real time data feeds.
People make about 15 million
API requests to us everyday.
And we also send out about one and half
million flight and trip notifications.
So if you get a push
notification to your phone,
telling you that your flight is delayed or
on time.
That possibly has come from us.
So a little bit about how the data
flows through our company.
We bring in all these
different types of data and
our sources and it flows through
our data acquisition team.
We have a team whose primary purpose
is to pull in all sorts of raw data,
a very heterogeneous datasets.
And process that into a normalized form.
So if you kind of follow the blue arrow
in this diagram you can see that it goes
through this raw data
channel through the data hub.
Which the data hub is a central
component of our system that I'll talk
a little bit more about in a second.
So the blue data, the blue line is
raw data coming in from the source
It goes through our data
acquisition system,
it turns into that purple line
which is a normalized form.
It then goes back through our data hub
again and into our processing engine.
Our processing engine is really where
most of the business logic happens.
The first thing we have to do
is we have to match any piece of
flight information against
a flight that we know about and
primarily the way we know about
flights is through schedules.
So we import schedules on a daily
basis from one of our partner
schedule providers.
That data,
once it's matched is then processed and
the processing basically looks at each
message, and tries to determine if
we think that that message needs
to be passed on to consumers.
So you know it looks at things like,
have we seen that message before.
Or is it a duplicate?
Is it from a data source that we trust?
Are there other things going on
that we need to know about that
may impact whether that message is true or
not?
And once we decide that a message
should be passed through,
if you follow the green line.
It goes into our process
data channel on our hub, and
it's then pushed out to
a couple different places.
So first of all,
it goes into our production database which
is where all of our real time data lives.
That database serves data to our websites,
to our mobile apps, and
a variety of other places.
It also goes into our
data warehouse which,
is where our analytics products use it.
I'll talk a bit more
about that in a minute.
And then, the stream of data actually
goes up to so many of our customers.
We don't need a database on our side.
They would rather build
a database on their side so
we actually just stream all of
the processed data directly to them.
They then host it within
their own systems.
So a little bit more about the hub, the
hub is central to how we move data around.
It's a technology that
we developed in-house.
And it's an object storage based,
scalable, highly available,
multi-channel data queuing and
eventing system.
The object storage part is,
we use Amazon S3 to store this data.
So it's an object storage system.
It's scalable,
we can scale it horizontally or
vertically depending on, but the what
type of data is flowing through it.
It's highly available meaning,
that we have multiple instances
of it in different data centers.
So if one that goes down we can
easily pull another one up or
it's we're going to cross
multiple instances.
And then it's multi channel.
So it's got a rest interface and
any surface can create
a new channel within the system and
start posting data to it.
That data is then queued based on
the time that it comes in, and
other services can be listening for
events on those channels.
So, as soon as a new piece of data
comes into one of those channels,
any service that's listening on that
channel, gets an event notification.
They, that service can then
act upon that piece of data.
And do whatever processing
it may need to do.
This project is open source and
anybody can download it and use it.
So a little bit about some of the data
that we collect and aggregate.
And FLIFO is kind of the industry term for
flight information.
And primarily we look at kind of
the five different parts of flight.
So we pull in information on gate
departure, and then that becomes a runway
departure, basically when the wheels
go up, that is a runway departure.
We do in-flight positional tracking,
so when your flight is moving along,
about once every ten seconds we get
notified of its latitude and longitude.
And its heading and its speed and
its vertical center descent rate and
several other variables.
Then once it lands,
as soon as the wheels touch the ground,
we're notified of a runway arrival and
when the door is opened at the gate,
we have gate arrival information.
All five of these data fields
come in three different forms.
So we have a scheduled,
scheduled departure and arrival.
We have estimated departure and arrival
which can come from a variety of sources,
either airlines, airports,
positional data, et cetera.
And then, we have actuals so
if we have an airport or
an airline that's sending us data about
exactly when the wheels touch down, or
exactly when that door opens on that
aircraft, we push that data as well.
We also generate some
data at flight stops.
So special incidents, if an aircraft
has an issue It's in the news.
We do flag our content with
a message from our support staff.
We do some prediction.
Right now we're just starting to get into
that market, or we're actually trying to
predict 24 hours out whether a flight
will be delayed, disrupted or on time.
We do some synthetic positions,
so over oceans, primarily.
We don't get tracking data
on aircraft over the oceans.
There is currently no satellite-based
tracking system for aircraft.
So we basically take the last
known position a heading, a speed.
And if we have a flight plan, we'll use
a flight plan to synthesize the positions
when we're not getting actual
positions over large bodies of water.
We also generate notifications,
so the push alerts,
the preflight emails,
delay notifications those types of things.
We create those based on what we see
in the data that's coming in to us.
We store all of our historical
data in a data warehouse,
so right now we have six years
of historical flight data.
And that powers our analytics products,
so we allow airlines to do competitive
analysis, and route analysis.
Routes are very important to airlines.
That's how they compete
with each other and
that's primarily how they
are judged by the FAA and
other governmental organizations
on whether they're on-time or not.
We also do airport operations analysis
things like taxi in and taxi out times.
Very important for lots of airports,
runway utilization,
hourly passenger flows through airports,
that type of information.
And we do on-time performance metrics so.
Airlines can look at how they're doing.
How many flights did they complete?
How many flights were on
time within 14 minutes?
And they can compare themselves
to their competitors.
So we host all of this in
a hybrid cloud architecture.
Hybrid cloud basically means that we have
our own private datacenter resources and
we also host resources in
the Amazon Web Services cloud.
Most of our core data processing and
service layer is in our private data
center and we're getting ready to spin
up a second private data center as well.
Right now, our main data center is in
Portland, Oregon, and we're going to spin
another one up on the east coast of
the United States probably in Q2 or Q3.
For our API's we try to keep
those close to our customers so
API end points and
web end points live in Amazon.
And they are automatically routed to
whichever end point is closest to you,
you will automatically be routed to them.
All of our private infrastructure
is virtualized with VMWare.
We pretty much have a fully
virtualized environment.
And we're an Agile shop, so
we have six small, fast teams.
Those are product centric teams, we
allow them to be as customer interactive
as they need to be, and
we try to make our teams semi autonomous.
So, teams get to choose their own tools,
they get to choose their
own development methodologies,
they choose a variety of things.
And We physically allow them
to do what they need to do to get
their job done as quickly as possible.
We try to automate everything.
You do something once manually and
then the next time you write a script or
program to do it.
And we also measure everything.
Right now, we're taking in about
2.5 billion metrics per month off
of our systems.
And we use those metrics to monitor
our application performance,
to monitor revenue, to monitor pretty
much everything we do in the company.
We really try to enable
total system awareness,
everything from the hardware layer
up to the website is monitored.
And we use industry best practices and
tools and of course, we try to recruit and
hire the best talent possible a little
bit about our software stock.
We're primarily a Java shop.
Our core processing services
are all written in Java.
We do use node JS in our
Microservice Edge layer.
And node JS is actually starting to move
more down into the processing service
layer as well.
We use many different types of data bases.
Our primary realtime
database is Post Press.
And we use Mongo for
the backend of our API services.
On the website, we're all HTML5 and
we're moving to React and Redux, and
we're making use of Elasticsearch for
quick searching and indexing on our data.
And, of course, we have iOS and
Android mobile applications.
So you can find out more about
Flightstats on our website.
If you need data for your applications,
please go to the developer center
at developer.flightstats.com.
You can sign up for
a free test account and
be able to pull data
directly off of our APIs.
If you're interested in the Hub,
like I said that's open source.
Please check out the Git Hub page and
if you have any additional questions,
feel free to contact
myself John Berkeley and
I'd be happy to answer any
of your questions via email.
Thanks for listening today and
hope you have a great day.
Bye.
Different data sources in the game
industry include using your finger.
What type of device is coming from?
The amount of headsets.
It's pretty much infinite,
as far as the number of ways we
can bring data in from the game.
And it could be joystick or mouse,
keyboards, there's lots of ways
as well as what happens inside
the game itself as far cars or
the driving, tires,
flying machines, anything.
The volume of data,
it really depends on the type of game and
how often they want to send the data in.
How many types of events they've tagged
and how many users are playing the game.
So if you have a user, you've 5 million
users that are playing your game and
you're tapping and
you're tracking each tap of the screen,
of where they went or each click of
the mouse as they were using it,
you're going to get
a lot of volume of data.
And so
you need to be prepared to bring in a lot
of different data very, very quickly.
As far as the variety of data, it depends.
You have round pizzas and
you have round tires.
I mean, they're completely different.
They're both round, but there's different
ways that you're going to want to know how
many pepperoni are on one pizza and
how many lug nuts go on a tire.
So the variety is really unlimited,
as well.
It really just depends on each game.
So, you have to be prepared to
bring in all kinds of data.
Touch data, wheel data,
track speeds, anything.
And if you put taxonomy together that
you can define as an example of verb,
object, location, value and any number
of other sources, then you can basically
track anything you want as long as they
all fall into the same kind of buckets.
And the buckets can be different
sizes based on the type of events.
They don't all need to be 4,
some can be 2, some can be 20,
it doesn't really matter.
The modeling challenge has really come
down to who designs the structure at which
you store your data and
how you want to retrieve that data.
Those kind of of storage and
retrieval models are very, very important,
because what it really
comes down to is speed.
You can record a lot of data and
it can take you five years to query it,
it doesn't really do you any good.
So you need to make sure you plan for
reporting speed, because that's ultimately
what within the organisation needs is
the ability to report on it very quickly.
The management challenges really come
down to trying to figure out what data to
store.
A lot of times we go into various
companies and you've got producers sitting
across the hall from designers, and
they don't even know each other.
They don't realize what they want and
the programmer says,
I'm going to put these events in and the
product manager who wants to figure out
how many times somebody crashed says,
well, I need these events in.
So unless they're communicating, you're
going to get the wrong type of data.
So the management challenge is trying
to make sure everybody communicates,
they decide on the taxonomy and
the structure and
then we can go forward with tagging and
getting in the entire game working.
We process, stayed in two main ways.
One is streaming data.
One is batched or scheduled data.
Streaming data has scripts that run
instantly the minute the data arrives.
And so as the data come in,
it gets processed and
then stored In a reporting format.
So they can easily generate reports
up to the second very, very quickly.
Batch processing data really depends on
the type of data where it's coming from.
Most of the time when we download
data from iTunes or YouTube or
something like that, it comes in a CSV or
a very similar format.
There's not really a lot of
processing we need to do.
It's more of ingesting that data.
There are processes we need to run
with some type of batch data, but
most of the batch data we
receive comes in as a CSV or
other similar already processed formats.
So typically, while you can do processing
in both modes most processing typically
happens with the streaming real-time data
than it does with offline batch data.
We actually didn't use any
technology in the a big data space.
We created our own, from scratch.
What we did was we decided
what kind of model we wanted.
How we were going to store data?
How we were going to retrieve data?
And ultimately,
how we were going to reduce the data?
Because the more and more and more data
you have, the slower it is to actually do
a query, because you have to look through
all the different pieces of data.
A lot of databases solve this problem for
you, but they were really doing it in more
generic way were we needed
something very specific.
So we started from scratch building our
own data storage and retrieval, and
reporting from the ground up.
When it came to scalability,
it was really about designing the parts of
the system that could be
independently scaled.
So if data's coming in in real-time,
we send that into what we call a gateway.
And the gateway could be three gateways,
let's say.
But if the data starts
getting over loaded,
I just have to add another gateway.
And a gateway is just this little
light layer that just receives data,
passes it on and goes back to it's job,
doesn't do anything else.
So it can receive a lot
of data very quickly, but
also I can just add another one.
And it just automatically logs in and
adds itself to a list and
now the data is being distributed
amongst four gateways instead.
Query engine is the same way.
When you're doing queries to try
to get data out of the system, so
you can build reports.
If I need more query engines,
because people are doing more reporting,
we can add more query engines.
So, the idea behind scalability is
trying to break the services up into
the type of services that
they most make sense.
So that if you need to,
you can add just the service without
rebuilding the entire platform.
My advice for people designing systems for
big data is to first,
try to understand what
you want to accomplish.
What's the goal?
I mean, we're going to ingest everything
and we're going to report on everything.
It's not really something that you can
achieve without some special thought.
If you're going to focus on,
your area's going to be say gardening,
then look at what kind of things you're
going to do in the gardening area and
try to focus on what that
type of data is going to be.
This isn't going to restrict you
to only being a gardener, but
it is going to give you focus
on how to design your system, so
that they're actually going to work for
you.
You're going to continually evolve your
systems, add more things to them and
grow them.
I wouldn't suggest starting with
an unlimited variety of options and
hoping you're going to
solve all the problems.
Start with the goal of what your current
solution is and expand from there.
Data can be fun, but
it can also be overwhelming.
So, try to keep the data in mind
without keeping the world in mind and
I think you'll be just fine.
In this video we will provide a quick
summary of the main points from our
first course on introduction to big data.
If you have just completed
our first course and
do not need a refresher,
you may now skip to the next lecture.
After this video,
you will be able to recall
what started the big data era and
the three main big data sources.
Summarize the volume,
variety, velocity and
veracity issues related to each source.
Explain the five step data science
process to gain value from big data.
Remember the main elements
of the Hadoop Stack.
We began our first course with
an explanation of how a lead torrent of
big data combined with cloud computing
capabilities to process data anytime and
anywhere has been at the core of
the launch of the Big Data Era.
This big torrent of big data is often
boil down to a few varieties of data
generated by machines, people and
organizations with machine generated data.
We refer to the data generated from real
time sensors and industrial machinery or
vehicles.
Web logs that track user behavior online.
environmental sensors,
personal health trackers among
many other sense data sources.
With human generated data, we really refer
to the vast amount of social media data,
status updates, tweets, photos and videos.
With organization generated data,
we refer to more traditional types of data
including transaction
information data bases and
structure data often
stored in data warehouses.
Note that big data can be structured,
semi-structured, and unstructured.
Which is a topic we will talk about
more and in depth later in this course.
Whatever your big data application is and
the types of big data you're using,
the real value will come from integrating
different types of data sources and
analyzing them at scale.
Overall, by modeling, managing and
integrating diverse streams
to improve our business and
add value to our big data even
before we start analyzing it.
As a part of modeling and
managing big data is focusing on
the dimensions of scale availability and
considering the challenges associated with
this dimensions to pick the right tools.
Volume, variety and
velocity are the main dimensions which
we characterized big data and
describe its challenges.
We have huge amounts of data
in different formats and
varying quality which
must be processed quickly
veracity refers to the biases,
noise, and abnormality in data,
or the unmeasurable certainty is in the
truthfulness and trustworthiness of data,
and valence refers to
the connectedness of big data.
Such as in the form of graph networks.
Each V presents a challenging
dimension of big data mainly of size,
complexity, speed, quality,
and consecutiveness.
Although we can list some
other v' based on the context.
We prefer to list these five as
fundamental dimensions which
this big data specialization
helps you work on.
Moreover, we must be sure to
never forget the sixth V: Value,
at the heart of the big
data challenge is turning
all of the other dimensions into
truly useful business value.
How will Big Data benefit you and
your organization?
The idea behind processing all
this Big Data in the first place
is to bring value to the problem at hand.
We need to take steps into
Big Data engineering and
scalable data science to
generate value out of Big Data.
We have all heard it.
Data signs turns big data into insides,
or even actions.
But what does that really mean?
Data signs can be taught of as
the basis for empirical research.
Like data is used to induce
information on the observations.
These observations are mainly data.
In our case, big data related to
a business or scientific use case.
Inside is a term we use to refer to
the data products of data science.
It is extracted from
a diverse amount of data
through a combination of exploratory
data analysis and modeling.
The questions are sometimes less
specific and it can require looking
carefully at the data for patterns in
it to come up with a specific question.
Another important point to recognize
is that data science is not static
one time analysis.
It involves a process where models
where you generate give us insights
are constantly improve to a further and
prequel evidence and iterations.
There are many ways to
look at this process.
One way of looking at it
as two distinct activities.
Mainly, big data engineering and
big data analytics,
or computational big data
science as I like to call it,
since more than simple
analytics are being performed.
A more detailed way of looking at
the process reveals five listing steps or
activities of the data science process,
namely acquire, prepare,
analyze, report, and act.
We can simply say that data science
happens at the boundary of all the steps.
Ideally, this process should
support experimental work,
which is constantly iterated and
leads to more scientific exploration,
as well as producing actionable
results during these explorations
using dynamic scalability on big data and
cloud platforms.
This five step process can be used in
alternative ways in real life big data
applications if we add the dependencies
of different tools to each other.
The influence of big data pushes for
alternative scalability approaches
at each step of the process.
Acquire includes anything
that helps us retrieve data,
including finding, accessing,
acquiring, and moving data.
It includes identification of and
authenticated access to all related data,
as well as transportation of data
from sources to destinations.
It includes ways to subset and
match the data to regions or
times of interest, which we sometimes
refer to as geospatial querying.
We divide the prepare data
step into two sub-steps,
based on the nature of the activity.
The first step in data preparation
involves exploring the data
to understand its nature,
what it means, its quality, and format.
It often takes a preliminary
analysis of data, or
samples of data, to understand it.
This is why this primary
step is called prepare.
Once we know more about the data
through exploratory analysis,
the next step is pre-processing
of data for analysis.
It includes cleaning data,
subsetting, or filtering data, and
creating data, which programs can read and
understand by modelling raw data
into a more defined data model, or
packaging it using a specific data format.
We will learn more about data models and
data formats later in this course.
If there are multiple data sets involved,
this step also includes integration
of different data sources or
streams, which is a topic we will
explore in our course three.
The prepared data then would be
passed on to the analysis step,
which involves selection of
analytical techniques to use,
building a model of the data,
and analyzing results.
This step can take a couple
of iterations on its own or
might require a data scientist
to go back to steps 1 and
2 to get more data or
package data in a different way.
So, exploration never ends.
Step 4 for communicating results includes
evaluation of analytical results,
presenting them in a visual way,
creating reports that include
an assessment of results with
respect to success criteria.
Activities in this step can often be
referred to with terms like interpret,
summarize, visualize, and post-process.
The last step brings us back to the very
first reason we do data science,
for a purpose.
Reporting insights from analysis and
determining actions from insights based
on the purpose you initially defined
is what we refer to as the act step.
We have now seen all of the steps
in a typical data science process.
Please note that this is an iterative
process and findings from
one step may require previous steps
to be repeated, but need information,
leading for further exploration and
application of these steps.
Scalability of this process to big
data analysis requires the use of
big data platforms like Hadoop.
The Hadoop ecosystem frameworks and
applications
provide such functionality through
several overarching themes and goals.
First, they provide scalability
to store large volumes of data
on commodity hardware.
As the number of systems increase, so
does the chance for
crashes and hardware failures.
They handle fault tolerance to
gracefully recover from these problems.
In addition, they are designed to handle
big data capacity and compressing text
files, graphs of social networks,
streaming sensor data and raster images.
We can add more data
types to this variety.
For any given data type,
you can find several projects in
the ecosystem that support it.
Finally, they facilitate
a shared environment,
allow multiple jobs to
execute simultaneously.
Additionally, the Hadoop ecosystem
includes a wide range of open source
projects backed by a large and
active community.
These projects are free to use and
easy to find support for.
Today, there are over 100
Big Data open source projects,
and this continues to grow, many rely
on Hadoop, but some are independent.
Here is, one way of looking at a subset
of tools in the Hadoop Ecosystem.
This layer diagram is organized
vertically based on the interface.
Lower level interfaces to storage and
scheduling on the bottom and
high level languages and
interactivity at the top.
The Hadoop distributed file system,
or HDFS, is the foundation for
many big data frameworks since it
provides scalable and reliable storage.
As the size of your data increases,
you can add commodity
hardware to HDFS to
increase storage capacity.
So it enables what we call
scaling out of your resources.
Hadoop YARN provide
flexible scheduling and
resource management over the HTFS storage.
Yarn is use at Yahoo to schedule
jobs across 40,000 servers.
MapReduce is a programming model
that simplifies parallel computing.
Instead of dealing with the complexities
of synchronization and scheduling you only
need to give MapReduce two
functions map and reduce.
This programming model is so
powerful that Google previously
used it for indexing websites.
MapReduce, only assumes
a limited model to express data.
Hive, and
Pig are two additional programming models,
on top of MapReduce,
to augment data modeling of MapReduce,
with relational algebra and
data flow modeling, respectively.
Hive was created at Facebook to
issue SQL-like queries using
MapReduce on their data in HDFS.
Pig was created at Yahoo to model
dataflow based programs using MapReduce.
Thanks to YARNs ability to
manage resources, not just for
MapReduce but other programming models.
Giraph was built for
processing large scale graphs efficiently.
For example, Facebook uses Giraph to
analyze the social graphs of its users.
Similarly, Storm, Spark and
Flink were built for
real time and
In-memory processing of big data.
On top of the YARN resource scheduler and
HDFS.
In-memory processing is a powerful
way of running big data applications,
even faster, achieving 100x better
performance for some tasks.
Sometimes your data processing or
tasks are not easily or
efficiently represented using the file and
directory model of storage,
examples of this include collections
of key values or large sparse tables.
NoSQL projects such as
Cassandra MongoDB and
HBase handle all these cases.
Cassandra was created at Facebook and
Facebook also use HBase for
its messaging platform.
Finally, running all this tools requires
a centralized management system for
synchronization, configuration And
to ensure high availability.
Zookeeper, created by Yahoo to
wrangle services named after animals,
performs these duties.
Just looking at the small number
of Hadoop stack components,
we can already see that most of them
are dedicated to data modeling.
Management, and
efficient processing of the data.
In the rest of this course,
we will give you fundamental knowledge and
some practical skills on how to start
modeling and managing your data, and
picking the right tools for this activity
from a plethora of big data tools.
Welcome to course two of
the big data specialization.
I'm Amarnath Gupta.
>> And I'm Ilkay Altintas.
We are really excited to work
with you in this course,
to develop your understanding and skills
in big data modeling and management.
You might have just finished our first
course, and see the potential and
challenges of big data.
If you haven't it's not required but for
those with less background in
the area you might find it valuable.
>> Let's explain what we mean by
big data modeling and management.
Suppose you have an application
where the data is big in a sense and
it has a large volume, or has high speed,
or comes with a lot of variations.
Even before you think of
how to handle the bigness,
you need to have a sense of
what the data looks like.
The goal of data modeling is to
formally explore the nature of data, so
that you can figure out what
kind of storage you need, and
what kind of processing you can do on it.
The goal of data management
is to figure out
what kind of infrastructure support
you would need for the data.
For example, does your environment need
to keep multiple replicas of the data?
Do you need to do statistical
computation with the data?
Once these operational requirements,
you'll
be able to choose the right system that
will let you perform these operations.
>> We will also introduce
management of big data as it is
streaming from data sources and talk
about storage architectures for big data.
For example,
how can high velocity data get ingested,
managed, stored in order to enable
real time analytical capabilities.
Or what is the difference between
data at rest and data in motion?
And how can a data system enable both?
>> Once you've understood the basic
concepts of data modeling,
data management, and streaming data,
we will introduce you
to the characteristics of large volume
data and how to think about that.
Thus, we will transition from
classical database management systems,
that is DBMSs,
to big data management systems, or BDMSs.
We'll present brief overviews of
several big data management systems
available in the marketplace today.
We are so excited to show you examples
of archived and streaming big data sets.
Our goal is to provide you with simple
hands on exercises that require
no programming, but show you what
big data looks like, and why various
big data management systems are suitable
for specific kinds of big data.
In the end you will be
able to design a simple
big data information system
using this knowledge.
We wish you a fun time learning and
hope to hear from you in the discussion
forums and learner stories.
>> Happy learning and think big data.
This is the second course in the 2016
version of our big data specialization.
>> After listening to learners like you,
we have changed some of the content and
ordering in the specialization.
This course takes you on the first
step of any big data project,
its modeling and management.
>> We hope that this background
on what big data looks like and
how it is modeled and managed in
a large scale system will make you feel
more prepared to take steps towards
retrieving and processing big data and
perform big data analytics which
are topics coming up in the next courses.
The third component of
a data model is constraints.
A constraint is a logical statement.
That means one can compute and test
whether the statement is true or false.
Constraints are part of the data model
because they can specify something about
the semantics, that is,
the meaning of the data.
For example,
the constraint that a week has seven and
only seven days is something that a data
system would not know unless this
knowledge is passed on to it
in the form of a constraint.
Another constraint, shown here,
Tells the system that the number of
titles for a movie is restricted to one.
Different data models,
as we'll see in the next module,
will have different kinds of constraints.
There may be many different
kinds of constraints.
A value constraint is a logical
statement about data values.
On a previous slide we have said,
that the age, that is,
the value of data elements representing
the age of an entity can not be negative.
We also saw an example of
uniqueness constraint when we said
every movie can have only one title.
In the words of logic,
there should exist no data object that's
a movie and has more than one title.
It's easy to see that enforcing
these constraints requires us
to count the number of titles and
then verify that it's one.
Now, one can generalize this to count
the number of values associated with
each object and check whether it lies
between an upper and lower bound.
This is often called a cardinality
constraint of data property.
In a medical example here,
the constraint has a lower limit of 0 and
an upper limit of 3.
A different kind of value constraint can
be enforced by restricting the type of
the data allowed in a field.
If we do not have such a constraint we
can put any type of data in the field.
For example, you can have -99 as
the value of the last name of a person,
of course that would be wrong.
To ensure that this does not happen,
we can enforce the type of the last name
to be a non-numeric alphabetic string.
This example shows a logical
expression for this constraint.
A type constraint is a special
kind of domain constraint.
The domain of a data property or
attribute is the possible set of values
that are allowed for that attribute.
For example, the possible values for
the day part of the date field
can be between 1 and 31.
While a month may have
the value between 1 and 12.
Or, alternately, a value from the set
January, February, ect till December.
Now, one can devise a more complex
constraint, where the value of the date
for April, June, and September and
November, are restricted between 1 and 30.
And if you think about it,
all three constraints that we have
described in the last slide
are value constraints.
So they only state how to restrict
the values of some data property.
In sharp contrast, structural properties
restrict the structure of the data.
We'll choose a more complex example for
this.
Suppose we are a matrix,
as shown in the example, and
we've restricted to be a square matrix.
So the number of columns is exactly
equal to the number of rows.
We have not put any restriction
on the number of rows or columns.
But just that they have to be the same.
Now this constrains
the structure of the matrix and
implies that the number of entries in
the structure will be a squared number.
If we convert this matrix to a three
column table as shown, and impose
the same squareness constraint, it will
translate to a more complex condition.
That the number of data
rows will be the square of
the number of unique values
in column one of the table.
We'll encounter some more structural
constraints in the next module.
The second component of a data model is
a set of operations that can be performed
on the data.
And in this module,
we'll discuss the operations without
considering the bigness aspect.
In course three,
we'll come back to the issue of performing
these operations when the data is large.
Now,operations specified
the methods to manipulate the data.
SInce different data models are typically
associated with different structures,
the operations on them will be different.
But some types of operations are usually
performed across all data models.
We'll describe a few of them here.
One common operation extract a part of
a collection based on the condition.
In the example here,
we have a set of records and
we're looking for a sub set that
satisfies the condition that
the fifth field has a value
greater than 100,000.
The only one record
satisfies this requirement.
Note that we called this operation
subsetting rather loosely.
Depending on the context,
it's also called selection or filtering.
The next common operation is retrieving
a part of a structure that is specified.
In this case,
we specify that we are interested
in just the first two fields
of a collection off records.
But this produces a new collection of
records which has only these fields.
This operation like before has many names.
The most dominant name is projection.
In the next module, we'll see several
versions of this operation for
different data models.
The next two operations are about
combining two collections
into a larger one.
The term combine may be
interpreted in various ways.
The most straightforward
of them is said union.
The assumption behind the union operation
is that the two collections
involved have the same structure.
In other words, if one collection has
four fields and another has 14 fields, or
if one has four fields on people and
the dates of birth, and the other has four
things about countries and their capitols,
they cannot be combined through union.
In the example here,
their two collections have three and
two records, respectively, with one
record that's common between them.
The green one.
The result collection has four record,
because duplicates are disallowed
because it's a set operation.
There is indeed another version of
union where duplicates are allowed and
will produce five records instead of four.
The second kind of combining,
called a Join, can be done when
the two collections have different data
content but have some common elements.
In the example shown,
the first field is the common element
between the two collections on the left.
In this kind of data combination
there are two stages.
First, for each data item think
of a record of collection one,
one finds a set of matching
data items in collection two.
Thus, the first records of
the two collections match
based on the first field.
In the second phase of the operation,
all fields of the matching
record pairs are put together.
In the first record of the result
collection shown on the right,
one gets the first four fields
on the first collection and
the remaining two fields
from the second collection.
Now in this one example, we found one pair
of matching records from the collections.
In general, one would find more
than one matching record pairs.
As you can see,
this operation is more complex and
can be very expensive when the size
of the true collections are large.
In the big data world, we often hear the
term structured data, that is, data having
a structure which is quite different
from the so-called unstructured data.
But what is a structure?
Let's consider file 1.
It's a typical CSV file that has
three lines with different content.
But the file content is uniform
in the sense that each line,
call it a record,
has exactly three fields,
which we sometimes call data properties or
attributes.
Further, the first two of these fields
are strings and the third one is a date.
We can add more records, that's
lines with the same pattern of data,
to the file in the same fashion.
The content will grow, but the pattern of
data organization will remain identical.
This repeatable pattern of data
organization makes the file structured.
Now let's look at file 2,
which is four records of five fields each,
except that the third record seems
to be missing the last entry.
Is this file structured?
We argue that it is, because the missing
value makes the third record incomplete,
but it does not break the structure or
the pattern of the data organization.
Let's looks at these
two files side by side.
Clearly file 2 has more fields, and hence
is sort of wider than the first file.
Would you say that they
have the same structure?
Well, on the face of it they don't.
But if you think more broadly,
you would notice that they
are both collection of k fields.
The size of the collection,
respectively three and four, differs.
And k is 3 in the first case and
5 in the second.
But we can think of 3 and 5 as parameters.
In that case, we will say that these
files have been generated by a similar
organizational structure, and
hence they have the same data model.
Now in contrast, consider this file.
Just looking at it, it's impossible to
figure out how the data is organized and
how to identify subparts of the data.
We would call this data unstructured.
Often, compressed data like JPEG images,
MP3 audio files,
MPEG3 video files, encrypted data,
are usually unstructured.
In module two, we'll elaborate on data
models that are not fully structured or
are structured differently.
This is the first of two
hands-on exercises involving
sensor data from a weather station.
In this one, we will look at
static data in a text file.
The next one we will look at live data
streaming from the weather station
in real time.
In this exercise, we will begin
by opening a terminal window and
changing into the directory
containing the station measurements.
We will look at these measurements in
a text file and then look at the key for
these measurements so
we can understand what the values mean.
Finally, we will plot the measurements.
Let's begin.
First, we will open a terminal window by
clicking on the Terminal icon on the top
of the toolbar.
Next, we'll cd into the directory
containing the sensor data.
We'll run cd
Downloads/big-data-two/sensor.
We can write ls to see
the contents of this directory.
The data from the weather station is
in a text file called wx-data.txt.
We can run more wx-data.txt to
see the contents of this file.
Each line of this file is
a separate set of measurements.
There are two columns in this file,
the first column is a time stamp and
it's separated by
a second column by a tab.
The second column itself has separate
columns and these are separated by commas.
The time stamp is the number
of seconds since 1970.
You'll notice that it increases for
each time stamp.
each measurement.
But sometimes measurements
come in at the same time.
For example this one at 006.
The measurements,
we see that the prefix is 0R1 for
most of them but some have 0R2.
If we look at the other measurements,
we see that all the 0R1 measurements
start with Dn, Dm, Dx, and so on.
Whereas R2 begins with Ta, Ua, and Pa.
If we scroll down in the text
file by hitting the space bar,
we'll see there are other
measurements besides R1 and R2.
For example, there's R5 that has Th,
Vh, Vs and so on.
And there's R0 which has
all the measurements.
So Dn, Dm, Dx, Ta, Ua, Pa.
And the remaining ones.
Next we'll open another internal
window and look at the key to this
measurements click on the tool
bar to open the terminal window.
cd into downloads big data two sensor
And the key to these measurements is
in a file called wxt520format.txt.
We can run more wxt520format.txt
to see this file.
This file says where each
of the prefix is mean, for
example Sn is the wind speed minimum.
Sm is the wind speed average.
And Ta is the air temperature.
So if we go back to our sensor file,
we see here Ta equals 13.9c.
That means the air temperature at this
time was 13.9 degrees celsius.
We can also create a plot of
the data in this text file
by running plot-data.py wx-data.txt Ta.
This says to plot the data in
the wx-data file and the measure that we
want to apply is Ta, which according
to our key, is the air temperature.
When we run it, it displays a plot of the
air temperature found in the text file.
In this hands-on exercise,
we will be looking at an image file,
which uses an array data model.
First, we will open a terminal window and
display an image file on the screen.
Next, we will examine the structure
of the image, and finally,
extract pixel values from
various locations in the image.
Let's begin.
First, we'll open a terminal window by
clicking on the terminal icon at the top
of the toolbar.
Next, we'll CDN2 the directory
containing the image,
cdn2downloads/bigdata2/image.
We can run ls to see the image
in different scripts.
The file, Australia.jpg,
is an image that we want to view,
we can use eog to view it.
Run eog Australia.jpg Eog is
a common image viewer on Linux.
Australia.jpg is a satellite image
of the Australian continent.
Now let's look at the structure
of this image file.
If we go back to our terminal window,
we can run the image
viewer in the background by
hitting CTRL+Z, and then bg.
We can view the dimensions or
structure of the array data model of this
image by running
dimensions.py Australia.jpg.
This says that the image has
5250 columns and 4320 rows.
So it is a two-dimensional image.
Additionally, each cell or
pixel within this image is
composed of three 8-bit pixels.
These pixels are composed of three
elements, red, green, and blue.
We can extract or
view the individual pixel elements
at a specific location in the image
by using the pixel.py script.
We can run pixel.py Australia.jpg 0
0 to see the value at one location.
The 0 0 location is
the corner of the image.
If we go back to the image, the corners
are all the ocean, so they're dark blue.
If we look at the value that was
extracted, we see that blue has a high
value of 50, whereas red and
green are low with 11 and 10.
If we view it at another corner,
by looking at 5000 0,
we'll see the same value.
If we go back to the image, the middle
of the image, which is the land,
is orange or yellow.
It's definitely not blue, so
let's take a look at a pixel value there.
Okay, run pixel.py
Australia.jpg 2000 2000.
This says that the red has a value of 118,
green is 89, and the blue is 57.
So the red and green are higher than blue,
so it's not ocean.
This is the second hands on exercises for
CSV data.
In the first, we saw how to import
a CSV file into a spreadsheet and
make a simple plot.
In this one,
we will learn how to filter data and
perform some aggregate operations.
We will begin by opening a terminal
window and starting a spreadsheet.
Next, we will load the CSV
data into the spreadsheet and
perform a filter over several columns.
Finally, we will calculate an average and
sum from the data.
Let's begin.
First, we open a terminal window by
clicking on the terminal icon in
the top toolbar.
We can start the spreadsheet
by writing oocalc.
Next, let's load our CSV
data into the spreadsheet.
We click on File > Open, CENSUS.CSV.
And click OK on this
dialog to load the data.
Column F in the spreadsheet is the state,
and
column H is the census population for
2010.
Let's create a filter that
just shows the data for
California, for
counties larger than one million people.
We can create this filter by first
selecting both the state name column and
the census 2000 population column.
Next we go to data,
filter, standard filter.
Here we change the field
name to be the state name,
the condition we leave at equals and
the value we use California.
This filters all the rows,
unless the state is California.
We then want to filter for
all the counties whose population
is greater than one million people.
To do that, in this second line here,
we change the operator to AND.
The field name should be
census 2010 population and
the condition should be greater than.
Then set the value to be one million.
And click OK.
We can see that all the data from the
spreadsheet has disappeared except where
the state name is California and
the population is greater
than one million people.
We can reset or remove this
filter to see all the data again
by going to Data > Filter.
Reset filter.
You can perform aggregate operations
on the data in a spreadsheet.
Next, let's perform some aggregate
operations over the data.
We can compute the average and
the sum of the data.
To do this, let's run these
calculations in a separate sheet.
Create a new sheet by clicking
on the green plus button.
To compute the average we select
a cell and enter =Average( and
then we select the data that we
want to compute the average from.
If we go back to sheet one.
We can select some of
the data from the H column.
So let's just choose several
counties in Alabama.
When we hit Enter,
it takes us back to sheet one and
we can see that the average is computing.
Similarly, we can compute the sum
by entering =sum, open parentheses.
Going back to sheet one and
selecting the columns we want to sum.
When we're done hit Enter and
the sum is computed.
In this hands on exercise,
we will be looking at JSON data.
First, we will open a terminal window and
then look at the contents of a JSON
file containing tweets from Twitter.
Next, we will examine
the schema of this JSON file.
Finally, we will extract different
fields from the JSON data.
Let's begin.
First, we'll open a terminal window,
by clicking on the terminal
icon at the top of the toolbar.
Next, we'll see cd into the directory
containing the json data,
by running cddownload/big/data/2/json.
We can run ls, to see the json file.
The json file is called twitter.json.
We can run more twitter.json to
view the contents of this file.
The json data contains semi-structured
data, which is nested several levels.
There are many tweets in this file, and
it's hard to read using the more command.
You can use space to scroll down and
when we're done, hit q.
We can run the jsonschema.pi command
to view the schema of this data.
We run jsonschema.pitwitter.json
And we'll add a pipe more at the end.
This shows the nested
fields within this data,
at the top level there are fields
like contributors text and id and so
on, but there are also fields nested
within these top level fields for
example entities also contains
called symbols media hashtags and
so on If we scroll down by hitting space,
we'll see that there's
several levels of nesting.
For example, user also has
follow_request_sent, id, and so on.
We can run the print json script to view
the contents of a particular tweet and
a particular field within that tweet.
Let's run print_json.py.
It asks for the file name so
we'll enter twitter.json.
And we'll look at tweet 99.
So let's look at the top
level field called text.
So here we see the text for
note the 99th tweet in this file.
We could also look at a nested field
within the file, by running print_json
again The file name is twitter.json.
We'll look at tweet 99 again.
And we'll look at the field
entities hashtags.
The hashtags that are embedded or
nested within the entities field.
This is the first of two hands
on exercises involving CSV Data.
In this exercise, we will import
a CSV file into a spreadsheet and
make a simple plot.
We will begin by opening a terminal window
and looking at a CSV file in the terminal.
Next, we will start
the spreadsheet application and
import the CSV data into the spreadsheet.
We can then look at the rows and columns
of the CSV file and make a simple plot.
Let's begin, first,
open a terminal shell by
clicking on the black terminal
icon at the top of the toolbar.
Next, let's cd into the directory
containing the CSV data.
We'll run cd space
Download/big-data-2/csv.
We can run ls to
see the CSV files.
The file census.csv contains
census data for the United States.
We can run the command more census.csv
to see the contents of this file.
The first line of this file is the header
with the columns separated by commas.
You can go down in
the file by hitting space.
Hit Q to quit more.
Next, let's start
a spreadsheet application.
We run oocalc to start this.
We can import the census
data CSV file into
the spreadsheet by going to File > Open.
Clicking on downloads.
Big Data 2, CSV, census.csv.
In this dialog click OK.
You can see into this spreadsheet,
import of the CSV data to
a bunch of rows and columns.
Each column that was separated
by a comma in the CSV file,
is a column in the spreadsheet.
We can see that our CSV file
was successfully imported into
the spreadsheet.
If we scroll down to
the bottom of the spreadsheet,
we can see how many rows
there were in the CSV file.
There are 3194 rows in the CSV file.
If this file instead had millions or
10 millions of rows,
then we would have to use a big
data system such as Hadoop or HDFS.
Let's scroll back to the top.
Next, let's make a simple plot of
some of the data in the CSV file.
Let's plot the population estimates for
several years for the state of Alabama.
The state of Alabama is
given in the second row and
the population estimates
are given in these columns.
Let's select J through O,
so you get the population
estimate for 2010 through 2015.
We can create a plot of these values
by clicking on the Chart button.
And clicking finish.
In the second hands on for CSV data,
we'll perform some filtering and
some aggregate operations over the data.
Welcome.
In this module,
we'll talk about data models.
If you completed the introductory
course of this specialization,
you might recall our
video on data variety.
One way to characterize data variety
is to identify the different models of
data that are used in any application.
So what is a data model?
And why do we care about data
models in the context of big data?
In this lesson, we'll introduce you to
three components of a data model and
what they tell us about the data.
So after this lesson, you'll be able
to distinguish between structured and
unstructured data.
Describe four basic data operations namely
selection, projection, union, and join.
And enumerate different types of data
constraints like type, value and
structural constraints.
You'll also be able to explain why
constraints are useful to specify
the semantics of data.
Now, regardless of whether the data is big
or small, one needs to know or determine
the characteristics of data before one can
manipulate or analyze them meaningfully.
Let's use a simple example,
suppose you have data is
a file of records with fields called first
name, last name and date of birth of
the employees in the company that this
file consists of records with fields,
and not for instance plain text,
gives us more insight
into the organization of the data in the
file and hence is part of the data model.
This aspect is called Structure.
Similarly, the consideration
that we can perform
data arithmetic with
the date of birth field, and
not with the first name field, is also
part of our understanding of data model.
These are called Operations.
Finally, we may know that in
this company no one's age
that is today's date minus the date
of birth, can't be less than 18.
So it gives us a way to detect records
with blatantly erroneous dates of birth.
In the following three videos,
we'll look at these three aspects
of data models more carefully.
We mentioned before that a data model
is characterized by the structure of
the data that it admits,
the operations on that structure, and
a way to specify constraints.
In this lesson,
we'll present a more detailed description
of a number of common data models.
We'll start with relational data.
It is one of the simplest and most
frequently used data models today, and
forms the basis of many other
traditional database management systems,
like MySQL, Oracle,
Teradata, and so forth.
So after this video you'll be able to
describe the structural components
of a relational data model.
Demonstrate which components
become a data model's schema.
Explain the purpose of primary and
foreign keys.
And describe Join and other operations.
The primary data structure for
a relational model is a table, like
the one shown here for a toy application.
But we need to be careful about relational
tables, which are also called relations.
This table actually
represents a set of tuples.
This is a relational tuple,
represented as a row in the table.
We were informally calling
this a record before.
But a relational tuple implies that unless
otherwise stated, the elements of it
like 203 or 204, Mary and
so forth, are atomic.
That is,
they represent one unit of information and
cannot be decomposed further.
We'll return to this issue
in the next few slides.
Thus, this is a relation of six tuples.
Remember, the definition of sets,
it's a collection of distinct
elements of the same type.
That means I cannot add
this tuple to the solution.
Because if I do,
it will be introducing a duplicate.
Now in practice, many systems will allow
duplicate tuples in a relation, but
mechanisms are provided to prevent
duplicate entries if the user so chooses.
So I cannot add it.
Here is another tuple I cannot add.
It has all the right
pieces of information, but
it's all in the wrong order.
So it is a tuple dissimilar with
the other six tuples in the relation.
Okay, so how does the system know
that this tuple is different?
This brings our attention to the very
first row that is the header of this table
painted in black.
This row is part of
the scheme of the table.
Lets look at it.
It tells us the name of the table,
in this case employee.
This also tells us the names of the six
columns called attributes of the relation.
And for each column,
it tells us the allowed data type, that
is the type constraint for each column.
Given this schema,
it should now be clear why the last
red row does not belong to this table.
The schema in a relational table
can also specify constraints,
shown in yellow in the third
line of the schema row.
It says that the minimum salary of
a person has to be greater than 25k.
Further, it states that every employee
must have a first and last name.
They cannot be left null,
that means without a value.
Why doesn't department or
title column have this constraint?
One answer can be that a newly
hired employee may not be assigned
a department or a title yet but
can still be an entry in the table.
However, the department column
has another constraint.
It restricts the possible values
that is the domain of the attribute
to only four possibilities.
HR, IT, research, and business.
Finally, the first says
that ID is a primary key.
This means it is unique for each employee.
And for
every employee knowing the primary key for
the employee will also uniquely know the
other five attributes of that employee.
You should now see that
a table with a primary key
logically implies that the table cannot
have a duplicate record because if we do,
it will violate the uniqueness constraint
associated with the primary key.
Let us introduce a new table containing
the salary history of employees.
The employees are identified
with the column EmpID, but
these are not new values that
this table happens to have.
They are the same IDs that are present in
the ID column of the employee's table,
presented earlier.
This is reflected in
the statement made on the right.
The term References means,
the values in this column can exist
only if the same values if you are in
employees the table being referenced,
also called the parent table.
So in the terminology of the relational
model, the EmpID column of EmpSalaries
table is called a foreign key that refers
to the primary key of the Employees table.
Note that EmpID is not a primary
key in this EmpSalaries table.
Because it is multiple to
post with the same EmpID
reflecting the salary of
the employee at different times.
You will remember join is a common
operation that we discussed before.
So here is an example of
a relational join performed
on the first three columns of employee and
EmpSalaries table.
Where employees.ID, and EmpSalaries.EmpID
columns are matched for equality.
The output table shows
all the columns involved.
The common column is represented once.
This form of join is
called a Natural Join.
It is important to understand that
join is one of the most expensive
that means time consuming and
space consuming operations.
As data becomes larger, and tables contain
hundreds of millions of tuples, the join
operation can easily become a bottleneck
in a larger analytic application.
So for analytical big data application
that needs joins, it's very important to
choose a suitable data management platform
that makes this operation efficient.
We will return to this
issue in module four.
We end this video on a practical note.
In many scientific and
business applications,
people start with CSV files,
manipulate them with the spreadsheet,
then migrate their relational system only
as an afterthought where the data becomes
too large to handle the spreadsheet.
While the spreadsheet offers
many useful features.
It does not conform and enforce many
principles of relational data models.
Consequently, a large amount of time
may be spent in cleaning up and
correcting data errors after
the migration actually happens.
Let me show a few examples from
a spreadsheet that has 125,000 rows and
over 100 columns.
The spreadsheet here lists terrorism
attacks gathered from news media.
So each row represents one attack.
This is a valuable piece of data for
people who study terrorism.
But we are going to look at it from
a relational data modelling viewpoint.
First, notice the column marked in green.
It lists two weapons used in
the attack separated by a semicolon.
Why is this really common?
It makes this column non-atomic.
It means that this column actually
has two different values.
In a relational design, this information
will be moved to another table
just like the multiple salaries of
employees were placed in a separate table.
Next, notice the column outlined in red.
It describes the amount of property
damaged by a possible terrorist attack.
In this column, the intended
legitimate values are unknown,
minor, major and catastrophic.
However, the value in the highlighted
part of the spreadsheet is minor and
then within bracket,
likely less than $1 million.
Which means a query like
find all attacks for
which the property damage is equal to
minor cannot be answered directly.
Instead, we need to perform
a substring search for
minor in the beginning of the description.
Which is doable, but
it's a more expensive operation.
This shows the columns of the spreadsheet.
So this is part of the schema of the data.
If you observe carefully you
will see a recurring pattern.
The designer of the data table determined
that there can be at most three types of
attacks within a single encounter and
represented with three separate columns.
Now in proper relational modeling,
one would say that there is a one to many
relationship between the attack and
the number of attack types.
In such a case, it would be more prudent
to place these attack type
columns in a separate table and
connect with the parent using a primary
key, foreign key relationship.
Here's another block,
with a similar pattern,
this time this is about the types and
subtypes of weapons used.
Now can you determine how you might
be able to reorganize this block?
We'll leave this as an exercise.
It can be said without a doubt,
and the Internet and
the worldwide web changed
everything in our lives.
The worldwide web is indeed the largest
information source there is today.
But what's the data model behind the web?
We will say that it is
the semi-structure data model.
So after going through this video you
will be able to distinguish between
the structured data model that we
talked about the last time and
semi-structured data model.
Further, you will recognize that the most
times the semi-structured data
refers to tree structured data.
And you can explain why tree
navigation operations are important for
formats like XML and JSON.
Let's a take a very simple web page.
Now this page does not have
a lot of content or stylization.
It doesn't even have links to other pages,
but
let's look at the corresponding HTML code.
This code is used by the browser so
that it can render the HTML, and
notice a few things in this data.
The entire data comes within the HTML and
slash HTML blocks.
And we similarly have a body begin and
end, a header begin and
end, a list begin and end and
a paragraph begin and end.
Everywhere here a block is
nested within a larger block.
The second item to notice is that
unlike a relational structure
there are multiple list items and
multiple paragraphs.
And any single document would
have a different number of them.
This means while the date object has
some structure it is more flexible.
So this is the hallmark office
semi structure date model.
Now XML, or
the extensible markup language, is another
well known standard to represent data.
You can think of XML as a generalization
of HTML where the elements, that's
the beginning and end markers within
the angular brackets, can be any string.
And not like the ones
allowed by standard HTML.
Let's see an example
from a biological case.
As you can see, there are two
elements called sample attribute.
They do structurally
different because they
have different numbers of sub
elements called the value.
Another interesting issue
about XML data processing
is that you can actually credit for
the structure elements.
For example, it is perfectly fine to ask,
what is the name of the element
which contains a sub-element whose
textual content is cell type?
As you can see, you'll get two results,
sample attribute.
An experimental factor because sample
attribute has a sub-element called
category and experimental factor
has a subelement called link and
each of these subelements
have the value celltape.
Now we cannot perform an operation
like this in a relational data model.
For example, we cannot say which relation
has a column with a value, John.
The same idea can also be seen in JSON or
the Java Script Object Notation, which
is a very popular format used for many
different data like Twitter and Facebook.
Consider the example here,
all of the format looks different.
We have a similar nested
structure varies that is lists
containing other lists which will contain
topples Which consists of p value ps.
So the key value pairs at atomic
property names and their values.
But one way to generalize about all these
different forms of semi structured data
is to model them as trees.
Let's go back to .xml.
The left side shows an XML document, and
the right side shows
the corresponding tree.
Since the top object of
the root element is document,
it is also the root of the tree.
Now under document we have
a report element with author and
date under it, and also a paper element
with title, author, and source under it.
The actual values,
like is the textual content of an element.
Since a text data item cannot
have any further components,
these text values are always
the leaves of the tree.
Now, modeling a document as a tree
has significant advantages.
A tree is a well-known data structure,
that allows what's called
a navigational access to data.
Imagine you are standing
on the note paper.
Now you can perform a getParent
operation and navigate the document.
Or you can perform a getChildren operation
to get to the title, author and source.
You can even perform a getSiblings
operation and get to the report.
You can also ask a textual query like
which strings have the substring data and
seek their root-to-node path to get to
the path from document to the text nodes.
You can possibly see how queries
can be evaluated on the tree,
now let us take the query.
Who is the author of XML query data model.
In one evaluation scheme we can navigate
up from the text note to title,
to paper, and then navigate down
to author and then to Don Robie.
Well how do we know that we have to get up
to paper before reversing the direction?
Well, paper is the least,
that's the lowest in the tree,
common ancestor of the author note,
and the XM query data model note.
We will come back to semi
structure data in a later module.
In this hands-on activity,
we will be looking at graph data in Gephi.
First, we will import data into Gephi and
then examine the properties of the graph.
Next, we will perform some statistical
operations on the graph data,
and then run some different
layout algorithms.
Let's begin.
We're not running Gephi in the Cloudera
virtual machine, on the Coursera website,
there will be a reading with instructions
on how to download, install, and
run Gephi on your native hardware,
instead of in the virtual machine.
Once you have Gephi started,
let's import the data into Gephi.
We'll go to File Import spreadsheet,
and in the CSV dialog,
we'll click the button with dot, dot, dot.
We'll choose diseasegraph.csv and
click open.
Make sure that as table says
edges table Click next.
And make sure Create
missing nodes is checked.
We'll click finish to import
the CSV file as a graph.
Gephi now shows the graph
in the center pane.
The little black circles
are the nodes of the graph and
the lines between them are the edges.
In the top right we can see that
there are 777 nodes and 998 edges.
Next let's perform some statistical
operations on this graph.
In the statistics pane we
can see average degree.
Let's compute the average degree
of the graph by clicking on Run.
This says that the average
degree is 2.569.
Let's close this,
let's compute the connected
components, we'll click on Run.
We'll leave this as a directed,
since the graph is directed.
Click OK.
It says that there
are 5 weakly connected components,
and 761 strongly connected components.
Let's close this.
Next, let's run some different
layout algorithms over the graph.
The bottom left,
we'll go to choose layout.
We'll choose Force Atlas and click run.
Click stop to stop the layout.
We can see that Gephi has grouped
strongly connected components together
in different clusters.
We can also see that they're parts
of the graph that are not connected.
Let's run a different layout algorithm.
The combo box,
choose Fruchterman Reingold, click run.
After it runs for a few seconds, click
stop, then click the magnifying glass,
center on graph, to see the whole graph.
In this layout,
all the nodes appear to be equally spaced.
But we can also see
the nodes with many edges.
In this hands on activity,
we will be working with Lucene,
a search engine that uses a vector
space model to index data.
First, we will open a terminal window and
change into the directory
containing the data and scripts.
Next, we will index some text
documents and query terms in Lucene.
After that we'll query
using weighted terms or
boosting to see how this
changes the rankings.
Finally, we will show the term
frequency-inverse document frequency or
TF-IDF in terms.
Let's begin.
First, let's open a terminal window by
clicking on the terminal icon at the top
of the tool bar.
Next, let's cd into the directory
containing the scripts and data.
We'll run cd
Downloads/big-data-2/vector/.
We'll run ls to see the scripts.
The data directory
contains three text files.
Each of these text files contains
news data about elections.
Let's index these files by
running runLuceneQuery.sh data.
Next, let's query Lucene for some terms in
these text documents and see the rankings.
Let's query for the term voters.
You can see the rankings and
scores that news1.csv ranked first,
news2.csv was the second ranking,
and the third was news3.csv.
Let's query for delegates.
For this term, we see that news2.csv
was first, and news1 was second, and
news3 did not contain the term at all.
Now, let's query for both terms,
voters and delegates.
In this result we see that
news2 was ranked first,
news1 was ranked second, and
news3 was ranked third.
Now lets use query term waiting or
boosting to increase
the relevance of voters.
I can do this by ensuring
voters carat 5 delegates.
The carat 5 notation is a syntax for
Lucene for boosting.
When we run this, we see that now,
news1 is ranked first,
news2 is ranked second,
and news3 is ranked third.
Notice this is different from the original
query with voters and delegates,
where news2 is ranked first and
news1 was ranked second.
Now let's look at the term frequency,
inverse document frequency or TF-IDF.
We'll enter q to quit this and
we'll run Lucene TF-IDF SH data.
Let's look at the TF-IDF for voters.
You can see that it ranked number 1 for
news1.
Second news 2 and news 3 is last.
Lets try delegates.
Here we see that news 2 had
a higher score than news 1,
and news 3 is not listed because
news 3 does not contain this term.
Hit q to quit.
So the next category of data we discuss
has the form of graphs or networks,
the most obvious example
being social networks.
Now speaking of social networks,
Tim Libzek created a social network
from the Lord of the Rings Trilogy.
This graph represents
the characters' allegiances,
that is who is faithful
to whom in the books.
So the nodes are characters and
other entities, like cities, and
the edges connecting pairs of
nodes represent allegiances.
So after this video, you'll be able to
identify graph data in practical problems
and describe path, neighborhood, and
connectivity operations in graphs.
But this specialization includes
a separate course in graph analytics
that provides a much more detailed
treatment on the subject.
Now what distinguishes a graph
from other data models
is that it bears two kinds of information.
One, properties and attributes of
entities and relationships, and
two, the connectivity structure that
constitutes the network itself.
One way to look at this data
is shown in the figure,
borrowed from the Apache Spark system.
In this representation,
the graph on the left is represented
by two tables on the right.
The vertex, or node table, gives IDs
to nodes and lists their properties.
The edge table has two parts.
The colored part represents
the properties of the edge,
whereas the white part contains just the
direction of the arrows in the network.
Thus, since there is a directed
edge going from node 3 to node 7,
there is a tupple 3,
7 in that part of the edge table.
Now this form of the graph model is
called the property graph model,
which we'll see many times in this
course and in the specialization.
Now representing connectivity information
gives graph data a new kind of
computing ability that's different from
other data models we have seen so far.
Even without looking at the properties
of the nodes and edges, one can get very
interesting information just by analyzing
or querying this connectivity structure.
Consider a social network with three
types of nodes, user, city, and
restaurant, and three types of edges,
friend, likes, and lives in.
The leftmost node, AG, represents me.
And I'm interested in finding a good
Italian restaurant in New York
that my friends, or their friends,
who also live in New York, like.
I shall possibly choose IT3 because
it has the highest number of
like edges coming into it from people
who have a lives in edge to New York.
And at the same time,
can be reached by following
the friend edges going out from me.
Now this shows a very important class
of operations and ground data, namely
traversal, that involves edge following
based on some sort of conditions.
A number of path operations
required some sort of optimization.
The simplest among these is the well known
shortest path query, which is applied to
node networks to find the best route from
a source location to a target location.
The second class of optimization
operations is required to find
an optimal path that must include
some user specified nodes, for
the operation has to determine the order
in which the nodes once we visited.
The classical application
is a trip planner,
where the user specifies the cities
she wishes to visit, and
the operation will optimize the criterion,
like the total distance covered.
The third category is a case where
the system must find the best possible
path in the network, given two or
more optimization criteria,
which cannot be satisfied simultaneously.
For example, if I want to travel
from my house to the airport
using the shortest distance, but also
minimizing the amount of highway travel,
the algorithm must find a best compromise.
This is called a pareto-optimality
problem on graphs.
The neighborhood of a node N in a graph is
a set of edges directly connected to it.
A K neighborhood of N is a collection
of edges between nodes that are,
at most, K steps away from N.
So going back to our mini social
network graph, Bob, Jill,
and Sarah are the first neighbors of AG,
while Max, Tim and
Pam belong to the second neighborhood and
not the first neighborhood of AG.
Finally, Jen is a third level neighbor.
An important class of analysis to perform
with neighborhoods is community finding.
A community and a social network can
be a very close group of friends.
So the graph shown in this
figure has four communities.
One can see in the figure that each
community has a higher density of edges
within the community and a lower density
across two different communities.
Finding densely connected parts of a graph
helps identify neighborhoods that
can be recognized as communities.
A more complex class of operations include
finding the best possible clusters,
which is another name for
communities in a graph, so
that any other grouping of nodes into
communities will be less effective.
Now, as graphs become bigger and denser,
these methods become harder to compute.
Thus, neighborhood-based
optimization operation present
significant scalability challenges.
If we inspect the neighborhood of
every node in a graph, sometimes,
we'll find neighborhoods that
are different from all others.
These neighborhoods are called anomalous.
Consider the following four graphs and
on the central red node.
The first graph is odd because
it's almost perfectly star shaped.
That is, the nodes that the red node
is connected to are almost unconnected
amongst themselves.
That's really odd because it
doesn't happen in reality much.
So it's an anomalous node.
The second figure shows
a neighborhood to which
a significantly large number of neighbors
has connected amongst themselves.
This makes the graph very cliquish,
where a clique refers to a neighborhood
where each node is connected to all other
neighborhood nodes in the neighborhood.
The third figure shows a neighborhood,
where some edges have an unusually
heavy weight compared to the others.
The fourth figure shows
a special case of the third,
where one edge is predominantly high
rate compared to all the other edges.
Connectedness is a fundamental
property of a graph.
In a connected graph,
each node is reachable from every
other node through some path.
If a graph is not connected, but there
are subgraphs of it, which are connected,
then these subgraphs are called connected
components of the original graph.
In the figure on the right,
there are four connected components.
A search gradient like
finding optimal paths
should be performed only within
each component and not across them.
For large graphs, there are several
new parallelized techniques for
the detection of connected components.
We will discuss a map
reduce based technique for
connected components in a later course.
We have discussed quite a few data models,
but
there are many other data models
that have been developed for
various purposes, and we really cannot
cover all of them in a single course.
We'll end these lectures on data models
with an example that may give you
an insight into a class of objects that
define in many different applications.
So after this video you'll be able
to describe how arrays can serve
as a data model, explain why images
can be modeled as vector arrays,
specify a set of operations on scalar and
vector arrays.
Now, we have all seen the arrays.
In the simplest case,
an array is a matrix like this.
Let's call this array A.
The top row in yellow,
gives the column numbers and
the left column, also in yellow,
gives the row numbers.
When we need to refer to a value
of the array as A(3, 2),
we mean the value of the cell in row 3 and
column 2.
This is called indexed structure,
where 3 and
2 are the row and column indices that are
necessary to get the value of a data item.
The area has two dimensions.
So hence there are two indexes.
If these were a three dimensional array,
we would have three indexes.
Now earlier,
we have seen that we can represent the two
dimensional array as a three column table.
One column for the row index,
one column for the column index, and
the last column for the value.
Thus a k dimensional array can be
represented as a relation with k
plus one columns.
The number of tuples in this
representation will be the product of
the size of the first dimension times the
size of the second dimension and so forth.
Then in this case,
the size is five in each dimension.
So there are 25 C column tuples in
a relation representing the array.
A more useful situation occurs
when the cells of an array have
a vectors as values.
As you can see in the 2D vector array
here, each cell has a three vector.
That is a vector with three elements.
Therefore, if we want to
receive a cell value and
treat it like before,
we'll get back the whole vector.
Now, this type of data
should look familiar to you,
because images often have a red,
green and blue channels per pixel.
In other words,
images of vector valued arrays where each
array cell has a three color vector.
We can also think of the array model
in the context of satellite images.
Where there are many more channels
depending on the range of wavelengths
each channel catches.
Let us consider the operations
on arrays of vectors.
Because it is a combination of two models,
one can create different combinations of
array operations, vector operations and
composite operations.
Here are some.
The dimension of the array here,
the first operation, is two.
If we pick up any dimension, say one.
The size of it is also two
because they're two elements,
zero and one in each dimension.
As we saw before, the value of the cell
(1,1) is a vector 16, 301, 74.
While the value of A11 component 2 is 74.
The length of the vector is a square root
of the sum of the elements of the vector.
So length of A11 would come to 310.375.
The distance function can be so
simple like the Euclidean distance
function between two vectors or
the cosine of an angle between them
as we saw in the previous lecture.
But it can also be something more complex,
based on the needs of the application.
Obviously one can also perform operations
like selection over indices so
we can ask which cells had
the zero value greater than 25.
Giving as the result zero one and
one zero.
You will experience some of these
operations in your hands on session.
Next, we'll look at a data model
that has been successfully used to
retrieve data from large
collections of text and images.
Let's stay with text for now.
Text is often thought of
as unstructured data.
Primarily because it doesn't really
have attributes and relationships.
Instead, it is a sequence of strings
punctuated by line and parent of breaks.
So one is to think of a different
way to find and analyze text data.
In this video, we'll describe that
finding text from a huge collection of
text data is a little different from
the data modules we have seen so far.
To find text,
we not only need the text data itself, but
we need a different structure that
is computed from the text data.
To create the structure,
we'll introduce the notion of the document
vector model which we call a vector model.
Further you will see
that finding a document
is not really an exact search problem.
Here, we'll give a query document and
ask the system to find all
documents that are similar to it.
After this video,
you'll be able to describe
how the similarity is computed and
how it is used to search documents.
Finally, you will see that search engines
use some form of vector models and
similarity search to locate text data.
And you will see that the same principle
can be use for finding similar images.
Let us describe the concept
of a document to an example.
So lets consider three types
of document shown here.
Now we'll create a matrix.
The rows of the matrix stand for
the documents and columns represent
the words in the documents.
We put the number of occurrences
of returning the document in
the appropriate cell of the matrix.
In this case, the count of each term
in each document happens to be one.
This is called the term frequency matrix.
So now that we have created
the term frequency matrix,
which we call tf for short.
We'll create a new vector called the
inverse document frequency for each term.
We'll explain why we need this
vector on the next slide.
First, let's see how it's computed.
The number of documents n here is 3.
The term new occurs
twice in the collection.
So the inverse document frequency or
IDF of the term new
is log to the base 2,
n divided by term count.
That is, log to the base 2,
3 divided by 2, which is 0.584.
We'll show the ideal score for
all six terms here.
Now some of you may wonder why we use
log to the base 2 instead of let's
say log to the base 10.
There is no deep scientific reason for it.
It's more of a convention in
many areas of Computer Science
when many important
numbers are powers of two.
In reality,
log to the base two of x is the same
number as log to the base ten of x
times log to the base two of ten.
The second number, that is log to
the base two of ten is a constant.
So the relative score of IDF does not
change regardless of the base we use.
Now let's understand this
number one more time.
The document frequency of a term is
the count of that term in the whole
collection divided by
the number of documents.
Here, we take the inverse of
the document frequency, so
that n, the number of documents,
is in the numerator.
Now before we continue, let's understand
the intuition behind the IDF vector.
Now suppose you have 100
random newspaper articles and
let's say 10 of them cover elections.
Which means all the others
cover all other subjects.
Now in this article, let's say we'll find
the term election 50 times in total.
How often do you think you'll find
the term is as in the verb is?
You can imagine that it will
occur in all hundred of them and
that too, multiple times.
We can safely assume that
the number of occurrences of is
will be 300 at the very least.
Thus the document frequency of is is six
times the document frequency of election.
But that doesn't sound right, does it?
Is is such a common word that it's
prevalence has a negative impact
on its informativeness.
So, now if you want to
compute the IDF of is and
election, the IDF of is will be far lower.
So, IDF acts like a penalty factor for
terms which are too widely used
to be considered informative.
Now that we have understood
that IDF is a penalty factor,
we will multiply the tf numbers through
the IDF numbers giving us this.
This is a column-wise multiplication
of the tf numbers with the IDF
numbers giving us what we
call the tf-idf matrix.
Therefore for each document, we have
a vector represented here as a row.
So that row represents the relative
importance of each term in the vocabulary.
Vocabulary means the collection of all
words that appear in this collection.
If the vocabulary has 3 million entries,
then this vector can get quite long.
Also, if the number of document
grows let's just say to 1 billion,
then it becomes a big data problem.
Now the last column after
each document of vector here
is the length of the document vector.
Which is really the square root of the sum
of squares of the individual term scores
as shown in the formula.
To perform a search in the vector space,
we write a query just like
we type terms in Google.
Here, the number of terms is three.
Out of which the term
new appears two times.
In fact, this is the maximum frequency
out of all terms in the query.
So we take the document vector of
the query and multiply each term
by the number of occurrences divided by
two which is the maximum term frequency.
Now in this case,
it gives us two non-zero terms.
0.584 and
0.292 for new and york.
Then we compute the length of
the query vector just like we did for
the document vectors
on the previous slide.
Next, we will compute the similarity
between the query vector and each document
with the idea that we'll measure how far
the query vector is from each document.
Now there are many similar functions
defined and used for different things.
A popular similarity measure
is the cosine function,
which measures the cosine function of
the angle between these two vectors.
The mathematical formula for
computing the function is given here.
The intuition is that if
the vectors are identical,
then the angle between them is zero.
And therefore,
the cosine function evaluates to one.
As the angle increases,
the value of the cosine function
decreases to make them more dissimilar.
The way to compute the function is to
multiply the corresponding elements of
the two vectors.
That is the first element
of one with the first
element of the second one and so forth.
And then sum of these products.
Here, the only contributing
terms are from new and
york because, these are the only two
non-zero terms in the query vector.
This sum is then divided by
the product of the document length and
the query length that we
have computed earlier.
Look at the result of the distance
function and you will notice that
the document 1 is much more similar
to the query than the other two.
So while similarity scoring and document
ranking process working effectively,
the method is a little cotton dry.
More often than not users would
like a little more control
over the ranking of terms.
One way of accomplishing this is to put
different weights on each query term.
And in this example, the query term
york has a default weight of one,
times has a weight of two.
And post has a weight of five
as specified by the user.
So relatively speaking,
york has a weight of 1 divided
by 1 + 5 + 2 is equal to 0.125.
Times has a weight of 0.25 and
post has a weight of 0.625.
Now the scoring method we showed
before will change a bit.
The query of vector and its length
were exactly as computed before.
However, now each term in the query
vector is further multiplied by these
relative weights.
In our case,
the term york now has a much higher rate.
So as expected, this will change
the ranking of the documents and
new york post will have the highest rank.
Now similarity search is often used for
images using a vector space model.
One can compute futures from images.
And one common feature
is a scatter histogram.
Consider the image here.
One can create the histogram of the red,
green and
blue channels where histogram is the count
of pixels having a certain density value.
This picture is mostly bright, so the
count of dark pixels is relatively small.
Now one can think of
histograms like a vector.
Very often the pixel values will
be bend before creating a vector.
The table shown is a feature vector
where the numbers for each row have been
normalized with the size of the image
to make the row sum equal to one.
Similar vectors can be computed of
the image texture, shapes of objects and
any other properties.
Thus making a vector space model
significant for unstructured data.
In our experience as educators
we have observed that
learners often make the assumption
that the format of the data
is the same as the logical model of the
data in the way that you operate on it.
The goal of this very
short lecture is to ensure
that we can clearly
distinguish between the two.
So, after watching this video you will be
able to explain the difference between
format, which is a serialized
representation of the data, as opposed to
data model which we have discussed
at length in the previous months.
Perhaps the simplest example of a data
format is a csv file, so here is
a snippet of a csv file from the global
terrorism database we discussed earlier.
We know that CSV or
common separative values means
that the term between two commas
is the value of an attribute.
But what is this value?
The common notion is that it's
a content of a single relation
where each line is a record
that's a tuple and
the iod value in the CSV corresponds
to the iod attribute as shown here.
Now that might very well be true but
let's look at a different example.
Let's say this snippet
here is my CSV file.
There is no difference between
the previous file and this one.
However, here is how I
like to see the data.
As you can see this is a graph,
and the data model is the same
although the format is still CSV.
This is the second hands on exercise for
sensor data.
In the first we looked at
static data in a text file.
In this one we'll be looking at
real-time streaming measurements.
First, we will open a terminal window, and
cd into the directory containing
the data and the scripts.
Next we'll connect to
the weather station and
look at the real-time
data as it streams in.
After that, we will look at the key to
remind ourselves what the fields mean.
And finally, we will plot the data
streaming from the weather station.
Let's begin.
First, open a terminal window,
by clicking on the terminal icon.
Top of the toolbar.
[NOISE] Let's run cd
Downloads/big-data-2/sensor.
You can run ls to see
the name of the scripts.
Let's run stream-data.py
to see the real-time data.
This shows us the real-time measurements
coming from the weather station.
By looking at the time stamps,
we can see that each measurement arrives
about one second after the previous one.
Additionally, we can see
that R1 comes fairly often,
whereas other measurements,
such as R2, are not as often.
We can open another terminal and
look at the key to remind ourselves
what these measurements mean.
The key is in wxt-520-format.txt.
We could run more
wxt-520-format.txt to view it.
If we go back to our live data,
we can see that the 19th
measurement here says Ta
was 22.5 degrees Celsius.
And look up here,
see that Ta is the air temperature.
The next measure we can see
that Dn was equal to 255D.
According to our key,
Dn is the wind direction minimum, and
the units are degrees.
We can also plot specific measurements
streaming live from the weather station.
Let's plot the wind speed average.
If we look at our key,
we see that the wind speed average is Sm.
So we can plot this by running
stream-plot-data.py sm.
This plots the data as the weather
station sends it to us.
If we look at the x-axis,
we can see that one measurement
comes in about every second.
We can plot other measurements by
choosing different fields from the key.
For example, we can plot the air pressure
by running stream-plot-data.py Pa.
Since Pa is the air pressure.
First thing we notice is that there's
only one measurement so far in the graph.
This means that the air pressure
measurements are not coming as
fast as the wind measurements.
In fact, we only got one.
In this hands-on activity,
we'll be looking at real time
data streaming from Twitter.
First, we'll open a terminal window and
cd into the directory containing
Python scripts to access this data.
Next, we'll look at the contents
of tweets streaming from Twitter
containing specific words.
Finally, we will plot the frequency
of these streaming tweets.
Let's begin.
First, click on the terminal
icon at the top of the toolbar.
Let cd into the directory containing
the python scripts to access the real time
data from Twitter.
We'll run CD downloads big-data-2 json.
We can run ls to see
the files in this directory.
The file auth should be created containing
your Twitter authentication information.
You could see the separate reading for
how to setup the Twitter app and
how to create this file.
Next, let's run the script live tweets
to view tweets in real time containing
a specific word.
Let's run LiveTweets.py president.
This will show the real time tweets
containing the word president.
[INAUDIBLE] Runs, in the first column,
you can see the time stamp of the tweet.
In the second column,
you can see the text.
When you're done, hit Ctrl + C.
Let's run LiveTweet again using
a different keyword that appear more
frequently.
Let's use the word time,
we'll run LiveTweet time
When we're done, hit Ctrl + C.
We can plot the frequency of these Tweets
by running the script plot Tweets.
Let's run plot, tweet, president to see
the frequency for the word president.
As this runs, we could see
the frequency changes over time.
I can see that the maximum was one.
And a few times,
there were just one tweet in that second.
When you're done looking at the graph,
click in the terminal window and
hit Enter.
Now, let's plot the frequency for
the word time.
Run PlotTweets.py time.
This plot shows that the word time appears
a lot more frequently than president.
We can see spikes in the frequency
of 40 and a maximum of around 65.
When you're done looking at the graph,
click on the terminal window and
press enter to quit.
With big data streaming from different
sources in varying formats, models, and
speeds it is no surprise that we
need to be able to ingest this data
into a fast and scalable storage system
that is flexible enough to serve many
current and future analytical processes.
This is when traditional data warehouses
with strict data models and data
formats don't fit the big data challenges
for streaming and batch applications.
The concept of a data lake was created in
response of these data big storage and
processing challenges.
After this video you
will be able to describe
how data lakes enable batch
processing of streaming data.
Explain the difference between
schema on write and schema on read.
Organize data streams and data lakes and
data warehouses on a spectrum of
big data management and storage.
What is a data lake?
Simply speaking, a data lake is
a part of a big data infrastructure
that many streams can flow into and
get stored for
processing in their original form.
We can think of it as a massive
storage depository with huge
processing power and ability to handle
a very large number of concurrence,
data management and analytical tasks.
In 2010,
the Pentaho Corporation's CTO James Dixon
defined a data link as follows.
If you think of a datamart as a store
of bottled water, cleansed and
packaged and structured for
easy consumption,
the data lake is a large body of
water in a more natural state.
The contents of the data lake stream
in from a source to fill the lake,
and various users of the lake can come
to examine it, dive in, or take samples.
A data lake works as follows.
The data gets loaded from its source,
stored in its native
format until it is needed
at which time the applications can freely
read the data and add structure to it.
This is what we call schema on read.
In a traditional data warehouse,
the data is loaded into the warehouse
after transforming it into a well
defined and structured format.
This is what we call schema on write.
Any application using the data needs to
know this format in order to retrieve and
use the data.
In this approach,
data is not loaded into the warehouse
unless there is a use for it.
However, schema on read
approach of data lakes ensures
all data is stored for
a potentially unknown use at a later time.
So how is a data lake
from a data warehouse?
A traditional data warehouse
stores data in a hierarchical file
system with a well-defined structure.
However, a data lake stores data as
flat files with a unique identifier.
This often gets referred to as
object storage in big data systems.
In data lakes each data is stored
as a binary large object or
BLOB and is assigned a unique identifier.
In addition, each data object is
tagged with a number of metadata tags.
The data can be searched
using these metadata tags
to retrieve it when there
is a need to access it.
From a users perspective,
metadata is stored is not a problem as
long as it is accessible when needed.
In Hadoop data architectures,
data is loaded into HDFS and processed
using the appropriate data management and
analytical systems on commodity clusters.
The selection of the tools is based on the
nature of the problem being solved, and
the data format being accessed.
We will talk more about
the processing of data streams and
data lakes in the next course
in this specialization.
To summarize a data lake is
a storage architecture for
big data collection and processing.
It enables collection of
all data suitable for
analysis today and
potentially in the future.
Regardless of the data source,
structure, and
format it supports storage of data and
transforms it only when it is needed.
A data lake ideally supports all parts
of the user base to benefit from
this architecture, including business,
storage, analytics and computing experts.
Finally, And perhaps most importantly,
data lakes are infrastructure components
within a big data architecture
that can evolve over time based
on application-specific needs.
What is a data stream?
After this video,
you will be able to summarize the key
characteristics of a data stream.
Identify the requirements of
streaming data systems, and
recognize the data streams
you use in your life.
When we talked about how
big data is generated and
the characteristics of the big
data using sound waves.
One of the challenges we mentioned was the
velocity of data coming in varying rates.
For some applications this
presents the need to process data
as it is generated, or
in other words, as it streams.
We call these types of applications
Streaming Data Processing Applications.
This terminology refers to a constant
stream of data flowing from a source,
for example data from a sensory machine or
data from social media.
An example application would be making
data-driven marketing decisions in
real time.
Through the use of data from
real-time sales trends,
social media analysis,
and sales distributions.
Another example for streaming data
processing is monitoring of industrial or
farming machinery in real time.
For monitoring and
detection of potential system failures.
In fact, any sensor network or
internet of things environment
controlled by another entity,
or set of entities falls
under this category.
For example,
as you have seen in an earlier video,
FlightStats is an application.
That processes about 60
million weekly flight events
that come into their
data acquisition system.
And turns it into real-time
intelligence for airlines and
millions of travelers
around the world daily.
So, how then do we define a data stream?
A stream is defined as
a possibly unbounded sequence of
data items or records.
That may or may not be related to,
or correlated with each other.
Each data is generally timestamped and
in some cases geo-tagged.
As you have seen in our examples,
the data can stream from many sources.
Including instruments, and
many internet of things application areas,
computer programs, websites,
or social media posts.
Streaming data sometimes get
referred to as event data as
each data item is treated as an individual
event in a synchronized sequence.
Streams pose very difficult challenges for
conventional data
management architectures.
Which are built primarily on the concept
of persistence, static data collections.
Due to the fact that most often we
have only one chance to look at and
process streaming data
before more gets piled on.
Streaming data management systems cannot
be separated from real-time processing
of data.
Managing and
processing data in motion is a typical
capability of streaming data systems.
However, the sheer size, variety and
velocity of big data adds further
challenges to these systems.
Such systems are designed to manage
relatively simple computations.
Such as one record at a time or
a set of objects in a short time
window of the most recent data.
The computations are done
in near-real-time,
sometimes in memory, and
as independent computations.
The processing components
often subscribe to a system,
or a stream source, non-interactively.
This means they sent nothing
back to the source, nor
did they establish
interaction with the source.
The concept of dynamic steering involves
dynamically changing the next steps or
direction of an application
through a continuous
computational process using streaming.
Dynamic steering is often a part of
streaming data management and processing.
A self-driving car is a perfect example
of a dynamic steering application.
But all streaming data applications
fall into this category.
Such as the online gaming example we
discussed earlier in this course.
Amazon Kinesis an other open-source Apache
projects like Storm, Flink,
Spark Streaming, and
Samza are examples of big
data streaming systems.
Many other companies also
provide streaming systems for
big data that are frequently
updated in response
to the rapidly changing
nature of these technologies.
As a summary, dynamic near-real-time
streaming data management,
processing, and steering is an important
part of today's big data applications.
Next, we will look at some
of the challenges for
streaming data management and processing.
Now that we have seen what
streaming data means,
let’s look at what makes streaming data
different and what some management and
processing challenges for
streaming data are.
After this video you will
be able to compare and
contrast data in motion and data at rest.
Differentiate between streaming and
batch data processing.
And list management and
processing challenges for streaming data.
We often hear the terms data addressed and
data in motion,
when talking about big data management.
Data-at-rest refers to mostly
static data collected from one or
more data sources, and the analysis
happens after the data is collected.
The term data-in-motion refers to a mode
although similar data
collection methods apply,
the data gets analyzed at the same
time it is being generated.
Just like the sensor data processing
in a plane or a self-driving car.
Analysis of data addressed is called
batch or static processing and
the analysis of streaming data
is called stream processing.
The run time and memory usage of most
algorithms that process static data,
is usually dependent on the data size, and
this size can easily be calculated
from files or databases.
A key property, of streaming data
processing is the size of the data
is unbounded and this changes the types
of algorithms that can be used.
Algorithms that require iterating or
looping over the whole data set are not
possible since with stream data,
you never get to the end.
The modeling and management of streaming
data should enable computations on
one data element or a small window
of group of recent data elements.
These computations can update metrics,
monitor and
plot statistics on the streaming data.
Or apply analysis techniques
to the streaming data
to learn about the dynamics of
the system as a time series.
Since computations need to
be completed in real time,
the analysis tasks processing
streaming data should be quicker or
not much longer than
the streaming rate of the data.
Which we define by it's velocity.
In most streaming systems,
the management, and
processing system subscribe to
the data source, but doesn't
send anything back to the stream source
in terms of feedback or interactions.
These requirements for streaming data
processing are quite different than batch
processing where the analytical steps
have access to often, all data and
can take more time to complete a complex
analytical task with less pressure
on the completion time of individual
data management and processing tasks.
Most organizations today
use a hybrid architecture.
Sometimes get referred to as
the lambda architecture for
processing streaming and
back jobs at the same time.
In these systems, streaming wheel over
the real-time data is managed and
kept until those data elements are pushed
to a batch system and become available
to access and process as batch data.
In such systems, a stream storage
layer is used to enable fast
trees of streams and
ensure data ordering and consistency.
And a processing layer for
data is used to retrieve data from
the storage layer to analyze it and
most probably little bit to a batch
data stream and notify the streaming
storage that the data set does no
longer need to be in streaming storage.
The big data challenges we discussed
were scalability, data replication,
and durability, and fault tolerance arise
in this type of data very significantly.
Among many there are two main
challenges that needs to be overcome
to avoid data loss, and
enable real time analytical tasks.
One challenge in streaming data
process is that the size and
frequency of the mean data can
significantly change over time.
These changes can be unpredictable and
may be driven by human behavior.
For example, streaming data found on
social networks such as Facebook and
Twitter can increase in
volume during holidays,
sports matches, or major news events.
These changes can be periodic and occur,
for example, in the evenings or weekends.
For example, people may post messages
on Facebook more in the evening
instead of during the day working hours.
Streaming data changes may also
be unpredictable and sporadic.
There can be an increase in data size and
frequency during during major events,
sporting matches and things like that.
Other changes include dropping or
missing data or even no data
when there are network problems or device
generating the data has hardware problems.
As an example of streaming
data fluctuation,
consider the number of Tweets per second.
On average,
there are 6,000 tweets sent every second.
However, in August 2013,
the world record was
set when over 144,000 tweets
were sent in a second.
That's a factor of 24 increase.
At the end of this lesson we will ask
you to focus on Twitter streams for
trending topics and any other topic.
You will notice how the rates
of Tweets streaming
changes between different times and
different topics.
To summarize, streaming data must be
handled differently than static data.
Unlike static data, where you can
determine the size, streaming data is
continually generated, and
you can not process it all at once.
Streaming data can unpredictably
change in both size and frequency.
This can be due to human behavior.
Finally, algorithms for
processing streaming data must
be relatively fast and simple.
Since you don't know when
the next data arrives.
In a previous lecture,
we said that new interesting solutions are
emerging in the big data product space.
While these solutions do not have
the full fledged power of a DBMS,
they offer novel feature combinations that
suit some application space just right.
One of these products is Aerospike,
which calls itself a distributed
NoSQL database and
key value store, and
goes on to say that it is architected for
the performance needs of
today's web scale applications.
The diagram here is from
an Aerospike whitepaper.
It shows how Aerospike relates to
the ecosystem for which it is designed.
The top layer shows several applications
for real time consumer facing systems,
such as travel recommendation systems,
pricing engines used for
stock market applications,
real time decision systems that
analyze data to figure out whether
an investment should be done and so forth.
Now, all of these systems
have the common need
that large amounts of data should be
accessible to them at any point of time.
The Aerospike system can interoperate
with Hadoop-based systems, so
Spark, or a Legacy database, or
even a real time data source.
It can exchange large volumes
of data with any such source and
serve fast lookups and
queries to the applications above.
Now that translates to a very
high availability robust and
strong consistency needs.
The figure here presents a high level
architecture diagram of Aerospike.
The first item to notice here
is what they call a fast bat,
which essentially refers to
the left side of the architecture.
The client system processes transactions.
That is data that are primarily managed in
a primary index that is a key value store.
This index stays in memory for
operational purposes.
However, the server also interacts with
the storage layer for persistence.
The storage layer uses three
kinds of storage systems,
in memory with a dynamic RAM or
DRAM, a regular spinning disk,
and flash/SSD, which is solid state device
for fast loading of data when needed.
In fact the Aerospike system
has optimized its performance with
characteristics of an SSD in mind.
For those of who are not sure
what an SSD is, you can think of
an SSD as a kind of storage device
whose random read performance is much
faster than speeding hard disk and the
write performance is just a little slower.
One vendor recently advertised its SSD
has sequence share read speeds of up to
2,500 MBPS and the sequential write
speeds as fast as 1,500 MBPS.
Now why is this important
in a big data discussion?
When we speak of scalability, grade
efficiency, fast transactions, and so
forth, we often do not mention
that part of the performance
guarantee is governed by the combination
of hardware and software.
So the ability to offer more efficient
persistent storage with fast IO
implies that while a significant amount
of information can be stored on disk,
it can be done without compromising
the overall system performance for
an environment that
needs fast data loading.
The second point of uniqueness
is a secondary index there.
Aerospike built secondary index
fields that are non-primary keys.
A non-primary key is a key attribute
that makes a tuple unique,
but it has not been
chosen as a primary key.
In Aerospike, secondary indices
are stored in main memory.
They are built on every node in a cluster
and co-located with the primary index.
Each secondary index entry
contains references to records,
which are local to the node.
As a key value store,
Aerospike uses standard database like
scalar types like integer, string, and
so forth, as well as lists like Reddis.
The map type is similar to the hashtag of
Reddis and contains attribute value pairs.
Since it is focused on real time web
application, it supports geospatial data,
like places with latitude and
longitude values or regency polygons.
This allows them to perform KV store
operations, for example, like is
the location of this in La Jolla,
which is a point-in-polygon query.
Or a distance query, like find hotels
within three miles of my location.
KV queries are constructed
programmatically.
Now interestingly, Aerospike also provides
a more declarative language called AQL.
AQL looks very similar to SQL,
the Standard Query Language for
relational databases.
A query like select name and
age from user star profiles projects
out the name and age values
from the profile's record set that
belongs to the ding space called users.
The language also allows
advocate functions, like sum and
average, and other user defined functions,
which the system may evaluate through
a map produced time operation.
We mentioned earlier that while most
medium assists today offer base
guarantees, Aerospike, despite being
a distributor information system,
actually offers ACID guarantees.
This is accomplished using
a number of techniques.
We'll consider a few of them to give you
a flavor of the mechanisms that current
systems use to balance between
large scale data management and
transaction management in a cluster
where nodes can join or leave.
You may recall that consistency
means two different things,
one is to ensure that all constraints,
like domain constraints, are satisfied.
The second meaning is applied
to distributor systems and
ensures all copies of a data
item in a cluster are in sync.
For operations and
single keys with replication and
secondary indices,
Aerospike provides immediate consistency
using synchronous writes to
replicas within the cluster.
Synchronous write means the write
process will be considered
successful only if
the replica is all subdated.
No other write is allowed on the record
while the object of replica is pending.
So what happens if there is an increase
in the number of write operations due to
an increase in ingestion rate?
In Aerospike, it is possible to relax
this immediate consistency condition
by bypassing some of
the consistency checks.
But if this is done, eventual
consistency will still be enforced.
Durability is achieved by storing data
in the flash SSD on every node and
performing direct reads from the flash.
Now durability is also maintained through
the process of replication because we have
multiple copies of data.
So even if one node fails, the latest copy
of the last data is available from one or
more replica nodes in the same cluster,
as well as in nodes residing
in remote clusters.
But does that just
contradict the CAP theorem?
The CAP theorem holds when
the network is partitioned.
That means when nodes in
different parts of the network
have different data content.
Aerospike reduces and tries to completely
eliminate the situation by making
sure that the master knows exactly
where all the other nodes are.
And the replication is
happening properly even when
the new nodes are joining the network.
In the previous modules, we talked
about data variety and streaming data.
In this module, we'll focus on a central
issue in large scale data processing and
management and that is when should
we use Hadoop or Yarn style system?
And when should we use a database system
that can perform parallel operations?
And then we'll explore how the state
of the art big data management systems
address these issues of volume and
variety.
We start with the problem
of high volume data and
two contrasting approaches for
handling them.
So after this video, you'll be able to
explain the various advantages of
using a DBMS over a file system.
Specify the differences between
parallel and distributed DBMS.
And briefly describe
a MapReduce-style DBMS and
its relationship with the current DBMSs.
In the early days,
when database systems weren't around or
just came in, databases were designed
as a set of application programs.
They were written to handle data that
resided in files in a file system.
However, soon this
approach led to problems.
First, there are multiple file formats.
And often, there was a duplication
of information in different files.
Or the files simply had inconsistent
information that was very hard to
determine, especially when the data was
large and the file content was complex.
Secondly, there wasn't
a uniform way to access data.
Each data access task, like finding
employees in a department sorted by their
salary versus finding
employees in all departments
sorted by their start date needed to
be written as a separate program.
So people ended up writing
different programs for
data access, as well as data update.
A third problem was rooted to
the enforcement of constraints,
often called integrity constraints.
For example, to say something like every
employee has exactly one job title.
One had arrived that condition,
as part of an application program called.
So if you want to change the constraint,
you need to look for
the programs where such
a rule is hard coded.
The fourth problem has to
do with system failures.
Supposed Joe, an employee becomes
the leader of a group and moves in to
the office of the old leader, Ben who has
now become the director of the division.
So we update Joe's details and
move on to update, Ben's new office for
the system crashes.
So the files are incompletely updated and
there is no way to go back,
and start all over.
The term atomicity means that all of
the changes that we need to do for
these promotions must happen altogether,
as a single unit.
They should either fully go through or
not go through at all.
This atomicity is very difficult to handle
when the data reside in one or more files.
So, a prime reason for the transition
to a DBMS is to alleviate these and
other difficulties.
If we look at the current DBMS,
especially relational DBMS,
we will notice a number of advantages.
DBMSs offer query languages,
which are declarative.
Declarative means that we
state what we want to retrieve
without telling the DBMS
how exactly to retrieve it.
In a relational DBMS, we can say,
find the average set of salary of
employees in the R&D division for
every job title and sort from high to low.
We don't have to tell the system how
to group these records by job title or
how to extract just the salary field.
A typical user of a DBMS who issues
queries does not worry about how
the relations are structured or whether
they are located in the same machine,
or spread across five machines.
The goal of data independence is to
isolate the users from the record
layout so long as the logical
definition of the data,
which means the tables and
their attributes are clearly specified.
Now most importantly, relational DBMSs
have developed a very mature and
continually improving methodology of
how to answer a query efficiently,
even when there are a large
number of cables and
the number of records
exceeds hundreds of millions.
From a 2009 account,
EB uses the tera data system with
72 machines to manage approximately
2.4 terabytes of relational data.
These systems have built powerful
data structures, algorithms and
sound principles to determine how
a specific array should be onset
efficiently despite the size of the data
and the complexity of the tables.
Now with any system,
bad things can happen.
Systems fail in the middle
of an operation.
Malicious processes try to get
unauthorized access to data.
One large can often underappreciated
aspect of a DBMS is
the implementation of transaction
safety and failure recovery.
Now, recall our discussion of atomicity.
In databases, a single logical operation
on the data is called a transaction.
For example, a transfer of funds
from one bank account to another,
even involving multiple changes
like debiting one account and
crediting another is a single transaction.
Now, atomicity is one of the four
properties that a transaction should
provide.
The four properties,
collectively called ACID are atomicity,
consistency, isolation and durability.
Consistency means any data
written to the database must be
valid according to all defined
rules including constrains.
The durability property ensures that
once a transaction has been committed,
it will remain so, even in the event
of power loss, crashes or errors.
The isolation property comes
in the context of concurrency,
which refers to multiple people
updating a database simultaneously.
To understand concurrency, think of
an airline or a railway reservation system
where hundreds and thousands of
people are buying, cancelling and
changing their reservations and
tickets all at the same time.
The DBMS must be sure that
a ticket should no be sold twice.
Or if one person is in the middle
of buying the last ticket,
another person does not see
that ticket as available.
These are guaranteed by
the isolation property that says,
not withstanding the number of people
accessing the system at the same time.
The transactions must happen as if they're
done serially, that is one after another.
Providing these capabilities is
an important part of the M in DBMS.
So next, we consider how traditional
databases handle large data volumes.
The classical way in which DBMSs
have handled the issue of large
volumes is by created parallel and
distributed databases.
In a parallel database, for
example, parallel Oracle,
parallel DB2 or post SQL XE.
The tables are spread across multiple
machines and operations like selection,
and join use parallel algorithms
to be more efficient.
These systems also allow a user
to create a replication.
That is multiple copies of tables.
Thus, introducing data redundancy, so
that failure on replica can be
compensated for by using another.
Further, it replicates in
sync with each other and
a query can result into
any of the replicates.
This increases the number of simultaneous
that is conquer into queries
that can be handled by the system.
In contrast, a distributed DBMS, which
we'll not discuss in detail in this course
is a network of independently running
DBMSs that communicate with each other.
In this case, one component knows some
part of the schema of it is neighboring
DBMS and can pass a query or part of
a query to the neighbor when needed.
So the important takeaway issue here is,
are all of these facilities
offered by a DBMS important for
the big data application that
you are planning to build?
And the answer in many
cases can be negative.
However, if these issues are important,
then the database management
systems may offer a viable option for
a big data application.
Now, let's take a little more time to
address an issue that's often discussed in
the big data word.
The question is if DBMSs are so powerful,
why do we see the emergence
of MapReduce-style Systems?
Unfortunately, the answer to this
question is not straightforward.
For a long while now, DBMSs have
effectively used parallelism, specifically
parallel databases in addition to
replication would also create partitions.
So that different parts of a logical
table can physically reside on different
machines,, then different parts of a query
can access the partitions in parallel and
speed up creative performance.
Now these algorithms not only improve
the operating efficiency, but
simultaneously optimize algorithms to
take into account the communication cost.
That is the time needed to
exchange data between machines.
However, classical parallel DBMSs did
not take into account machine failure.
And in contrast, MapReduce was
originally developed not for storage and
retrieval, but for distributive
processing of large amounts of data.
Specifically, its goal was to support
complex custom computations that could
be performed efficiently on many machines.
So in a MapReduce or MR setting,
the number of machines
could go up to thousands.
Now since MR implementations were
done over Hadoop file systems,
issues like node failure were
automatically accounted for.
So MR effectively used in complex
applications like data mining or
data clustering, and these algorithms
are often very complex, and
typically require problem
specific techniques.
Very often,
these algorithms have multiple stages.
That is the output from one processing
stage is the input to the next.
It is difficult to develop these
multistage algorithms in a standard
relational system.
But since these were genetic operations,
many of them were designed to work
with unstructured data like text and
nonstandard custom data formats.
Now, it's now amply clear that this
mixture of data management requirements
and data processing analysis requirements
have created an interesting tension in
the data management world.
Just look at a few of
these tension points.
Now, DBMSs perform storage and
retrieval operations very efficiently.
But first,
the data must be loaded into the DBMS.
So, how much time does loading take?
In one study,
scientists use two CVS files.
One had 92 attributes with
about 165 million tuples for
a total size of 85 gigabytes.
And the other had 227 attributes
with 5 million tuples for
a total size of 5 gigabytes.
The time to load and index this data in
MySQL and PostgreSQL, took 15 hours each.
In a commercial database running on
three machines, it took two hours.
Now there are applications like
the quantities in the case we discussed
earlier where this kind of loading
time is simply not acceptable,
because the analysis on
the data must be performed
within a given time limit
after it's arrival.
A second problem faced by
some application is that for
them, the DBMSs offer
too much functionality.
For example, think of an application
that only looks at the price of an item
if you provide it with a product name or
product code.
The number of products it serves
is let's say, 250 million.
This lookup operation happens
only on a single table and
does not mean anything
more complex like a join.
Further, consider that while there
are several hundred thousand customers
who access this data,
none of them really update the tables.
So, do we need a full function DBMS for
this read-only application?
Or can we get a simpler solution which
can use a cluster of machines, but
does not provide all the wonderful
guarantees that a DBMS provides?
At the other end of the spectrum,
there is an emerging class of optimization
that meets all the nice transactional
guarantees that a DBMS provides.
And at the same time, meets the support
for efficient analytical operations.
These are often required for
systems like Real-Time Decision Support.
That will accept real-time data like
customer purchases on a newly released
product will perform some
statistical analysis, so
that it can determine buying trends.
And then decide whether in real-time,
a discount can be offered
to this customer now.
It turns out that the combination
of traditional requirements and
new requirements is leading
to new capabilities, and
products in the big data
management technology.
On the one hand, DBMS technologies
are creating new techniques that make
use of MapReduce-style data processing.
Many of them are being
developed to run on HDFS and
take advantage of his data
replication capabilities.
More strikingly, DBMSs are beginning
to have a side door for
a user to perform and
MR-style operation on HDFS files and
exchange data between the Hadoop
subsystem and the DBMS.
Thus, giving the user the flexibility
to use both forms of data processing.
It has now been recognized
that a simple map and
reduce operations are not sufficient for
many data operations leading to
a significant expansion in the number
of operations in the MR ecosystems.
For example,
Spark has several kinds of join and
data grouping operations in
addition to map and reduce.
Sound DBMSs are making use of large
distributed memory management
operations to accept streaming data.
These systems are designed with the idea
that the analysis they need to perform on
the data are known before.
And as new data records arrive,
they keep a record of the data
in the memory long enough to finish
the computation needed on that record.
And finally, computer scientists and
data scientists are working
towards new solutions
where large scale distributed algorithms
are beginning to emerge to solve different
kinds of analytics problems like
finding dense regions of a graph.
These algorithms use
a MR-style computing and
are becoming a part of a new
generation of DBMS products
that invoke these algorithms
from inside the database system.
In the next video, we'll take a look at
some of the modern day data management
systems that have some
of these capabilities.
As we mentioned in the last lesson, there
is no single irricuteous solution for
big data problems.
So in this lesson,
our goal will be to explore some existing
solutions in a little more depth.
So after this lesson, you'll be able to.
Explain the at least five
desirable characteristics of
a Big Data Management System,
explain the differences between acid and
base, and
list examples of BDMSs and describe some
of their similarities and differences.
So we start from high level, suppose there
were an ideal big data management system.
What capabilities or
features should such a system have?
Professor Michael Carey of
the University of California Irvine
has described a number of characteristics.
We'll go through them and
use them as an idealistic yardstick
against which we compare
existing solutions.
First, the ideal BDMS would allow for
a semi-structured data model.
Now that does not mean it will only
support a specific format like XML.
The operative word here is flexible.
The flexibility can take many forms,
one of which Is the degree to which
schemas should be supported by the system.
In a perfect world, it should support
a completely traditional application which
requires the development of a schema.
At the same time, it should also support
applications which require no schema,
because the data can vary in terms
of its attributes and relationships.
A different axis of flexibility
is in the data types it supports.
For example, it should support
operations on text and documents.
It should also permit social media and
other data that have a time component and
need temporal operations, like before,
after, during, and so on.
Similarly, it should
allow spacial data and
allow operations like find all data
within a five mile radius of a landmark.
As we saw in a previous lesson,
a big advantage of a DBMS is that
is provides a query language.
There is a notion that query languages
present a steep learning curve for
data science people with no
background in computer science.
However, to effectively
manage large volumes of data,
it's often more convenient
to use a query language and
let the query processor automatically
determine optimal ways to receive data.
Now this query language may or
may not look like SQL,
which is the standard query language used
by the modern relational systems, but
it should at least be equally powerful.
Now this is not an unreasonable feature
given that most DBMS vendors offer their
own extension of SQL Of course it's not
enough to just have a good query language.
Today's big data systems must
have a parallel query engine
which will run on multiple machines.
The machines can be connected to
a shared nothing architecture, or
shared memory architecture,
or a shared cluster.
The shared nothing means two machines
do not share a disk or memory.
But this is a critical requirement for
any BDMS regardless of how complete
the supported query languages is for
efficiency sake Continuing with our list,
the next
capability of a BDMS is often
not emphasized as much as it should be.
Some applications working on top
of a BDMS will issue queries
which will only have a few conditions and
a few small objects to return.
But some applications, especially those
generated by other software tools or
machine learning algorithms can
have many many conditions and
can return many large objects.
In my own work, we have seen how internet
bots can blast an information system
with really large queries that
can potentially choke the system.
But that should not happen in a BDMS.
Now, we discussed streaming
data in a previous lesson.
In many cases,
a BDMS will have both streaming data,
which adds to the volume,
as well as to the large data that
need to be combined with the streaming
data to solve a problem.
An example would be to combine
streaming data from weather stations
with historical data to make
better predictions for wild fire.
We have discussed the definition,
significance and
importance of scalability before.
However, what a BDMS needs to guarantee
that it is designed to operate over a
cluster, possibly a cluster of hundred or
thousand of machines and
that it knows how to handle a failure.
Further the system should be able
to handling new machines joining or
existing machines leaving the cluster.
Finally, our BDMS must have
data management capabilities.
It should be easy to install, restart and
configure, provide high availability and
make operational management as
simple as possible even when
a BDMS is declined across data centers
that are possibly geographically apart
In a prior module, we discussed
the ACID properties of transactions and
said that BDMSs guarantee them.
For big data systems,
there is too much data and
too many updates from too many users.
So the effort to maintain ACID properties
May lead to a significant
slowdown of the system.
Now, this lead to the idea, that while
the ACID properties are still desirable,
it might be more practical to relax
the ACID conditions and replace them
with what's called the BASE properties,
beginning with Basic availability.
This states that the system
does guarantee the availability
of data in the following sense.
If you make a request,
there will be a response to that request.
But, the response could still
be failure to obtain data or
the data isn't Inconsistent state or
changing state.
Well this is not unusual because
it's much like waiting for
a check to clear a bank account.
Second, there is a soft state.
Which means the state of the system
is very likely to change over time.
So even during times without input,
there may be changes going on through
the system due to eventual consistency.
Thus the state of
the system is always soft.
And finally there's eventual consistency.
This means that the system will
eventually become consistent
once it stops receiving input.
When it stops receiving input,
the data will propagate to everywhere
that it should sooner or later go to but
in reality the system will
continue to receive input.
And it's not checking the consistency
of every transaction at every moment
because there's still lots
of transactions to process.
So, if you make a new Facebook post,
your friend in Zambia, who is supposed
to see your update but is served by a very
different data center in a different
geographic region, will certainly
see it but may not see right away.
Now for those of you who have a bit
of computer science background,
we just want to mention in passing that
there is actually some theoretical results
behind this relaxation.
The result comes from what's
called the CAP Theorem.
Also named Bauer's theorem after
the computer scientist Eric Bauer.
He states, that it is impossible for
a distributed computer system
to simultaneously provide all
three of the following guarantees.
Consistency.
It means all nodes see the
same data at any time.
Availability, which is a guarantee
that every request receives a response
about whether it succeeded or failed.
And Partition Tolerance.
Which means the system
continues to operate
despite arbitrary partitioning
due to network failures.
Now, most of the big data systems
available today will adhere
to these BASE properties,
although several modern systems
do offer the stricter ACID properties,
or at least several of them.
Now given the idealistic background
of what is desirable and
achievable in a big data system,
today's marketplace for
big data related products
looks somewhat like this.
Now this is Matt Turk's depiction of big
data products from a couple of years back.
You would notice that the products
are grouped into categories, like no SQL,
massively parallel databases, analytic
systems, real time systems, and so forth.
In this lesson, we'll do a quick
tour through a few of these products
from different areas of this landscape.
In each case our goal will to be assess
what aspects of our ideal BDMS they cover,
and whether they have obvious limitations.
Now we will not cover all features
of every system, but will highlight
those aspects of the system that
are relevant to our discussion on BDMS.
The first up in our rapid tour
of modern systems is Redis.
Redis calls itself an in-memory
data structure store.
In simple terms, Redis is not a full blown
DBMS, in the sense we discussed earlier.
It can persist data on disks, and
does so to save its state, but
it's intended use is to optimally
use memory and memory based methods
to make a number of common data
structures very fast for lots of users.
Here is a list of data
structures that Redis supports.
A good way to think about them is
to think of a data lookup problem.
Now, in the simplest case,
a lookup needs a key value pair
where the key is a string and
the value is also a string.
So for a lookup we provide the key and
get back the value.
Simple, right?
Let's see.
I'm sure you've seen captures like this.
These are small images used by websites
to ensure that the user is a human and
not a robot.
The images presented to the user,
who is supposed to write the text he or
she sees in the image, into a text box.
Upon success, the user is let in.
To implement this,
one obviously needs a key value stored,
where the key is the idea of the image.
And the value is the desired text.
Now what if we wanted to use
the image itself as the key,
instead of an ID number that
you generate separately?
The content of the image,
which let's say is a .jpg file,
can be thought of as a binary string.
But can it serve as a key then?
According to the Redis specification,
it can.
The Redis string can be binary and
can have a size of up to 512 megabytes,
although its internal limit is higher.
So, small images like this can indeed
be used as binary string keys.
In some application scenarios,
keys may have an internal structure.
For example,
product codes may have product family,
manufacturing batch, and the actual
product ID strung together into one ID.
The example shown here is a typical
Twitter style key to store the response
to comment one, two, three, four.
How long do we want to
keep the comment around,
this is a standard big data issue
when it comes to streaming data
whose data values have limited
utility beyond the certain period.
One typically would not look for
this response possibly three
months after the conversation.
One would certainly not like to keep
such a value in memory for a long time.
Because the memory is being used as
a cache for rapid access to current data.
In fact Redis has the ability
to delete an expired key and
can be made to call a function
to generate a new key.
An interesting side
benefits to structured keys
that it can encode
a hierarchy to the structure.
In the example,
we show keys that represent
increasingly finer subgroups of users.
With this structure,
a lookup on user.commercial.entertainment
will also retrieve values
from user.commercial.entertainment.movie
industry.
A slightly more complex case occurs
when the value is not atomic,
but a collection object like a list
which by definition is an ordered set.
An example of such a list
can come from Twitter,
that uses Redis list to store timelines.
Now borrowed from a Twitter presentation
about their timeline architecture
our timeline service can
take a specific ID, and
it quickly identifies all tweets of
this user that are in the cache.
These tweets are then populated
by the content of the tweet,
then returned as a result.
This list can be long, but the insertion
and delete operations on the list
can be performed in constant
time which is in milliseconds.
If a tweet is retweeted,
the IDs of those tweets are also added
to the list of the first tweet, as you can
see for the three cases in the figure.
When the lists are long,
space saving becomes an important issue.
So Redis employs a method called
Ziplists which essentially
compacts the size of the list in
memory without changing the content.
Often producing significant
reduction in memory used.
Of course,
while Ziplists are very efficient for
retrieval, they are a little more complex
for insertion and deletion operations.
Since Redis is an open source system,
Twitter made a few innovations
on the Redis data structures.
One of these innovations is that
they created lists of Ziplists.
This gave them the flexibility of
having constant timing insertions and
deletions and at the same time used the
compressed representation to save space.
In 2012, the timeline service has about
40 terabytes of main memory, serving
30 million user queries per second.
Running on over 6,000
machines in one data center.
For those interested I would like to point
you to two wonderful Twitter presentation
explaining Twitter's use of Redis
among other design issue for
a realtime data system like Twitter.
We also introduce links in
the supplemental readings for this lesson.
Now the value to be looked up by the keys
can actually be more complicated and
can be records containing
attribute value pairs themselves.
Redis values can be hashes
which are essentially named containers
of unique fields and their values.
In the example, the key, std:101,
is associated with five
attributed value pairs.
The hashed attributes
are stored very efficiently.
And even when the list of attributed
value pairs in a hash is really long,
retrieval is efficient.
Horizontal scalability or
scale out capabilities refers
to the ability of a system
to achieve scalability when the number
of machines it operates on is increased.
Redis allows data partitioning through
range partitioning and hash partitioning.
Rate partitioning takes a numeric key and
breaks up the range of keys into bins.
In this case, by bins of 10,000
each of bin is assigned a machine.
And ultimately, a partitioning is where
computing a hashing function on a key.
Suppose we have 10 machines.
We pick the key and use the hash
function to get back a number.
We represent the number, modular 10,
and the result, in this case,
2, is the machine to which
the record will be allocated.
Replication is accomplished in
Redis through master-slave mode.
The slaves have a copy of the master node.
And can serve read queries.
Clients write to the master node.
And master node replicates to the slaves.
Clients read from the slaves to
scale up the read performance.
The replication processes are synchronous.
That is that slaves do not get replicated
data, it locks them with each other.
However, the replication
process does ensure
that they're consistent with each other.
The next system we'll explore is Vertica.
Which is the relational DBMS
designed to operate on top of HTFS.
It belongs to a family of DBMS
architectures called column stores.
Other products in
the same family are UCDV,
Carrot Cell Xvelocity from Microsoft and
so forth.
The primary difference
between a row store and
a column store is shown
in the diagram here.
Logically, this table has five columns.
Emp number, department number,
hire date, employee last name and
employee first name.
In a row oriented design the database
internally organizes the record
two four by two.
In a column store,
the data is organized column wise.
So the nth number column is stored
separately from the department id
column and so forth.
Now suppose a query
needs to find the ID and
department ID of all employees who were
hired after first of January, 2001.
The system only needs to look up
the hire date column to figure
out which records qualify.
And then pick up the values of the ID,
and the department of ID columns for
the qualifying records.
The other columns are not touched.
So if a table has 30 to 50 columns, very
often only a few of them are needed for
any single query.
So for tables with 500 million rows and
40 columns a typical query is very fast,
and uses much less memory because a full
record is not used most of the time.
My own experience is that with
an application that needed a database
with 150 billion tuples in a table.
Accounting operation took a little
under three minutes to complete.
A second advantage of the column store
comes from the nature of the data.
In a column store,
data in every column is sorted.
The figure on the right shows
three sorted columns of a table
with three visible columns.
The bottom of the first column shown here
has many accurate sixteen
transactions on the same day.
The second column has customer ids which
can be numerically close to each other.
They are all within seventy
values of the first customer.
So in the first case we can just
say that the value is one, one,
2007, and
the next 16 records have this value.
That means we do not have to store
the next 16 values thus saving space.
Now this form of shortened
representation is called compression.
And this specific variety is
called run-length encoding or RLE.
Another form of encoding can
be seen in the second column.
Here the customer ids a long integer,
but for
the records shown there
are nearby numbers.
So, if we pick a value in the column and
just put the difference between
this value and
other values The difference will be small.
It means,
we'll need fewer bites to represent them.
This one of compression is called
Frame-of-reference encoding.
The lesson to remember here is
that compressed data presentation
can significantly reduce the total
size of a database and if BDMS.
Should use all such tricks
to improve space efficiency.
While the space efficiency and
performance of Vertica is impressive for
large data, one has to be careful
about how to design a system with it.
Like Google's Web Table, and
Apache Cassandra, Vertica allows
the declaration of column-groups.
These are columns like first name and
last name which are very
often accessed together.
In Vertica,
a column group is like a mini table
which is treated like a little
row storied in the system.
But because these groups represent
activists that are frequently co accessed
the grouping actually
improves performance.
So an application developer is
better off when the nature and
the frequency of user queries
are known to some degree.
And this knowledge is applies
to designing the column groups.
An important side effect of column
structure organization of vertical
Is that the writing of data into
Vertica is a little slower.
When rows are added to a table,
Vertica initially places
them in a row-wise data structure and
then converts them into a column-wise
data structure, which is then compressed.
This lowness can be perceptible for
large uploads or updates.
Vertica belongs to a new breed of
database systems that call themselves
analytical databases.
This means two slightly different things.
First, Vertica offers many more
statistical functions than in
classical DBMS.
For example one can perform
operations over a Window
to see an example consider a table of
stock ticks having a time attribute,
a stock name and
a value of the stock called bid here.
This shows that data values in
the table now we would like to compute
a moving average of
the bit every 40 seconds.
We show the query in a frame below.
Now we aren't going into the details of
the query just consider the blue part.
It says the average,
which is the AVG function in yellow.
It must be computed on
the last column which is bit.
But, this computation
must be over the range that is
computed on the timestamp call.
So, the range is defined by a 40
second row before that current row so,
here the computation of the average
advances for the stock abc.
And for each computation,
the system only considers the rows whose
timestamp is within 40 seconds
before the current row.
The table on the right shows
the result of the query.
The average value, 10.12.
Is the same as the actual value, because
there are no other rows within 40 seconds.
The next two result rows average
over the preceding rows,
was times R within 40
seconds of the current row.
When we get to the blue row,
that we notice that it occurs 1 minute
16 seconds after the previous row.
So we cannot consider the previous
sort in the computation.
Instead, the result is just the value
of the bid in the current row.
The takeaway from this example is
that analytical computations like
this are happening inside the database and
not in an external application.
This brings us to the second feature
of Vertica as an analytical database.
R is a well known free statistics
package that's used by statisticians,
data minors, predictive analytics experts.
Today, R can not only
read data from files,
but it can go to an SQL database and
grab data to perform statistical analysis.
Over time, R has evolved and
given rights to distributed R which
is a high performance platform for R.
As expected in this distributed setting,
the system operates in
a master slave mode.
The master node coordinates computations
by sending commands to the workers.
The worker nodes maintain
data partitions and
apply the computation
functions to the data.
Just getting the data parallelly,
the essential data structure
is a distributed array.
That is an array that is
partitioned as shown here.
Now in this diagram
the partitions are equal, but
in practice they may be
all different sizes.
On which, one can compute a function for
each of these mini-arrays.
The bottom diagram, shows a simple
work flow of constructing and
deploying a predictive model.
The role of Vertica here,
is that it's a data supplier to the worker
nodes of R, and a model consumer.
The data to be analyzed is
the output of the vertica query,
which is transferred in memory through
a protocol called vertica fast transfer
through distributed R as a dArray.
When the model is created in R,
it should come back as a code that
goes through vertica as a function.
This function can be
called from inside Vertica
as if it was a user defined function.
Now in sophisticated applications,
the features of the data needed for
predicted modeling will also be
computed inside the DBMS possibly
using the new analytical operations
of Vertica that we've just shown.
Now this will make future
computation much faster and
improve the efficiency of
the entire analytics process.
Going forward, we believe that most DBMS's
will want to play in the analytics field,
will support similar functions.
Most of you have heard of
MongoDB as a dominant store for
JSON style semi-structured data.
MongoDB is very popular and
there are a number of excellent
tutorials on it on the web.
In this module we would like to discuss
a relatively new big data management
system for semistructured data that's
currently being incubated by Apache.
It's called AsterixDB.
Originally, AsterixDB was conceived by
the University of California Irvine.
Since it is a full fledged DBMS,
it provides ACID guarantees to
understand the basic design of AsterixDB,
let's consider this incomplete JSON
snippet taken from an actual tweet.
We have seen the structure of JSON before.
Here we point out that entities and
user, the two parts
in blue are nested, that means embedded,
within the structure of the tweet.
If we represent a part of the schema of
this abbreviated structure in AsterixDB,
it will look like this.
Here a dataverse is like a name space for
data.
Data is declared in terms of data types.
The top type, which looks like
a standard data with stable declaration,
represents the user portion of the JSON
object that we highlighted before.
The type below represents the message.
Now, instead of nesting it like JSON.
The user attribute highlighted in
blue is declared to have the type
TwitterUserType, thus it captures
the hierarchical structure of JSON.
We should also notice that
the first type is declared as open.
It means that the actual data can have
more attributes than specified here.
In contrast, the TweetMessage
type is declared as closed,
meaning that the data instance must have
the same attributes as in the schema.
AsterixDB can handle spatial data as given
by the point data types shown in green.
The question mark at the end of the point
type says that this attribute is optional.
That means all instances need not have it.
Finally, the create dataset actually
asks the system to create a dataset
called TweetMessages, whose type is
the just declared quick message type.
AstrerixDB which runs on HDFS provides
several options for credit support.
First it has its own query language
called the Asterix query language
which resembles the XML
credit language query.
The details of this query language
are not important right now.
We are illustrating the structure of
a query just to show what it looks like.
This particular query asks for
all user objects from the dataset
TwitterUsers in descending order of their
follower count and in alphabetical
order of the user's preferred language.
What is more interesting and distinctive
is that AsterixDB has a creative
processing engine that can process
queries in multiple languages.
For its supported language
they've developed a way to
transfer the query into a set of low
level operations like select and
join which their query
exchange can support.
Further, they've determined how
a record described in one of these
languages can be transformed
into an Asterix.
In this manner, the support hive queries,
which is expressed in like this.
Xquery, Hadoop map reduce,
as wall as a new language
called SQL++ which extends SQL for JSON.
Like a typical DB BDms,
AsterixDB is designed to operate
on a cluster of machines.
The basic idea, not surprisingly,
is to use partition data parallellism.
Each data set is divided into
instances of various types
which can be decomposed to different
machines by either range partitioning or
hash partitioning like
we discussed earlier.
A runtime distributed execution
engine called Hyracks is used for
partitioned parallel
execution of query plans.
For example, let's assume we have
two relations, customers and orders,
as you can see here.
Our query is find the number of orders for
every market segment that
the customers belong to.
Now this query need a join operation
between the two relations,
using the O_CUSTKEY as a foreign
key of customer into orders.
It also needs a grouping operation,
which for
each market segment will pull together all
the orders which will then be counted.
You don't have to understand the details
of this diagram at this point.
We just want to point out that
the different parts of the query
that are being marked,
the customer filed here has two partitions
that reside on two nodes,
NC one and NC two respectively.
The orders file also has two partitions.
But each partition is dually replicated.
One can be accessed either of nodes NC3 or
NC2 and the other on NC1 and NC5.
Hyracks will also break up
the query into a number of jobs and
then fill it out which tasks can
be performed in parallel and
which ones must be
executed stage by stage.
This whole thing will be managed
by the cluster controller.
The cluster controller is also
responsible for replanning and
reexecuting of a job
if there is a failure.
AsteriskDB also has the provision
to accept real time data from external
data sources at multiple rates.
One way is from files in a directory path.
Consider the example of tweets.
As you have seen with the hands-on demo,
usually people acquire tweets by accessing
data through an api that twitter provides.
Very typically a certain volume of tweets,
lets say for
every 5 minutes, is accumulated into
a .json file in a specific directory.
The next 5 minutes,
in another .json file, and so forth.
The way to get this
data into asterisks DB,
is to first create an empty
data set called Tweets here.
The next task is to create a feed.
That is an externally resource.
One has to specify that it's coming from
the local file system called local fs here
and the location of the directory,
the format and
the data type it's going to copy it.
Next, the feed is connected
to the data set and
the system starts reading unread
files from the directory.
Another way for AsteriskDB to access
external data is directly from an API,
such as the Twitter API.
To do this,
one would create a dataset as before.
But this time the data feed is
not on the local file system.
Instead it uses the push Twitter
method which invokes the Twitter
client with the four authentication
parameters required by the API.
Once the feed is defined it is
connected to the data set as before.
Now we move to another Apache product for
large scale text data
searching called Solr.
Systems like Solr, and
its underlying text indexing engine, are
typically designed for search problems.
So they would typically be
part of a search engine.
But before we talk about Solr or
large scale text, we need to first
appreciate some fundamental challenges
when it comes to storing,
indexing, and matching text data.
The basic challenge comes from
the numerous ways in which
a text string may vary, making it
hard to define what a good match is.
Let us show some of these challenges.
Remember in each case,
we're asking whether the strings shown on
either side of the double
tilde sign should match.
The first issue is about spelling
variations and capitalization.
The second issue relates
structured strings.
Where different parts of a string
represent different kind of information.
We have seen this before for file paths,
URLs, and like in this case, product IDs.
The problem is that the searcher may
not always know the structure or
my job on misposition,
the internal punctuations.
The next problem is very common with
proper nouns which are represented in
various ways, including dropping a part of
the string, picking up only the initials.
But consider the last variation, should
BH Obama really match the full name?
The next example is about
frequently used synonyms.
If the document has one of the synonyms,
while the query uses another,
should they match?
Example 5 illustrates
a very common problem.
People use abbreviations all the time.
If we look at text and social media and
instant messaging, we see a much
wider variety of abbreviations.
How well should they met with
the real correct version of the term?
Now problem six is a special
case of problem five.
Many long nouns are shortened
because we take the first initial
letter of each significant word.
We say significant because we
drop words like of as shown here.
This is called initialism.
Just so you know, when an initialism
can be said like a real word,
it's called an acronym.
Thus IBM is an initialization,
but NATO is an acronym.
Now problem seven and
problem eight show two
different situation where we first must
decide what to do with the period sign.
In the first case, we should not
find a match because students and
American are in two different
sentences punctuated by a period sign.
But in the second case we should
find a match because the period
does not designate a sentence boundary.
Lucene, the engine on which Solr is
built is effectively not a database,
but a modern inverted index.
What's an inverted index?
Let's first define a vocabulary
as a collection of terms.
Where a term may be a single word or
it can be multiple words.
It can a single term or
it can be a collection of synonyms.
But how would a search
engine know what a term is?
We'll revisit this question
in a couple of slides.
For now, let's just say that if we
have a corpus of documents, we can
extract most of the terms and construct
a vocabulary for that collection.
We can then define occurrence, as a list
containing all the information necessary
for each term in the vocabulary.
It would include information like,
which documents have the term?
The positions in the document
where the term occurs.
We can then go on to compute the count of
the term in the document and the corpus.
Referring back to a previous module
in this course, we can also compute
the term frequency and inverse
document frequency for the collection.
An inverted index is
essentially an index which for
every term stores at least the ID of
the document where the term occurs.
Practically, other computed numbers or
properties associated with the terms
will also be included in the index.
Solr is an open source
enterprise search platform.
The heart of Solr is its search
functionality built for full text search.
However, Solr provides much
more than tech search.
It can take any structured document,
even CSV files
which can be broken up into fields,
and can index each field separately.
Full text indexes where text columns
are supplemented by indexes for
other types of data, including numeric
data, dates, geographic coordinates, and
fields where domains are limited
to an emergent set of values.
Solr provides other facilities
like faceted search and
highlighting of terms that match a query.
Now if you're not familiar
with the term faceted search,
let's look at the screenshot
from amazon.com.
I performed a search on the string,
Dell laptop.
Consider the highlighted
part of the image.
Each laptop record carries a lot of
attributes like the display size,
the processor speed,
the amount of memory, and so forth.
These attributes can be put into builds
like processor type has Intel i5, i7, etc.
Faceted search essentially extracts
the individual values of these fields and
displays them back to the user, usually
with a count of the number of records.
We see this in the upper
part of the marked portion,
which says there are 5619
laptops per 411 tablets.
These are called facets.
If a user clicks on a facet,
documents with only those values,
that's just the tablets,
will be presented back to the user.
Now let's get back to the question
of what a term is, and
how a Solr system should know it.
Solr allows the system designer to
specify how to parse a document,
by instructing how to tokenize
a document and how to filter it.
Tokenization is the process of
breaking down the characters read.
For example, one can break
the stream at white spaces, and
get all the words as tokens.
Then, it can filter out the punctuation
like the period, the apostrophe, and so
on, just to get the pure words.
The code snippet on the right
essentially achieves this.
It uses a standard tokenizer that gets
the words with immediate punctuation.
The first filter removes the punctuations.
The second filter turns
everything into lowercase.
And the third filter uses
a synonym file to ensure that
all the synonyms get the same
token after ignoring the case.
The last filter removes common
English words like a and the.
While a similar process would need to
happen when we get the query string.
It will also need to go through a
tokenization and token filtering process.
In the query analyzer example, there
are six filters within the tokenizer.
We use a pattern tokenizer which
will remove the white spaces and
periods and semi-colon.
The common grams filter creates
tokens out of pairs of terms, and
in doing so, makes sure that words
in the stopword file are used.
So if we have the string,
the cat, the term the should
not be ignored in this filter.
Now, the filters here
are executed in order.
After the common grams
filter is already done,
the next filter removes all
the stopwords in the file.
The fifth filter makes sure that if
the queries coming from a web form,
all the HTML characters are stripped off.
Finally, the remaining words are stemmed,
so that runs and
running in the query would match
the word run in the document.
We'll end this section with a discussion
on Solr queries, that is searches.
We present a CSV file with nine
records and seven attributes.
We issue queries against
the system by posing a web query.
In these examples, we show some of
the queries one can post to the system.
This will be covered in more detail
during the hands-on session.
Just notice that the q equal to is a query
and the fl is what you want to back.
Listens on activity who will be performing
queries assessing the Postgres database.
First, will open a terminal window and
start the Postgres shell.
Next, we will look at table and
column definitions in database.
Who’s in query the content
of the buy-clicks table?
And see how to do this query, but filter
specific rows and columns from the table.
Next, we will perform average and
some aggregation operations
on a specific column.
And finally,
we will see how to combine two tables
by joining them on a single column.
Let's begin.
First, click on the terminal
icon at the top of the toolbar
to open a Terminal window.
Next, let's start the Postgres
shell by running psql.
The Postgres shell allows us to
enter queries and run commands for
the postgres database.
We can see what tables are in
the database by running \d.
This says that there are three
tables in the database,
adclicks, buyclicks and gameclicks.
We could use \d table name to see
the definition of one of these tables.
Let's look at the definition of buyclicks,
we enter \d buyclicks.
This shows that there's seven
columns in the database.
These are the column names and here's
the data type for each of the columns.
Now let's look at the contents
of the buyclicks table.
We can query the contents by running
the command select * from buyclicks;.
The select says that
we want to do a query.
The star means we want to
retrieve all the columns and
from buyclicks says,
which table to perform the query from.
And finally, all commands in Postgres
shell need to end with a semicolon.
When we run this command we see
the contents of the buyclicks table.
Column header is at the top and
the contents are below.
Again hit Space to scroll through
the contents, and hit Q when we're done.
Now, let's view the contents
of only two of the columns.
Let's query only the price and
the user id from the buyclicks table.
To do this we run select price,
userid from buyclicks.
This command says,
we want to query only the price and
userid columns from the buyclicks table
When we run this,
We only get those two columns.
We can also perform queries that
just select certain rows and
meet a certain criteria.
For example,
let's make a query that only shows
the rows containing the price over $10.
You can do this by running select price,
userid from buyclicks where price > 10.
This query says, we only want to see
the price and userid columns from
the buyclicks table where the value in the
price column has a value greater than 10.
We run this, we see that we always
have price values greater than 10.
The SQL language has a number of
aggregation operations built into it.
For example,
we can take the average price by running,
select avg(price) from buyclicks.
This command will show the average price
from all the data in the buyclicks table.
Another aggregate operation is sum.
We can see the total price by running,
select sum(price) from buyclicks.
We can also combine two tables
by joining on a common column.
If you recall we have three
tables in our database adclicks,
buyclicks and gameclicks.
We look at the description the definition
of adclicks buy running \d adclicks.
You can see that it also
has a column called userid.
Let's combine buyclicks and
adclicks based on this common column.
You can do this by running, select adid,
buyid, adclicks.userid from adclicks join
buyclicks on adclicks.userid
= buyclicks.userid
This query says,
we want to just see the adid, buyid and
userid columns, and
we want to combine the adclicks table,
the buyclicks table, and
we will be combining them on
the userid column and
it's common in both those tables.
When we run it,
you see just the three columns.
Next we'll consider queries
where two tables are used.
Let's consider the query,
find the beers liked by drinkers who
frequent The Great American Bar.
For this query, we need
the relation's Frequents and Likes.
Now look at the scheme of these
relations in the light blue box.
They have a common
attribute called drinker.
So if we use the attribute drinker,
we need to tell the system
which one we are referring to.
Now look at the SQL query, the FROM clause
in the query has these two relations.
To handle a common attribute name issue,
we need to give nicknames,
aliases to these relations.
Therefore in the FROM clause we say,
Likes has the alias L and
Frequents has the alias F.
Since we want to find beers like before,
we use a SELECT DISTINCT clause for beer.
As we saw before, using SELECT DISTINCT
avoids duplicates in the result.
The WHERE clause has two
kinds of conditions,
the first kind is
a single table condition.
In this case, bar = The Great American Bar
on the Frequents relation.
The second kind is a joined condition
which says that the drinker's attribute in
the frequency relation is the same as the
drinker's attribute of the Likes relation.
We encode this in SQL in the last
line of the query using aliases.
Why did we not say L.beer in the SELECT
clause or F.bar in the first condition?
We could have,
the query would have been equally right.
But we are using a shortcut because we
know that these attributes are unique
already in the query.
Now let's look at the query again,
this time from the viewpoint
of evaluating the query.
There are many ways to evaluate the query,
but
the way it's most likely
to be evaluated is this.
The query will first look at the tables
that have single table conditions.
So it would perform a select operation
on the Frequents table to match
the records of the condition
that The Great American Bar
equal to The Great American Bar.
Why is this strategy good?
It's because the selection operative
reduces the number of triples to consider.
Thus, if there are thousand
triples in the relation frequents,
maybe 60 of them matches the desired bar.
So in the next step, we have to deal with
a fewer number of records than thousand.
All right, the next step will
be a Join with a Likes relation.
A Join requires two relations
in a Join condition,
the Join condition comes from the query.
The first relation shown with
an underscore symbol here
is a result of the previous operation.
Another way of saying this
is that the result of
the selection is piped
into the Join operation.
That means we do not create
an intermediate table from
the result of the selection.
The results are directly supplied to the
next operator, which in this case is Join.
Now the result of the Join operator is an
intermediate structure with columns beer
from Likes relation and
the drinker from the Frequents
relation that we've processed.
This intermediate set of triples is
piped to the Project operation that
picks up the beer column.
Now we need to process
the DISTINCT clause for
Deduplicate elimination,
which then goes to the Output.
We have already seen how the select
project queries on single tables
are evaluated when the tables
are partitioned across several machines.
We'll now see how we process Join
queries in the same setting.
For our case, consider that the Likes and
Frequents tables are on
two different machines.
In the first part of the query,
the selection happens on the machine
with the Frequents table.
The output of the query is a smaller
table with the same scheme as Frequents,
that is with drinkers and bars.
Now we define an operation
called Semijoin,
in which we need to move data
from one machine to another.
The goal of the Semijoin operation is
to reduce the cost of data movement.
That is to move data from
the machine which has
the Frequents data to
the machine with the Likes data.
The cost is reduced if we ship less data.
The way to it is to first find which
data the join operation actually needs.
Clearly, it needs only the drinkers
column and not the bars column.
So the drinkers column is projected out,
then
just this column is transmitted
to the second machine.
Finally, the join is performed by looking
at the values in the Likes column
that only matches the values
in the shipped data.
That means only the data from Likes that
matches the drinkers that are chosen.
These are then the join results which
would go to the output of the operation.
Now here you can see the Semijoin
operation graphically.
The red table on the left is the output
of the selection operations on the left.
The white table on the right
is the table to be joined to.
Since we need only the Drinkers column,
it is projected to create
a one-column relation.
Notice that the red table has two entries
for Pete, who frequented two bars.
But the output of the project
is condensed in the yellow table
to just show the Drinkers,
where Pete appears only once.
For those of you with
a background in computer science,
this can be done using a hash
map like data structure.
This one-column table is now shipped
to Site2, which has the Likes relation.
Now at Site2, the Shipped relation
is used to find matches from
the Drinkers column and
it finds only one match called Sally.
So the corresponding result triples,
in this case,
only one triple is produced
at the end of this operation.
Now, the original table and
the matching table are shipped
to the last of the operation
to finish the Join operation.
And more efficient version of
this is shown in the next slide.
In this version, the first two
steps this and that are the same.
Then the result of the reduce
is also shipped to Site1 to find
the matches from the red relation.
Another reduce operation
is performed on Site1 now
to get the matching records
on the red relation.
Finally, these two reduced
relations are shipped to
the site where the final join happens.
And all of this may seem
like a lot of detail.
Let me repeat something I've said before.
If we have a system like DB2 or Spark SQL
that implements multi-site joins, it
will perform this kind of operation under
the hood, you don't have to know them.
However, if we were to implement
a similar operation and all that you have
is Hadoop, you may end up implementing
this kind of algorithm yourself.
The queries in real life are little more
complex than what we have seen before.
So let's consider a more complex query.
Let’s find bars where the price
of Miller is the same as or
less than what the great American bar
called TGAB here charges for Bud.
You may say, but we do not really
know what TGAB charges for Bud.
That's correct, so
we can break up the query into two parts.
First, we will find this unknown price,
and then we'll use that price
to find the bars that would sell Miller
for the same price or better price.
Now this is a classic situation where
the result from the first part of
the query should be fed as
a parameter to the second query.
Now this situation is called a subquery.
We write this in SQL as
shown in the slide here.
What makes this query different is that
the part where price is less than equal
to, instead of specifying
a constant like $8,
we actually place another query which
computes the price of a Bud at TGAB.
The shaded part is called the inner query,
or the subquery.
In this case, both the outer query and
the inner query use the same relation,
which is Sells.
Now in terms of evaluation,
the inner query is evaluated first,
and the outer query uses its output.
Now while it may not be
obvious at this time,
notice that the inner query is
independent of the outer query.
In other words,
even if we did not have the outer query,
we can still evaluate the inner query.
We say in this case that
the subquery is uncorrelated.
Let's look at another
example of a subquery.
In this example,
we want to find the name and
manufacturer of each beer
that Fred didn't like.
So how do we know what Fred didn't like?
We do however know that the set of
beers that Fred likes because they
are listed in the Likes relation.
So we need to subtract this set from the
total set of beers that the company has
recorded.
This subtraction of sets can
be performed in several ways.
One of them is to use
the NOT IN construct.
So the query class's job is to take
every name from the Beers table and
output it only if it does not appear
in the set produced by the inner query.
Similar to the previous query,
the subquery here is also uncorrelated.
Now this is a more sophisticated query.
The intention is to find
beers that are more expensive
than the average price of beer.
But since beers have different
prices in different bars,
we have to find the average for every bar.
Therefore the idea is to find
the average price of beer for
every bar and then compare the price of
each beer with respect to this average.
Now look at the query and the table.
Let's assume we are processing
the first table.
The beer is Bud, and the price is $5.
Now we need to know if $5 is greater than
the average price of beer sold at HGAT.
To do this,
we need to compute the inner query, okay?
So now let's look at the fourth row.
The price of Guinness needs to be
compared to that average again for HGAT.
In fact for
every table processed by the outer query,
one needs to compute the inner query for
that bar.
This makes the inner subquery
correlated with the outer query.
Now a smart query processor will store
the average once it's computed and
then reuse the stored value instead
of computing over and over again.
What's an aggregate query?
Let's use a simple example of
finding the average price of Bud.
This is like a simple select project
query with the additional aspect
that it takes a list of price values
of Bud from different bars and
then computes an average.
In the example shown,
the average of the five prices is 4.2.
In other words the average function,
the AVG function, takes a list of
values and produces a single value.
Now there are many functions
that have this behavior.
The SUM function takes
a list of values and
adds them up to produce a single value.
The COUNT function takes
a list of list of values and
counts the number of items
in that list and so on.
These are called aggregate functions.
Now if we wanted to count only the price
values that are different, that is 3,
4, and 5 just once, we can write
the SELECT clause a little differently.
We would say that the average
is over distinct values
of price which in this
case will result in 4.
You should recognize that most analytical
operations need to use statistical
functions which are aggregates.
So another important
analytical requirement
is computing the statistical
aggregate by groups.
For example, we often compute the average
salaries of employees per department.
Now back to our example here,
we want to find the average price paid for
Bud per drinker, where we know
that a drinker visits many bars.
So the grouping variable here is drinker.
So we have three attributes at play,
price which we need to aggregate,
drinker which we need to group by,
and bar which is a join attribute.
The fourth attribute, namely beer,
is used for selection and
does not participate in grouping.
So after the selection we will
get an intermediate relation
containing drinker, bar, and price.
With this, the GROUP BY operation
will create one result row for
each drinker and place the average
price over all such rows.
Now how does GROUP BY and
aggregate computation work
when the data is partitioned?
Let's take the same query.
We are looking for the average
price of Bud grouped by drinker.
But this time the result of the selection
are in two different machines.
Imagine that this time they are range
partitioned by row numbers,
which we have not shown
to maintain clarity.
Now with the GROUP BY operation the data
will get repartitioned by the grouping
attribute, that's drinker.
And then the aggregate
function is computed locally.
To accomplish this repartitioning task,
each machine groups its own data locally,
determines which portions of data should
be transmitted to a different machine,
and accordingly ships it to that machine.
Now there are several variants
of this general scheme
which are even more efficient.
Now if this reminds you of the map
operation you saw in your previous course,
you are exactly right.
This fundamental process of grouping,
partitioning, and redistribution of data
is inherent in data-parallel computing and
implemented inside database systems.
Welcome back.
In this video, we will provide you
a quick summary of the main points from
our last course on big data modeling and
management.
If you had just completed our second
course and do not need a refresher,
you may now skip to the next lecture.
After this video, you will be able
to recall why big data modeling and
management is essential in preparing
to gain insights from your data,
summarize different kids of data models.
Describe streaming data and the different challenges
it presents, and explain the differences
between a database management system and
a big data management system.
In the second course, we described
a data model as a specification
that precisely characterizes
the structure of the data,
the operations on the data, and
the constraints that may apply on data.
For example, a data model may state that
a data is structured like
a two-dimensional array or a matrix.
For this structure,
one may have a data access operation,
which given an index of the array,
we use the cell of the array to refer to.
A data model may also specify
constraints on the data.
For example, while a total
data set may have many arrays,
the name of each array must be unique and
the values of a specific array
must always be greater than zero.
Database management systems handle
low level data management operations,
help organization of the data
using a data model, and
provide an open programmable
access to data.
We covered a number of data models.
We showed four models that were
discussed in more details.
The relational data to date
is the most used data model.
Here, data is structured like tables
which are formally called relations.
The relational data model has been
implemented in traditional database
systems.
But they are being refreshly implemented
in modern data systems over Hadoop and
Spark and
are getting deployed on cloud platforms.
The second category of data gaining
popularity is semi-structured data,
which includes documents like HTML pages,
XML data and
JSON data that are used by
many Internet applications.
This data can have one element nested or
embedded within another data element and
hence can often be modeled as a tree.
The third category of data
models is called graph data.
A graph is a network where
nodes represent entities and
edges represent relationships
between pairs of such entities.
For example, in a social network,
nodes may represent users and
edges may represent their friendship.
The operations performed on graph data
includes traversing the network so
that one can find friend of
a friend of a friend if needed.
In contrast to the previous three models,
that there is a structure to the data,
the text data is much more unstructured
because an entire data item
like a new article can
be just a text string.
However, text is the primary form of data
in information retrieval systems or
search engines like Google.
We also discussed streaming data,
or data with velocity, as a special
class of data that continually come
to the system at some data rate.
Examples can be found in data coming
from road sensors that measure traffic
patterns or stock price data from
the stock exchange that may come
in volumes from stock
exchanges all over the world.
Streaming data is special because a stream
is technically an infinite data source.
And therefore,
we keep filling up memory and
storage and will eventually go
beyond the capacity of any system.
Streaming data, therefore, needs
a different kind of management system.
For this reason,
streaming data is processed in memory,
in chunks which are also called windows.
Often only the necessary
part of the data stream or
the results of queries against
the data stream is stored.
A typical type of query against streaming
data are alerts or notifications.
The system notices an event like multiple
stock price changing within a short time.
Streaming data is also used for
prediction.
For instance, based on wind direction and
temperature data streams,
one can predict how a wildfire
is going to spread.
In the last course, we also covered
a number of data systems that we called
big data management systems.
These systems use
different data models and
have different capabilities, but
are characterized by some common features.
They are also designed from the start for
parallel and distributed processing.
Most of them implement data partition
parallelism, which, if you can recall,
refers to the process of segmenting
the data into multiple machines so
data retrieval and manipulations can be
performed in parallel on these machines.
Many of these systems allow a large
number of users who constantly update and
query the system.
Some of the systems do not maintain
transaction consistency with every update.
That means,
not all the machines may have all
the updates guaranteed at every moment.
However, most of them provide
a guarantee of eventual consistency,
which means all the machines will
get all updates sooner or later.
Therefore, providing better accuracy and
time.
The third common characteristic
of big data management systems is
that they are often built on top of
a Hadoop-like platform that provides
automatic replication and
a map-reduce style processing ability.
Some of the data operations performed
within these systems make use of these
lower level capabilities.
After this refresher on data modeling and
management, let's start big data
integration and processing.
So, hi.
In the previous course, we saw
examples of different data models and
talked about a few current
data management systems.
In this module,
we'll focus on data retrieval.
Data retrieval refers to
the way in which data desired
by a user is specified and
retrieved from a data store.
Note that in this course, we are using
the term data retrieval in two ways.
Assume that your data is stored in a data
store that follows a specific data model,
like for
example the relational data model.
By data retrieval, we will refer to, one,
the way you specify how to get
the desired data out of the system,
this is called the query
specification method, and two,
the internal processing that occurs within
the data management system to compute or
evaluate that specified retrieval request.
While query specification can apply to
small data stores or large data stores,
we'll keep an eye on the nature of
query evaluation when the data is big.
Further, we'll consider how
the query specification changes
when we deal with faster streaming data.
A query language is a language in which
a retrieval request is specified.
A query language is often called
declarative, which means it lets you
specify what you want to retrieve without
having to tell the system how to retrieve.
For example, you can say,
find all data from relation employee
where the salary is more than 50k.
Now, you don't have to write a program
which will tell the system to open a file,
skip the first 250 bytes,
then in a loop pick the next 1024 bytes,
probe into the 600th byte and
read an integer, and so forth.
Instead of writing such
a complicated procedure,
you just specify the data items that
you need and the system does the rest.
For example, SQL,
structured query language,
is the most used query language for
relational data.
Now, in contrast to a query language,
a database programming
language like Oracle's PL/SQL or
Postgres's PgSQL are high-level
procedural programming languages
that embed query operations.
We will look at some query
languages in detail and
show examples of database
programming languages.
The first query language
we'll look at is SQL,
which is the ubiquitous query
language when the data is structured,
but has been extended in many ways
to accommodate other types of data.
For this course, we'll stick to
the structured aspect of the language.
Now, you should know that SQL is used for
classical database management systems
like Oracle as well as modern Hadoop
style distributed systems such as Spark.
Now, we will work with
an illustrative example.
First, we need to define
the schema of the database.
Now, think of a business called the
Beer Drinkers Club that owns many bars,
and each bar sells beer.
Our schema for
this business has six relations of tables.
The first table lists these bars,
the names, addresses, and
the license number of the bar.
Notice that the attribute name is
underlined because it is the primary key
of the bars relation.
Recall that the primary key
refers to a set of attributes,
in this case just the name,
that makes a record unique.
Note that the relation bars
with the attribute name
within parenthesis is the same
as the table shown on the right.
We will use both representations
as we go forward.
The second table called Beers, this is
the names and manufacturers of beer.
Now, not every bar sells the same
brands of beer, and even when they do,
they may have different prices for
the same product because of differences
in the establishment costs.
So the Sells table records which
bar sells which beer at what price.
Now, our business is special.
It also keeps information about
the regular member customers.
So the Drinkers relation has the name,
address, and phone of these customers.
Well, not only that,
it knows which member visits
which bars and
which beer each member likes.
Clearly, the Beer Drinkers Club
knows its customers.
The most basic structure of an SQL
query is a SELECT-FROM-WHERE clause.
In this example, we're looking for
beer names that are made by Heineken.
So we need to specify
our output attribute,
in this case the name of the beer.
The logical table which will be used to
answer the query, in this case, Beers.
And the condition that all the desired
data items should satisfy,
namely, the value of the attribute
called manf is Heineken.
Now, there are few things to notice here.
First, the literal Heineken
is put within quotes,
because it's a single string literal.
Remember that in this case,
the string is supposed to match exactly,
including the case.
Secondly, if you go back to the data
operations discussed in course two,
you will recognize that this form
of query can also be represented
as a selection operation on the relation
Beers with a condition on the manf
attribute, followed by
a projection operation
that outputs the name attribute from
the result of the selection operation.
So the selection operation finds all
tuples of beer for which the manufacturer
is Heineken, and from those tuples
it projects only the name column.
The result of the query is a table
with one single attribute called name.
We illustrate some more features of SQL,
using two example queries.
The first looks for
expensive beer and its price.
Let's say we consider a beer to be
expensive if it costs more than $15
per bottle.
From the schema,
we know that the price information is
available in the table called Sells.
So the FROM clause should use Sells.
The WHERE clause is intuitive and
specifies the price of the beer
to be greater than 15.
Now notice that the Sells relation
also has a column called bar.
Now, if two different bars sell
the same beer at the same price,
we'll get both entries in the result.
But that's not what we want.
Now regardless of the multiplicity
of bars that have the same price for
the same beer,
we want the result just once.
So this is achieved through
the SELECT DISTINCT statement,
which ensures that the result
relation will have no duplicate.
The second example shows the case
where more than one condition
must be specified by the result.
In this query,
the business must be in San Diego and
at the same time it must be
a temporary license holder,
which means the license
number should start with 32.
As we see here, these conditions
are put together by the AND operator.
Thus, the query will pick
the third record in the table
because the first record satisfy the first
condition and not the second condition.
In a few slides, we'll come back to
the evaluation of this type of queries
in the context of big data.
Now, remember, one can also place a limit
on the number of results to return.
If our database is large, and
we need only five results, for
example, for a sample to display,
we can say LIMIT 5.
Now, the exact syntax of this LIMIT
clause may vary between DBMS vendors.
Now if the table of beers was large and
had millions of entries,
the table would possibly need
to be split over many machines.
Another way of saying that is that
the table will be partitioned
across a number of machines.
Since a query simply
performs a selection and
projection here,
it can be evaluated in parallel.
Remember that name is
the primary key of the table.
One standard way of partitioning the data
is called a range partitioning
by the primary key.
This simply means that the rows
of the table are put in groups
depending on the alphabetical
order of the name value.
So beers with names starting with E and
B here are placed in Machine 1.
Those starting with C and
D are in Machine 2.
And if there are too many rows for
entries where the name starts with H,
maybe H is split into Machines 5 and 6.
This is shown in the sketch here.
Next, we will show how queries
are performed over partition tables.
But before we do that, you should know
that all database management companies,
like IBM, Chair Data, Microsoft, and
others, have a solution like this for
large volumes of data,
where data partitioning is used.
Newer systems, like Spark and SQL,
are naturally distributed, and
therefore, offer data partitioning.
So, we show the same partition
tables as we saw before.
Now we'll ask two queries.
The first query asks for
all tuples as records from the beers table
where the name of the beer starts with Am.
And the second query is
exactly what we asked before.
The first query in
the SQL looks like this.
We said SELECT* FROM Beers to mean
all attributes from table beers.
The WHERE clause shows the syntax for
a partial match query.
In this query,
there are two new syntax elements.
The first is a predicate called like.
When we use like,
we're telling the query engine
that we only have partial information
about the string we want to match.
This partly specified string
is called a string pattern.
That means, there is this part
of the string we know and
a part that we do not know.
In this case, we know that our design
string starts with Am, so we'd write Am,
and then we put % to refer to the part
of the string that we do not know.
Putting them together, we get Am%.
If we wanted to find, say,
Am somewhere in the middle of the string,
we would write the pattern as %Am%.
The second query is not new.
We saw it in the last slide.
However, as we'll see next, evaluating
the second query will be a little more
tricky in a partition database than
that we usually see for big data.
Let's talk about the first query
in this data partition setting.
The question to ask is, do we need to
touch all partitions to answer the query?
Of course not, we know that the name is
a primary key for the table of beers.
We also know that the system did arrange
partitioning on the name attribute.
This means that the evaluation
process should only access Machine 1
because no other machine will have
records for names starting with A.
Now this is exactly what we, as humans,
do when we look up an entry in
a multivolume encyclopedia.
We look for the starting words, then
figure out which specific volume would
have that entry,
then pick up just that volume.
Thus, so long as the system
knows the partitioning strategy,
it can make its job much more efficient.
When a system processes
thousands of queries per second,
this kind of efficiency actually matters.
Now raised partitioning is
only one of many partitioning
schemes used in a database system, okay.
Let's try to answer the second query
in the same partition setting.
Now the query condition is on
the second attribute, manf.
Now in one sense, it's a simpler query.
There is no light pattern here, and
we know exactly the string that we are
looking for, namely the string Heineken.
However, this time,
we really cannot get away
by using the partitioning information
because the partitioning activity is
different from the attribute on which
the query condition is applied.
So this query will need
to go to all partitions.
Technically speaking,
the query needs to be broadcast
from the primary machine to all machines,
as shown here.
Next, this broadcast query
will be independently, and
in parallel,
execute the query on the local machine.
Then, these results need to be
brought back into the primary machine.
And then,
they need to be unioned together.
And only then, the results can be
formed and returned to the client.
Now, this might seem
like a lot of extra work.
However, remember, the shaded part of
the query is executed in parallel,
which is the essence of
dealing with large data.
Now, at this point, you might be thinking,
wait a minute, what if I had 100 machines,
and the desired data
is only in 20 of them?
Should we needlessly go through all 100
machines, find nothing in 80 of them, and
return 0 results from those machines?
Then why do the extra work?
Can it not be avoided?
Well, to do this, it would need
one more piece in the solution,
it's called an index structure.
Very simply,
an index can be thought of as a reverse
table, where given the value in a column,
you would get back the records where the
value appears as shown in the figure here.
Using an index speeds up query
processing significantly.
With indexes, we can solve this
problem in many different ways.
The top table shows the case where
each machine has its own index for
the manf column.
This is called a local index because
the index is in every machine
that holds the data for
that table on that machine.
In this case,
looking up Heineken in the index,
we would know which records
would have the data.
Since the index is local, the main query
will indeed go to all machines, but
the lookup will be really instant, and the
empty results would return very quickly.
In the second case,
we adopted a different solution.
Here, there is an index on the main
machine, all on a separate index server.
Now when we place a data
record in a machine,
this index keeps an account of the machine
that contains the record with that value.
Look at the second table to the right.
Given the value of Heineken,
we know that it is only in three machines,
and therefore,
we can avoid going to the other machines.
Clearly, we can always use
both indexing schemes.
This will use more space,
but queries will be faster.
Now this gives you some of the choices
you may need to make with big data,
whether you use a parallel DBMS or
a distributed data solution.
Welcome to Big Data Integration and
Processing.
Welcome to course three of
the big data specialization.
I'm Amarnath Gupta.
And I'm Ilkay Altintas.
We are really excited to
work with you in this course
to develop your understanding and skills
in big data integration and processing.
By now you might have just
finished our first two courses and
learned the basics of big data
modelling and management.
If you haven't, it's not required.
But for those that less background
in the data modelling and
data management areas you
might find it valuable.
We understand that you may not have
any background on data management.
We are going to introduce Query languages,
we'll first look at SQL in some detail,
and then move to Query languages for
MongoDB which is a semi structured
data management system, and Aerospike,
which is a key value store.
We will also introduce concepts
related to processing of big data as
big data pipelines.
We talk about data structures and
transformations related to batch and
stream processing as steps in a pipeline.
Providing us a way to talk
about big data processing
without getting into the details
of the underlying technologies.
Once we have reviewed the concepts and
related systems, we will switch gears
to hands on exercises with Spark,
one of the most popular big data engines.
We will show you examples of patch and
stream processing using Spark.
As you know for
many data science applications
one has to use many different databases
and analyze the integrated data.
In fact, data integration is one leading
cause leading to the bigness of data.
We'll give you a rapid exposure to
information integration systems
through use cases and point out the big
data aspects one should pay attention to.
We are also excited to show you
examples of data processing using Splunk.
Our goal here is to provide you
with simple hands on exercises
that require no programming, but
show you how one can use interfaces like
Splunk to manage and process big data.
We wish you a fun time learning and
hope to hear from you in the discussions
forums and learner stories as usual.
Well, happy learning and think big data
In this video, we will talk about
the challenges of ingesting and
processing big data and
remind ourselves why need any paradigm and
programming models for big data.
After this video, you will be able to
summarize the requirements of programming
models for big data and
why you should care about them.
You will also be able to explain
how the challenges of big
data related to its variety, volume and
velocity affects its processing.
Before we start,
let's imagine an online gaming newscase,
just like the one we have for
Catch the Pink Flamingo.
You just introduced the game,
and users started signing up.
You start with a traditional
relational database,
keeping track of user sessions and
other events.
Your game server receives
an event notification every time
a user opens his session and
makes a point in the game.
Initially, everything is great,
your game is working and
the database is able to handle the event
streams coming into the server.
However, suddenly your game becomes
highly popular a good problem to have.
The database management system in
your game server won't be able to
handle the load anymore.
You start getting errors that the events
can't be inserted into the database
at the speed they are coming in.
You decide that you will have a buffer or
a queue to process the advancing chunks.
Maybe also at the same time processing
them to be organized in windows of time or
game sessions.
However, in time as the demand goes up,
you will need more processing nodes and
even more database servers
that can handle the load.
This is, a typical scenario that
most web sites face when confronted
with big data issues related to
volume and velocity of information.
As this scenario demonstrates,
solving the problem in one step
might be possible initially.
But the more reactive fixes
the game developers add, the system
becomes less robust and
more complicated to evolve.
While the developers initially
started with an application and
the database to manage.
Now they have to manage a number
of issues related to this
infrastructure management just to
keep up with the load on the system.
Similarly, the database servers
can be effected and corrupted.
The replication and fault tolerance of
them need to be handled separately.
Let's start by going through these issues.
Let's say,
one of the processing nodes went down.
The system needs to manage and
restart the processing and
there will be potentially some
data loss in the meantime.
The system would need to
check every processing node
before it can discard data.
Each note and each database has
to be replicated separately.
Batch computations that need data from
multiple data servers need to access and
maintain use of the data separately which
might end up being quite slow and costly.
Big data processing techniques
we will address in this course,
will help you to reduce the management
of the mentioned complexities,
including failing servers and
breaking compute nodes.
While helping with the scalability of the
management and processing infrastructure.
We will talk about using big data systems
like Spark to achieve data parallel
processing scalability for
data applications on commodity clusters.
We will use to Spark Runtime Libraries and
Programming Models to
demonstrate how big data systems can
be used for application management.
To summarize, what our imaginary game
application needs from big data system.
First of all, there needs to be a way
to use common big data operations
to manage and split large volumes
of events data streaming in.
This means the partitioning and
placement of data in and
out of computer memory along with a model
to synchronize the datasets later on.
The access to data should
be achieved in a fast way.
The game developers need
to be able to deploy
many event processing jobs to
distributed processing nodes at once.
And these are potentially the data
nodes we move the computations to.
It should also enable
reliability of the computing and
enable fault tolerance from failures.
This means enabling
programmable replications and
recovery of event data when needed.
It should be easily
scalable to a distributed set of
nodes where the data gets produced.
It should also enable scaling out.
Scaling out is simply adding new
resources like distributed computers to
process more or faster data at
scale without losing performance.
There are many data
types in an online game.
Although, we talked about
time click events and
scores, it would be easy to imagine
there are graphs of players,
text-based chats, and
images that need to be processed.
Our big data system should
enable processing of such
a mixed variety of data and
potentially optimize handling of
each type separately as well
as together when needed.
In addition, our system should
have been able both streaming and
batch processing, enabling all
the processing to be debuggable and
extensible with minimal effort.
That means being able to handle
operations at small chunks of data
streams with minimal delay,
that is what we call low latency.
While at the same time handle processing
of potentially all available data
in batch form and
all through the same system architecture.
Latency is a word that we use and
hear a lot in big data processing,
here we refer to how fast the data
is being processed, or simply
the difference between production or event
time and processing time of a data entry.
In other words, latency is quantification
of the delay in the processing of
the streaming data in the system.
While some big data
systems are good at it.
Hadoop for instance is not a great choice
for operations that require low latency.
Let's finish by remembering
the real reasons for
all these requirements
of big data processing.
Making a different from processing
in a traditional data architecture.
Big data has varying volume and
velocity requiring the dynamic and
scalable batch and stream processing.
Big data has a variety requiring
management of data in many
different data systems and
integration of it all at scale.
Next, we'll describe
aggregation functions.
We have seen the first query before.
Select count(*) simply
translates to a count function.
Now we could also say
db.Drinkers.find.count.
But using count directly
is more straightforward.
Now, let's ask to count the number
of unique addresses for drinkers.
So, we don't care what the address is.
We just care if it exists.
This is accomplished through
the $exists:true expression.
Thus, if an address exists for
a drinker, it will be counted.
Another area where we need to count is
when we have an array valued attribute,
like places.
If we just want the number
of elements in the raw list,
we'll write db.country.findplaces.length
and we'll get six.
However, if we want distinct values, we'll
use distinct instead of find and then
use the length for counting the number
of distinct elements, in this case 4.
Now, MongoDB uses an internal machinery
called the aggregation framework,
which is modeled on the concept
of data processing pipelines.
That means documents enter
a multi-stage pipeline which transforms
the documents at each stage until
it becomes an aggregated result.
Now we have seeing a similar mechanism for
relational data.
The aggregation pipelines starts
by using the aggregate primitive.
The most basic pipeline stages provides
filters that operate like queries and
the document transformations that
modify the form of the output document.
The primary filter operation is $match,
which is followed by a query condition.
In this case, status is A.
And expectedly, the $match operation
produces a smaller number of documents
to be processed at the next stage.
This is usually followed
by the $group operation.
Now this operation needs to know which
attributes should be grouped together.
In the example here cust_id
is the grouping attribute so
it is passed as a parameter
to the $group function.
Now notice the syntax.
_id:$cust_id says that the grouped
data will have an _id attribute,
and its value will be
picked from the cust_id
attribute from the previous
stage of computation.
Thus, the $ before the cust_id
is telling the system that
cust_id is a known variable in
the system and not a constant.
The $group operation also needs a reducer,
which is a function that operates on an
activity to produce an aggregate result.
In this case, the reduce function is sum,
which operates on the amount
attribute from the previous stage.
Like $cust_id, we use $amount to
indicate that it's a variable.
As we saw in the relational case,
data can be partitioned into chunks on
the same machine or on different machines.
These chunks are called chards.
The aggregation pipeline of MongoDB
can operate on a charded collection.
The grouping operation in MongoDB
can accept multiple attributes like
the four shown here.
Also shown is a post grouping directive
to sort on the basis of two attributes.
The first is a computed count
variable in ascending order.
So the one designates the ascending order.
The next sorting attribute is secondary.
That means if two groups have
the same value for count,
then they'll be further sorted
based on the category value.
But this time the order is descending
because of the -1 directive
In course two we have seen Solar,
a text search engine from Apache.
MongoDB has a built in text search engine
which can be invoked through the same
aggregation framework we saw before.
Imagine that MongoDB documents in this
case are really text documents placed in
a collection called articles.
In this case, the $match directive of
the aggregate function must be told
it's going to perform a text
function on the article's corpus.
The actual text function is $search.
We set search terms like "Hillary
Democrat" such that having
either term in a document will
satisfy the search requirement.
As is the case of any text engine,
the results of any search returns
a list of documents, each with a score.
The next task is to tell MongDB to
sort the results based on textScore.
What's the $meta here?
Meta stands for metadata,
that is additional information.
Remember that the aggregation
operations are executed in a pipeline.
Any step in the pipeline can
produce some extra data, or
metadata, for each processed document.
In this example, the metadata
produced by the search function
is a computed attribute called textScore.
So this directive tells the system to pick
up this specific metadata attribute and
use it to populate the score attribute
which would be used for sorting.
Finally, the $project class
does exactly what is expected.
It tells the system to output only
the title of each document and
suppress its id.
The last item in our
discussion of MongoDB is join.
We have seen that join is a vital
operation for data management operations.
Interestingly, MongoDB introduced this
equivalent of join only in version 3.2.
So, the joining in MongoDB also
happens in the aggregation framework.
There are a few ways of
expressing joins in MongoDB.
We show one here that explicitly performs
a join to a function called look up.
We use an example form
the MongoDB documentation.
Now here are two document collections,
order and inventory.
Notice that the item key in
orders has values abc, jkl, etc.
And the sku key in the inventory has
comparable values abc, def, etc.
So these two are joinable by value.
The way to specify this join,
one can use this query.
The db.orders.aggregate
declaration states that orders is
sort of the home, or local collection.
Now in the aggregate, the function
$lookup needs to know what to look up for
each document in orders.
The from attribute specifies the name
of the collection as inventory.
The next two parameters are the local and
foreign matching keys,
which are item and sku, respectively.
The last item, as:,
is a construction part of
the join operation which says how to
structure the match items into the result.
Now before we show you the results,
let's see what should match.
The abc item in order should
match the abc in sku.
Similarly, the jkl item
should match the jkl in sku.
Okay, but there is one more twist.
Here is the actual result.
The first two records show
exactly what we expect.
There is a new field called
inventory-docs in the batching record.
The third record however,
shows something interesting.
Inventory has two records shown here,
what do they match?
Now they match the empty
document in orders because
orders has a document
whose item field is null.
So it matches documents and
inventory where the sku item is also null,
explicitly as in document 5, or
implicitly as in document 6.
This concludes our discussion of
queries in the context of MongoDB.
In this hands on activity, we'll be
using Pandas to read CSV files and
perform various queries on them.
Pandas is a data analysis library for
Python.
First, we'll create a new
Jupyter Python Notebook.
Next, we will use Pandas to read
a CSV file into a DataFrame.
We'll then view the contents of the
DataFrame and see how to filter rows and
columns of it.
Next, we will perform average and
sum operations on the DataFrame.
And finally, show how to merge two
DataFrames by joining on a single column.
Let's begin.
We'll start by creating
a new iPython notebook.
Clicking on New and
selecting Python 3 under notebooks.
First, we'll import the Pandas
library by writing import pandas.
Remember that in iPython notebooks,
to run a command,
we hold down the shift key and hit Enter.
Next, let's read buyclicks.csv
into a Pandas DataFrame.
We'll put it in a variable
called buyclicksDF.
We'll read it using pandas.read_csv,
and we'll read the buy-clicks.csv file.
We can see the contents of the file by
just running the variable by itself.
And notice that the file has many rows and
then iPython truncates this,
the dot, dot, dot.
We can see only the top five
rows by calling .head(5).
Next, let's look at only two
columns in the buyclicks data.
Let's look at price and user ID.
We can do these by first entering
buyclicks DataFrame in the same text for
specifying only certain columns to
show is open bracket open bracket and
then the name of the columns
you want to view.
So, want your price and
user ID, and again,
we only want to see the first five rows,
so we'll do .head(5).
Now, let's query the buyclicks data for
only the prices less than 3.
First, we'll enter buyclicksDF,
One square bracket,
to filter our particular column,
we enter buyclicksDF and then column name.
Now, we specify the limit of
the query by entering <3.
This shows first five rows where
the price is less than three.
We can also perform aggregate
operations on Panda's DataFrames.
We can sum all the price data by
entering buyclicksDF['price'].sum.
Another aggregate operation we can
perform is looking at the average.
Let's look at the average for price.
The function is called mean.
So, once your buyclicksDF ['price'].mean.
Can also join two DataFrames
on a single column.
First, let's read in another
CSV into a different DataFrame.
We'll read in adclicks.csv.
So we'll says adclicksDF
= pandas.read_csv,
we'll say ('ad-clicks.csv').
To verify that we read this data
successfully, let's look at the contents.
Now, let's combine
the buyclicks DataFrame and
the adclicks data frame
on the user ID call.
We'll put the result in the new
DataFrame called mergeDF.
So we'll say mergeDF = adclicksDF.merge
Then, we need to say which
DataFrame we're merging with,
buyclicksDF, and
the column that we're merging on.
So we'll say on='userid'.
Finally, we can look at the contents
with this merged DataFrame.
So now from MongoDB we will go to
Aerospike which is a key value store.
Key value stores typically offer an API.
That is the way to access data using a
programming language like Python or Java.
We will take a very brief look
at Aerospike, which offers both
a programmatic access and
a limited amount of query access to data.
The data model of Aerospike
is illustrated here.
Data are organized in lean spaces which
can be in memory or on flash disks.
Name spaces are top level data containers.
The way you collect data in name spaces
relates to how data is stored and managed.
So name space contains records,
indexes, and policies.
Now policies dictate name space
behavior like how data is stored,
whether it's on RAM or disk, or
how how many replicas exist for
a record, and when records expire.
A name space can contain sets,
you can think of them as tables.
So here there are two sets,
people and places,
and a set of records
which are not in any set.
Within a record,
data is stored in one or many bins.
Bins consist of a name and a value.
The example written here is in Java, and
you don't have to know Java to
follow the main point here.
Here we are creating indexes on key
value data that's handled by Aerospike.
This data set comes from Twitter.
Each field of a tweet is extracted and
put into Aerospike as a key value pair.
So we declare the namespace to be
example, and the record set to be tweet.
The name of the index to be TestIndex,
and the name of the bin as user name.
Since this index is stored
on disk an SQL-like command,
like SHOW INDEX, shows the content
of the index as you can see here.
This routine shows
how data can be inserted into
Aerospike programmatically.
Again, the goal is to point out a few
salient aspects of data insertion
regardless of the syntax of the language.
Now since this is a key value store,
one first needs to define the key.
This line here says that the key in
the namespace call example, and set call
tweet, is the value of the function getId,
which returns the ID of a tweet.
When the data is populated,
we are essentially creating bins.
Here, user name is the attribute and
the screen name obtained
from the tweet is the value.
The actual insertion
happens here in the client.
The client.put statement,
where we need to mention the key and
the bins we have just created.
Now why are we inserting
two bins at a time?
Two bins with two ids and user name?
This is an idiosyncrasy
of the Aerospike client.
After data is inserted one can
create other data using AQL
which is very much like SQL.
This screenshot shows a part of
the output of a simple select star query.
Now in your hands-on exercise, you'll be
able to play with the Aerospike data.
This is just a screenshot showing
the basic query syntax of AQL,
that is Aerospike Query Language,
and a few examples.
The last two lines show a couple of
interesting features of the language.
The operation between 0 and 99,
is a nicer way of stating a range query,
which gives a lower and
upper limits on a variable.
The last line shows the operation cost,
which transforms one type
of data to another type.
Here it transforms coordinates,
that is latitude and longitude data,
to a JSON format called GeoJSON which is
designed to represent geographic data
in a JSON structure.
We will finish our coverage of queries
with a quick reference to an advanced
topic, which is beyond
the scope of this course.
Now you have seen in prior courses that
streaming data is complex to process
because a stream is infinite in nature.
Now does this have any impact on
query languages and evaluation?
The answer is that it absolutely does.
We'll mention one such impact here.
This shows a pictorial
depiction of streaming data.
The data is segmented into five pieces,
shown in the white boxes in the upper row.
These can be gathered, for example every
few seconds, or every 200 data objects.
The query defines a window to select
key of these data objects
as a unit of processing.
Here case three.
So three units of data
are picked up in a window unit.
To get the next window it
is moved by two units,
this is called a slide of the window.
Since the window size is three and
the slide is two,
one unit of information overlaps
between the two consecutive windows.
The lower line in this diagram shows
the initialized item, let's ignore it,
followed by two window sets of
data records for processing.
Thus the query language therefore,
will have to specify a query
that's an SQL query, over a window,
which is also specified in the query.
Now in a traffic data stream example,
the SQL statement might look like this.
Where the window size is 30 second, and
the slide is the same size as window
giving output every 30 seconds.
So streaming data results in changes
in both the query language and
the way queries are processed.
In this hands-on activity,
we will be querying documents in MongoDB.
First, we will start a MongoDB server and
then run the MongoDB Shell.
We will see how to show the databases and
collections in the MongoDB Server.
We will look at an example
document in the database and
see how to find distinct values for
a field.
Next, we will search for
specific field values and
see how to filter fields
returned in a query.
Finally, we will search using
regular expressions and operators.
Let's begin,
first we'll start the MongoDB server.
Open the terminal window by clicking on
the terminal icon, the top of the toolbar.
We'll cd into
Downloads/big-data-3-mongodb.
We'll start the MongoDB server by running
./mongodb/bin/mongod --dbpath db.
The arguments dbpath db
specified that the database on
MongoDB is in the directory named db.
Run this to start the server.
Next, we'll start the MongoDB Shell so
that we can perform queries.
We'll open another terminal window.
Again, cd into
Downloads/big-data-3-mongodb.
We'll start the shell by
running ./mongodb/bin/mongo.
We can see what databases are available in
the MongoDB server by running the command,
show dbs.
We've created the sample database
with JSON data from Twitter.
We can use the use command
to change to this database.
We'll run use sample.
We can see the collections in this
database by running, show collections.
There's only one collection called users.
So, all of the queries will be
using the users collection.
Let's count how many documents there
are in the users collection by writing
db.users.count.
We can look at one of these documents
by writing db.users.findOne.
This document contains
Jason from a Twitter tweet.
You can see the field names
here with their values.
There are also nested fields
under the user field.
And each of these fields also has values.
You can find the distinct values for
particular field,
by using the distinct command.
Let's find the distinct values for
the username field.
We'll write
db.users.distinct("user_name").
Next, let's find all the documents in
this collection where the field username
matches the specific value.
The value we'll search for
is ActionSportsJax.
We'll run the command db.users.find.
And the field name is username, and
the value we're searching for
is ActionSportsJax.
Results of this query is
compressed all in one line.
If we append the .pretty
to the previous query.
We can see the formatted output.
So we'll run the same
command with append .pretty.
We can filter the fields
returned from the queries.
Let's perform the same query again but
only show the tweet_id field.
We can do this by adding a second
argument to the find command.
So we'll run the same command again,
but add a second argument,
saying tweet_ID: 1.
The underscore ID field is a primary
key used in all documents in MongoDB.
You can turn this off by adding
another field to our filter.
We'll run the same command again,
but turn of _ID.
Next, we use the regular expression search
to find strings containing the document.
For example, if we want to find all
the tweets containing the text FIFA,
we can run db.users.find tweet_text FIFA.
There are no results in this query
because this query is searching for
tweet text equals FIFA.
That is the entire contents and
the value of tweet_text must be FIFA.
Instead, if we want to look for
FIFA anywhere in the tweet_text,
we can do a regular expression search.
To do this,
replace the double quotes with slashes.
So we'll run the same command again.
But replacing double quotes with slashes.
We can count how many documents are
returned by this query by running the same
command again, but appending .count.
We can also search for documents in
MongoDB where the field values are greater
than or less than a certain value.
For example, lets find tweet
mention count greater than six.
We'll run db.users.find, and
the field name is tweet_mentioned_count.
And we want to look for the value
where this field is greater than six.
So I'll enter a .
In a prior course we looked at JSON as
an example of semi-structured data,
and we demonstrated that JSON
data can be thought of as a tree.
In this course,
we'll focus on querying JSON data.
Before we start, lets review
the details of the JSON structure, and
get an initial sense of how
to query this form of data.
Let's consider a simple
JSON collection and
look at the structures,
substructures actually, it's composed of.
The atomic element in the structure
is a key value pair, for example,
name is the key and sue is the value,
in this case, an atomic string value.
To query a key value pair,
we should be able perform one basic
operation given the key, return the value.
Now, the value can also be an array,
an array is a list.
So the query operations on it can either
be on its position in the list or
on the value.
Thus, we should be able to ask for the
second element of the array called badges.
Or we should be able to seek objects
of which the key called badges
has a value of blue.
Notice here that the document
collection here is itself an array,
within square brackets and
it's just two elements in it.
The top level array does not have a key,
by default it's called db.
These key value peers
are structured as tuples,
often with a name In the snippet shown,
favorites has a tuple
of two key value pairs.
Now, tuples can be thought of as
relational records, as the operations
would include, projection of an attribute,
and selection over a set of tables.
On the other hand,
the area called 'points',
has two tuples, these two tuples named.
As you will see, we'll address
these tuples by their positions.
Finally, this one has nesting,
that means a mini structure can be
embedded within another structure.
So we need operations
that will let us navigate
from one structure to any of
it's embedded structures.
Now just like a basic SQL query states,
which parts of which records from one or
more people should be reported,
a MongoDB query states
which parts of which documents from
a document collection should be returned.
The primary query is expressed as a find
function, which contains two arguments and
an optional qualifier, there are four
things to notice in this function.
The first is the term collection,
this tells the system which
document collection to use, and
therefore is roughly similar to the From
clause when restricted to one table.
So if the name of the collection is beers,
the first part would say db.beers.find.
The second item is a query filter
which lists all conditions that
the retrieved documents should satisfy,
so it's like a Where clause.
Now, if we want to return everything,
then this filter is left blank.
Otherwise, we'll fill it in a couple
of ways shown in the next few slides.
The third term is a projection class
which is essentially a list of variables
that we want to see in the output.
The fourth and last item sits
after the find function ends and
is separated by a dot,
it's called a cursor modifier.
The word cursor relates back
to SQL where cursor is defined
as a block of results that is
returned to the user in one chunk.
This becomes important when the set of
results is too large to be returned all
together, and
the user may need to specify how much, or
what portion of results
they actually want.
So, we'll start out with a few queries,
where we show how the same query
can be expressed in SQL, and
in MongoDB The first query
wants everything from Beers.
The SQL query is structured
on the table Beers, and
the SELECT * asks to return all rows.
In MongoDB the same query
is more succincted,
since the name of the collection
is already specified in
calling the find function,
the body of the find function is empty.
That means there are no query conditions
and no projection clauses in it.
The second query
needs to return the variables beer and
price for all records.
So the find function here needs an empty
query condition denoted by the open and
closed brace symbols, but the projection
clauses are specifically identified.
There is a 1 if an attribute is output and
a 0 if it is not.
As a shortcut,
only variables with 1 are required.
Okay, so when do you use 0?
A common situation is the following.
Every MongoDB document has
an identifier named _id.
By default every query will
return the id of the document.
If you don't want it to return
this designated attribute,
you should explicitly say, _id:0.
Next we will add query conditions.
That is the equivalent of
the Where clause in SQL.
Our query number three has the query
condition where name is equal to a value.
In MongoDB, that equal to translate
to a variable colon value form.
Notice the symbol used for
a string is quotes.
Query four is more interesting for
two reasons.
First, we see a way in which
the distinct operation is specified.
Notice here that the primary query
function is not find any more but
a new function called distinct.
As we'll see later again in our slides,
MongoDB uses a few special query
functions for some of the operations.
So, you need to know, which function
should be used in what context,
when you write MogoDB queries.
Secondly, in this query,
we have a non-equality condition,
namely, the price is greater than 15.
This example shows MongoDB style
of using operators in a query.
It's always variable:
followed by MongoDB's name for the
operator, and then the comparison value.
So where would you find
MongoDB's operators?
Here are some of the operators
supported in MongoDB.
These operators and others are listed
in the URL shown at the bottom.
The operators shown here are color coded.
The top blue set
are the comparison operators.
We see the $gt, greater than,
operation that we used in the last slide.
The green colored operations are array
operations which we'll see shortly.
And the yellow operators at the bottom
are logical operations that
combine two conditions in different ways
like the AND operation we saw in SQL.
Now, the last operator $nor,
is interesting,
because it is used to specify queries
when neither of two conditions must hold.
For example, find all beer
whose name is neither bad nor
is the price less than $6 per bottle.
Now I would strongly encourage you
to play with these operators in
your hands on session.
Now I'm sure you remember
the like query in SQL.
MongoDB uses regular expressions
to specify partial string matches.
Now some of you may not know
what a regular expression is.
Let's first use some examples.
The first example is the same query
we saw before when we're asking for
beer manufacturers,
whose name has a sub string A-M in it,
so A-M can appear
anywhere within the name.
To do this,
the query condition first states that
it is going to use a $regex operation.
And then we have to give
the partial string as /am/.
Then it gives the directive
that this match
should be case insensitive by placing
an i after the partial string.
And if we just wanted to do names we
would stop right after the find function.
But here we also want to do a count,
which is a post operation
after the find, so we use .count
at the end of the find function.
Now, what if we have the same query,
but we want the partial string A-m?
To appear at the beginning of the name and
you'd like the A to really
be a capital letter.
In this case we use
the caret sign to indicate
that the partial string is at
the beginning of the name.
Naturally we also drop the i at the end
because the match is no longer case
insensitive A more complex
partial string pattern will be a case
where our name starts with capital A-m,
then has a number of characters
in the middle and ends with corp.
So for the first part,
the string pattern is ^Am.
For the second part, that is,
any character in the middle, we use dot
to represent any character, and star
to represent zero or more occurrences.
For the third part, we say corp but
put a dollar at the end to say that it
must appear at the end of the string.
The regular expression pattern is
a sub-language, in itself, and
is supported by most
programming languages today.
We will refer you to the following
URL to learn more about it.
Also, note an example that,
instead of saying, find.count,
we can directly use the count function,
natively defined in MongoDB.
One important feature of JSON is that
everything contain arrays, as a type of
collection objects, this enables us
to query arrays in multiple ways.
One of them,
is to consider an array as a list and
perform intersection operations,
the first query shows this.
The data item is shown on the right.
It has the area value attribute
called tags with three entries.
The first query asks if two specific
strings belong to the array.
In other words, it wants to get
the document whose tagged attribute
intersects with the query supplied array.
In this case, there is an intersection and
the document is returned.
In the second case, it is asking for
a documents who's tags
attribute has no intersection.
Now notice the $nin operator so
there is no intersection with this list.
So in this document there exists and
intersection so nothing will be returned.
A different kind of array query uses
the positions of the list elements and
wants to extract a portion of the array.
This is illustrated in
the third query which asks for
the second and third items of the array.
To encode this in MongoDB,
we use the $slice operator
which needs two parameters,
the number of variable limits to skip,
and the number of variable limits
to extract after skipping.
In this case, we need to extract items two
and three, so the skip value is one and
the number of items is two,
thus returning summer and Japanese.
Now, we could get the same result if we
pose the query using the last statement.
In this case, the minus says that
the system should count from the end and
the true says that it should
extract two elements.
Now if we omitted the minus sign,
it will come from the beginning and
fetch the first two elements.
Finally, we can also ask for a document
who's second element in tags is summer.
In this case we use an array index
tags.1 to denote the second element.
Compound statements are queries
with multiple query conditions that
are combined using logical operations.
The query shown here has one condition,
which is the and,are in terms of MongoDB,
the $and of three different clauses.
The last clause is
the most straight forward,
it states that the desired
item should not be Coors.
The first clause is an or, that is,
a $or, between two sub-conditions,
A the prices either 3.99, or B it is 4.99.
The second clause is also an or
of two sub conditions,
A the rating is good, and
B the quantity is less than 20.
This query shows that the $and and
the $or operators need a list
that is an array of arguments.
To draw a quick comparison,
here's the example of the same
query imposed with SQL.
Now, an important feature of
semi-structured data is that
it allows nesting.
We showed three documents here,
where there is an area named points,
which in turn has two tuples with
the elements points and bonus.
Let's assume that these three
documents are part of a collection, so
they form three items in
an area called users.
Our goal is to show how we can
write queries to extract data
from these documents with nesting.
The first query wants
to find documents for
which, the value of points should
be less than or equal to 80.
Now, which ones?
Now, points.0,
refers to the first tuple
under the outer points, and
points.0.points, refers to
the first element of that tuple.
Clearly, only the second
documents satisfies this query.
Now, what happens if we have
the same query but we drop the zero?
Now, we are looking for points.points
without specifying the array index.
This means that the points element in
any of the tuples should
have a value of 80 or less.
So now, the first and the second
document will satisfy the query.
We can put multiple conditions
as seen in the third query.
It looks for a document where the points
element of a tuple, should be utmost 81,
and the bonus should be exactly 20, and
clearly the second document qualifies.
But does the third document qualify?
In this case, the first tuple
satisfies points greater than 81 and
the second tuple satisfies
bonus equal to 20.
The answer is no, because the comma
is treated as an implicit and
condition within the same double,
as shown in the yellow braces.
Now remember that we said in course
two that all semi-structured
data can be viewed as a tree.
Now, what if I pick a node of a tree and
ask for all the descendents of that node?
That would require the system
to recursively get chideNodes,
over increasing depth from the given node.
Unfortunately, at this time,
MongoDB does not support recursive search.
A different kind of scaling problem arises
when we try to answer queries over a large
number of data sources, but before we do
that let's see how a query is answered in
the virtual data integration setting.
We are going to use a toy
scenario in a medical setting
simple as we have four data sources.
Each with one table for
the sake of simplicity.
Notice that two sources, S1 and
S3, have the same schema.
Now this is entirely possible because
sources may be independent of each other.
Further, there is no guarantee that
they would have the same exact content.
Maybe these two sources represent
clinics at different locations.
So next, we look at the target schema.
For simplicity, let's consider that
it's not an algorithmically creative
probabilistic mediator schema but just a
manually designed schema with five tables.
But while we assume that
the target schema is fixed
we want the possibility that
we can add more sources.
That means more clinics
as the system grows.
Now I'm beginning to
add the schema mapping.
Now there are several techniques
of specifying schema mappings.
One of them is called Local-as-View.
This means we write the relations in each
source as a view over the target schema.
But this way of writing the query,
as we can see here, may seem odd to you.
It's called syntax, but
you don't need to know it.
Just as an example, the first few things
the treats relation in S1 maps to,
so you see that arrow, that means maps to.
So it maps to the query select doctor,
chronic disease from treats patient,
has chronic disease.
Where treatspatient.patient Is equal
to has chronic disease dot patient.
We see the query here in the yellow box.
The only thing we should notice here
is that the select class on the query
has two attributes doctor and
chronic disease which are exactly the same
attributes of the treats relation in S1.
Now let's ask a query that
gives the target schema.
Which doctors are responsible for
discharging patients?
Which translates to
the SQL query shown here.
Now, the problem is how to translate
this query to a query that can
be sent to the sources.
Now ideally this should be simplest query
with no extra operations as shown here.
S3 treats means treats
relation in sources 3.
Now you can see the ideal answer.
To find such an optimal query
reformulation, it turns out that this
process is very complex and becomes
worse as a number of sources increases.
Thus query reformulation
becomes a significant scalability problem
in a big data integration scenario.
Let's look at the second use case
public health is a significant
component of our healthcare system.
Public health systems monitor detect and
take action when epidemics strike.
Not so long ago we have witnessed public
health concerns due to Anthrax virus,
the swine flu and the bird flu.
But these epidemics caused a group
called WADDS to develop a system for
disease surveillance.
This system would connect all local
hospitals in the Washington, DC area, and
is designed to exchange
disease information.
For example, if a hospital lab has
identified a new strain of a virus,
other hospitals and the Centers for
Disease Control, CDC,
in the network,
should be able to know about it.
It should be clear that this needs a data
integration solution where the data
sources would be the labs, the data would
be the lab tests medical records and
even genetic profiles of the virus and
the subjects who might be infected.
The table here shows the different
components with this architecture.
We will just digest the necessary
parts for our requirement.
Just know that RIM which stands for
Reference Information Model is global
schema that this industry has developed
and expects to use as a standard.
Why we want to exchange and combine new
information from different hospitals?
Every hospital is independent and
can implement their own information
system any way they see fit.
Therefore even when there
are standards like HL-7 that
specify what kind of data a held
cache system should have an exchange.
There are considerable variations in
the implementation of the standard itself.
For example the two wide boxes show
a difference in representation
of the same kind of data, this should
remind you of the data variety problem.
Let's say, we have a patient
with ID 19590520 whose lab
reports containing her plasma protein
measurements are required for
analyzing her health condition.
The problem is that the patient
went to three different clinics and
four different labs which all
implement the standards differently.
On top of it?
Each clinic uses its own
electronic medical record system
which we have a very large amount of data.
So the data integration system's job is to
transform the data from the source schema
to the schema of the receiving
system in this case the rim system.
This is sometimes called
the data exchange problem.
Informally a data exchange
problem can be defined like this.
Suppose we have a given database
whose relations are known.
Let us say we also know
the target database's schema and
the constraints the schema will satisfy.
Further we know the desired schema
mappings between the source and
this target schema.
What we do not know is how to populate
the tuples in the target database.
From the tuples in the socialization in
such a way that both schema mappings and
target constraints
are simultaneously satisfied.
In many domains like healthcare,
a significant amount of effort has been
spend by the industry in
standardizing schemas and values.
For example LOINC is a standard for
medical lab observations.
Here item like systolic blood pressure or
gene mutation are encoded in this
specific way as given by this standard.
So, if we want to write that
the systolic/diastolic pressure of
a individual is 132 by 90, we'll not write
out the string systolic blood pressure,
but use the code for it.
The ability to use standard code
is not unique to healthcare data.
The 50 states of the US all
have two letter abbreviations.
Generalizing therefore, whenever we have
data such as the domain is finite and have
a standard set of code available, we give
a new opportunity of handling big deal.
Mainly, reducing the data
size through compression.
The compression refers to a way of
creating an encoded
representation of data.
So that this encoder form is smaller
than the original representation.
A common encoding method is
called dictionary encoding.
Consider a database with 10 million
record of patient visits a lab.
Each record indicates a test and
its results.
Now we show it this way like
in a columnar structure
to make the point that the data is kept
in a column stored relational database
rather than a row store
relational database.
Now consider the column for test code.
Where the type of test is codified
according to the standard.
We replace a string representation
of the standard by a number.
The mapping between
the original test code and
the encoded number are also
stored separately.
Now suppose there
are a total of 500 tests.
So this separate table called
the dictionary here has 500 rows,
which is clearly much smaller
than ten million right?
Now 500 distinct values can be
represented by encoding them in 9 bits,
because 2 to the power of 9 is 512.
Other encoding techniques would be applied
to attributes like date and patient ID.
That's full large data we cannot reduce
the number of total actual rules.
So we have to store all ten million rules.
But we can reduce the amount of space
required by storing data in a column
oriented data store and
by using compression, indeed modern
systems use credit processing algorithms
to operate directly on compress data.
Data compression is an important
technology for big data.
And just like is a set of qualified
terms for lab tests, clinical data
also uses SNOMED which stands for
systematized nomenclature of medicine.
SNOMED is a little more
than just a vocabulary.
It does have a vocabulary of course.
The vocabulary is the collection
of medical terms in human and
medicine to provide codes, terms, synonyms
and definitions that cover anatomy,
diseases, findings, procedures,
micro organisms, substances etcetera.
But it also has relationships.
As you can see,
a renal cyst is related to kidney because
kidney's the finding site of a renal cyst.
If we query against an ontology,
it would look like a graph grid.
In this box,
we are asking to find all patient
findings with a benign tumor morphology.
In terms of querying, we are looking for
edges of a graph where one noticed
the concept that we need to find which is
connected to a node called benign neoplasm
that is benign tumor through an edge
called associated morphology
that applying this query against
the data here produces all benign tumors
of specific organs as you can
see by the orange rounded group.
But now that we have these terms,
we can use these terms to search
outpatient records with these terms would
have been used so
what's the essence of this used case.
This is can shows that an in division
system in a public health domain and
in many other domains must
be able to handle variety.
In this case there's a Global Schema
called RiM shown here all queries and
analyses performed by a data analysts
should be against this global schema.
However, the actual data which is
generated by different medical facilities
would need to be transformed
into data in this schema.
This would require not only
format conversions, but
it would need to respect all constraints
imposed by the source and by the target.
For example, a source may not distinguish
between an emergency surgical procedure
and a regular surgical procedure.
But the target may want to
put them in different tables.
We also saw that
the integration system for
this used case would need to use
quantified data but this gives
us the opportunity to use data compression
to gauge story and query efficiency.
In terms of variety, we saw how
relational data like patient records XML
data like HL7 events, and
graph data like ontologies, are co-used.
To support this, the integration
system must be able to do both model
transformation and query transformation.
Query transformation is the process of
taking a query on the target schema.
Converting it to a query
against a different data model.
For example, part of an SQL query against
the RIM may need to go to snowmad and
hence when you to be converted to
a graph query in the snowmad system.
Model transformation is
a process of taking data
represented in one model
in one source system and
converting it to an equivalent data
in another model the target system.
Hello, my name is Victor Lou.
I am the Solutions Engineer of
Global Philanthropy of Daameer.org.
Helping researchers, academia,
and non-profits find the insights
that matter using data.
Today I am here to give you
a production environment,
personalized music recommendation project.
That was done for PonoMusic and
so what is Pono Music?
Pono Music is revolutionizing music
listening by bringing back native,
high-resolution audio.
It's the way that artists intended and
recorded their music.
Neil Young, the iconic artist and
musician is also the founder and CEO.
Pono Music is the only complete
high-resolution music ecosystem.
That includes the Pono player, the Pono
Music store, the Pono Music community.
They have been super
generous in allowing us to
take a look behind the scenes as how
we built out the recommendations.
So, David Meer supports their mission
by providing a music recommendation
engine that is both scalable and
flexible as Pono grows their user base.
Let's begin by visiting Pono
music's website as you can see,
they have a few shelves that focus on
various recommendations that are not
tailored to each individual user.
If you login,
then an additional shelf would appear
that would deliver the recommendations
that are created in data gear.
So how does DataMirror accomplish this.
In a nutshell, DataMirror is a end to end,
antalis platform which contains ingestion,
preparation analysis, visualization and
operationalization all the same platform.
And having all the capabilities
in one platform is superior to
traditional technology stack.
Integration between disparate technologies
brings a lot of unnecessary challenges.
We take advantage of open
source big data technologies.
Specifically, we run natively and
Hadoop and Spark for our back end.
And we leverage D3JS on the front end for
visualizations.
Our Excel-like interface makes it easy for
folks who don't know how to code to
also get in with the data modeling.
It is very much self-service.
In the case of Pono Music's
data mirror deployment,
we have deployed a Hadoop
on Amazon on web services.
But we can also be deployed off premise if
needed it doesn't have
to be in the clouds.
In fact, we could work with many many
different distributions of Hadoop.
We can access dean rear through
any modern web browser.
As you can see here we're using Google
Chrome but it works on any browser, right?
So lets go ahead and take a look at
the a; let's log into data grip,
so we're going to go ahead and
log in here..
So what you're seeing here is the browser
tab and we can see various artifacts
which include connections such
as connections to the pull nose,
salesforce.com instance or
a connection to AWS S3 instance.
Because DataMirror comes with so
many prebuilt connectors which include
Connections to salesforce.com and S3.
We can easily grant access to
those systems in order to pull or
push data in and out of the dev.
For example, let's take a quick look at
the salesforce.com configuration here.
As you can see, we've already configured
salesforce as the connector type.
When we hit next here,
we'll we that you can authorize
a data manager to retrieve data.
We're not going to do it because
this is a production environment, so
I don't want to disrupt the pools.
But if we were to click it, it'll give
us a salesfloor.com blogging stream.
And so as soon as we login, the Datameer
would have access via the O-Off token.
And so this is valid for a period of time.
I'm going to go ahead and
hit the cancel button as this
is a production environment.
And so now we're ready to look
at an import job artifact.
So this is the sales force import job and
as you can see we go in here and
we configure it.
We can see that it's connected to
the Pono Music SMDC connection.
I'm going to go ahead and
hit next here.with salesforce.com,
we just have to simply define the SOQL,
which is basically a querying
language that's based on SQL.
To locate data contained within
the salesforce.com objects.
You can see the select statement here,
you can also see the familiar
from statement, and you can also
see the where statement as well.
So in order to protect
the privacy of the users,
Datameer has the capability to obfuscate
sort of columns that are sensitive.
And so in other words, we can scramble
sensitive fields such as email or
physical addresses.
And at this point in time, I'm going to
go ahead and cancel out, and I'm going to
show the next part of this demo in
an obfuscated workbook environment.
The artifacts contained in the obfuscated
folders are duplicates of the import job
of the workbook from their production
counterparts as you can see here.
So as you can see in the import
job settings we have configured
the same connections here but
for the obfuscated columns here.
Now we're obfuscating the owner
email as well as the street address.
Now we hit Next here.
And so you can see, various fields are
being pulled here from Salesforce, right.
And in particular,
I want to highlight the.
The owner email, that field, so as you
can see these are the obfuscated fields.
Similarly, the actual street address,
that's also masked as well.
I'm going to go ahead and hit Cancel.
I will go back to, rather we're going to
go check out the workbook environment,
which is where we do the preparation and
analysis.
To the obfuscated workbook environment.
As you can see we're starting
with a raw source of data here.
This was the data that was
contained in the data sheet.
Take note that there's a variety of icons
that indicate different types of sheets.
So you could see here this
is the raw data type.
This is a regular worksheet.
You have a union sheet and
you have a joint sheet and
we'll go into a little bit
more detail as we get to them.
So, as you can see,
the interface is very much like Excel.
Looking at the second sheet pairs, and
it's using a function called group by.
So the group by function is a type of
aggregation function in Datameer speak.
As you can see, you can build
the functions by pointing and clicking.
But you can also enter the formula
to create nested functions or
Apply arithmetic
operations just as a cell.
We take all the unique combinations
of albums purchased for
each of the unique email
using a group pair function.
Then we pull out each of the elements
of the pairings using a list element
function, so let's see here.
If you were to build a function
from scratch, you can see this.
So then you create a group by function,
and then direct it at a column.
You basically pass it to argument.
To find out the occurrence
of each pairing of albums,
we're going to go ahead and
look at this LR sheet.
And so these are, we're using group
by functions as well here, so
we're grouping by the first item one,
and then item two.
And then, we're doing a group count,
which is counting the frequency
of occurrences of those cells.
Similarly, we're going to
do a similar thing but
with the item two first now, and then
item one, and then doing a group count.
And the reason is,
we don't care about the order.
And so, we repeat this on the next sheet
reversing the order of the albums to make
sure that we capture all the combinations
since the order doesn't matter to us.
And then we use our unit sheet function
to append the second frequency
counting sheet to the first frequency
counting sheet, as you can see here.
It's drag and drop, of course, and
so we've connected them together.
You can do multi-sheets but
in this case we only have two, right.
So it's, okay.
We ignore the co-occurrent set sheet as it
is currently not used in the final output.
We were kind of experimenting
with other recommendation models.
We're rebuilding those workbooks.
So one of the really cool features for
we can execute the workbook, but
deselect the storage of
intermediary sheets.
This means that we only need
relevant functions are executed
at a to the data lineage of columns that
are contained in the selector sheet.
Moving on, we have to create
a separate sheet from the raw data,
that counts the number of times an album
occurs across all of the purchases.
So you can see here, which students will
buy an album and then we do a count.
We bring the code occurrences and
the frequency together using the join
feature as you can see,
it is a drag and drop interface.
You got the obfuscated workbook
each of the worksheets here and
within each worksheets,
you got various columns.
You can bring those, you can drag and
drop them into here to do the joins.
You can do different types of joins,
you got the inner, outer, etc.
You can also do multi column joins.
You can do multi sheet joins.
You can also select which columns
you want to keep during the join.
Go ahead and cancel out here.
Datameer does not allow us to add
additional functions to a joint sheet so
we duplicate it by right clicking and
then hitting the duplicate button.
And then we create the next sheet,
which contains a link to columns, so
it will be linked to the rating sheet.
This is, see the link columns back
to the joint sheets and then.
We simply add a calculation
where it's the number of times
the co-occurrence occurs divided by
the number of times that the first album
in the column appears
throughout the data set.
The idea is to give a high recommendation
for albums that appear frequently
together While simultaneously
penalizing albums that are too common.
And so at this point,
I would like to write a few more joins
that bring together the album ID,
the email,
recommended album ID based on the album
ID and email, so take a look here.
So, as you can see here and then,
before we finish,
we also do an anti joint by performing
the outer left joint with
the almighty in the email.
And then filtering, so this is,
by the way, this is a double column joint.
And then we do a filter, so
then we filter out all the, for
the obfuscated owner
fields that are empty.
We apply a filter to it.
So finally, we use a few group I
functions to do some deep duplication,
so we use group by functions again.
And then, so we make sure that the album
functions are unique for each user and
then we use a group max function.
In order to preserve the highest
rating for each of the unique
recommendations the final desired
output is on the recommenders sheet.
It leverages the group top end function,
so you can see here group top numbers.
So we only want to look at the to
20 recommendations for each user.
And in addition,
we also create a email row number field,
which is a key that needed for
salesforce.com, and
it is generated by a simple
concatenation function here.
Something that note that [SOUND] is
big on data governance, data lineage.
As you can see, we can keep track of
how all the raw data flows through
from the raw data set all
the way to the end product.
So each workbook functions can be
also exported in JSON format to keep
track of revision history.
We're not ready to operationalize
things and so how do we do it?
Get our workbook configurations.
Go ahead and exit out of the workbook.
Let's go back to
the production environment.
As you can see,
the workbook recalculation retriggers
when the import job is completed.
We also only retain the latest results, so
we select purge historical results,
as you can see here.
As I mentioned earlier, a data mirror
makes it easy to operationalize a workbook
because we only select
the final output sheets.
And, so you see everything's unchecked
except for the recommended sheet.
And Datameer basically will automatically
determine what is a critical path
of the intermediary sheets to
produce the desired output sheet.
Once the recommendation
workbook is calculated,
then this triggers the export job run.
I'm going to go ahead and
move to the export job artifact.
Exit out of this.
Go ahead and save, or not save.
We'll see the export job,
let's go ahead and configure that.
Hit Next, Share.
CSV outputs, so.
This triggers the export job to run,
which is how we basically push
the results of the recommendations to S3.
We elected to use S3 because we
are already hosting at services and
S3 is an affordable storage solution.
We cannot push directly to
salesforce.com at the present because
It's a only connection.
Therefore, we need to push
data to the storage area,
which can be scheduled for using Apex.
A general challenge for
is the role limitation on each pool.
Fortunately, DataMirror comes
with the option to push
files that are broken
into one megabyte chunks.
So as you can see here in
advanced settings 1 megabyte, and
then we set a type of
consecutive numbering scheme.
And so it's dynamic naming conventions
using time stamps and numbering for
each of the chunks.
So that sums up the current
co-curds/d deployment.
As you've seen, we have easily
integrated data from Salesforce.com,
created a recommendation model, and
set up a push to S3 automatically for
easy consumption back to Salesforce.com.
Finally, we operationalized this by
triggering each of the steps sequentially
all in sitting on top of
the powerful Hadoop platform.
What's next?
Well, Pono Music is working on
implementing Google Analytics tracking for
each user at the Apple pages.
So let's go back to
the Apple Music Store here.
Just for an example, let's take a look
at the Train Led Zeppelin Two Album.
As you can see all of those album
IDs that we were looking at earlier,
these are actually embedded in the URL.
This means that in the near future, we
can actually adapt recommendations based
on the buying behavior to recommendations
based on both buying and browser behavior.
We can look at recommendations based on
genre, perhaps we can try to look at most
recent purchases or browsing behavior in
the last three to six to nine months.
Or we could use album metadata such as
album release date to give additional
recommendations.
Also, it is quite simple to just
duplicate the recommendations workbook in
[INAUDIBLE] to try any
number of these options.
And so,
that means we can do a lot of AB testing,
as we track how users react to each of
the modified recommendation algorithms.
The possibilities are literally endless.
So anyhow, thanks again for
checking out how Data Mirror
builds a simple code current
recommendation engine for music.
Please feel free to direction questions or
comments to me at
victor.liu@datamirror.com.
Thanks again.
Amarnath just finished overviewing
querying and integrational big data.
Although, fundamental understanding
of these concepts are important.
Some of these tasks can be accomplished
using graphical user interface
based tools or software products.
In this short module,
we introduce you to two of those tools.
Splunk and Datameer.
We have selected a few videos from
the site of our sponsors Splunk,
to give you an overview of using such
tools for different applications.
You will also have a short
hands-on activity on Splunk.
In addition,
we provide you a comprehensive video on
using Datamere in
the digital music industry.
Keep in mind, Splunk and
Datamere are just two of the many
tools in this category, but
they represent a huge industry.
Open XC is an open source hardware-software platform.
We wanted to see what correlations we could actually create within this model dashboards.
It plugs into your car, and it gives you all the data that you can possibly want.
What we're interested in is looking at how you
can make the car much more modular and customizable,
getting a lot of this data and afford cars
out and letting developers do whatever they want with it.
You could kind of like update technology as technology progresses.
So what we're really trying to do is like catch up with
the consumer electronics design cycle not the automotive design cycle types.
The clock hasn't started yet.
One of the tests that we did was a gas car versus an electric car.
So we're trying to see which is faster,
which is expecting the most energy,
which is the most cost efficient.
And we wanted to
measure doesn't electric car driver drive different than a gas car driver.
So actually by using the Open XC data,
and by splunking that creating links in
dashboards will give it to match ups and correlations.
It all comes down to how much are they mashing the gas.
We've been internally calling that dashboard the "Lead Foot Dashboard".
Who's the most efficient driver?
There's one of our drivers actually going low and
slow and actually using into the brakes not really gnashing on the gas,
and driving more like a normal person would.
When you drive an electric car, it's a lot quicker off the line than a gas powered car.
So, we find people kind of smashing
on the gas pedal but sort of easing up on the electric pedal.
So I've got some data for you here.
We see. What's this I'm doing?
It says you're doing.
There we go.
Battery car is high. There you go.
Hurry up.
There we go. We don't even need because Open XC, We just cut it.
These are basically all of
the sensor readings that are being broadcast from that Firefly box.
It's plugged into the diagnostics port of the car.
It's about how much power can we kind of give
away in order to incentivize a community of makers.
We want to be able to actually harness that and create
an environment where they can much more quickly,
experiment with our ideas,
enrich the platform in general,
make our vehicles in that sense more valuable.
In this hands on activity,
we will be performing queries in Splunk.
First, we will open a browser and
login to Splunk.
Next, we will import a CSV file and
search its contents.
We will see how to filter fields for
specific values and
also perform statistical
calculations on the data.
Let's begin.
First, open a web browser and
navigate to the Splunk web page.
We'll enter localhost:8000.
Next we'll log in to Splunk using
admin and the default password.
Next, we'll import a CSV file into Splunk.
We'll click on Add Data.
Upload We'll click on Select File.
And we'll choose the census.csv
file that we downloaded.
Click Next.
On the left,
it should say source type csv.
If it does not, click on the button and
go down to Structured and select csv.
In this table,
we see a preview of the data.
You should see the column names
of the CSV file at the top.
Click on Next.
Review.
And Submit.
Now that the file has been imported
successfully, click on Start Searching.
In the search box,
it fills in the default query,
source="cencus.csv" the host name and
sourcetype="csv"
We could change these fields
to search other files or
other data types if we
imported those into Splunk.
Now let's search census.csv for
particular values in the fields.
Let's search for all the data
where the state is California.
We'll enter STNAME="California".
You'll see the results down here.
You could search for
other states by using or.
For example, we can add OR
STNAME="Alaska".
This will search for
state names equal to California or Alaska.
We can add conditions
to our query as well.
Let's search for state equals California
whose population was over one million.
We'll do this by saying
STNAME = "California"
CENSUS2010POP > 1000000.
Can limit the results to one or
more columns.
You do this by adding pipe table
CTYNAME to the end of our query.
In Spunk queries, the pipe command is used
to send the outputs from the first part of
the query into the next.
You can also show more than
one column from the output.
If we add a comma CENSUS2010POP
to the end of this,
we'll see both the city name and
the population.
You can also see a visualization of this
data by clicking on the Visualization tab.
At the bottom, on the x-axis,
we see the county names, and
the y values are the population numbers.
Now let's perform some
statistics on this data.
We'll begin by counting the number of
records where the state is California.
You can do this by saying
STNAME="California" pipe stats count.
Now switch back to the statistics tab,
see the result here
Now let's see the total population for
California.
You can replace count
with sum(CENUS2010POP)
You can also calculate
the average population.
We'll replace sum with mean.
Hello, My name is Mitch Fleichmann,
senior instructor here at Splunk.
Today we are going to
install Splunk on Linux.
I'm using one of
the Splunk Education Linux servers.
Let's examine the environment.
First of all,
notice I'm logged in as the user splunker.
As a best practice,
do not install Splunk as the root user.
I'm currently in the /opt directory,
where I've already downloaded
the tarball from splunk.com/download for
this platform.
As a final check, let's check the system
to make sure we have the correct operating
system and kernel.
This is indeed a Linux machine, let's
get confirmation that it is also 64 bit.
So we are good to go.
The next step is to unzip and
untar the installer and
that we can do with the gunzip and
tar commands.
When everything untucks, you'll notice
a new sub directory created named splunk.
And we can navigate to the splunk/bin
directory to start up Splunk.
Couple of ways to start
Splunk with no switches.
On the first startup, you'll be prompted
to read and agree to the software license.
Or as a shortcut, you can start
up Splunk and accept the license.
And notice a couple of port numbers
being grabbed, port 8000 for
splunk web and port 8089 for
splunk management.
The splunk daemon has started.
Splunk is generating its own keys.
And we can see the splunk web interface,
the URL.
As a best practice,
you may also want to consider automating
splunk to start when the machine boots.
That you can do as the root user.
By issuing the splunk enable command,
enable boot-start as the -user splunker,
the same user that we
just consult splunk with.
So lets log in to splunk web and
see how the system looks.
And for that we'll go back to the browser.
Go to the appropriate URL.
And we can see upon first login,
you are prompted to login with
the credentials admin, password changeme.
Since this is the first login,
you also coach to change your
password to something more secure.
And it's highly recommended to
follow this best practice as well.
And also on first connection,
you'll also see a splash screen
showing you what's new in version 6.
In this case, Powerful Analytics.
Some changes to the UI to
make it more intuitive.
Simplified component management for
cluster management,
folder management and so on.
Also a richer developer experience.
Close down this window and
you can explore the navigation options.
And notice in the left side,
you see a panel showing you
the apps to navigate to and manage.
And on the right side, you see some
panel showing you data in the system and
various links for help.
Let's go to the search and
reporting app by clicking here.
And you can see the search far up top,
some tips on how to search and
then data to search.
Since this is a fresh install,
there is no data to search, so
the next step is to index data and
begin searching.
Good luck.
[SOUND] Hello, this is Chris Busheers,
part of the Splunk education team.
In this video, I'll show you how
install Splunk onto a Window's server.
First we need to get the software
from the splunk.com download page.
We will need to select that
the platform is 32 or 64-bit.
If you aren't sure if your system is 32 or
64-bit, you can check
your system properties.
As you can see, this server is 64-bit,
so we can install that version.
If we saw a system type of 32-bit,
we would download the 32-bit version.
We run the installer by
double clicking on it.
There is button to view the license
agreement, and a check box to accept it.
At this point we can either install
Splunk with the defaults, or
customize our installation.
Let's click on the customize options
to see what settings can be selected.
The first option is to change
the installation location of Splunk.
We are fine with this location,
so we click Next.
Now we must choose what account type
to install Splunk as, Local System or
Domain Account.
A Local System account will allow
Splunk to access all data on, or
forwarded, to this machine.
A Domain Account will allow
you to collect logs and
metrics from remote machines as
well as local and forwarded data.
You are required to provide a Domain
Account with the proper domain rights
to use this type.
Local System works well for
us, so we click Next.
We can select to have a shortcut to Splunk
added, and click Install to continue.
[MUSIC]
Once installed, we can select to have
Splunk launch, and click Finish.
This Splunk web interface
opens in our default browser.
We enter the default user name of admin,
and a password of change made.
A dialog box appears asking
us to change our password.
It is always best practice to do this.
Once logged in, we are taken to
the Splunk launcher homepage.
And that's all it takes to get
Splunk installed on Windows.
Now dig in, and start exploring.
[SOUND]
Our third and
final case is applicable to most companies
that create customer-focused products.
They want to understand how their
customers are responding to the products,
how the product marketing
efforts are performing,
what kind of problems customers
are encountering, and what new features or
feature improvements the customers
are seeking, and so forth.
But how does the company
get this information?
What kind of data sources
would carry this information?
The figure show some of these sources.
They are in focused user surveys,
emails sent by the customers, in blogs and
product review forums, specialized
groups on social media and user forums.
In short, they are on the Internet or
in material received through the Internet.
Now, how many sources are there?
Two.
The number would vary.
A new sites, a new postings, and
new discussion threads
would come up all the time.
In all of these,
the goal is to identify information that
truly relates to the companies product,
its features and its utility.
To cast this as a type
of big data problem,
we look at a task that computer
scientists called Data Fusion.
Consider a set of data sources, S,
as we mentioned on the last slide and
a set of data items, D.
A data item represents a particular
aspect of a real world entity
which in our case is
a product of the company.
For each data item, a source can, but
not necessarily will, provide a value.
For example,
the usability of an ergonomically
split keyboard can have a value good.
The value can be atomic,
like good, or a set, or a list or
sometimes embedded in the string.
For example, the cursor sometimes
freezes when using the touchpad,
is a string which has
a value about the touchpad.
The goal of Data Fusion is to find
the values of Data Items from a source.
In many cases, the system would find
a unique true value of an item.
For example, the launch data of a product
in Europe should be the same true value
regardless of the data
source one looks at.
In other cases, we could find
a value distribution of an item.
For example, the usability of our
keyboard may have a value distribution.
That's with Data Fusion, we should be
able to collect the values of real world
items from a subset of data sources.
It is a subset because
not all Data Sources
will have relevant information
about the Data Item.
There are some other versions
of what a Data Fusion is but for
our purposes we'll stick with
this general description.
Now one obvious problem with the Internet
is that there are too many data
sources at any time,
these lead to many difficulties.
First, it is to be understood
that with too many data sources
there will be many values for
the same item.
Often these will differ and
sometimes they will conflict.
A standard technique in this case
is to use a voting mechanism.
However, even a voting
mechanism can be complex
due to problems with the data source.
One of the problems is to estimate
the trustworthiness of the source.
For each data source,
we need to evaluate whether it's reporting
some basic or known facts correctly.
If a source mentions details
about a rainbow colored iPhone,
which does not exist,
it's trustworthiness reduces
because of the falsity of
the provided value of this data item.
Accordingly, a higher vote count can be
assigned to a more trustworthy source.
And then, this can be used in voting.
The second aspect is Copy Detection.
Detecting weather once was has copied
information from another can be very
important for
detail fusion task in customer analytics.
If a source has copied information,
it's such that discounted vote count
can be assigned to a copy value and
voting that means the copy in
source will have less weight.
Now this is especially relevant when we
compute value distributions, because if we
treat copies as genuine information, we
will statistically bias the distribution.
Now here is active research on how to
detect copies, how to determine bias and
then arrive at a statistically sound
estimation of value distribution.
But to our knowledge, these methods are
yet to be applied to existing software for
big data integration.
It should be very clear by now but
there are two kinds of big data
situations when it comes to information.
The first two uses cases that we
saw requires an integration system
to consider all sources because
the application demand so.
In contrast, problems where data comes
from too many redundant, potentially
unreliable sources like the Internet, the
best results can be obtained if we have
a way of evaluating the worthiness of
sources before information integration.
But this problem is
called Source Selection.
The picture on the right shows the result
of a cost benefit analysis for
data fusion.
The x-axis indicates the number
of sources used, and
the y-axis measures the proportion
of true results that were returned.
We can clearly see that the plot peaks
around six-to-eight sources, and
that the efficiency falls
as more sources are added.
In a cost benefit analysis,
the cost must include both the human and
the computational costs,
while the benefit is a function of
the accuracy of the fusion result.
The technique for
solving this problem comes from economics.
Assuming that cost and
benefits are measure in the same unit, for
example, dollars.
They proposed to continue
selecting sources
until the marginal benefit is
less than the marginal cost.
Now recent techniques were performing
this computation at quite scalable.
In one setting,
selecting the most beneficial sources
from a total of one million
sources took less than one hour.
This completes our coverage of
the big data integration problems.
Hello and welcome.
My name is Rene and I'll be sharing with
you, how to create a report using Pivot.
To access the Pivot interface,
click Pivot on the navigation menu.
The first step is to select
a prebuilt data model.
Now the data model allows you
to create compelling reports and
dashboards without having to know
how to write complex search queries.
As a side note data models are typically
created by a knowledge manager that
understands their
organization's index data.
Grasps the search language and
are familiar with lookups,
transactions, field extractions and
calculated fields.
For our example, we're going to
use Buttercup Games Online Sales.
Now, this data model includes
the online sales activities.
It's made up of nine objects.
Each object represents a specific set
of events in a hierarchical structure.
The http request would include the largest
number of events in this data model.
The next object, successful request,
would be a subset of the http
request events and so on.
Let's say that we want to create a report
for purchases over the last seven days.
We would select the most
appropriate object.
In this case we're going to
select successful purchase.
After you have selected the object
you will notice that a new
Pivot view will display.
If you notice, the count of
successful purchase is the total
number of events for this specific object.
Now, it is based off of all time.
Before you begin, you should have an idea
of what type of report you want to create.
So let's say that we
want to create a bar chart.
We're going to select that
from the left navigation pane.
So the third icon will allow me
to click and select Bar Chart.
So at this point we are ready
to start building our report.
The first selection is Time Range.
Let's set that to the last seven days.
The next one is Filter, now we don't need
to define Filter, because we've already
selected an object of successful purchase
and that's what we're reporting against.
Now, for my x axis,
I'm going to select product name.
You'll notice that I can set the label.
I can set the sort order.
I can even set how many
maximum bars that I want.
The next thing to define is the y axis.
At this time it's set to
count of successful purchase.
But I want the total sales by product.
So I'm going to select price and
then you'll notice that my
value is already set to sum.
So I'm going to keep it as sum.
My report is starting to look really good.
But after reviewing it I might decide that
I want to see values segmented by host.
So let's do that,
in order to set the segmentation
of a specific product name I could go and
set the color to the field that I want.
So I'm going to select Host.
Now, you'll see that my total
sales are segmented by host.
So we really like this report.
Let's go ahead and save it.
So we're going to click on Save As.
Select report and give it a title.
Let's call it Product Sales by Host.
We're going to click Save and
then we're going to view our report.
It was that easy to create
a report through Pivot.
Now, let's just say that we want to go and
work with another Pivot.
This time we're going to just go and
create a statistic table
to view some of that data.
Let's go ahead and click Pivot again.
We'll select the same data model.
Buttercup games online sales and
let's keep to the object that
we're familiar with right now,
successful purchases.
As I mentioned, I want to just
simply create a statistic table.
I want to show you how
we'd go about doing that.
So the first step is to think about what
are some of the row data that you want?
Let's just assume that we want to view
the product names within their categories.
So, let's go ahead, under Split Rows,
we're going to select category first.
Notice that I can set a label if I want.
Let's go ahead and
set it capitalized category.
I'm going to add that to my table.
You'll see that it
becomes the first column.
Now I want to add another column.
Let's go ahead and
click the plus right next to categories.
Again we're still working
with the split rows.
I'm going to select product name, again if
you want to set a label you can do that.
Now this is the label of our column.
Add to table.
And I want you to notice that
now we are viewing each product
within their category.
Now at this point if you look at
the statistic that is being defined,
it's the count of successful purchases.
That is defined as column values.
Now if I want to add to this,
I can append and have another column.
Let's go ahead and click the plus next
to the Count of successful purchase.
This time I want to add the price.
And you'll notice that I have
different values available.
I could do a Sum, a Count,
an Average, Max, Min.
Let's keep it as a Sum and
let's add a label of Total Sales.
And let's Add To Table.
So this is just to show you
how quick it is to go and
build a table with the statistics
that you would need.
Now at this point, if ever you decide,
I only want to view the data for
the last seven days.
Just note that you could go
back up to your filter and
your first filter is
based off of all time.
So we could set that to
the last seven days.
So of course that the data
in our table will change.
Now, the last thing I want to show you
here is if ever you did want to see
the count and the total sales per host,
as we've defined in our previous example.
That is where you could go
to the split columns and
define how you wish to
split that information.
So let's go ahead and select host again.
And I'm just going to
click on add to table.
Now I could see that the information
has been split by host.
I have www1 count of successful
purchases as well as total sales.
And then I have the split of www2 I have
the count and the total sales and etc.
So this concludes our short
video hope you enjoy it.
Thank you.
Welcome.
In this short module we'll talk about
information integration which refers
to the problem of using many different
information sources to accomplish a task.
In this module, we'll look at the problems
and solutions through a few use cases.
So after this video, you'll be able to
explain the data integration problem,
define integrated views and schema
mapping, describe the impact of increasing
the number of data sources, appreciate
the need to use data compression,
And describe record linking,
data exchange, and data fusion tasks.
Our first use case starts with
an example given at an IBM website for
their information integration products.
It represents a very common
scenario in today's business world.
Due to the changing market dynamics,
companies
are always selling off a part of their
company or acquiring another company.
As these mergers and acquisitions happen,
databases which were developed and
stored separately in different companies
would now need to be brought together.
Now take a minute to read this case.
This is the case of an expanding financial
services group that's growing its customer
base in different countries.
And all they want is a single view
of their entire customer base.
In other words, it does not matter
which previous company originally had
the customers, Suncorp-Metway
want to consolidate all customer
information as if they were
in one single database.
And in reality, of course, they may
not want to buy a huge machine and
migrate every subsidiary
company's data into it.
What they're looking to create is possibly
a software solution which would make all
customer-related data to appear as though
they were together as a single database.
This software solution is called
an information integration system.
This will help them ensure that they have
a uniform set of marketing campaigns for
all their customers.
Let's try to see, hypothetically, of
course, what might be involved in creating
this combined data and what kind of use
the integrated data might result in.
So we first create
a hypothetical scenario.
Although Suncorp have a large
number of data sources,
we will take a much simpler situation and
have only two data sources from two
different financial service companies.
The first data source,
which is an insurance company that manages
it's data with a relation of DBMS,
this database has nine tables where the
primary object of information is a policy.
The company offers many
different types of policies
sold to individual people by their agents.
Now as it's true for all insurance
companies, policyholders pay their monthly
dues, and sometimes people make claims
against their insurance policies.
When they do, the details of the claims
are maintained in the database.
These claims can belong to different
categories, and when the claims have
paid to the claimants, the transaction
is recorded in the transactions table.
As we have done several times now,
the primary keys of the table
are the underlined attributes here.
The second company in
our example is a bank,
which also uses a relational database.
In this bank, both individuals and
businesses called corporations here,
can have accounts.
Now accounts can be of different types.
For example, a money market account
is different from a savings account.
A bank also maintains its transactions
in a table, which can be really large.
But the dispute in a bank record
case happens when the bank is
charged a customer, or the customer has
declined responsibility of the charge.
This can happen, for example, if a
customer's Internet account was hacked or
a debit card got stolen.
The bank keeps a record
of these anomalies and
fraudulent events in a disputes table,
all right.
Let's see what happens after the data
from these two subsidiary companies
are integrated.
After the merger the company wants to
do a promotional goodwill activity.
They would like to offer
a small discount to their
insurance policyholders if they're also
customers of the newly acquired bank.
How do you identify these customers?
Let's see.
In other words, we need to use the table
shown on the left to create the table
shown on the right called
discount candidates.
One is to create a yellow tables from
the insurance company database, and
the blue table from the bank database,
and then join them to construct the table
with a common customer ID, and both
the policyKey and bank account number.
Now, this relation, which is derived that
is computed by querying two different
data sources and combining their results,
is called an integrated view.
It is integrated because the data is
retrieved from different data sources,
and it's called a view because
in database terminology
it is a relation computed
from other relations.
To populate the integrated
view discount candidates,
we need to go through a step
called schema mapping.
The term mapping means to
establish correspondence between
the attributes of the view, which is
also called a target relation, and
that of the source relations.
For example, we can map the full address
from individuals to the address attribute
in discountCandidates, but
this would only be true for
customers whose names and
addresses match in the two databases.
As you can see, policyholders uses
the full name of a customer, whereas
individuals has it broken down into first
name, middle initial, and last name.
On the other hand, full address is
a single field in individuals, but
represented in full attributes
in the policyholders relation.
The mappings of account number and
policyKey are more straightforward.
Well, what about customer ID which doesn't
correspond to anything in the four
input relations?
We'll come back to this later on.
Okay, now we'll define
an integrated relation.
How do we query?
For example,
how do you find the bank account number
of a person whose policyKey is known?
You might think, what's the problem here?
We have a table.
Just say select account number from
discount candidates where policyKey
is equal to 4-937528734, and we're done.
Well, yes, you can write this query,
but how the query be evaluated?
That depends on what's called the query
architecture of the data
integration system.
The figure on the left shows
the elements of this architecture.
We'll discover it in more detail,
but on this slide,
we'll just describe
the three axes of this cube.
The vertical z axis specifies
whether we have one data source or
multiple data sources.
Our interest is in the case where
there are multiple data sources.
The x axis asks whether the integrated
data is actually stored physically
in some place or whether it is computed
on the fly, each time a query is asked.
If it is all precomputed and stored,
we say that the data is materialized.
And if it is computed on the fly,
we say it's virtual.
The y axis asks whether
there is a single schema or
global schema defined all
over the data integrated for
an application or whether the data
stay in different computers and
it is accessed in a peer-to-peer
manner at runtime.
Thus, the seemingly simple select
project query will be evaluated
depending on which part of the cube
our architecture implements.
But for now,
let's return to our example use case.
An obvious goal of an information
integration system
is to be complete and accurate.
Complete means no eligible record
from the source should be absent in
the target relation.
Accurate means all the entries in
the integrated relation should be correct.
Now we said on the previous
slide that a matching
customer is a person who
was in both databases and
has the same name and
address in the two databases.
Now let's look at some example records.
Specifically, consider the records
marked by the three arrows.
The two bank accounts and
the policy record do not match for name or
for address.
So our previous method would discard them.
But look at the records closely.
Do you think they might all
belong to the same customer?
Maybe this lady has a maiden name and
a married name, and
has moved from one address to another.
Maybe she changed her Social Security
number somewhere along the way.
So this is called
a record linkage problem.
That means we would like to ensure that
the set of data records that belong to
a single entity are recognized,
perhaps by clustering
the values of different attributes or
by using a set of matching rules so
that we know how to deal with it
during the integration process.
For example, we need to determine
which of the addresses should be
used in the integrated relation.
Which of the two bank accounts?
If the answer is both accounts 102 and
103, we will need to change
the schema of the target's relation
to a list instead of an atomic number
to avoid creating multiple tuples for
the same entity.
As we saw, the schema of adding
process is a task of figuring out
how elements of the schema from two
sources would relate to each other and
determining how they would
map the target schema.
You also saw that this is not really
a simple process, that we are trying to
produce one integrated relation using
a couple of relations from each source.
In a Big Data situation,
there are dozens of data sources, or
more because the company's growing and
each source may have a few hundred tables.
So it becomes very hard to actually solve
this correspondence-making problem
completely and accurately just because
the number of combinations one has to
go through is really, really high.
One practical way to tackle this problem
is not to do a full-scale detail
integration in the beginning but
adopt what's called a pay-as-you-go model.
The pay-as-you-go data
management principle is simple.
The system should provide some basic
integration services at the outset and
then evolve the schema mappings between
the different sources on an as needed
basis.
So given a query, the system should
generate a best effort or approximate
answers from the data sources for
a perfect schema mappings do not exist.
When it discovers a large number
of sophisticated queries or
data mining tasks over certain sources,
it will guide the users to make
additional efforts to integrate
these sources more precisely.
Okay, so how does the first
approximate schema mapping performed?
One approach to do this is called
Probabilistic Schema Mapping.
We'll describe it in more detail next.
In the previous step,
we just decided to create the disk count
candidates rrelation in an ad hoc way.
And in a Big Data situation,
we need to carefully determine
what the integrated schema,
also called mediated schemas, should be,
and we should evaluate them properly.
Since our toy company is trying
to create a single customer view,
it's natural to create an integrated
table called customers.
But how can we design this table?
Here are some options.
We can create the customer table to
include individuals and corporations and
then use a flag called customer
type to distinguish between them.
Now in the mediated schema then,
the individuals first name,
middle initial, last name,
policyholder's name and
corporation's name would all
map to Customer_Name similarly.
The individual's full address,
the corporation's registered address,
and the policyholder's address,
plus city, plus state,
plus zip would all map
to customer address.
Now we can enumerate all such choices of
which attributes to group together and
map for each single attribute
in the target schema.
But no matter how you'll do it,
it will never be a perfect fit because
not all these combinations
would go well together.
For example, should that date of
birth be included in this table?
Would it make sense for corporations?
In Probabilistic Mediated Schema Design,
we answer this question by
associating probability values
with each of these options.
To compute these values, we need to
quantify the relationships between
attributes by figuring out which
attributes should be grouped or
clustered together?
Now two pieces of information
available in the source schemas
can serve as evidence for
attribute clustering.
One, the parallel similarity
of source attributes, and two,
statistical properties
of service attributes.
The first piece of information indicates
when two attributes are likely to be
similar and is used for
creating multiple mediated schemas.
One can apply a collection of
attribute matching modules
to compute pairwise similarity.
For example, individual names and
policyholder names
are possibly quite similar.
Are individual names versus
corporation names similar?
Now, the similarity between two
source attributes, EIN and EZ,
measure how closely the two attributes
represent the same real world concept.
The second piece of information indicates
when two attributes are likely
to be different, and is used for
assigning probabilities to
each of the mediated schemas.
For example, date of birth and
corporation name possibly
will never co-occur together.
But for
large schemas with large data volumes,
one can estimate these measures by
taking samples from the actual database
to come up with reasonable
similarity co-occurrence scores.
To illustrate attribute regrouping, we
take a significant re-simplified example.
Here we want to create customer
transactions as a mediated relation
based upon the bank transactions and
insurance transactions.
Each attribute is given
an abbreviation for simplicity.
Below, you can see three
possible mediated schemas.
In the first one,
the transaction begin and end times
from bank transactions are grouped into
the same cluster as transaction date time
from the insurance transactions,
because all of them are the same type.
Similarly, transaction party, that
means who is giving or receiving money,
and transaction description are grouped
together with transaction details.
The second schema keeps
all of them separate.
And the third candidate schema
groups some of them and not others.
Now that we have multiple mediated
schemas, which one should we choose?
Now I'm presenting here
a qualitative account of the method.
The primary goal is to look for
what we can call consistency.
A source schema is consistent
with a mediated schema if
two different attributes of the source
schema do not occur in one cluster.
And in the example, Med3,
that means related schema three,
is more consistent with bank
transactions because, unlike Med1,
it keeps TBT,
TET in two different clusters.
Once this is done, we can count the number
of consistent sources for each candidate
mediated schema and then use this count
to come up with a probability estimate.
This estimate can then be used
to choose the k best schemas.
Should one ever choose more
than one just best schema?
Well, that's a hard question
to answer in general.
It is done when the top capability
estimates are very close to each other.
[SOUND] The Splunk platform for
operational intelligence is
a revolutionary suite of products that
is unlocking unprecedented value for
thousands of customers around the world.
Why Splunk?
It all starts with machine data.
Machine data is the big data generated by
all the technologies that
power our businesses.
From the applications, servers, websites,
and network devices in the data center and
the cloud, to the mobile device
in the palm of your hand.
Thermostats, train sensors, electric cars,
and the Internet of things.
Machine data is everywhere.
It's fast-growing and complex.
It's also incredibly valuable, why?
Because it contains a definitive
record of all activity and behavior.
Splunk software collects and
indexes this data at massive scale,
from wherever it's generated,
regardless of format or source.
Users can quickly and
easily monitor, search, analyze, and
report on their data, all in real time.
Machine data is different.
It can't be processed and
analyzed using traditional methods.
Splunk software does not rely on brittle
schemas and inflexible databases.
Splunk is easy to deploy, easy to use, and
easy to scale, whether on premises or
in a public, private, or hybrid cloud.
Splunk is also available
as a cloud service.
And for big data environments that
used Hadoop for cheap app storage,
we have Hunk, Splunk analytics for Hadoop.
[MUSIC]
Our customers from around
the world illustrate why so
many organizations use Splunk.
Intuit has standardized on Splunk,
delivering operational visibility for
their leading online products, including
QuickBooks, Quicken, and TurboTax.
Intuit considers Splunk one of
their cornerstone technologies
that is helping them innovate and
deliver better service to their customers.
Cisco, one of the world's
largest technology providers,
empowers their global security
team with Splunk enterprise
to gain a centralized view into
end user and system activities.
Splunk has dramatically helped
improve their incident detection and
response rate.
Splunk was key to Domino's Pizza's
success during the Super Bowl,
by monitoring database uptime and
order response.
Armed with new levels of
customer understanding,
Domino's was able to strengthen their
online business, in addition to saving
hundreds of thousands of dollars replacing
legacy technologies with Splunk.
We are thrilled to hear Domino's
call Splunk their secret sauce.
Another great Splunk story includes
cars and the Internet of things.
Working together with the Ford Motor
Company and Ford's OpenXC platform,
Splunk delivered connected car dashboards
to examine driving behavior and
vehicle performance.
UK-based Tesco is one of
the world's largest retailers,
with nearly 1 million customers and
a half billion online orders per week.
Customer satisfaction
is a critical metric.
Tesco deployed Splunk to gain a unified
view across their websites, transactions,
and business, gaining valuable digital
intelligence about their customers.
Splunk was founded to pursue a disruptive
vision to make machine data accessible,
usable, and valuable to everyone.
Find out more about Splunk and
operational intelligence by
downloading the executive summary.
Or better yet,
experience the value firsthand by
downloading Splunk software for free.
Chances are someone in your
organization already has.
[SOUND]
Aggregations in Big Data Pipelines.
After this video you will
be able to compare and
select the aggregation operation that
you require to solve your problem.
Explain how you can use aggregations to
compact your dataset and reduce volume.
That is in many cases.
And design complex operations in your
pipeline, using a series of aggregations.
Aggregation is any operation on a data set
that performs a specific transformation,
taking all the related data
elements into consideration.
Let's say we have a bunch of stars
which are of different colors.
Different colors denote diversity or
variety in the data.
To keep things simple, we will use
letter 'f' to denote a transformation.
In the following slides,
we will see examples of how 'f' can take
the shape of different transformations.
If we apply a transformation that does
something using the information of
all the stars here,
we are performing an aggregation.
Loosely speaking, we can say
that applying a transformation 'f'
that takes all the elements of data
as input is called 'aggregation'.
One of the simplest aggregations is
summation over all the data elements.
In this case,
let's say every star counted as 1.
Summing over all the stars gives 14,
which is the summation of 3 stars for
yellow,
5 stars for green, and
6 stars for color pink.
Another aggregation that you could perform
is summation of individual star colors,
that is, grouping the sums by color.
So, If each star is a 1,
adding each group will result in 3 for
yellow stars, 5 for green stars,
and 6 for pink stars.
In this case,
the aggregation function 'f' will output
3 tuples of star colors and counts.
In a sales scenario, each color could
denote a different product type.
And the number 1 could be replaced
by revenue generated by a product
in each city the product is sold.
In fact,
we will keep coming back to this analogy.
You can also perform average
over items of similar kind,
such as sums grouped by color.
Continuing the example earlier,
you can calculate average revenue per
product type using this aggregation.
Other simple yet useful aggregational
operations to help you extract meaning
from large data sets are maximum,
minimum, and standard deviation.
Remember, you can always perform
aggregation as a series of operations,
such as maximum of the sums per product.
That is, summation followed by maximum.
If you first sum sales for
each city, that is for
each product,
then you can take the maximum of it
by applying maximum function to
the result of the summation function.
In this case, you get the product,
which has maximum sales in the country.
Aggregation over Boolean data
sets that can have true-false or
one-zero values could be a complex mixture
of AND, OR, and NOT logical operations.
A lot of problems become easy
to manipulate using sets.
Because sets don't allow duplicate values.
Depending on your application,
this could be very useful.
For example, to count the number
of products from a sales table,
you can simply take all
the sales tables and create sets
of these products in those tables,
and take a union of these sets.
To summarize, by choosing the right
aggregation, you can generate compact and
meaningful insights that enable faster and
effective decision making in business.
You will find that in most cases,
aggregation results in
smaller output data sets.
Hence, aggregation is an important tool
set to keep in pocket when dealing with
large data sets, and big data pipelines.
Big Data Processing Pipelines:
A Dataflow Approach.
Most big data applications
are composed of a set of operations
executed one after another as a pipeline.
Data flows through these operations,
going through various
transformations along the way.
We also call this dataflow graphs.
So to understand big data
processing we should start by
understanding what dataflow means.
After this video you will be able to
summarize what dataflow means and
it's role in data science.
Explain split->do->merge as a big
data pipeline with examples,
and define the term data parallel.
Let's consider the hello
world MapReduce example for
WordCount which reads one or
more text files and
counts the number of occurrences
of each word in these text files.
You are by now very familiar with
this example, but as a reminder,
the output will be a text
file with a list of words and
their occurrence frequencies
in the input data.
In this application,
the files were first split into HDFS
cluster nodes as partitions of
the same file or multiple files.
Then a map operation, in this case,
a user defined function to count words
was executed on each of these nodes.
And all the key values that were output
from map were sorted based on the key.
And the key values with the same word
were moved or shuffled to the same node.
Finally, the reduce operation
was executed on these nodes
to add the values for
key-value pairs with the same keys.
If you look back at this example, we see
that there were four distinct steps,
namely the data split step,
the map step, the shuffle and
sort step, and the reduce step.
Although, the word count
example is pretty simple it
represents a large number of
applications that these three
steps can be applied to achieve
data parallel scalability.
We refer in general to this
pattern as "split-do-merge".
In these applications, data flows
through a number of steps, going through
transformations with various scalability
needs, leading to a final product.
The data first gets partitioned.
The split data goes through a set of
user-defined functions to do something,
ranging from statistical operations to
data joins to machine learning functions.
Depending on the application's
data processing needs,
these "do something" operations can
differ and can be chained together.
In the end results can be combined
using a merging algorithm or
a higher-order function like reduce.
We call the stitched-together
version of these sets of steps for
big data processing "big data pipelines".
The term pipe comes from
a UNIX separation that
the output of one running program gets
piped into the next program as an input.
As you might imagine,
one can string multiple programs together
to make longer pipelines with various
scalability needs at each step.
However, for big data processing,
the parallelism of each step in
the pipeline is mainly data parallelism.
We can simply define data parallelism
as running the same functions
simultaneously for the elements or
partitions of a dataset on multiple cores.
For example,
in our word count example, data
parallelism occurs in every
step of the pipeline.
There's definitely parallelization
during map over the input
as each partition gets
processed as a line at a time.
To achieve this type of data parallelism,
we must decide on the data granularity
of each parallel computation.
In this case, it is a line.
We also see a parallel grouping of
data in the shuffle and sort phase.
This time, the parallelization is
over the intermediate products,
that is, the individual key-value pairs.
And after the grouping of
the intermediate products
the reduce step gets parallelized
to construct one output file.
You have probably noticed that
the data gets reduced to a smaller set
at each step.
Although, the example we have given is for
batch processing, similar techniques
apply to stream processing.
Let's discuss this for
our simplified advanced stream
data from an online game example.
In this case, your event gets ingested
through a real time big data ingestion
engine, like Kafka or Flume.
Then they get passed into
a Streaming Data Platform for
processing like Samza,
Storm or Spark streaming.
This is a valid choice for processing
data one event at a time or chunking
the data into Windows or Microbatches
of time or other features.
Any pipeline processing of data can
be applied to the streaming data here
as we wrote in a batch-
processing Big Data engine.
The process stream data can then be
served through a real-time view or
a batch-processing view.
Real-time view is often subject to change
as potentially delayed new data comes in.
The storage of the data can be
accomplished using H-Base, Cassandra,
HDFS, or
many other persistent storage systems.
To summarize, big data pipelines
get created to process data
through an aggregated set of steps that
can be represented with the split-
do-merge pattern with
data parallel scalability.
This pattern can be
applied to many batch and
streaming data processing applications.
Next we will go through some processing
steps in a big data pipeline in
more detail, first conceptually,
then practically in Spark.
Now that we went through an overview
of the Spark ecosystem and
the components of the Spark stack, it is
time for us to start learning more about
its architecture and run our first
Spark program in the cloud VM.
After this video you will be
able to describe how Spark
does in-memory processing using the
Resilient Distributed Dataset abstraction,
explain the inner workings of
the Spark architecture, and
summarize how Spark manages and
executes code on Clusters.
I mentioned a few times that
Spark is efficient because it
uses an abstraction called RDDs for
in memory processing.
What this means might not be
clear to some of you yet.
Let's remember the alternative.
In Hadoop MapReduce,
each step, also pipeline,
reads from disk to memory,
performs the computations and
writes back its output from
the memory to the disk.
However, writing data to disk
is a costly operation and
this cost becomes even more
with large volumes of data.
Here is an interesting fact.
Memory operations can
be up to 100,000 times
faster than disk operations in some cases.
Spark instead takes advantage of this and
allows for
immediate results of transformations
in different stages of the pipeline and
memory, like MAP and REDUCE here.
Here, we see that the outputs
of MAP operations
are shared with reduce operations
without being written to the disk.
The containers where the data
gets stored in memory
are called resilient distributed
datasets or RDDs for short.
RDDs are how Spark distributes data and
computations across
the nodes of a commodity cluster,
preferably with large memory.
Thanks to this abstraction,
Spark has proven to be 100 times
faster for some applications.
Let's define all the words
in this interesting name
beginning with the last one, datasets.
Datasets that RDD distributes comes
from a batch data storage like HDFS,
no SQL databases, text files or streaming
data ingestion systems like Cafco.
It can even conveniently read and
distribute the data from your local disc
like text files into Spark, or
even a hierarchy of folders.
When Spark reads data from these sources,
it generates RDDs for them.
The Spark operations can transform RDDs
into other RDDs like any other data.
Here it's important to mention
that RDDs are immutable.
This means that you cannot
change them partially.
However, you can create new RDDs by
a series of one or many transformations.
Next, let's look at what distributed
means in the RDD context.
As I mentioned before, RDDs distribute
partitioned data collections and
computations on clusters even
across a number of machines.
For example, running on the Amazon Cloud.
The complexity of this operation is
hidden by this very simple interface.
Computations are a diverse set of
transformations of RDDs like map,
filter and join.
And also actions on the RDDs like counting
and saving them persistently on disk.
The partitioning of data can be changed
dynamically to optimize Spark's
performance.
The last element is resilient, and
it's very important because in a large
scale computing environment it is
pretty common to have node failures.
It's very important to be
able to recover from these
situations without losing
any work already done.
For full tolerance in such situations,
Spark tracks the history of each
partition, keeping a lineage
over RDDs over time,
so every point in your calculations,
Spark knows which are the partitions
needed to recreate the partition
in case it gets lost.
And if that happens,
then Spark automatically figures out
where it can start the recompute from and
optimizes the amount of processing
needed to recover from the failure.
Before we create our first Spark program
using RDDs in Pi Spark in the cloud
layer VM,
let's review Spark's architecture.
From a bird's eye view,
Spark has two main components,
a driver program and worker nodes.
The driver program is where
your application starts.
It distributes RDDs on your
computational cluster and
makes sure the transformations and
actions on these RDDs are performed.
Driver programs create
a connection to a Spark cluster or
your local Spark through
a Spark context object.
The default Spark context
in the Spark shell is
an object called SC for Spark context.
For example, in the upcoming reading for
creating word counts in Spark,
we will use SC as the context to
generate RDDs for a text file
using the line of code shown here.
The driver program manages a potentially
large number of nodes called worker nodes.
On a local computer, we can assume
that there's only one worker node and
it is where the Spark operations execute.
A worker node in Spark keeps
a running Java virtual machine,
called JVM commonly, called the executor.
Depending on the illustration,
executor can execute task
related to mapping stages or
reducing stages or
other Spark specific pipelines.
This Java virtual machine is the core
that all the computation is executed,
and this is the interface also to the rest
of the Big Data storage systems and tools.
For example, if we ever had the Hadoop
file system, HTFS, as the storage system,
then on each worker node,
some of the data will be stored locally.
As you know, the most important point
of this computing framework is to bring
the computation to data.
So Spark will send some
computational jobs to be executed
on the data that are already available
on the machine thanks to HDFS.
Data will be read from HDFS and
get processed in memory,
the results will be stored as one RDD.
The actual computation is running
straight in the executor,
that is the JVM that runs your Scala or
Java codes.
Instead, if you are using PySpark
then there will be several Python
processes generally, one for task but
you can configure it depending
on your application.
In a real Big Data scenario, we have many
worker nodes running tasks internally.
It is important to have a system that can
automatically manage provisioning and
restarting of these nodes.
The cluster manager in
Spark has this capability.
Spark currently supports mainly three
interfaces for cluster management,
namely Spark's standalone cluster manager,
the Apache Mesos, and Hadoop YARN.
Standalone means that there's a special
Spark process that takes care of
restarting nodes that are failing or
starting nodes at the beginning
of the computation.
YARN and Mesos are two external research
measures that can be used also for
these purposes.
Choosing a cluster manager
to fit your application and
infrastructure can be quite confusing.
Here, we give you a good
article as a starting point on
how to pick the right cluster manager for
your organization.
To summarize, the Spark architecture
includes a driver program.
The driver program communicates
with the cluster manager for
monitoring and
provisioning of resources and
communicates directly with worker
nodes to submit and execute tasks.
RDDs get created and passed within
transformations running in the executable.
Finally, let's see how this
setup works on the Cloudera VM.
In the Cloudera VM,
we are using Spark in standalone mode and
everything is running locally.
So it's a single machine and on the same
machine we have our driver program,
the executor JVM and
our single PySpark process.
With that, we are ready to start with
our first reading to install Spark and
then running our word count program
using the Spark environment.
After a brief overview of some
of the processing systems
in the Big Data Landscape, it is time for
us to dive deeper into Spark.
Spark was initiated at
UC Berkeley in 2009 and
was transferred to
Apache Software Foundation in 2013.
Since then, Spark has become a top
level project with many users and
contributors worldwide.
After this video, you will be able
to list the main motivations for
the development of Spark,
draw the Spark stack as a layer diagram,
And explain the functionality of
the components in the Spark stack.
As we have discussed in our earlier
discussions, while Hadoop is great for
batch processing using
the MapReduce programming module,
it has shortcomings in a number of ways.
First of all, since it is limited to
Map and Reduce based transformations,
one has to restrict their big data
pipeline to map and reduce steps.
But the number of applications
can be implemented using Map and
Reduce, it's not always possible and
it is often not the most efficient
way to express a big data pipeline.
For example, you might want to do a join
operation between different data sets or
you might want to filter or
sample your data.
Or you might have a more
complicated data pipeline with
several steps including joins and
group byes.
It might have a Map and Reduce face,
but maybe another map face after that.
These types of operations are hard or
impossible to express using MapReduce and
cannot be accommodated by
the MapReduce framework in Hadoop.
Another important bottleneck in
Hadoop MapReduce that is critical for
performance, is that MapReduce relies
heavily on reading data from disc.
This is especially a problem for iterative
algorithms that require taking several
passes through the data using
a number of transformations.
Since each transformation will need
to read its inputs from the disk,
this will end up in a performance
bottleneck due to IO.
Most machine learning pipelines
are in this category,
making Hadoop MapReduce not ideal for
machine learning.
And as I mentioned in the system overview,
the only programming language
that MapReduce provides
a native interface for is Java.
Although, it's possible to run Python code
to implementation for it is more complex
and not very efficient especially when
you are running not with text data, but
with floating point numbers.
The programming language issue
also affects how interactive
the environment is.
Most data scientist
prefer to use scripting
languages due to their
interactive shell capabilities.
Not having such an interface in Hadoop
really makes it difficult to use and
adapt my many in the field.
In addition in the big data
era having support for
streaming data processing is a key for
being able to run similar analysis on
both real time and historical data.
Spark came out of the need to
extend the MapReduce framework
to overcome this shortcomings and
provide an expressive cluster computing
environment that can provide interactive
querying, efficient iterative analytics
and streaming data processing.
So, how does Apache Spark provide
solutions for these problems?
Spark provides a very rich and
expressive programming module that
gives you more than 20 highly efficient
distributed operations or transformations.
Pipe-lining any of these steps in Spark
simply takes a few lines of code.
Another important feature of Spark is
the ability to run these computations
in memory.
It's ability to cache and
process data in memory,
makes it significantly faster for
iterative applications.
This is proven to provide a factor
of ten or even 100 speed-up
in the performance of some algorithms,
especially using large data sets.
Additionally, Spark provides support for
batch and streaming workloads at once.
Last but not least,
Spark provides simple APIs for Python,
Scala, Java and SQL programming
through an interactive shell to
accomplish analytical tasks through both
external and its built-in libraries.
The Spark layer diagram,
also called Stack,
consists of components that build on
top of the Spark computational engine.
This engine distributes and monitors tasks
across the nodes of a commodity cluster.
The components built on top of this
engine are designed to interact and
communicate through this common engine.
Any improvements to
the underlying engine becomes
an improvement in the other components,
thanks to such close interaction.
This also enables building applications
that's span across these different
components like querying data using
Spark SQL and applying machine learning
algorithms, the query results using Sparks
machine learning library and MLlib.
The Spark Core is where
the core capability is
of the Spark Framework are implemented.
This includes support for
distributed scheduling,
memory management and full tolerance.
Interaction with different schedulers,
like YARN and Mesos and
various NoSQL storage systems like
HBase also happen through Spark Core.
A very important part of
Spark Core is the APIs for
defining resilient distributed data sets,
or RDDs for short.
RDDs are the main programming
abstraction in Spark,
which carry data across many computing
nodes in parallel, and transform it.
Spark SQL is the component of Spark
that provides querying structured and
unstructured data through
a common query language.
It can connect to many data sources and
provide APIs to convert
query results to RDDs in Python,
Scala and Java programs.
Spark Streaming is where data
manipulations take place in Spark.
Although, not a native real-time interface
to datastreams, Spark streaming enables
creating small aggregates of data coming
from streaming data ingestion systems.
These aggregate datasets
are called micro-batches and
they can be converted into RDBs in
Spark Streaming for processing.
MLlib is Sparks native library for
machine learning algorithms
as well as model evaluation.
All of the functionality is potentially
ported to any programming language Sparks
supports and
is designed to scale out using Spark.
GraphX is the graph analytics
library of Spark and
enables the Vertex edge data model of
graphs to be converted into RDDs as
well as providing scalable implementations
of graph processing algorithms.
To summarize, through these
layers Spark provides diverse,
scalable interactive management and
analyses of big data.
The interactive shell enables data
scientists to conduct exploratory
analysis and create big data pipelines,
while also enabling the big
data system integration engineers
to scale these analytical pipelines
across commodity computing clusters and
cloud environments.
There are many big data
processing systems, but
how do we make sense of them in order to
take full advantage of these systems?
In this video,
we will review some of them, and
a way to categorize big data processing
systems as we go through our review.
After this video, you will be able
to recall the Hadoop ecosystem,
draw a layer diagram with three layers for
data storage, data processing and
workflow management.
Summarize an evaluation criteria for
big data processing systems and
explain the properties of Hadoop,
Spark, Flink,
Beam, and Storm as major big
data processing systems.
In our introduction to big data course,
we talked about a version of
the layer diagram for the tools
in the Hadoop ecosystem organized
vertically based on the interface.
Lower level interface is the storage and
scheduling on the bottom and
higher level languages and
interactivity at the top.
Most of the tools in the Hadoop ecosystem
are initially built to complement
the capabilities of Hadoop for distributed
filesystem management using HDFS.
Data processing using the MapReduce
engine, and resource scheduling and
negotiation using the YARN engine.
Over time,
a number of new projects were built
either to add to these
complimentary tools or to handle
additional types of big data management
and processing not available in Hadoop.
Arguably, the most important
change to Hadoop over time
was the separation of YARN from
the MapReduce programming model
to solely handle resource
management concerns.
This allowed for Hadoop to be extensible
to different programming models.
And enabled the development of
a number of processing engines for
batch and stream processing.
Another way to look at the vast number of
tools that have been added to the Hadoop
ecosystem, is from the point of view of
their functionality in the big
data processing pipeline.
Simply put, these associate to three
distinct layers for data management and
storage, data processing, and resource
coordination and workflow management.
In our second course,
we talked about the bottom layer
in this diagram in detail,
namely the data management and storage.
While this layer includs Hadoop's HDFS
there are a number of other systems that
rely on HDFS as a file system or implement
their own no SQL storage options.
As big data can have a variety of
structure, semi structured and
unstructured formats, and
gets analyzed through a variety of tools,
many tools were introduced to
fit this variety of needs.
We call these big data management systems.
We reviewed redis and
Aerospike as key value stores,
where each data item is
identified with a unique key.
We got some practical
experience with Lucene and
Gephi as vector and
graph data stores, respectively.
We also talked about Vertica
as a column store database,
where information is stored
in columns rather than rows.
Cassandra and
Hbase are also in this category.
Finally, we introduce Solr and
Asterisk DB for managing unstructured and
semi-structured text, and
mongoDB as a document store.
The processing layer is where these
different varieties of data gets
retrieved, integrated, and analyzed,
which is the primary focus of this class.
In the integration and processing layer
we roughly refer to the tools that
are built on top of the HDFS and YARN,
although some of them work with
other storage and file systems.
YARN is a significant enabler of many of
these tools making a number of batch and
stream processing engines like Storm,
Spark, Flink and being possible.
We will revisit these processing
engines and explain why we have so
many later in this lecture.
This layer also includes tools like Hive,
or Spark SQL, for
bringing a query interface
on top of the storage layer.
Pig, for scripting simple big data
pipelines using the MapReduce framework.
And a number of specialized analytical
libraries for machine learning and
graph analytics, like Giraph as GraphX of
Spark are examples of such libraries for
graph processing.
And Mahout on top of the Hadoop stack and
MLlib of Spark are two options for
machine learning.
Although we have a basic overview of
graph processing and machine learning for
big data analytics later in this course,
we won't go into the details here.
Instead, we will have a dedicated
course on each of them
later in this specialization.
The third and top layer in our diagram is
the coordination and management layer.
This is where integration,
scheduling, coordination, and
monitoring of applications across many
tools in the bottom two layers take place.
This layer is also where the results of
the big data analysis gets communicated to
other programs, websites, visualization
tools, and business intelligence tools.
Workflow management systems help to
develop automated solutions that can
manage and coordinate the process of
combining data management and analytical
tests in a big data pipeline, as
a configurable, structured set of steps.
The workflow driven thinking also
matches this basic process of data
science that we overviewed before.
Oozie is an example of a workflow
scheduler that can interact with
many of the tools in the integration and
processing layer.
Zookeeper is the resource coordination and
monitoring tool and
manages and coordinates all these tools
and middleware named after animals.
Although virtual management is
my personal research area and
I talk more about it in other venues,
in this specialization we focus mainly
on big data integration and processing.
And we will not have a specific
lecture on this layer in this course.
We give you a reading on big data
workflows after this video as
further information and
a starting point for the subject.
In data integration and
processing pipelines,
data goes through a number of operations,
which can apply
a specific function to it, can work
the data from one format to another,
join data with other data sets, or
filter some values out of a data set.
We generally refer to these as
transformations, some of which can also
be specially named aggregations as you
have seen in Amarnath's earlier lectures.
In this video we will reveal some common
transformation operations that we see
in these pipelines, some of which,
we refer to as data parallel patterns.
After this video you will
be able to list common data
transformations within big data pipelines,
and design
a conceptual data processing pipeline
using the basic data transformations.
Simply speaking, transformations
are higher order functions or
tools to convert your data from
one form to another, just like
we would use tools at the wood shop
to transform logs into furniture.
When we look at big data
pipelines used today,
map is probably the most
common transformation we find.
The map operation is one of the basic
building blocks of the big data pipeline.
When you want to apply a process
to each member of a collection,
such as adding 10% bonus to each
person's salary on a given month a map
operation comes in very handy.
It takes your process and
understand that it is required to perform
the same operation or
process to each member of the set.
The figure on the left
here shows the application
of a map function to data
depicted in grey color.
Here colors red, blue, and
yellow are keys to identify each data set.
As you see, each data set is executed
separately even for the same colored key.
The reduce operation helps you then
to collectively apply the same
process to objects of similar nature.
For example, when you want to add your
monthly spending in different categories,
like grocery, fuel, and dining out,
the reduce operation is very useful.
In our figure here on the top left,
we see that data sets in
grey with the same color
are keys grouped together
using a reduced function.
Reds together, blues together,
and yellows together.
It would be a good idea to check out
the Spark word count hands-on to see
how map and reduce can be used
effectively for getting things done.
Map and reduce are types of
transformations that work on a single
list of key and data pairings just
like we see on the left of our figure.
Now let's consider a scenario where
we have two data sets identified
by the same keys just like the two
sets and colors in our diagram.
Many operations have such needs where
we have to look at all the pairings of
all key value pairs,
just like crossing two matrices.
For a practical example
Imagine you have two teams,
a sales team with two people, and
an operations team with four people.
In an event you would want each
person to meet every other person.
In this case, a cross product, or
a cartesian product, becomes a good
choice for organizing the event and
sharing each pairs' meeting location and
travel time to them.
In a cross or cartesian product operation,
each data partition gets
paired with all other data partitions,
regardless of its key.
This sometimes gets
referred to as all pairs.
Now add to the cross product by
just grouping together the data
partitions with the same key,
just like the red data.
And the yellow data partitions here.
This is a typical match or join operation.
As we see in the figure here, match
is very similar to the cross product,
except that it is more
selective in forming pairs.
Every pair must have something in common.
This something in common is
usually referred to as a key.
For example,
each person in your operations team and
sales team is assigned
to a different product.
You only want those people to meet
who are working on the same product.
In this case your key is product.
And you can perform and
match operation and
send e-mails to those people
who share a common product.
The number of e-mails is likely to be less
than when you performed a cartesian or
a cross product, therefore reducing
the cost of the operation.
In a match operation, only the keys
with data in both sets get joined,
and become a part of the final
output of the transformation.
Now let's consider listing
the data sets with all the keys,
even if they don't exist in both sets.
Consider a scenario where you
want to do brainstorming sessions
of people from operations and sales, and
get people who work on the same
products in the same rooms.
A co-group operation will do this for you.
You give it a product name
as they key to work with and
the two tables, the sales team and
operations team.
The co-group will create groups
which contain team members
working on common products even if a
product doesn't exist in one of the sets.
The last operation we will
see is the filter operation.
Filter works much like a test
where only elements that pass
a test are shown in the output.
Consider as a set that contains teams and
a number of members in their teams.
If your game requires people to pair up,
you may want to select teams which
have an even number of members.
In this case, you can create a test
that only passes the teams which have
an even number of team members shown as
divided by 2 with 0 in the remainder.
The real effectiveness of the basic
transformation we saw here
is in pipelining them in a way that
helps you to solve your specific
problem just as you would perform
a series of tasks on a real block
of wood to make a fine piece of
woodwork that you can use to steer your
ship, which in this case is
your business or research.
Now that we revealed all three layers,
we are ready to come back to
the Integration and Processing layer.
Just a simple Google search for
Big Data Processing Pipelines
will bring a vast number of pipelines
with large number of technologies
that support scalable data cleaning,
preparation, and analysis.
How do we make sense of it all to
make sure we use the right tools for
our application?
We will continue our lecture to review
a set of evaluation criteria for
these systems and some of the big data
processing systems based on this criteria.
Depending on the resources we have access
to and characteristics of our application,
we apply several
considerations to evaluate and
pick a software stack for big data.
Of these, first one we consider
is the Execution Model,
and the expressivity of it to support for
various transformations of batch or
streaming data, or
sometimes interactive computing.
Semantics of streaming,
including exactly once or
at least one processing for each event, or
being able to keep the state of the data,
is an important concern for
this execution model.
Latency is another important criteria,
depending on the application.
Having a low latency system
is very important for
applications like online gaming and
hazards management.
Whereas most applications
are less time critical,
like search engine indexing, and would
be fine with a batch processing ability.
Scalability for both small and
large datasets and different
analytical methods and algorithms,
is also an important evaluation criteria.
As well as support for
different programming language
of the libraries used by the analytical
tools that we have access to.
Finally, while all big data
tools provide fault tolerance,
the mechanics of how the fault tolerance is
handled is an important issue to consider.
Let's review five of
the big data processing
engines supported by the Apache Foundation
using this evaluation criteria.
The MapReduce implementation of
Hadoop provides a batch execution
model where the data from HDFS gets
loaded into mappers before processing.
There is no in-memory processing support,
meaning the mappers write the data on
files before the reducers can read it,
resulting in a high-latency and
less scalable execution.
This also hinders
the performance of iterative and
interactive applications that require many
steps of transformations using MapReduce.
Although the only native
programming interface for
MapReduce is in Java, other programming
languages like Python provide modules or
libraries for Hadoop MapReduce
programming, however with less efficiency.
Data replication is the primary
method of fault tolerance,
which in turn affects the scalability and
execution speed further.
Spark was built to support iterative and
interactive big data processing
pipelines efficiently using an in-memory
structure called Resilient Distributed
Datasets, or shortly, RDDs.
In addition to map and reduce operations,
it provides support for
a range of transformation
operations like join and filter.
Any pipeline of transformations can
be applied to these RDD's in-memory,
making Spark's performance very high for
iterative processing.
The RDD extraction is also designed
to handle fault tolerance with
less impact on performance.
In addition to HDFS,
Spark can read data from many storage
platforms and it provides support for
streaming data applications using
a technique called micro-batching.
Its latency can be on the order of
seconds depending on the batch size,
which is relatively slower compared
to native streaming platforms.
Spark has support for a number of
programming languages, including Scala and
Python as the most popular ones,
as well as built-in libraries for
graph processing and machine learning.
Although Flink has very
similar transformations and
in-memory data extractions with Spark,
it provides direct support for
streaming data,
making it a lower-latency framework.
It provides connection interfaces to
streaming data ingestion engines like
Kafka and Flume.
Flink supports application
programming interfaces in Java and
Scala just like Spark.
Starting with it's original
version called Stratosphere,
Flink had it's own execution engine
called Nephele, and had an ability
to run both on Hadoop and also separately
in its own execution environment.
In addition to map and reduce,
Flink provides abstractions for
other data parallel database
patterns like join and group by.
One of the biggest advantage of using
Flink comes from it's optimizer
to pick and apply the best pattern and
execution strategy.
There has been experiments comparing
fault tolerance features of Flink
to those of Sparks, which conclude
that Sparks slightly better for Spark.
The Beam system, from Google,
is a relatively new system for
batch and stream processing with
a data flow programming model.
It initially used Google's own Cloud data
flow as an execution environment, but
Spark and Flink backends for
it have been implemented recently.
It's a low-latency environment with
high reviews on fault tolerance.
It currently provides application
programming interfaces in Java and
Scala, and a Python SDK is in the works.
SDK means software development kit.
Beam provides a very strong streaming and
windowing framework for streaming data.
And it is highly scalable and reliable,
allowing it to make trade-off
decisions between accuracy,
speed, and cost of processing.
Storm has been designed for
stream processing in real
time with very low-latency.
It defined input stream interface
abstractions called spouts, and
computation abstractions called bolts.
Spouts and bolts can be pipelined
together using a data flow approach.
That data gets queued until
the computation acknowledges
the receipt of it.
A master node tracks running jobs and
ensures all data is processed
by the computations on workers.
Nathan Mars, the lead developer for
Storm, built the Lambda Architecture
using Storm for stream processing and
Hadoop MapReduce for batch processing.
The Lambda Architecture
originally used Storm for
speed layer and Hadoop and
HBase for batch and
serving layers, as seen in this diagram.
However, it was later used as a more
general framework that can combine
the results of stream and batch processing
executed in multiple big data systems.
This diagram shows a generalized Lambda
Architecture containing some of the tools
we discussed earlier, including using
Spark for both batch and speed layers.
In this course, we picked Spark
as a big data integration and
processing environment since it supports
most of our evaluation criteria.
And this hybrid data processing
architecture using built-in data querying,
streaming, and analytical libraries.
We will continue our discussion with
Spark and hands-on exercises in Spark.
Analytical operations
in big data pipelines.
After this video,
you will be able to list common analytical
operations within big data pipelines and
describe sample applications for
these analytical operations.
In this lesson, we will be
looking at analytical operations.
These are operations used in analytics,
which is the process of
transforming data into insights for
making more informed decisions.
The purpose of analytical operations is to
analyze the data to discover meaningful
trends and patterns, in order to gain
insights into the problem being studied.
The knowledge gained from these insights
ultimately lead to more informed
decisions driven by data.
Here are some common analytical operations
that we will discuss in this lecture.
Classification, clustering,
path analysis and connectivity analysis.
Let's start with classification.
In classification, the goal is to predict
a categorical target from the input data.
A categorical target is one
with discreet values or
categories, instead of continuous values.
For example, this diagram shows
a classification task to determine the
risk associated with a loan application.
The input consists of the loan amount,
applicant information such as income,
age, debts, and a down payment.
From this input data,
the task is to determine whether
the loan application is low risk or
high risk.
There are many classification techniques
or algorithms that can be used for
this problem.
We will discuss a specific one, namely,
decision tree in the next slide.
The decision tree algorithm is
one technique for classification.
With this technique,
decisions to perform the classification
task are modeled as a tree structure.
For the loan risk assessment problem,
a simple decision tree is shown here,
where the loan application is
classified as being either low risk, or
high risk, based on the loan amount.
The applicant's income,
and the applicant's age.
The decision tree algorithm is implemented
in many machine learning tools.
This diagram shows how to specify
decision tree from input data, KNIME.
A graphical user-interface-based
machine learning platform.
Some examples of classification
are the prediction of whether cells from
a tumor are benign or
malignant, categorization of
handwritten digits as being zero,
one, two, etc, up to nine.
And determining whether a credit card
transaction is legitimate or fraudulent,
and classification of a loan application
as being low-risk, medium-risk or
high-risk, as you've seen.
Another common analytical
operation is cluster analysis.
In cluster analysis, or clustering,
the goal is to organize similar
items in to groups of association.
This diagram shows an example of cluster
analysis in which customers are clustered
into groups according to their
preferences of movie genre.
So, customers who like Sci-Fi
movies are grouped together.
Those who like drama movies
are grouped together,
and customers who like horror
movies are grouped together.
With this grouping, new movies,
as well as other products,
such as books, can be offered to
the right type of costumers in order to
generate interest and increase revenue.
A simple and commonly used algorithm for
cluster analysis is k-means.
With k-means,
samples are divided into k clusters.
This clustering is done in order
to minimize the variance or
similarity between samples
within the same cluster
using some similarity
measures such as distance.
In this example, k is equal to three, and
k-means divides the original data shown
on the left into three clusters,
shown as blue, green, and
red on the chart on the right.
The k-means clustering algorithm is
implemented on many machine-learning
platforms.
The code here shows how to read in and
parse input data, and
perform k-means clustering on the data.
Other examples of cluster analysis
are grouping a company’s customer base
into distinct segments for more effective
targeted marketing, finding articles or
webpages with similar topics for
retrieving relevant information.
Identification of areas in the city with
rates of particular types of crimes for
effective management of law
enforcement resources, and
determining different groups of weather
patterns such as rainy, cold or snowy.
Classification and cluster analysis
are considered machine learning and
analytical operations.
There are also analytical
operations from graph analytics,
which is the field of analytics where
the underlying data is structured as, or
can be modeled as the set of graphs.
One analytical operation using
graphs as path analysis,
which analyzes sequences of nodes and
edges in a graph.
A common application of path analysis
is to find routes from one
location to another location.
For example, you might want to find the
shortest path from your home to your work.
This path may be different depending on
conditions such as the day of the week,
time of day, traffic congestion,
weather and etc.
This code shows some operations for
path analysis on neo4j,
which is a graph database system
using a query language called Cypher.
The first operation finds the shortest
path between specific nodes in a graph.
The second operation finds all
the shortest paths in a graph.
Connectivity analysis of graphs
has to do with finding and
tracking groups to determine
interactions between entities.
Entities in highly interacting
groups are more connected
to each other than to entities
of other groups in a graph.
These groups are called communities, and
are interesting to analyze as they
give insights into the degree and
patterns of the interaction between
entities, and also between communities.
Some applications of connectivity analysis
are to extract conversation threads.
For example,
by looking at tweets and retweets.
To find interacting groups, for example,
to determine which users are interacting
with each other users, to find
influencers, for example, to understand
who are the main users leading to
the conversation about a particular topic.
Or, who do people pay attention to?
This information can be used to
identify the fewest number of
people with the greatest influence.
For example, for political campaigns,
or marketing on social media.
This code shows some operations for
connectivity analysis on neo4j using
the query language, Cypher, again.
The first operation finds the degree
of all the nodes in a graph,
and the second creates a histogram
of degrees for all nodes in a graph
to determine how connected a node in
a graph is, we need to look at its degree.
The degree of a node is the number
of edges connected to the node.
A degree histogram shows the distribution
of node degrees in the graph and
is useful in comparing graphs and
identifying types of users, for
example, those who follow, versus those
who are followed in social networks.
To summarize and add to these techniques,
the decision tree algorithm for
classification and k-means algorithm for
cluster analysis that we covered in this
lecture are techniques
from machine learning.
Machine learning is a field of analytics
focused on the study and construction of
computer systems that can learn from data
without being explicitly programmed.
Our course on machine learning in
this specialization will cover these
algorithms in more detail,
along with other algorithms used for
classification and cluster analysis.
As well as algorithms for
other machine learning tasks,
such as regression,
association analysis, and tools for
implementing and
executing machine learning algorithms.
As a summary of the Graph Analytics,
the Path Analytics technique for finding
the shortest path and the connectivity
analysis technique for analyzing communities
that we discussed earlier,
are techniques used in graph analytics.
As explained earlier,
graph analytics is the field of analytics,
where the underlying data is structured or
can be modeled as a set of graphs.
Our graph analytics course in the
specialization will cover these and other
graph techniques, and we'll also cover
tools and platforms for graph analytics.
In summary, analytic operations
are used to discover meaningful
patterns in the data in order to provide
insights into the problem being studied.
We looked at some of the examples of
analytical operations for classification,
cluster analysis, path analysis and
connectivity analysis in this lecture.
In this hands-on activity,
we'll be performing word count on
the complete works of Shakespeare.
First, we will copy the Shakespeare
text into the Hadoop file system.
Next, we will create a new
Jupyter Notebook, and
read the Shakespeare
text into a Spark RDD.
We will then perform WordCount
using map and reduce,
and write the results to HDFS and
view the contents.
Let's begin.
In the intro to big data course,
we copy the Shakespeare text into HDFS.
Let's see if it's still there.
If not, we can copy it now.
Click on the terminal icon
at the top of the toolbar.
Now we can run hadoop fs- ls to see what's
in our hadoop filesystem directory.
There are no files in HTFS,
so let's copy it.
If you already have words.txt in your HTFS
directory, you can skip this next step.
Cd into downloads,
big-data-3/spark-wordcount.
We can do ls to see the file.
Let's copy this file to HTFS.
We run Hadoop,
fs copy from local, words.txt.
We can write Hadoop fs -ls again
to verify that the file is there.
Now let's do work count in spark.
We will do this in an iPython
notebook using Jupyter server.
Look on the web browser icon,
the top of the toolbar.
And go to the Jupyter server URL,
which is local host port 8889.
Next, let's create a new iPython notebook
The first step is to read the words.txt
files in HTFS into a spark RDD.
We'll call the RDD, lines.
We can read it using the spark context SC,
in calling the text file method.
The argument is the URL of
the word set TXT file and HDFS.
Let's run this We can
view the contents of this RDD
by calling lines.take(5).
The argument 5 says how many
lines to show of the RDD.
Next, we'll transform this RDD
of lines into an RDD of words.
We'll say, words = lines.flatmap,
lambda line:
line.split Double quote
space double quote.
This creates a new RDD called, words,
by running flatMap over the line RDD.
The argument is this lambda expression.
A lambda in Python is a simple way
to declare a one line expression.
In this case,
there's one argument called line and
we called it split method on this line and
we split on spaces.
We can run this and
look at the contents of words.
We can see that each element
now is an individual word.
Next, we'll create tuples of these words.
We'll put them in a new RDD called tuples.
Enter, tuples
= words.map:lambda
word; (word, 1).
This creates the tuples
by transforming words.
This uses map and another lambda function.
In this case, the lambda takes
one argument and returns a tuple.
Where the first value of
the tuple is the word.
The second value, is the number 1.
Not that in this case, we use map,
whereas before, we used flat map.
In this case, we want a tuple for
every word in the words.
So we have a one to one mapping
between inputs and outputs.
Previously, while we were splitting lines
into word, each line had multiple words.
In general,
you want to use map when you have a one to
one mapping between inputs and outputs.
In flatMap you have a one to many or
none mapping between inputs and
outputs Let's run this and look at tuples.
We can see that each word now has
a tuple initialized with the count of 1.
We can now count all the words by
combining or reducing these tuples.
We'll put this in a new RDD called counts.
So we'll say counts equals
tuples.reduce by key.
Lambda a,b:.
a + b.
In this case, the lambda function
takes two arguments, a and be, and
will return the result of adding a and b.
To view the result,
You can see now that the counts for
each words have been created.
We can write this result back to HDFS.
Let's say
counts.coalesce(1).saveAsTextFile,
and then the URL.
The coalesce means we only
want a single output file.
Let's go back to our shell and
view the results.
We'll run hadoop fs -ls
to see the directory.
And run it again to look inside
the wordcount directory.
And once more,
to look inside wordcount/outputDir.
As you recall,
the output from hadoop jobs is part-0000.
This is also true for spark jobs.
Let's copy this file to
the local file system.
We'll run hadoop fs CopyToLocal
wordcount/outputDir/part-00000.
You can view the results with more.
In this hands on activity,
we will be using Spark Streaming
to read weather data.
First, we open
the Spark Streaming Jupyter Notebook.
Next, we will look at sensor format and
measurement types.
We'll then create a Spark DStream of
weather data, read the measurements, and
create a sliding window of the data.
We will define a function to display the
maximum and minimum values in the window.
We start to stream processing
to give their results.
Before we begin this activity, we need
to change the virtual box settings for
our carder virtual machine.
Start streaming needs more
than one thread of execution.
So we need to change the settings to
add more than one virtual processor.
First, shut down your cloudera virtual
machine and go to the virtual box manager.
Select the cloudera virtual box and
click on settings.
Next, click on system, click on Processor.
And change the number of
CPU's to be two or more.
When you're done, click okay,
and start the machine as usual.
Let's begin.
First, click on the browser icon
at the top of the tool bar.
Navigate to the Jupyter Notebook server,
monitoring local host calling 8889.
We'll then go in to downloads.
Big data 3.
Spark-streaming.
Let's then open Spark-Streaming notebook.
This first line, shows the example
data we get from the weather station.
Each line has a time stamp and
a set of measurements.
Each of these abbreviations is
a particular type of measurement,
followed by the actual value.
The next cell shows the key for
these measurements.
For this hands-on, we are interested
in the average wind direction.
Which is abbreviated as DM.
This next cell, defines a function
that parses each line of text and
pulls out the average wind speed.
We define it here, so
we don't have to type it in later.
Let's run this cell.
Next, let's create
a streaming spark context.
First, we'll need to import the module.
We'll enter from pyspark.streaming
import StreamingContext.
We can create a new streaming context.
We'll put in in a variable called ssc.
We'll enter ssc = StreamingContext(sc,1).
The SC is a StreamingContext.
The 1 specifies the batch interval,
1 second in this case.
Let's run this.
Next, we'll create a dstream.
We'll import the streaming weather data,
over a TCP connection.
We'll put this in a dstream called, Lines.
Let's say lines = ssc.socketTextStream,
we'll enter the host name in
port of the weather station,
rtd.hpwren.ucsd.edu for 12028.
Let's run this.
Next, we'll create a new d-stream called
vals that would hold the measurements.
We'll say vals = lines.flatMap parse.
This calls the parse function,
we defined above for
each of the lines coming
from the weather station.
The resulting D-Stream will have just
the average wind direction values.
We'll run this.
Next, we'll create a window that
will aggregate the D-Stream values.
We'll say, window = vals.window(10,5).
The first argument specifies that the
length of the window should be 10 seconds.
The second argument specifies that
the window should move every 5 seconds.
Let's run this.
Next, we'll define a function
that prints the minimum and
maximum values that we see.
We'll start by entering the definition.
Def stats,
this will take an rdd as an argument.
Next, let's print the entire
contents of the rdd.
Print, parenthesis rdd.collect,
this'll print the entire
content of the rdd.
In a real big data application,
this will be impractical due
to the size of the data.
However, for this hands on,
the rdd is small, and so
we can use this to see
the contents of the rdd.
Next, we'll print the min and max.
Before we do that however,
we should check to make sure that
the size of the rdd is greater than zero.
We'll check that rdd.count
is greater than 0.
Finally, we'll print the MinID, MAX.
We'll enter print (“max = {} min =
{}”) Outside of the quote we'll do
.format(rdd.max,rdd.min())).
Let's run this, next,
let's call this function stats.
So all the rdds in our sliding window.
I'll enter window.foreachRDD(stats).
Run this.
We're now ready to start
our streaming processing.
We can do this by entering ssc.start.
We'll run this to start the streaming.
When we want to stop this streaming,
we'll run ssc.stop
Please scroll up and
look at the beginning of the output.
We'll see that it's printing the full
window and the min and max values.
Notice that in the beginning,
the window is not yet filled.
In this case, there's only three entries.
We count to see that the window
is moving by five measurements.
For example, the last five
measurements in the second window,
are the first five measurements
in the third window.
In this hands on activity we
will be using SparkSQL to
query data from an SQL database.
First we will open
the SparkSQL Jupyter Notebook.
We will connect Spark to a Postgres table.
And then view the Spark DataFrame
schema and count the rows.
We will view the contents
of the data frame.
See how to filter rows and columns.
And finally perform aggregate
operation on a column.
Let's begin.
First, click on the browser icon,
the top of the toolbar.
>> [SOUND]
>> Next,
navigate to the Jupyter Notebook server.
It's localhost:8889.
Go to Downloads,
Big Data 3, Spark SQL.
To open the SparkSQL Notebook.
The first three cells have
already been entered for you.
First, we import the SQLContext, run this.
Next, we create an SQLContext
from the SparkContext run this.
And next, we'll create a Spark DataFrame
from a Postgres table.
We used the read attribute format.
The jdbc argument means that we're
using a Java database connection.
The next line sets the URL option.
It says we're using Postgres
database running on the local host.
The database name is Cloudera and
the username is Cloudera.
The second option, DB table,
says we want our data frame
to be the game clicks table.
And finally we call load.
Let's execute this.
You can see the schema of the data
frame by calling df.printschema.
This shows the name of each
column along with the data type.
We can count the rows in this
df frame by calling df.count.
We can look at the first five
rows by calling df.show(5)
This shows all the columns
in the data frame.
We can select specific columns
by using the select method.
Let's select just the User ID and
Team Level columns.
I'll enter df.select("userid",teamlevel.
Parenthesis.
And finally we only want to
see the top five rows.
So we'll do .show(5).
We can also select rows
that have a specific value.
Let's look for the rows where
the team level is greater than one.
We'll enter df.filter.
We'll specify that we want team level
greater than one by entering df,
square bracket, team level,
greater than one.
And again, we only want the user ID and
team level columns.
And finally only the first five rows.
We can use the group by method to
aggregate a particular column.
For example, the ishit column
has a value of zero or one.
And we can use group by to count how
many times each of these values occurs.
Or a df.groupby ishit, and
we'll call count to count the values
We can also perform aggregate statistical
operations on the data in a data frame.
Let's compute the mean and
sum values for ishit.
First we need to import
the statistical functions we'll
run from.pyspark.sql.functions
import star.
Next we'll run df.select
(mean) ishit,sum ishit
We can also join two data
frames on a particular column.
Let's join the existing data frame of the
game clicks table with the adclicks table.
First, we need to create data frame for
the adclicks table.
Let's go back up.
Copy the content of this cell,
Paste it.
We put the adclicks table
the data frame called df2.
And we'll change the db table
option to the adclicks.
Run it.
Let's print the schema of df2.
You can see that it also has
a column called user id.
So let's join the game clicks
data frame with the add
clicks data frame on this column.
We put the result in a new
data frame called merged.
We'll say merge = df.join.df2 "userid".
We'll run it.
Let's look at the schema.
We'll call merge.printschema.
We can see that this merged data frame
has the column for both game clicks and
adclicks.
Finally we'll look at the top five
rows in this merged data frame.
We'll run merge.show.
We have now seen some
simple transformations and
how Spark can create RDDs from
each other using transformations.
We learned that transformations are
evaluated after an action is performed.
So we can simply define actions as RDD
operations that trigger the evaluation of
the transformation pipeline and return
the final result to the driver program or
save the results to a persistent storage.
We can also call them the last
step in a Spark pipeline.
Let's now look at a few action operations.
After this video, you will be able to
explain the steps of a Spark pipeline
ending with a collect action and list
four common action operations in Spark.
A very common action in Spark is collect.
In this example, we can imagine that
initially we are reading from HDFS.
The RDD partitions that go through
the transformation steps in our big data
pipeline are defined as flatMap and
groupbyKey.
When the final step is done,
the collect action is called and
Spark sends all the tasks for
execution to the worker notes.
Collect will send all the resulting
RDDs from the workers and
copy them to the Java virtual
machine on the driver program.
And then, this will be piped
also to our Python shell.
While collect copies all the data,
another action, take,
copies the first n results of the driver.
If the results are too large
to fit in the driver memory,
then there's an opportunity to write
them directly to HDFS instead.
Among many other actions,
reduce is probably the most famous one.
Reduce takes two elements and
returns a result, like sum.
But in this case, we don't have a key,
we just have a large area of some values.
And we are running this function over and
over again to reduce everything
to one single value.
For example,
to the global sum of everything.
Another very useful action Is saveAsText,
to save the results to local disk or
HDFS, and
this is very useful if the output of
the power computation is pretty large.
Hello, I hope you enjoyed your first
programming experience with Spark.
Although the words count
example is simple,
it is useful in starting to
understand how to work with RDDs.
After this video, you'll be able to use
two methods to create RDDs in Spark,
explain what immutable means,
interpret a Spark program as a pipeline
of transformations and actions, and
list the steps to create a Spark program.
So let's remember where we are.
We have a Driver Program that
defines the Spark context.
This is the entry point
to your application.
The driver converts all the data to RDDs,
and
everything from this point on
gets managed using the RDDs.
RDDs can be constructed from files or
any other storage.
They can also be constructed from
data structures for collections and
programs, like lists.
All the transformations and actions on
these RDDs take place either locally,
or on the Worker Nodes
managed by a Cluster Manager.
Each transformation results in
a new updated version of the RDD.
The RDDs at the end get converted and
saved in a persistent storage like HDFS or
your local drive.
As we mentioned before,
RDDs get created in the Driver Program.
The developer of the Driver Program,
who in this case is you,
is responsible for creating them.
You can just read in a file
through your Spark Context, or
as we have in this example,
you can provide an existing collection,
like a list to be turned into
a distributed collection.
You can also create an integer
RDD using parallelize,
and provide a number of partitions for
distribution as we do create
the numbers RDD in this line.
Here, the range function in Python
will give us a list of
numbers starting from 0 to 9.
The parallelize function
will create three partitions
of the RDD to be distributed, based on
the parameter that was provided to it.
Spark will decide how to assign partitions
to our executors and worker nodes.
The distributed RDDs can in the end be
gathered into a single partition on
the driver using
the collect transformation.
Now let's think of a scenario were we
start processing the created RDDs.
There are two types of operations
that help with processing in Spark,
namely Transformations and Actions.
All partitions written in RDD,
go through the same transformation in
the worker node, executors when
a transformation is applied to an RDD.
Spark uses lazy evaluation for
transformations.
That means they will not be
immediately executed, but
instead wait for
an action to be performed.
The transformations get computed
when an action is executed.
For this reason,
a lot of times you will see run
time errors showing up at the action stage
and not at the transformation stages.
It is very similar to Haskell or Erlang,
if any of you are familiar
with these languages.
Let's put some names on
these transformations.
We can have a pipeline by converting a
text file into an RDD with two partitions.
Filter some values out of it, and
maybe apply a map function to it.
In the end, the run,
the collect action on the mapped RDDs
to evaluate the results of the pipeline
and convert the outputs into results.
Here, filter and map are transformations,
and collect is the action.
Although the RDDs are in memory,
and they are not persistent,
we can use the cash function
to make them persistent cash.
For example, in order to reuse the RDD
created from a database query that could
otherwise be costly to re-execute,
we can instead cache these RDDs.
We need to use caution when
using the cache option,
as it can consume too much memory and
generate a bottleneck itself.
As a part of the Word Count example, we
mapped the words RDD to generate tuples.
We then applied reduceByKey
to tuples to generate counts.
In the end, we convert the number
of partitions to one so
that output is one file
when written to this later.
Otherwise, output will be spread
over multiple files on disk.
Finally, saveAsTextFile is an action
that kickstarts the computation and
writes to disk.
To summarize, in a typical Spark program
we create RDDs from external storage or
local collections like lists.
Then we apply transformations
to these RDDs,
like filter, map, and reduceByKey.
These transformations get lazily
evaluated until an action is performed.
Actions are performed both for local and
parallel computation to generate results.
Next, we will talk more about
transformation and actions in Spark.
In the last video,
we talked about the programming model for
Spark where RDD's get generated from
external datasets and gets partitioned.
We said, RDDs are immutable meaning they
can't be changed in place even partially.
They need a transformation
operation applied to them and
get converted into a new RDD.
This is essential for keeping track
of all the processing that has been
applied to our dataset providing the
ability to keep a linear chain of RDDs.
In addition, as a part of a big data
pipeline, we start with an RDD.
And through several transformation steps,
many other RDDs as
intermediate products get executed
until we get to our final result.
We also mention that
an important feature of Spark
is that all these transformation are lazy.
This means they don't execute
immediately when applied to an RDD.
So when we apply a transformation,
nothing happens right away.
We are basically preparing our big
data pipeline to be executed later.
When we are done defining all
the transformations and perform an action,
Spark will take care of finding the best
way to execute this computation and
then start all the necessary
tasks in our worker nodes.
In this video, we will explain some
common transformation in Spark.
After this video, you will be able
to explain the difference between
a narrow transformation and
wide transformation.
Describe map, flatmap,
filter and coalesce as narrow
transformations and
list two wide transformations.
Let's take at look at, probably the
simplest transformation, which is a map.
By now,
you're well versed in home networks.
It applies the function to each
partition or element of an RDD.
This is a one to one transformation.
It is also in the category of element-wise
transformations since it transforms
every element of an RDD separately.
The code example in the blue
box here applies a function
called lower to all
the elements in a text_RDD.
The lower function
turns all the characters in
a line to lower case letters.
So the input is one line
of text with any kind of
capitalization and the outfit is going
to be the same line, all lower case.
In this example, we have two worker
nodes drawn as orange boxes.
The black boxes are partitions
of our dataset.
We work by partition and not by element.
As you would remember this, it is the
difference between Spark and MapReduce.
The partition is just a chunk of our data
with some number of elements in it and
the map function gets applied to all
elements in that partition in each
worker node locally.
Each node applies the map
function to the data or
RDD partition they received independently.
Let's look at a few more in
element-wise transformation category.
FlatMap is very similar to map.
However, instead of returning
an individual element for each map,
it returns an RDD with an aggregate of
all the results for all the elements.
In the example in the blue box,
the split_words fuction
takes a line as an input,
which is one element and it's output
is each word as a single element.
So, it splits a line to words.
The same thing gets done for each line.
When the output for
all the lines is flattened,
we get a simple
one-dimensional list of words.
So, we'll get all the words in
all the lines in just one list.
Depending on the line length the output
partitions might be of different sizes.
Detected here by the height of
each black box being different.
In Spark terms, map and
flatMap are narrow transformations.
Narrow transformation refers to
the processing where the processing
logic depends only on data that is
already residing in the partition and
data shuffling is not necessary.
Another very important
transformation is filter.
Often, we're interested just
in a subset of our data or
we want to get rid of bad data.
Filter transformation takes the function
take executes on each element
of a RDD partition and
returns only the elements that
the transformation element returns true.
The example code in the blue box here,
applies a filter
function that filters out words
that start with the letter a.
The function starts with a,
takes the input word,
then transforms it to lowercase and
then checks if the word starts with a.
So, the output of this operation will be
a list with only words that start with a.
This is another narrow transformation.
So, it only gets executed locally
without the need to shuffle any RDD
partitions across the word kernels.
The output of filter depends on
the input and the filter functions.
In some cases,
even if you started with even RDD
partitions within the worker nodes,
the RDD size can significantly vary across
the workers after a filter operation,
then this happens is a pretty good
idea to join some of those partitions
to increase performance and
even out processing across clusters.
This transformation is called coalesce.
Coalesce simply helps with balancing
the data partition numbers and sizes.
When you have significantly reduced
your initial data after some filters and
other transformations,
having a large number of partitions
might not be very useful anymore.
In this case,
you can use coalesce to reduce the number
of partitions to a more manageable number.
Until now, we talked about narrow
transformations that happen in a worker
node locally without having to
transfer data through the network.
Now, let's start talking
about wide transformations.
Let's remember our Word Count example.
As a part of the Word Count example, we
map the words RDD could generate tuples.
The output of map is a key value pair
list where the key is the word and
the value is always one.
We then apply it reduceByKey
to tuples to generate counts,
which simply sums the values for
each key or word.
Let's imagine for a second that we use
groupByKey instead of reduceByKey.
We will come back to reduceByKey
in just a little bit.
Remember, mapped outputs tuples,
which is a list of key value
pairs in the forms of word one.
At each worker node, we will have
tuples that have the same word as key.
In this example, apple as the key and
1 as the count and 2 worker nodes.
Trying to group together, all the counts
of a word across worker nodes
requires shuffling of
data between these nodes.
Just like we do for the word apple here.
GroupByKey is the transformation
that helps us combine values with
the same key into a list without applying
a special user define function to it.
As you see on the right, the result
of a groupByKey transformation on all
the map outputs by the word apple is
the key ends up in a list with all ones.
If you instead apply the function to
list like summing up all the values,
then we could have had
the word count results.
In this case, 2.
If we instead applied a function to
the list like summing up all the values,
then we would have had
the word count results.
If we need to apply such functions to
a group of values related to a key like
this, we use the reduceByKey operation.
ReduceByKey helps us to combine
the value using a reduce function,
which in the word count
case is a simple summation.
In groupByKey and
reduceByKey transformations,
we observe the behavior that require
shuffling of the data across work nodes,
we call such transformations
wide transformations.
In wide transformation operations,
processing depends on data
residing in multiple partitions
distributed across worker nodes and this
requires data shuffling over the network
to bring related datasets together.
As a summary, we have listed a small
number of transformations in Spark with
some examples and distinguished between
them as narrow and wide transformations.
Although this is a good start,
I advise you to go through the list
provided at the link shown here after
you complete this beginner course.
Read about the rest of the transformations
in Spark before you start programming in
Spark and have fun with transformations.
Lastly, we will introduce
you to Spark GraphX.
After this video,
you will be able to describe GraphX is,
explain how vertices and
edges are stored in GraphX, and
describe how Pregel works at a high level.
GraphX is Apache Spark's Application
Programming Interface for
graphs and graph-parallel computation.
GraphX uses a property graph model.
This means, both nodes.
And edges in a graph can
have attributes and values.
In GraphX, the node properties
are stored in a vertex table and
edge properties are stored
in an edge table.
The connectivity information, that is,
which edge connects which nodes,
is stored separately from the node and
edge properties.
GraphX is built on special RDDs for
vertices and edges.
VertexRDD represents a set of vertices,
all of which have an attribute called A.
The EdgeRDD here extends
this basic edge storing by
the edges in columnar format on
each partition for performance.
Note that VertexID are defined
to be unique by design.
The edge class is an object
with a source vertex and
destination vertex and an edge attribute.
In addition to the vortex and
edge views of the property graph,
GraphX also has triplet view.
The triplet view logically joins
vortex and edge properties.
GraphX has an operator that
can execute operations
from the Pregel library for
graph analytics.
This Pregel operator executes
in a series of super steps
which defines a messaging protocol for
vertices.
We will revisit graph analytics and
using GraphX in more detail in
course five of the specialization.
In summary, Spark can be used for
graph parallel computations.
GraphX uses special RDDs for
storing vertex and edge information.
And the pregel operator works
in a series of super steps.
Now, we will introduce you to Spark MLlib.
After this video, you will be
able to describe what MLlib is,
list the main categories of
techniques available in MLlib,
and explain code segments
containing MLlib algorithms.
MLlib is a scalable machine learning
library that runs on top of Spark Core.
It provides distributed implementations
of commonly used machine learning
algorithms and utilities.
As with Spark Core, MLlib has APIs for
Scala, Java, Python, and R.
MLlib offers many algorithms and
techniques commonly used in
a machine learning process.
The main categories are machine learning,
statistics and some common utility
tools for common techniques.
As the name suggests,
many machine learning algorithms
are available in MLlib.
These are algorithms to build models for
classification, regression, and
clustering.
There are also techniques for
evaluating the resulting models.
For example,
you can compute the values for
a receiver of creating characteristic
that we call an ROC curve.
A common statistical technique for
plotting the performance
of a binary classifier.
Statistical functions
are also provided in MLlib.
Examples are summary statistics,
means, standard deviation, etc.
Correlations and
methods to sample a dataset.
MLlib also has techniques commonly
used in the machine learning process,
such as dimensionality reduction and
feature transformation methods for
preprocessing the data.
In short, Spark MLlib offers
many techniques often used in
a machine learning pipeline.
Let's take a look at an example to
compute summary statistics using MLlib.
Note that we will use the spark pipe
of API similar to the ones used for
our other examples in this course.
Here is the code segment to
compute summary statistics for
a data set consisting
of columns of numbers.
Lines of code are in white, and
the comments are in orange.
The first line imports statistics
functions from the stat module.
The second line creates an RDD
of Vectors with the data.
You can think of each vector
as a column in a data matrix.
The next line denoted with three invokes
the column stats function to compute
summary statistics for each column.
The last three lines show
by four print out the mean,
variance and number of non-zero
entries for each column.
As you can see from this example,
computing the summary statistics for
a data set is very
straightforward using a MLlib.
Here is another example.
Although we will go through the ratio
learning details in our next course,
here we give you a hint of how to
use two ratio learning techniques.
One for Classification,
and one for Clustering.
This code segment, shows the six steps to
build a DecisionTree for classification.
The first line imports
the DecisionTree module,
the second line imports MLUtils module,
the next line fails the DecisionTree
to classify the data for two classes.
Then, the model is printed out and
finally the model is saved in a file.
Here is another MLlib example,
this time for clustering.
This code segment shows the 5-step
code to build a k-means clustering.
The first line imports the k-means module,
the second line
imports an array module from numpy,
the next two lines read in the data and
parses it using space as the limiter,
then the k-means model
is built by dividing the parsedData
into three clusters.
Finally, the cluster centers
are printed out for each.
In summary,
MLlib is Spark's machine learning library.
It provides algorithms and
techniques that are implemented
using distributors processing.
The main categories of algorithms and
techniques available in machine
learning library are machine learning,
statistics and utility functions for
the machine learning process.
Over the next couple of videos,
we will introduce you to the basic
components of the Spark stack.
In this lecture, we start with Spark SQL.
After this video, you will be able to
process structured data using Spark's SQL
module and explain the numerous
benefits of Spark SQL.
Spark SQL is the component of Spark
that enables querying structured and
unstructured data through
a common query language.
It can connect to many data sources and
provides APIs to convert
the query results to RDDs in Python,
Scala, and Java programs.
Spark SQL gives a mechanism for
SQL users to deploy SQL queries on Spark.
Spark SQL enables business
intelligence tools to connect to
Spark using standard connection
protocols like JDBC and ODBC.
Spark SQL also provides APIs to
convert the query data into DataFrames
to hold distributed data.
DataFrames are organized as named
columns and basically look like tables.
The first step to run any SQL Spark
is to create a SQLContext.
Once you have an SQLContext,
you want to leverage it
to create a DataFrame so you can deploy
complex operations on the data set.
DataFrames can be created
from existing RDDs,
Hive tables or many other data sources.
A file can be read and converted into
a DataFrame using a single command.
The show function here will display
the DataFrame in your Spark show.
RDDs can be converted to DataFrames but
require a little more work.
First you will have to
convert each line into a row.
Once your data is in a DataFrame,
you can perform all sorts of
transformation operations on it
as shown here, including show,
printSchema, select, filter and groupBy.
To summarize, Spark SQL lets you
run relational queries on Spark.
It also lets you connect to
a variety of databases, and
deploy business intelligence
tools over Spark.
We will go through some of this
functionality in one of the readings and
in the upcoming hands-on session.
Next we will talk about Spark streaming.
After this video you will be able to
summarize how Spark reads streaming data,
list several sources of streaming
data supported by Spark, and
describe Spark's sliding windows.
Spark streaming provides
scalable processing for
real-time data and
runs on top of Spark Core.
Continuous data streams are converted or
grouped into discrete RDDs which
can then be processed in parallel.
Spark Streaming provides APIs for Scala,
Java, and Python,
like other Spark products.
Spark Streaming can read
data from many different
types of resources,
including Kafka and Flume.
Kafka is a high throughput published
subscribed messaging system,
and Flume collects and
aggregates log data.
Spark Streaming can also read from batch
input data sources, such as HDFS,
S3, and many other non SQL databases.
Additionally, Spark Streaming can read
directly from Twitter, raw TCP sockets,
and many other data sources that
are real-time data providers.
So how does it all work?
Here we show you a flow of
transformations and actions
which you will try in the upcoming reading
and hands-on exercises on Spark Streaming.
Spark streaming reads
streaming data and
converts it into micro batches
which we call DStreams which is short for
discretized stream.
In this example a 10 second
stream gets converted
into five RDDs using a batch
length of 2 seconds.
Similar to other RDDs,
transformations such as map, reduce,
and filter can be applied to DStreams.
DStreams can be aggregated
into Windows allowing you to apply
computations on sliding window of data.
In this example the Window
size is 4 seconds and
the sliding interval is 2 seconds.
In summary, Spark Streaming is
Spark's library to work with
streaming data in near real time.
DStreams can be used just
like any other RDD and
can go through the same
transformation as batch datasets.
DStreams can create a sliding window to
perform calculations on a window of time.
Now that we know what machine learning
is and have seen some examples of it,
let's talk about how we
do machine learning.
In this lecture we will get an overview of
the main categories of machine learning
techniques.
After this video you will be able to
describe the main categories of
machine learning techniques and
summarize how supervised learning
differs from unsupervised learning.
There are different categories of
machine learning techniques for
different types of problems.
The main categories are listed here.
They are classification,
regression, cluster analysis, and
association analysis.
We will cover each one in
detail in the following slides.
In classification, the goal is to
predict the category of the input data.
An example of this is predicting the
weather as being sunny, rainy, windy, or
cloudy.
The input data in this case would be
sensor data specifying the temperature,
relative humidity, atmospheric pressure,
wind speed, wind direction, etc.
The target or what you're trying to
predict would be the different weather
categories, sunny, windy,
rainy, and cloudy.
Another example is to classify
a tumor as either benign or malignant.
In this case,
the classification is referred to as
binary classification since
there are only two categories.
But you can have many categories as well.
As the weather prediction
problem shown here.
Another example is to identify hand
written digits as being in one of ten
categories, zero to nine.
Some more examples of classification
are classifying a tumor from a medical
image as being benign or malignant.
Predicting whether it
will rain the next day.
Determining if a loan application is
high-risk, medium-risk or low-risk.
Identifying the sentiment of a tweet or
review as being positive,
negative, or neutral.
When your model has to predict
a numeric value instead of a category,
then the task becomes
a regression problem.
An example of regression is to
predict the price of a stock.
The stock price is a numeric value,
not a category.
So this is a regression task
instead of a classification task.
If you were to predict whether
the stock price will rise or
fall, then that would be
a classification problem.
But if you're predicting
the actual price of the stock,
then that is a regression problem.
That is the main difference between
classification and regression.
In classification,
you're predicting a category and
in regression,
you're predicting a numeric value.
Some other examples of regression
are estimating the demand of a product
based on time or season of the year.
Predicting a score on a test,
determining the likelihood of
how effective a drug will be for
a particular patient, predicting
the amount of rain for a region.
In cluster analysis,
the goal is to organize similar
items in your data set into groups.
A very common application of
cluster analysis is referred to as
customer segmentation.
This means that you're separating your
customer base into different groups or
segments based on customer types.
For example it would be very beneficial
to segment your customers into seniors,
adults and teenagers.
These groups have different likes and
dislikes and
have different purchasing behaviors.
By segmenting your customers to different
groups you can more effectively provide
marketing adds targeted for
each groups particular interests.
Note that cluster analysis is
also referred to as clustering.
Some other examples of cluster
analysis are, identifying areas of
similar topography, such as desert region,
grassy areas, mountains etc.
Categorizing different types of
tissues from medical images.
Determining different groups of weather
patterns, such as snowy, dry, monsoon.
And discovering hot spots for different
types of crime from police reports.
The goal in association analysis is
to come up with a set of rules to
capture associations between items or
events.
The rules are used to determine when
items or events occur together.
A common application of association
analysis is known as market
basket analysis.
Which is used to understand
customer purchasing behavior.
For example, association analysis can
reveal that banking customers who have
CDs, or Certificates of Deposits,
also tend to be interested in
other investment vehicles such
as money market accounts.
This information can be used for
cross selling.
If you advertise money market accounts to
your customers with CDs they are likely to
open such an account.
According to data mining folklore
a supermarket chain used association
analysis to discover a connection between
two seemingly unrelated products.
They discovered that many
customers who go to the store
late on Sunday night to buy
diapers also tend to buy beer.
This information was then
used to place beer and
diapers close together and
they saw a jump in sales of both items.
This is the famous diaper,
beer connection.
Some other applications of association
analysis are recommending similar
items based on the purchasing behavior or
browsing histories of customers.
Finding items that are often purchased
together, such as garden hose and
potting soil, and
offer sales on these related items at the
same time to drive sales of both items.
Identifying web pages that
are often accessed together so
that you can more efficiently offer up
these related web pages at the same time.
We have now looked at the different
categories of machine learning techniques.
They are classification,
regression, cluster analysis, and
association analysis.
We have also seen some
examples of each category
There is also another categorization
of machine learning techniques, and
that is supervised versus
unsupervised approaches.
In supervised approaches the target,
which is what the model is predicting,
is provided.
This is referred to as having labeled
data because the target is labeled for
every sample that you
have in your data set.
Referring back to our example of
predicting a weather category of sunny,
windy, rainy or cloudy,
every sample in the data set is labeled
as being one of these four categories.
So the data is labeled and predicting the
weather categories is a supervised task.
In general, classification and
regression are supervised approaches.
In unsupervised approaches
on the other hand,
the target that the model is
predicting is unknown or unavailable.
This means that you have unlabeled data.
Going back to our cluster analysis
example of segmenting customers into
different groups.
The samples in your data are not
labeled with the correct group.
Instead, the segmentation is performed
using a clustering technique to group
items based on characteristics
that they have in common.
Thus, the data is unlabeled and
the task of grouping customers into
different segments is an unsupervised one.
In general, cluster analysis and
association analysis
are unsupervised approaches.
In summary,
in this lecture we looked at the different
categories of machine learning techniques.
We discussed classification, regression,
cluster analysis and association analysis.
We also defined what supervised and
unsupervised approaches are,
in machine learning.
In this lecture,
we will review each of the steps in
the machine learning
process in greater detail.
After this video, you will be able
to explain the goals of each step in
the machine learning process, and list key
activities in each step in the process.
This is the machine learning process
that we saw in the last lecture.
In this lecture,
we will cover each step in more detail.
We will describe the goals
of each step and
the key activities performed in each step.
The first step in the data science
process is to acquire the data.
The goal of the step is to identify and
obtain all data related
to the problem at hand.
First, we need to identify all
related data and the sources.
Keep in mind, that data can come from
different sources such as files,
databases, the internet, mobile devices.
So remember to include all data related
to the problem you're addressing.
After you've identified your data and
data sources,
the next step is to collect the data and
integrate data from the different sources.
This may require conversion,
as data can come in different formats.
And it may also require aligning the data,
as data from different sources may have
different time or spacial resolutions.
Once you’ve collected and integrated your
data, you now have a coherent data set for
your analysis.
The next step after acquiring data is
to prepare it to make it suitable for
analysis.
There are two parts to this step,
explore data and preprocess data.
We will discuss data exploration first.
In data exploration, you want to
do some preliminary investigation
in order to gain a better understanding of
the specific characteristics of your data.
This in turn will guide
the rest of the process.
With data exploration,
you'll want to look for
things like correlations,
general trends, outliers, etc.
Correlations provide information
about the relationship
between variables in your data.
Trends in your data will reveal if the
variable is moving in a certain direction,
such as transaction volume
increasing throughout the year.
Outliers indicate potential
problems with the data, or
may indicate an interesting data
point that needs further examination.
Without this data exploration activity,
you will not be able to
use your data effectively.
One way to explore your data is
to calculate summary statistics
to numerically describe the data.
Summary statistics are quantities
that capture various characteristics
of a set of values with a single number,
or a small set of numbers.
Some basic summary statistics that you
should compute for your data set are mean,
median, mode, range and
standard deviation.
Mean and median are measures of
the location of a set of values.
Mode is the value that occurs most
frequently in your data set, and
range and standard deviation
are measures of spread in your data.
Looking at these measures will give you
an idea of the nature of your data.
They can tell you if there's
something wrong with your data.
For example, if the range of
the values for age in your data
includes negative numbers, or
a number much greater than a hundred,
there's something suspicious in
the data that needs to be examined.
Visualization techniques
also provide quick and
effective ways to explore your data.
Some examples are, a histogram,
such as the plot shown here,
shows the distribution of the data and
can show skewness or
unusual dispersion in outliers.
A line plot, like the one in the lower
left, can be used to look at trends in
the data, such as,
the change in the price of a stock.
A heat map can give you an idea
of where the hot spots are.
A scatter plot effectively shows
correlation between two variables.
Overall, there are many types
of plots to visualize data.
They are very useful in helping
you understand the data you have.
The second part of the prepare
step is preprocess.
So, after we've explored the data, we need
to preprocess the data to prepare it for
analysis.
The goal here is to create the data
that will be used for analysis.
The main activities on this
part are to clean the data,
select the appropriate variables to
use and transform the data as needed.
A very important part of
data preparation is to
clean the data to address quality issues.
Real world data is nothing.
There are many examples of quality issues
with data from real applications including
missing values, such as income
in a survey, duplicate data,
such as two different records for the same
customer with different addresses.
Inconsistent or invalid data,
such as a six digit zip code.
Noise in the collection of data
that distorts the true values.
Outliers, such as a number much
larger than 100 for someone's age.
It is essential to detect and
address these issues that can negatively
affect the quality of the data.
Other activities in data preprocessing
can be broadly categorized as
feature selection and
feature transformation.
Feature selection refers to
choosing the set of features to
use that is appropriate for
the application.
Feature selection can
involve removing redundant or
irrelevant features, combining features,
or creating new features.
During the exploring data step,
you may have discovered that two
features are very correlated.
In that case,
one of these features can be removed
without negatively effecting
the analysis results.
For example,
the purchase price of a product and
the amount of sales tax pain
are very likely to be correlated.
Eliminating the sales tax
amount then will be beneficial.
Removing redundant or irrelevant features
will make the subsequent analysis simpler.
You may also want to combine features or
create new ones.
For example,
adding the applicants education level
as a feature to a loan approval
application would make sense.
There are also algorithms to
automatically determine the most relevant
features based on various
mathematical properties.
Feature transformation maps the data
from one format to another.
Various transformation operations exist.
For example, scaling maps
the data values to a specified
range to prevent any one feature from
dominating the analysis results.
Filtering or aggregation can be used to
reduce noise and variability in the data.
Dimensionality reduction maps the data
to a smaller subset of dimensions
to simplify the subsequent analysis.
We will discuss techniques to prepare
data in more detail later in this course.
After preparing the data to
address data quality issues and
preprocess it to get it in
the appropriate format,
the next step in the machine learning
process is to analyze the data.
The goals of the staff are to
build a machine learning model,
to analyze the data and to evaluate
the results that you get from the model.
The analyze steps starts with this
determining the type of problem you have.
You begin by selecting appropriate machine
learning techniques to analyze the data.
Then you construct the model using
the data that you've prepared.
Once the model is built, you will
want to apply it to new data samples
to evaluate how well the model performs.
Thus data analysis involves selecting
the appropriate technique for
your problem, building the model,
then evaluating the results.
As there are a different
types of problems,
there are also different
types of analysis techniques.
We will cover algorithms for
building machine learning models in a much
more detail in week three of this course.
The next step in the machine learning
process is reporting results from your
analysis.
In reporting your results, it is important
to communicate your insights and
make a case for
what actions should follow.
In reporting your results,
you will want to think about what to
present, as well as how to present.
In deciding what to present, you should
consider what the main results are,
what insights were gained
from your analysis, and
what added value do these insights
bring to the application.
Keep in mind that even negative results
are valuable lessons learned, and
suggest further avenues for
additional analysis.
Remember that all findings
must be presented so
that informs decisions can be made for
next steps.
In deciding how to present,
remember that visualization is an
important tool in presenting your results.
Plots and summary statistics
discussing the explore step
can be used effectively here as well.
You should also have tables with
details from your analysis as backup,
if someone wants to take
a deeper dive into the results.
In summary, you want to report your
findings by presenting your results and
the value added with graphs
using visualization tools.
The final step in
the machine loading process
is to determine what action should be
taken based on the insights gained.
What action should be taken based
on the results of your analysis?
Should you market certain products
to a specific customer segment to
increase sales?
What inefficiency is can be
removed from your process?
What incentives would be effective
in attracting new customers?
Once a specific action
has been determined,
the next step is to implement the action.
Things to consider here include, how can
the action be added to your application?
How will end users be affected?
Assessing the impact of the implemented
action is then necessary to evaluate
the benefits gained.
The results of this assessment
determine next steps,
which could suggest additional analysis or
further opportunities,
which would begin another cycle
of the machine learning process.
In summary, we've looked at the steps in
the machine learning process in detail.
The goals or main activities of each
step were discussed in this lecture.
Remember that this is
an iterative process,
in which each step can be repeated
more than once, and findings from
each step may require a previous step
to be repeated with new information
Hello, everyone.
You have probably heard of machine
learning before, enough to grab your
attention and bring you to this class.
However, you might be wondering
what machine learning is.
We will talk about that
in this lecture and
discuss how we can see machine learning
in action in our day-to-day life.
After this video you will be able to
explain what machine learning is.
And list three applications of machine
learning encountered in everyday life.
Since this course is about machine
learning, lets define what that means.
We hear this term a lot these
days used in many contexts.
So it's good to start out with a solid
definition of what machine learning means.
Machine learning is the field of study
that focuses on computer systems that can
learn from data.
That is the system's often called
models can learn to perform a specific
task by analyzing lots of examples for
a particular problem.
For example, a machine learning
model can learn to recognize
an image of a cat by being shown lots and
lots of images of cats.
This notion of learning from data
means that a machine learning
model can learn a specific task
without being explicitly programmed.
In other words, the machine learning
model is not given the step
by step instructions on how to
recognize the image of a cat.
Instead, the model learns
what features are important
in determining whether it picture contains
a cat from the data that has analyzed.
Because the model learns to
perform this task from data
it's good to know that the amount and
quality of data available for
building the model are important factors
in how well the model learns the task.
Because machine learning
models can learn from data
that can be used to discover hidden
patterns and trends in the data.
These patterns and trends lead to
valuable insights into the data.
Thus the use of machine learning allows
for data driven decisions to be made for
a particular problem.
So to summarize, the field of machine
learning focuses on the study and
construction of computer systems
that can learn from data
without being explicitly programmed.
Machine learning algorithms and
techniques are used to build models,
to discover hidden patterns and
trends in the data allowing for
data-driven decisions to be made.
You may have heard that machine learning
is an inter-disciplinary field.
This is very true.
Machine learning combines concepts and
methods from many disciplines, including
math, statistics, computer science,
artificial intelligence, and optimization.
In applying machine learning to a problem,
domain knowledge is essential
to the success of end results.
By domain knowledge we mean
an understanding of the application or
business domain.
Knowledge about the application,
the data related to the application, and
how the outcomes will be used are crucial
to driving the process of building
the machine learning model.
So domain knowledge is also an integral
part of a machine learning solution.
Machine learning has been used in many
different learning application, many of
which you'll probably encounter in your
daily life, perhaps without realizing it.
One application of machine learning that
you likely used this past weekend, or
even just today,
is credit card fraud detection.
Every time you use your credit card,
the current purchase is analyzed
against your history of credit card
transactions to determine if the current
purchase is a legitimate transaction or
a potentially fraudulent one.
If the purchase is very different
from your past purchases, such as for
a big ticket item in a category that
you had never shown an interest in or
when the point of sales location
is from another country,
then it will be flagged
as a suspicious activity.
In that case,
the transaction may be denied.
Or you may get a call from your
credit card company to confirm that
the purchase was indeed made by you.
This is a very common use of machine
learning that is encountered in
everyday life.
Another example application of machine
learning encountered in daily life is
handwritten digit recognition.
When you deposit a hand-written check into
an ATM, a machine learning process is used
to read the numbers written on the check
to determine the amount of the deposit.
Handwritten digits are trickier
to decipher than typed digits
due to the many variations
in people's handwriting.
A machine learning system can sift through
the different variations to find similar
patterns to distinguish a one from a nine,
for example.
Recommendations in what sites is
another example application of
machine learning that most people
have experienced first hand.
After you buy an item on a website you
will often get a list of related items.
Often this will be displayed
as customers who bought this
item also bought these items,
or you may also like.
These related items have been associated
with the item you purchased by
a machine learning model, and
are now being shown to you since
you may also be interested in them.
This is a common application of
machine learning used often in
sales and marketing.
Here are some other examples of where
machine learning has been used.
Like targeted ads on mobile devices.
Sentiment analysis of social media data,
climate monitoring to detect seasonal
patterns, crime pattern detection, and
a healthiness analysis of drugs
among many other applications.
As you can see from this short list,
machine learning has been used in
various applications including science,
medicine, retail, law enforcement,
education and many others.
Let's take a few minutes to discuss the
different terms which refer to this field.
The term we are using for this course is
machine learning, but you may have heard
other terms such as data mining,
predictive analytics and data slangs.
So what is the difference
between these different terms?
As we have discussed, machine learning
has its roots since statistics,
artificial intelligence, and
computer science among other fields.
Machine learning encompasses
the algorithms and
techniques used to learn from data.
The term data mining became popular
around the time that the use
databases became common place.
So data mining was used to refer to
activities related to finding patterns in
databases and data warehouses.
There are some practical data management
aspects to data mining related to
accessing data from databases.
But the process of finding
patterns in data is similar, and
can use the same algorithms and
techniques as machine learning.
Predictive analytics refers to analyzing
data in order to predict future outcomes.
This term is usually used in the business
context to describe activities such as
sales forecasting or predicting
the purchasing behavior of a customer.
But again the techniques used to make
these predictions are the same techniques
from machine learning.
Data science is a new term that is
used to describe processing and
analyzing data to extract meaning.
Again machine learning techniques
can also be used here.
Because the term data science became
popular at the same time that big
data began appearing, data science usually
refers to extracting meaning from big data
and so includes approaches for collecting,
storing and managing big data.
These terms evolved at different times and
may have encompassed
different sets of activities.
But there have always been more
similarities than differences between
them.
Now they are often used
interchangeably and
have come to mean
essentially the same thing.
The process of extracting valuable insight
from data, the core algorithms and
techniques for doing this do not
change with different terms.
To summarize, in this lecture we've
discussed what machine learning is and
how it is being used.
Machine learning models learn from data to
perform a task without being explicitly
programmed.
They are used to discover patterns and
trends in the data.
And a lab for data driven decisions to
be made for the problems being studied.
We also discuss in this lecture examples
of how machine learning is being used.
We see how the example applications
that machine learning can be applied
to many different areas.
What are the steps in
the Machine Learning Process?
We will discuss those in this lecture.
After this video, you will be able
to identify the steps in the machine
learning process and discuss why
the machine learning process is iterative.
This diagram illustrates the steps
in the machine learning process.
In this lecture,
we will cover an overview of these steps.
In the next lecture,
we will cover each step in more detail.
It should be kept in mind that all of
these steps need to be carried out with
a clear purpose in mind.
That is, the problem or opportunity that
is being addressed must be defined with
clearly stated goals and objectives.
For example,
the purpose of a project may be to study
customer purchasing behavior to come up
with a more effective marketing strategy
in order to increase sales revenue.
The purpose behind the project will
drive the machine learning process.
The first step in the machine
learning process is to get
all available data related
to the problem at hand.
Here, we need to identify all data
sources, collect the data, and
finally integrate data from
these multiple sources.
The next step in the machine learning
process is to prepare the data.
This step is further divided into two
parts, explore data and pre-process data.
The first part of data preparation
involves preliminary exploration
of the data to understand the nature
of the data that we have to work with.
Things we want to understand about
the data are its characteristics, format,
and quality.
A good understanding of the data
leads to a more informed analysis and
a more successful outcome.
Once we know more about the data
through exploratory analysis,
the next part is pre-processing
of the data for analysis.
This includes cleaning data,
selecting the variables to use, and
transforming data to make the data more
suitable for analysis in the next step.
The prepared data then would be
passed on to the analysis step.
This step involves selecting
the analytical techniques to use,
building a model using the data,
and assessing the results.
Step four in the machine learning
process it to communicate results.
This includes evaluating the results with
respect to the goal set for the project.
presenting the results in
a easy to understand way and
communicating the results to others.
The last step is to apply the results.
This brings us back to
the purpose of the project.
How can the insights from our analysis
be used to provide effective marketing
to increase sales revenue?
Determining actions from insights gained
from analysis is the main
focus of the act step.
Note that the machine learning
process is a very iterative one.
Findings from one step may require
a previous step to be repeated
with new information.
For example, during the prepare step, we
may find some data quality issues that may
require us to go back to the acquire
step to address some issues with data
collection or to get additional data that
we didn't include in the first go around.
Each step may also require
several iterations.
For example, it is common to try different
analysis techniques in the analyze step
in order to get reasonable
results from the model.
So, it is important to recognize that
this is a highly iterative process, and
not a linear one.
Now that Maya has explained
the basics of machine learning,
let's remember how big data
influences analytical applications.
And how we can take advantage of
the existing big data tools and
techniques in machine learning.
How can machine learning
algorithms be scaled up
to process large volumes of data?
Let's talk about that now.
After this video, you will be able to
explain how machine learning
techniques can scale up to big data.
And discuss the role of distributed
computing platforms like Hadoop and
Spark in applying machine
learning to big data.
With the massive amounts of data
that need to be processed for
applications, such as drug
effectiveness analysis,
climate monitoring, and
website recommendations to name a few.
We need to be able to add scalability
to machine learning techniques.
How do we apply machine learning at scale?
One way, is to scale up by
adding more memory, processors,
and storage to our system so
that it can store and process more data.
This is not the big data approach.
Specialized hardware such as
graphical processing units, or
GPUs for short,
can also be added to speed up the miracle
operations common in machine
learning algorithms.
Although this is a good approach,
this is also not the big data approach.
As we learned in our introductory course,
one problem with this approach
is that larger specialized
hardware can be very costly.
Another problem is that we
eventually will hit a limit.
There's only so
much hardware you can add to a machine.
An alternative approach is to scale out.
This means using many local commodity
distribution systems together.
Data is distributed over these
systems to gain processing speed up.
As shown in this illustration the idea is
to divide the data into smaller subsets.
The same processing is applied to
each subset, or map, and the results
are merged at the end to come up with the
overall results for the original dataset.
Let's consider an example,
where we want to apply the same operation
to all the samples in
a dataset of N samples.
In this case, N is four.
If it takes T time units to perform this
operation on each sample,
then with sequential processing
the time to apply that operation
to all samples, is N times T.
If we have a cluster of four processors,
we can distribute the data
across the four processors.
Each process performs the operation on
the dataset subset of N over four samples.
Processing of the four subsets
of the data is done in parallel.
That is, the subsets
are processed at the same time.
The processing time for the distributed
approach is approximately N over 4 times T
plus any overhead required to merge
the subset results and maybe shuffle them.
This is a speedup of nearly four
times over the sequential approach.
On a distributed computing
platform such as Spark or Hadoop,
scalable machine learning algorithms
use the same scale out approach.
Data is distributed across
different processors,
which operate on the data subsets
in parallel using map, reduce, and
other distributed
parallel transformations.
This allows for
machine learning techniques to be
applied to large volumes of data.
In this course, we will use Spark and
its scalable machine learning library,
MLF, to show you how machine
learning can be applied to big data.
And don't forget,
this is the processing of the machine
learning on where the data resides.
And we call this, the Big Data Approach.
However, you can also imagine
a scenario where you also
update the machine learning
algorithms to scale up.
So you can paralyze the machine
learning algorithms themselves,
and also use processing of big
data together with this approach.
In this video, we will provide you with
a quick summary of the main points
from our first three courses to
recall what you have learned.
If you have just completed our third
course and do not need a refresher,
you might skip to the next lecture.
We started our first course explaining
how a new torrent of big data
combined with cloud computing
capabilities to process data anytime and
anywhere has been at the core of
the launch of the big data era.
Such capabilities enable or
present opportunities for
many dynamic data-driven applications,
including energy management,
smart cities, precision medicine,
and smart manufacturing.
These applications are increasingly
more data-driven, dynamic and
heterogeneous in terms of
their technology needs.
They're also more process-driven and
need to be tackled using
a collaborative approach by a team that
puts value on accountability and
reproducibility of the results.
Overall, by modeling,
managing, integrating diverse
data streams we add value
to our big data and
improve our business even more
before we start analyzing it.
A part of modeling and
managing big data is focusing on
the dimensions of the scalability and
considering the challenges associated with
these dimensions to pick the right tools.
We also talked about characteristics
of big data, referring to some Vs
like volume, variety, velocity,
veracity and valence.
Each week presents a challenging
dimension of big data,
namely size, complexity, speed,
quality and connectedness.
We also added a sixth V,
value, referring to the real reason
we are interested in big data.
To turn it into an advantage in the
context of a problem using data science
techniques, big data needs to be analyzed.
We explained a five steps process for data
science that includes data acquisition,
modeling, management,
integration, and analysis.
The influence of big data pushes for
alternative scalability approaches
at each step of the process.
If we just focus on the scalability
challenges related to the three Vs,
we can say big data has varying volume and
velocity, requiring dynamic and
scalable batch and stream processing.
Big data has variety, requiring management
of data in many different data systems,
and integration of it at scale.
In our introduction to
the big data course,
we talked about the version of a layer
diagram for the tools in the Hadoop
ecosystem, organized vertically
based on the interface.
Low level interfaces for storage and
scheduling on the bottom
and high level languages and
interactivity at the top.
Most of the tools in the Hadoop ecosystem
were initially built to compliment
the capabilities of Hadoop for distributed
file system management using HDFS.
Data processing using
the MapReduce engine, and
resource scheduling, and
negotiation using the YARN engine.
Over time,
a number of new projects were built,
either to add to these complementary
tools or to handle additional types of
big data management and processing not
available in Hadoop, just like Spark.
Arguably, the most important
change to Hadoop over time
was the separation of YARN from
the MapReduce programming model
to solely handle resource
management concerns.
This allowed for Hadoop to be extensible
to different programming models and enable
the development of a number of processing
engines for batch and stream processing.
Another way to look at the vast number of
tools that have been added to the Hadoop
ecosystem is from the point of
view of their functionality
in the big data processing pipeline.
Simply put, these are associated
with three distinct layers for
data management and storage,
for data processing and
for resource coordination and
workflow management.
In our second course, we talked in detail
about the bottom layer in this diagram,
namely data management and storage.
While this layer includes Hadoop's HDFS,
there are a number of other systems
that rely on HDFS as a file system or
implement their own no-SQL storage option.
As big data can have a variety of
structured, semi-structured, and
unstructured formats and
gets analyzed through a variety of tools,
many tools were introduced to
fit this variety of needs.
We call these big data management systems.
We reviewed Redis and Aerospike as
key value stores where each data item
is identified with a unique key.
We also got some practical
experience with Lucene and
Gephi as vector and
graph-stores respectively.
We also talked about Vertica as
a column-store database where
information is stored in
columns rather than rows.
Cassandra and
HBase are also in this category.
Finally, we introduced Solr and
Asterisk DB for managing unstructured and
semi-structured text and
MongoDB as a document store.
The processing layer is where
all these different types
of data get retrieved,
integrated, and analyzed,
which was the primary
focus of our third course.
In the integration and processing layer,
we roughly refer to the tools that
are built on top of HTFS and YARN,
although some of them were with
other storage and file systems.
YARN is a significant enable of many of
these tools making a number of batch and
stream processing engines like Storm,
Spark, Flink and Beam possible.
This layer also includes tools
like Hive and Spark SQL for
bringing a query interface on top
of the storage layer, Pig for
scripting simple big data pipelines
using the MapReduce framework and
a number of specialized
analytical libraries,
formation learning, and graph analytics.
Giraph and GraphX of Spark are examples
of such libraries for graph processing.
Mahout on top of the Hadoop stack and
MLlib of Spark Are two options for
machine learning.
Although we had a basic overview
of graph processing and
machine learning for big data
analytics earlier in our second and
third courses,
we haven't gone into the details there.
In this course, we will use Spark's MLlib
as one of our two main tools,
providing a deeper introduction to
the machine learning library of Spark.
The third and top layer in our diagram is
the coordination and management layer.
This is where integrations,
scheduling, coordination, and
monitoring of applications across many
tools in the bottom two layers take place.
This layer is also where the results of
the big data analysis get communicated
to other programs, websites, visualization
tools and business intelligence tools.
Workflow management systems help to
develop automated solutions that
can manage and coordinate the process
of combining data management and
analytical tasks in a big data pipeline as
a configurable, structured set of steps.
Workflow driven thinking also matches
this basic process of data science
that we overviewed before.
Oozie is an example workflow
scheduler that can interact with
many of the tools in the integration and
processing layer.
Zookeeper is the resource
coordination tool which monitors and
manages and coordinates all these
tools and named after animal.
Now that we've reviewed all three
layers we are ready to come back to
the integration and processing layer, but
now in the context of machine learning.
In which we will use machine
learning techniques to
apply to our five step data science
process and analyze big data.
Just a simple Google search for
big data processing pipelines will bring
a vast number of pipelines with
a large number of technologies
that support scalable data cleaning,
preparation, and analysis.
How do we make sense of all of it to
make sure we use the right tools for
our application?
How do we pick the right
pre-processing and
machine learning techniques to
start doing predictive modeling?
Over the next few weeks Dr.
Mei will walk you through some of the most
fundamental machine learning techniques,
along with introductory hands
on exercises we designed for you to ease
you into the world of machine learning.
Let's get started.
Let's go through an overview of the tools
we will be using in this course.
After this video you will be
able to describe what KNIME is.
Describe what Spark MLlib is, and contrast
KNIME and MLlib as machine learning tools.
The machine learning tools that we will
be using in this course are KNIME and
Spark MLlib.
These are both open source tools.
This lecture will introduce
these tools to you.
You will need to use them for
the hands on activities in this course.
KNIME Analytics is a platform for data
analytics, reporting, and visualization.
The KNIME platform uses a graphical user
interface based approach with drag and
drop features to facilitate
constructing an analytic solution.
The basic components in KNIME
are referred to as nodes.
Each node provides
a specific functionalities,
such as reading in a file,
creating a specific type of machine
running model and generating a plot.
Nodes can be connected to create
machine running workflows or pipelines.
KNIME stands for
Konstanz Information Miner.
The Konstanz is for
the University of Konstanz in Germany.
And note that the K in KNIME is
silent in the pronunciation.
In KNIME you assemble the steps that
need to be performed in a machine
learning process by connecting
nodes to create a workflow.
To create a workflow the user
chooses the appropriate nodes
from the node repository and
assembles them into a workflow.
The workflow can then be
executed in the KNIME work bench.
A node implements a specific
operation in a workflow.
In this screenshot we see two nodes.
The file reader node is used to
read data from a text file or
a URL or a web address.
The decision tree learner node
builds a decision tree model.
Each node can have input and output ports
and can be connected to other nodes.
When a node is executed,
it takes data from its input port,
performs some operations on the data and
writes the results to the output port.
Data is transferred between
nodes that are connected.
A node can be configured by opening
up its configuration dialog.
This is where the parameters for
the node can be set.
The Node Repository is where you will find
all the nodes available in your KNIME
installation.
The nodes are organized by categories.
KNIME provides an array of nodes to
perform operations for data access,
data manipulation, analysis,
visualization, and reporting.
As you can see, KNIME provides
a visual approach to machine learning.
It's GUI-based, drag-and-drop approach
provides an easy way to create and
execute a machine learning workflow.
The open source version of KNIME however
is limited in how large of a dataset
it can handle.
There are commercial extensions to
KNIME to manage large datasets and
offer other extra functionalities, but
these extensions are not open source.
Now let's talk about Spark MLlib.
You've worked with Spark before if
you took the third course in this
specialization on big data.
Spark is a distributed computing platform.
MLlib is a scalable machine learning
library that runs on top of Spark.
It provides distributed implementations of
commonly used machine learning algorithms
and utilities.
The ML and MLlib of course stands for
machine learning.
To implement machine learning operations
in Spark MLlib, you need to write code.
So MLlib is not a GUI-based approach.
This segment of code reads and
parses data from a file,
then builds a decision
tree classification model.
MLlib, as with the base Spark core,
provides an application programming
interface, or API, for
Java, Python, Scala and R.
This means that you can write code in
these programming languages to execute
the base operations provided in Spark.
Spark MLlib runs on
a distributed platform.
It provides machine
learning algorithms and
techniques that are implemented
using distributed processing.
So MLlib is used for processing and
analyzing large datasets.
And as we have discussed, writing code is
required to implement operations in MLlib.
In summary, KNIME is a GUI-based machine
learning tool, while Spark MLlib provides
a programming-based scalable platform for
processing very large datasets.
You will be using both Spark MLlib and
KNIME throughout this course.
We have readings and hands-on exercises to
help you get familiar with these popular
open source tools for machine learning.
I think you will find it very informative
and fun to work with these tools.
Welcome to course four of
the big data specialization.
I'm Ilkay Altintas, for the new learners
I'm the Chief Data Science Officer
at the San Diego Supercomputer Center at
the University of California, San Diego.
I feel honored to teach you
the basics of big data modeling,
management, and
analysis in this specialization.
And to work with Dr.
Mai Nguyen on this class.
>> And I'm Mai Nguyen, while most of
you might be familiar with Ilkay,
I'm a new face.
I'm excited to be here to teach you
what I love doing, machine learning.
I received my PhD in computer science
with a focus on machine learning
from the University of
California in San Diego.
Since then,
I have worked as a data scientist,
and instructor of machine
learning in various venues.
I am the Lead for Data Analytics at SDFC.
In this role, I work on data
science projects doing research
on scalability on machine
learning methods to big data.
>> We are really happy to have you in this
course to develop your understanding and
skills in machine learning.
>> And
give you an introductory level experience
with application of machine
learning to big data.
By now you might have just finished
our first three courses and
learned the basics of big data modeling,
management, integration, and processing.
If you haven't, it's not required.
But for those with less background
in big data management and
systems, you might find it valuable.
>> We understand that you may
not even have heard anything on
machine learning yet.
That's why we will start by
discussing what machine learning is.
Describing some sample applications and
presenting the typical process
of a machine learning project to give
you a sense of what machine learning is.
Then we will delve into some
commonly used machine learning
techniques like classification and
clustering.
>> We are also going to show you how
to explore your data, prepare it for
analysis, and evaluate the results you
get with your machine learning model.
These are all necessary steps for
a successful machine learning solution.
>> As you know, for
many data science applications
one has to use many different tools and
methods to analyze data.
In fact, keeping up with the rapid
development of new tools is
one of the challenges of
today's big data environment.
In this course, we will introduce you to
two different types of machine learning
tools namely Nime and Spark MNL.
Nime is a graphical user interface based
tool that requires no programming.
And as representative of
a set of tools used in visual
workflow approach to machine learning.
You will have hand on practice with
Nime as you go through the exercises in
this course.
We are also excited to show you
examples of data processing
using Sparks Machine Learning library and
OwlWeb.
Our goal here is to provide you
with simple hands-on exercises that
require introductory level programming,
to inspire you on how big data machine
learning tools can be operated.
We wish you a fun time learning and
hope to hear from you in the discussion
forums and learner stories as always.
>> We have suggested time estimates
each week for the course.
But feel free to take the course
at a faster or slower pace.
And don't forget to connect to other
learners through the forums to
enhance your learning experience.
>> Happy learning.
In the last lecture we
discussed data quality issues.
We will now discuss some common techniques
for addressing those quality issues.
After this video, you will be able
to define what imputation means,
illustrate three ways to
handle missing values, and
describe the role of domain knowledge
in addressing data quality issues.
As we discussed in the last lecture,
real world data is messy.
Some data quality issues that you can
find in your data are missing values,
duplicate data, invalid data,
noise and outliers.
You will need to clean your data if you
want to perform any meaningful analysis
on that data.
Recall that missing data occurs
when you don't have a value for
certain variables in some samples.
A simple way to handle missing data is
to simply drop any samples with missing
values or NAs.
All machine learning tools provide
a mechanism or command for
filtering out rows with
any missing values.
The advantage of this approach
is that it is very simple.
The caveat is that you are removing
data when you filter out examples.
If the number of samples dropped is large,
then you end up losing a lot of your data.
An alternative to dropping
samples with missing data is to
impute the missing values.
Imputing means to replace the missing
values with some reasonable values.
The advantage of this approach is that
you're making use of all your data.
Oc course, imputing is more complicated
than simply dropping samples.
There are several ways to
impute missing values.
One strategy is to replace
the missing values with the mean or
median value of the variable.
For example, a missing value for years of
employment can be replaced by the mean or
median value for years of employment for
all current employees.
Another approach is to use
the most frequent value
in place of the missing value.
For example, the most frequently
recorded age of customers
associated with the specific item can
be used if that value is missing.
Alternatively, a sensible value can
be derived as a replacement for
a missing value.
For example, a missing value for
income can be set to zero for
customers less then 18 years old, or
it can be replaced with an average
value based on occupation and location.
Note that this approach requires
knowledge about the application and
the variable with missing values in
order to make reasonable choices
about what valuables would be sensible
to replace the missing values.
In the case of duplicate data one
approach is to delete the older record.
Another approach is to
merge duplicate records.
This often requires a way to determine
how to resolve conflicting values.
For example, in the case of multiple
addresses for the same customer,
some logic for determining similarities
between addresses might be necessary.
For example,
St period is the same as Street.
To address invalid data, consulting
another data source may be necessary.
For example,
an invalid zip code can be corrected
by looking up the correct zip
code based on city and state.
A best estimate for a reasonable value
can also be used as a replacement.
For example, for
a missing age value for an employee,
a reasonable value can be estimated based
on the employee's length of employment.
Noise that distorts the data
values can be addressed by
filtering out the source of the noise.
For example, filtering out the frequency
of a constant background noise
will remove that noise
component from a recording.
This filtering must be
done with care however,
as it can also remove some components
of the true data in the process.
Outliers can be detected through
the use of summary statistics and
plots of the data.
Outliers can significantly skew
the distribution of your data and
thus the results of your analysis.
In cases where outliers are not
the focus of your analysis,
you will want to remove these
outlier samples from your data set.
For example,
when a thermostat malfunctions and
causes values to fluctuate wildly,
or to be much higher or
lower than normal,
these samples should be filtered out.
In some applications, however, outliers
are exactly what you're looking for.
So when you detect outliers,
you don't want to throw them out.
Instead, you want to
examine them more closely.
A classic example of this is in fraud
detection, where outliers represent
potential fraudulent use and
those samples should be analyzed closely.
In order to address data
quality issues effectively
knowledge about
the application is crucial.
Things such as how the data was collected,
the user population, the intended use
of the application etc, are important.
This domain knowledge is essential
to making informed decisions on how
to best impute missing values,
how to handle duplicate records and
invalid data and what to do about
noise and outliers in your data.
This activity we'll be exploring
weather data in Spark.
First, we will load weather data from
a CSV file into a Spark DataFrame.
Next, we will examine the columns and
schema of the DataFrame.
We will then view the summary statistics
and drop rows with missing values.
Finally, we will compute
the correlation between two columns.
Let's begin.
First, we'll create a new
Jupyter Python notebook.
You do this by clicking on New and
choosing Python 3.
Next, we'll import SQL context.
This is done by entering from
pyspark.sql import SQLContext.
Next, we'll create an instance
of the SQLContext.
We'll enter sqlContext = SQLContext(sc).
Now let's read our weather
data into a DataFrame.
We'll call the DataFrame df and
we'll read it using the sqlContext.
We'll enter sqlContext.read.load.
The first argument is the URL of the file.
That's
file:///home/cloudera/Downloads/big-data--
4/daily_weather.csv.
The second argument specifies
the format of how to read the file.
In this case, we're going to use the
Spark CSV package from Databricks to load
the CSV directly into the DataFrame.
We need to use this because
the Cloudera image only has Spark 1.
In Spark 2 and later,
this package is included so
we don't have to use this argument.
We'll enter ,format= and
the name of the package is
com.databricks.spark.csv.
The next argument specifies that the first
line in the CSV file is the header,
header='true'.
The last argument tells Spark
to try to infer the schema
from the CSV header, inferSchema='true'.
Run this.
Now let's look at our DataFrame.
We can run a df.columns to see
the names of all the columns.
We can also run df.printSchema to
see the schema of the DataFrame.
Next, let's look at the summary
statistics for the data.
We can do this using the describe method.
We'll run df.describe().show().
This shows summary statistics for
all the columns in the DataFrame.
There's a lot of information here,
so lets just choose one column.
Let's look at air pressure at 9 AM.
We can see the summary statistics for
air pressure 9 AM by running
df.describe('air_pressure_9am').show().
There are five statistics in this output,
the count, the number of rows,
the mean, the standard deviation,
and the min and max values.
We can see the total number of columns in
the DataFrame by running len(df.columns).
We can also see the total number of rows
in the DataFrame by writing df.count.
This says that there are 1,095
rows in the DataFrame.
However, the summary statistics for
air_pressure_9am,
we see the count is 1,092.
Summary statistics do not
include rows of missing values.
This means that there are three rows in
the air_pressure_9am column that have
missing values.
We can drop these missing values.
Let's create a new DataFrame where
we've dropped these missing values.
We'll call the new DataFrame df2.
To drop the missing values, we'll enter
df.na.drop(subset=['air_pressure_9am']).
We can then count the total number of
rows in the new DataFrame, df2.count.
We see this value agrees with
our earlier value of 1092.
Next, let's compute the correlation
between two columns in the DataFrame.
We'll compute the correlation between
rain accumulation and rain duration.
To do this, we'll enter df2.stat.corr and
then the names of the two columns,
rain_accumulation_9am and
rain_duration_9am.
Visualizing your data is a very
effective way to explore your data.
We'll look at different ways to
visualize your data in this lecture.
After this video,
you will be able to discuss how plots
can be useful in exploring data,
describe how you would use a scatter plot,
and summarize what a boxplot shows.
Visualizing data,
that is looking at data graphically,
is a great way to explore your data set.
Data visualization is a nice complement
to using summary statistics for
exploring data.
We will cover several ways to
visualize your data in this lecture.
There are several types of plots that
you can use to visualize your data.
We will go over histogram, line plot,
scatter plot, bar plot, and box plot.
These are the most commonly used plots,
but there are many others as well.
A histogram is used to display
the distribution of a variable.
The range of values for the variable
is divided into the number of bins, and
the number of values that fall
into each bin is counted.
Which determines the height of each bin.
A histogram can reveal many things
about a variable in your data, for
example, you can usually determine
the central tendency of a variable,
that is where the majority
of the values lie.
You can also see the most frequent
value of values for that variable.
A histogram also shows whether the values
for that variable are skewed and
whether the skewness is to
the left towards smaller values or
to the right towards larger values.
You can also pick outliers in
the histogram as shown on the bottom plot.
A line plot shows how data
values change over time.
The values of a variable or
variables are shown on the Y axis and
the X axis shows the motion of time.
The resulting line displays
the data values over time.
A line plot can show
patterns in your variables.
For example, a cyclical pattern
can be detected as in this plot,
where the values start high,
then decrease and go back up again.
Trends can also be detected as
shown in the upper-right plot
where the values fluctuate but
show a general upward trend over time.
It is also easy to compare how multiple
variables change over time on a single
line plot as displayed in
the center bottom plot.
A scatter plot is a great way to visualize
the relationship between two variables.
One variable is on the x axis.
The other variable is on
the y axis Each sample is
a product using the values of the 2
variables aspects and Y coordinates.
The resulting plot shows how one variable
changes as the other is changed.
A scatter plot can be used to display
the correlation between 2 variables.
For example, 2 variables such as
the high temperature of the day, and
the low temperature of the day,
can have a positive correlation
as shown in this plot.
A positive correlation means that as
the value of one variable increases,
the value of the other variable
also increases by a similar amount.
The upper right scatter plot shows
a negative correlation between two
variables.
This means that as the value
of one variable increases,
there is a corresponding decrease in
the other variable, two variables
can also have a non-linear correlation
as shown in the lower left plot.
This means that a change
in one variable will not
always correspond to the same
change in the other variable.
This is indicated by the curve in
the scatter plot as opposed to something
closer to a straight line for
linear correlation.
There can also be no correlation
between two variables.
In this case, you will see something
like randomly placed dots as
displayed in the lower right plot,
indicating no
relationship between how the two variables
change with respect to each other.
A bar plot is used to show
the distribution of categorical variables.
Recall that a histogram is also used to
look at the distribution of the values
of the variable.
The difference is that in general,
a histogram is used for
numeric variables whereas a bar plot
is used for categorical variables.
In a bar chart, the different categories
of a categorical variable is shown along
the x-axis, and the count of instances for
each category is displayed on the y-axis.
This is an effective way to
compare the different categories.
For example, the most frequent
category can be easily determined.
A bar plot is also a great way to
compare two categorical variables.
For example, this plot compares
two categorical variables.
One in blue and the other in orange,
each with three different categories.
Here you can see that for
the first category,
the blue variable has the higher count,
while the orange variable has a higher
count for the second and third category.
This type of Bar Plot is
called a Grouped Bar Chart.
And the different variables
of products side by side.
A different kind of comparison can be
performed using a Stacked Bar chart
as seen in a lower right quad.
Here, the accounts for the two variables
are stacked on top of each other for
each category.
With this bar chart, you can
determine that the combined count for
the first category is about equal to
the combine count for the second category,
while the compliant count for
the third category is much larger.
A box plot is another plot that shows
the distribution of a numeric variable,
it shows the distribution in a different
format than the histogram, however.
This is how a box plot displays
the distribution of values for
a variable, the gray portion
in the figure is the box part.
The lower and upper boundaries of
the box represent the 25th and
75th percentiles respectively.
This means that the box represents
the middle 50% of the data,
the median is the 50th percentile,
meaning that 50% of
the data is greater than its value and
50% of the data is less than this value.
The top and bottom lines are the Whiskers
and represent the 10th and
90th percentiles respectively.
So, 80% of the data are in the region
indicated by the upper extreme and
lower extreme.
Any data values outside of
this region are outliers and
are indicated as single
point on the box plot.
Note that there are different
variations of the box plot,
with the whiskers representing
different types of extreme values.
Box plots provide a compact way to
show how variables are distributed, so
they are often used to compare variables.
The box plot on the left for
example compares the base salary for
two different roles.
This plot can quickly provide information
regarding the median value, the range and
the spread of the two different variables.
We can quickly see that
the median salary for
the marketing role is higher
than the research role.
We can also see that the variation or
spread of the values for
marketing is greater than for research,
due to the larger area of the purple box.
A box plot can also show you if
the distribution of the data values is
symmetrical, positively skewed or
negatively skewed.
Here we see that a box plot can
also be displayed on its side.
A symmetric distribution is
indicated if the line in the box
which specifies the median,
is in the center of the box.
A negative skew is indicated
when the median is to the right
of the center of the box.
This means that there are more
values that are less than the median
than there are values
greater than the median.
Similarly, a positive skew is indicated
when the median is to the left
of the center of the box.
To summarize,
data visualization provides a quick and
intuitive way to examine your data.
Data visualization should be
used in conjunction with summary
statistics that we discussed in
the last lecture to explore data.
The different types of plots that we have
covered in this lecture will also be very
helpful in communicating your results
throughout your machine learning project.
Let's look at how we can use summary
statistics to explore data in more detail.
After this video you will be able to
define what a summary statistic is,
list three common summary statistics and
explain how summary statistics
are useful in exploring data.
Summary statistics are quantities
that describe a set of data values.
Summary statistics provide a simple and
quick way to summarize a dataset.
We will discuss three main
categories of summary statistics.
Measures of location or centrality,
measures of spread, and measures of shape.
Measures of location are summary
statistics that describe the central or
typical value in your dataset.
These statistics give a sense of
the middle or center of the dataset.
Examples of these are mean,
median and mode.
The mean is just the average
of the values in a dataset.
The median is the value in the middle if
you sorted the values in your dataset.
In a sorted list, half of the values
will be less than the median and
half will be greater than the median.
If the number of data values is even,
then the median is the mean
of the two middle values.
The mode is a value that is repeated
more often than any other value.
In this example we have
a dataset with ten values.
For this dataset,
the mean is 51.1 which is the number
of all the values divided by 10.
The median is 46, if you sort these
numbers, the middle numbers are 42 and 50.
The average of these two numbers is 46.
There are two modes for
the this dataset, 42 and 78,
since each occurs twice,
more than any other value in the dataset.
Measures of spread describe how
dispersed or varied your dataset is.
Common measures of spread are minimum,
maximum, range,
standard deviation and variance.
Minimum and
maximum are of course the smallest and
largest values in your
dataset respectively.
The range is simply the difference
between the maximum and minimum and
tells you how spread out your data is.
Standard deviation describes the amount
of variation in your dataset.
A low standard deviation value means
that the samples in your dataset
tend to be close to the mean.
And a high standard deviation value means
that the data samples are spread out.
Variance is closely related
to standard deviation.
In fact the variance is the square
of the standard deviation.
So it also indicates how spread out
the data samples are from the mean.
For the same dataset, the range is 66
which is a difference between the largest
number which is 87 and
the smallest number which is 21.
The variance is 548.767,
you can calculate this using
a calculator or a spreadsheet.
And the standard deviation is 23.426
which is the square root of the variance.
Measures of shape describe the shape
of the distribution of a set of values.
Common members of shape are skewness and
kurtosis.
Skewness indicates whether the data
values are asymmetrically distributed.
A skewness value of around zero
indicates that the data distribution
is approximately normal, as shown in
the middle figure in the top diagram.
A negative skewness value indicates that
the distribution is skewed to the left,
as indicated in the left
figure in the top diagram.
A positive skewness
value on the other hand
indicates that the data distribution
is skewed to the right.
Kurtosis measures the tailedness
of the data distribution or
how heavy or
fat the tails of the distribution are.
A high kurtosis value describes a
distribution with longer and fatter tails
and a higher and sharper central peak,
indicating the presence of outliers.
A low kurtosis value on the other hand,
describes a distribution with shorter and
lighter tails and lower and
broader central peak,
suggesting the lack of outliers.
In our age example, the skewness is about
0.3 indicating a slight positive skew.
And the kurtosis is -1.2 indicating
a distribution with a low and
broad central peak and
shorter and lighter tails.
Measures of dependence determine if any
relationship exists between variables.
Pairwise correlation is a commonly
used measure of dependence.
This is a table that shows pairwise
correlation for a set of variables.
Note that correlation applies
only to numerical variables.
Correlations is between zero and one,
with zero indicating no correlation,
and one indicating a one
to one correlation.
So a correlation of
0.89 is very strong and
this is expected since a person's height
and weight should be very correlated.
The summary statistics we just covered
are useful for numerical variables.
For categorical variables, we want to look
at statistics that describe the number of
categories and
the frequency of each category.
This is done using a contingency table.
Here's an example that shows
a distribution of people's pets and
their colors.
We can see the most common pet is
a dog and least common's a fish.
Similarly, black is the most common
color and orange the least common.
The contingency table also shows
the distribution between the categories.
For example, only fish are orange
while most of the brown pets are dogs.
In addition to looking at
the traditional summary statistics for
numerical variables, and
category count for categorical variables.
For machine learning problems,
we also want to examine some additional
statistics to quickly validate the data.
One of the first things to
check is the number of rows and
the number of columns in your dataset.
Does the number of rows match
the expected number of samples?
Does the number of columns match
the expected number of variables?
These should be very quick and
easy checks.
Another easy data validation check is
to look at the values in the first and
last few samples in your dataset
to see if they're reasonable.
For example, do the temperature values
looks to be in the right units of measure.
Do the values for rainfall look correct or
are there some values
that look out of place?
Are the data types for
your variables correct, for example,
is the date field captured as dates or
timestamp.
Or is it capture as a string or
numerical value?
These will have consequences in how
these fields should be processed.
Another important step is to check for
missing values.
You need to determine the number
of samples with missing values.
You also need to determine
if there are any variables
with a high percentage of missing values.
Handling missing values is a very
important step in data preparation
which we will cover in the next module.
Having this information will be very
helpful in determining how missing values
should be handled in data preparation.
We covered several types of summary
statistics useful for exploring data and
machine learning.
The statistics provide useful information
about your dataset and should be
thoroughly examine if you want to get
a better understanding of your data.
Now that we are familiar with some
commonly use terms to describe data,
let's look at what data exploration is and
why it's important.
After this video,
you will be able to explain why data
exploration is necessary, articulate
the objectives of data exploration,
list the categories of techniques for
exploring data.
Data exploration means
doing some preliminary
investigation of your data set.
The goal is to gain a better understanding
of the data that you have to work with.
If you understand the characteristics of
your data, you can make optimal use of it
in whatever subsequent processing and
analysis you do with the data.
Note that data exploration is also
called exploratory data analysis, or
EDA for short.
How do you go about exploring data?
There are two main categories of
techniques to explore your data,
one based on summary statistics and
the other based on visualization methods.
Summary statistics provide important
information that summarizes a set
of data values.
There are many such statistics.
Many of them you have
probably heard of before,
such as mean, median,
and standard deviation.
These are some very commonly
used summary statistics.
A summary statistic provides a single
quantity that summarizes some aspects of
the dataset.
For example, the mean, is a single
value that describes the average value
of the dataset,
no matter how large that dataset is.
You can think of the mean as an indicator
of where your dataset is centrally located
on a number line, thus summary
statistics provide a simple and
quick way to summarize a dataset.
Data visualization techniques allow
you to look at your data, graphically.
There are several types of plots that
you can use to visualize your data.
Some examples are histogram,
line plot, and scatter plot.
Each type of plot serves a different
purpose, we will cover the use of plots to
visualize your data in
an upcoming lecture.
What should you look for
when exploring your data?
You use statistics and
visual methods to summarize and
describe your dataset, and
some of the things you'll want to look for
are correlations,
general trends and outliers.
Correlations provide information
about the relation took between
variables in your data.
By looking at correlations,
you may be able to determine that
two variables are very correlated.
This means they provide the same or
similar information about your data.
Since this contain redundant information,
this suggest that you may want to
remove one of the variables
to make the analysis simpler.
Trends in your data will reveal
characteristics in your data.
For example, you can see where
the majority of the data values lie,
whether your data is skilled or
not, what the most frequent value or
values are in a date set, etc.
Looking at trends in your data can also
reveal that a variable is moving in
a certain direction, such as sales revenue
increasing or decreasing over the years.
Calculating the minimum, the maximum and
range of the data values are basic
steps in exploring your data.
Determining outliers is
a also very important.
Outliers indicate potential
problems with the data and
may need to be eliminated
in some applications.
In other applications,
outliers represent interesting data points
that should be looked at more closely.
In either case, outliers usually
require further examination.
In summary, what you get by exploring
your data is a better understanding of
the complexity of the data so
you can work with it more effectively.
Better understanding in turn will
guide the rest of the process and
lead to more informed analysis.
Summary statistics and
visualization techniques
are essential in exploring your data.
This should be used together
to examined a dataset.
In the next two lectures,
we will look at a specific methods that
you can apply to explore your data.
In this lesson you will learn how
to prepare data for analysis.
After this video, you will be able
to articulate the importance of data
preparation, define the objectives
of data preparation, and
list some activities in preparing data.
The raw data that you get directly from
your sources is rarely in the format
that you can use to perform analysis on.
The goal of data preparation is to create
the data that will be used for analysis.
This means cleaning the data, and putting
the data in the right format for analysis.
The latter generally involves selecting
the appropriate features to use and
transforming the data as needed.
The data that you've acquired
will likely have many problems.
An important part of data preparation is
to clean the data that you have to work
with to address what are referred
to as data quality issues.
There are many types of
data quality issues,
including missing values, duplicate data,
inconsistent or invalid data,
noise, and outliers.
The problems listed here can negatively
affect the quality of the data and
compromise the analysis process and
results.
So it is very important to detect and
address these data quality issues.
Some techniques to address data quality
issues include removing data records
with missing values,
merging duplicate records,
generating a best, or at most reasonable,
estimate for invalid values.
We will discuss these techniques in
more detail in the next lecture.
Since the goal of the step of data
preparation is cleaning the data,
it is referred to as Data Cleaning or
Data Cleansing.
After the data has been cleaned,
another goal of data preparation is to
get the data into the format needed for
the analysis.
This step is referred to by many names,
Data Munching, Data Wrangling and
Data Preprocessing.
The two broad categories of data
wrangling are feature selection and
feature transformation.
Feature selection involves
deciding on which features
to use from the existing
ones available in your data.
Features can be removed,
added or combined.
Feature transformation involves
changing the format of the data
in some way to reduce noise or variability
or make the data easier to analyze.
Two common feature transformations
are scaling the data so
that all features have the same value
range and reducing the dimensionality,
which is effectively the number
of features of the data.
We will discuss these techniques
later in this lesson.
Data preparation is a very important
part of the machine learning process.
It can be a tedious process,
but it is a crucial step.
If you do not spend the time and
effort to create good data for
the analysis,
you will not get good results,
no matter how sophisticated the analysis
technique you are using is.
Always remember, garbage in, garbage out.
So take the time to prepare your data
if you want good analysis results.
A very important part of data preparation
is to assess the quality of your data.
We will look at some common data
quality issues in this lecture.
After this video, you will be able to
describe three data quality issues,
name three reasons for
poor data quality and
explain why data quality
issues need to be addressed.
Real world data is often very messy, so
it's a given fact that you will need
to clean your data by identifying and
addressing many issues that
affect the quality of your data.
Let's take a closer look at what
these data quality issues are.
A very common data quality
issue is missing data.
Recall that a sample in your dataset
typically contains several variables or
features like name, age and income.
For some samples, some of these
variables may not have a value.
These are referred to as
missing values in the data.
Missing values are also referred
to as N/A for not available.
So you will see N/A and
missing values used interchangeably.
You may have missing values in your data
if you have an optional field in your
data set.
For example, the field age is often
an optional field on a survey.
Also many people may choose not
to provide a response for income.
And so you will end up with missing values
for the variable income in your data set.
In some cases, a variable may
not be applicable to all cases.
For example, income may not be
applicable to people who are retired or
unemployed or to children.
So you will not have an entry for
income in all of your samples.
You can also have missing values, due to a
data collecting device that malfunctions,
a network problem that affects
how the data was transmitted, or
something else that goes wrong during
the data collection process itself, or
the process of transmitting the data or
storing the data.
Duplicate data occurs when your data set
has data objects that are duplicates or
new duplicates of one another.
An example of this is when there
are two different records for
the same customer with
different addresses.
This can come about, for example,
if a customer's address has changed,
but the second address was simply
added to this customer's records instead
of used to update the first address.
Duplicate data can occur when
merging data from multiple sources.
Invalid or
inconsistent data occurs when you have
an impossible value for a variable.
Some common examples are when you have
a six digit zip code, the letters AB for
state abbreviations, or
a negative numbers for age.
These invalid data values can
come about when there is a data
entry error during data collection.
For example, if you allow people
to type in their zip code and
someone accidentally includes an extra
digit to their five digit zip code,
then you will end up with
an invalid six digit zipcode.
Noise refers to anything
that can distort your data.
Noise can be introduced during
the data collection process or
data transmission process.
An example is buzzing in the background
when an audio message is recorded
due to background noise or
a faulty microphone.
Another example is an overly bright
image due to an incorrect light
exposure setting.
An Outlier is a data sample with
values that are considerably different
than the rest of the other
data samples in a data set.
An example scenario, that can create
Outliers is when there's a sense of
failure that causes values being recorded
to be much higher or lower than normal.
In this case, you want to remove
the Outliers from your data.
In other applications however,
such as fraud detection,
outliers are the important samples
that should be examined more closely.
So depending on the application,
outliers may need to be removed or
be kept for further analysis.
If you simply ignore these
data quality issues,
any analysis that is performed
will produce misleading results.
In addition, some implementations
of analysis techniques
cannot handle some of these
problems such as missing values.
So, problems that we've discussed
in this lecture need to be
addressed before any meaningful
analysis can be performed.
We will discuss some techniques for
handling data quality
issues in the next lecture.
If you have been in a conversation
on machine learning,
you have probably heard terms like
feature, sample, and variable.
We will be defining some of
those terms in this lecture.
After this video, you will be able
to describe what a feature is, and
how it relates to a sample.
Name some alternative terms for feature.
Summarize how a categorical feature
differs from a numerical feature.
Before we delve into the methods for
processing and
analyzing data, let's first start with
defining some term used to describe data,
starting with sample and variable.
A sample is an instance or
example of an entity in your data.
This is typically a row in your dataset.
This figure shows part of a dataset
of values related to weather.
Each row is a sample representing
weather data for particular day.
The table in the figure shows four samples
of weather data, each for different day.
In this table, each sample has
five values associated with it.
These values are different
information pieces about the sample
such as the sample ID, sample date,
minimum temperature, maximum temperature,
and rainfall on that day.
We call these different values
variables of the sample.
There are many names for
sample and variable.
Some other terms for sample that you
might hear in a machine learning
context include record, example,
row, instance and observation.
It is helpful to realize that all of
these terms mean the same thing in
machine learning.
That is, they all refer to a specific
example of an entity in your dataset.
There are also many names for the term
variable, such as feature, column,
dimension, attribute, and field.
All of these terms refer to
specific characteristics for
each sample in your dataset.
An important point to emphasize
about variable is that,
they are additional
values with a data type.
Each variable has a data
type associated with it.
The most common data types are numeric and
categorical.
There are other data types as
well such as string and date but
we will focus on two of the more common
data types, numeric and categorical.
As the name implies, numeric variables
are variables that take on number values.
Numeric variables can be measured, and
their values can be sorted in some way.
Note that a numeric variable can
take on just integer values or
be continuous valued.
It can also have just positive numbers,
negative numbers or both.
Let's go over some examples
of various numeric variables.
A person's height is a positive,
continuous valued number.
The score in an exam is a positive number
that range between zero and a 100%.
The number of transactions per
hour is a positive integer,
whereas the change in a stock price
can be either positive or negative.
A variable with labels,
names, or categories for
values instead of numbers
are called categorical variables.
For example a variable that describes
the color of an item, such as the color of
a car, can have values such as red,
silver, blue, white and black.
These are non-numeric values
that describes some quality or
characteristic of an entity.
These values can be thought of as names or
labels that can be sorted into categories.
Therefore, categorical variables are also
referred to as qualitative variables, or
nominal variables.
Some examples of categorical
variables are gender, marital status,
type of customer, for example,
teenager, adult, senior.
Product categories, for example,
electronics, kitchen, bathroom and
color of an item.
To summarize, a sample is an instance or
example of an entity in your data.
A variable captures a specific
characteristic of each entity.
So a sample has many
variables to describe it.
Data from real applications
are often multidimensional,
meaning that there are many dimensions or
variables describing each sample.
Each variable has a data
type associated with it,
the most common data types are numeric and
categorical.
Note that there are many terms to
describe these data related concepts.
The data used in machine learning
processes often have many variables.
This is what we call
highly dimensional data.
Most of these dimensions may or may not
matter in the context of our application
with the questions we are asking.
Reducing such high dimensions to
a more manageable set of related and
useful variables improves the performance
and accuracy of our analysis.
After this video, you will be able to
explain what dimensionality reduction is,
discuss the benefits of
dimensionality reduction, and
describe how PCA transforms your data.
The number of features or variables
you have in your data set determines
the number of dimensions or
dimensionality of your data.
If your dataset has two features,
than it is two dimensional data.
If it has three features than
it has three features and so on.
You want to use as many features as
possible to capture the characteristics of
your data, but
you also don't want the dimension
audio of your data to be too high.
As the dimensionality increases, the
problem spaces you're looking at increases
requiring substantially more instances
to adequately sample of that space.
So as the dimensionality increases,
the space that you are looking
at grows exponentially.
As the space grows data
becomes increasingly sparse.
In this diagram we see how
the problem space grows as
the dimensionality
increases from 1 to 2 to 3.
In the left plot, we have a one
dimensional space partitioned into four
regions each with size of 5 units.
The middle plot shows a two
dimensional space with 5x5 regions.
The number of regions has
now going from 4 to 16.
In the third plot, the problem space is
three dimensional with 5x5x5 regions.
The number of regions
increased even more to 64.
We see that as the number of dimensions
increases, the number of regions
increases exponentially and
the data becomes increasingly sparse.
With a small dataset relative to the
problem space, analysis results degrade.
In addition, certain calculations used in
analysis become much more difficult to
define and calculate effectively.
For example, distances between samples
are harder to compare since all samples
are far away from each other.
All of these challenges represent
the difficulty of dealing with high
dimensional data and as referred
to as the curse of dimensionality.
To avoid the curse of dimensionality,
you want to reduce
the dimensionality of your data.
This means finding a smaller subset of
features that can effectively capture
the characteristics of your data.
Recall from the lecture on feature
selection part of data preparation is to
select the features to use.
For example, you can a feature that is
very correlated with another feature.
Using feature selection
techniques to select assessitive
features is one approach to
dimensionality reduction.
Another approach to dimensionality
reduction is to mathematically determine
the most important dimension to keep and
ignore the rest.
The idea is to find a smallest
subset of dimensions that
capture the most variation in your data.
This reduces the dimensions of the data
while eliminating the relevant features
making the subsequent analysis simple.
A technique commonly use to find
the subset of most important dimensions is
called principal component analysis,
or PCA for short.
The goal of PCA is to map the data from
the original high dimensional space
to a lower dimensional space that
captures as much of the variation in
the data as possible.
In other words,
PCA aims to find the most useful subset
of dimensions to summarize the data.
This plot illustrates the idea behind PCA.
Here, we have data samples in a two
dimensional space that is defined
by the x axis and the y axis.
You can see that most of the variation in
the data lies along the red diagonal line.
This means that the dat samples are best
differentiated along this dimension
because they're spread out,
not clumped together along this dimension.
This dimension indicated by the red
line is the first principle component
labelled as PC1 in the part.
It captures the large amount of variance
along a single dimension in data.
PC1, indicated by the red line does
not correspond to either axis.
The next principle component is determined
by looking in the direction that is
orthogonal, in other words perpendicular,
to the first principle component which
captures the next largest
amount of variance in the data.
This is the second
principal component PC2 and
it's indicated by
the green line in the plot.
This process can be repeated to find as
many principal components as desired.
Note that the principal components do
not align with either the x-axis or
the y-axis.
And that they are orthogonal, in other
words, perpendicular to each other.
This is what PCA does.
It finds the underlined dimensions,
the principal
components that capture as much of
the variation in the data as possible.
These principal components form a new
coordinates system to transform
the data to, instead of the conventional
dimensions like X, Y, and Z.
So how does PCA help with
dimensionality reduction?
Let's look again in this plot with
the first principle component.
Since the first principle component
captures most of the variations in
the data, the original data sample can
be mapped to this dimension indicated by
the red line with minimum
loss of information.
In this case then,
we map a two-dimensional dataset to
a one-dimensional space while keeping
as much information as possible.
Here are some main points about
principal components analysis.
PCA finds a new coordinate system for
your data,
such that the first coordinate
defined by the first principal
component Captures the greatest
variance in your data.
The second coordinate defined by
the second principal component captures
the second greatest variance in a data,
etc..
The first few principle components that
capture most of the variance in a data
can be used to define
a lower-dimensional space for your data.
PCA can be a very useful technique for
dimensionality reduction,
especially when working
with high-dimensional data.
While PCA is a useful technique for
reducing the dimensionality of your
data which can help with
the downstream analysis,
it can also make the resulting analysis
models more difficult to interpret.
The original features in your data set
have specific meanings such as income,
age and occupation.
By mapping the data to a new coordinate
system defined by principal components,
the dimensions in your transformed
data no longer have natural meanings.
This should be kept in mind when using
PCA for dimensionality reduction.
In this activity, we will use KNIME to
perform data exploration of weather data.
First, we will create
a new KNIME workflow.
We'll then input the weather data.
Next, we will create
a histogram of air temperature.
Create a scatter plot
between two variables.
Create a bar chart to show the
distribution of a categorical variable.
And finally, create a box plot to
compare two different distributions.
Let's begin.
First, we will create
a new workflow in KNIME.
To do this we go to the File menu.
Select new, select new KNIME workflow and
click on next.
Then we type the name of
the workflow we want to create.
We'll call this one plots.
Click on finish.
Next we want to load
weather data into KNIME.
To do this we'll use a file reader node.
To add this node,
go to the bottom left node repository.
And in the box type in file reader.
Drag File Reader to the canvas.
Next, double click on File Reader to
configure it with the weather data.
Click on the Browse button.
We'll choose the weather file.
That's daily_weather.csv.
We can see preview of
the data at the bottom half
of the file reader configure dialog.
You can see values for
each column in the CSV file.
Click OK to close the dialog.
Next, we want to create
a histogram of air temperature.
We'll add the histogram
node to the workflow.
Again, we go to the node repository and
type in histogram.
We'll drag and
drop histogram to the workflow and
we'll connect File Reader to histogram.
We'll click and
hold on output to File Reader and
drag to the input of histogram and
release.
Before we configure the histogram node,
we need to run the file reader node.
We can do that by selecting
the file reader and
either clicking on the green
arrow at the top or
right clicking and choosing execute here.
Once we've done that,
double-click on histogram.
We'll select error_temp_9AM
as the biding column and
also add error_temp_9AM to
the aggregation column.
We'll leave the default
number of bins as ten.
Click on OK.
Now we'll run the workflow.
You can click on the two arrow green
button at the top to run all the nodes.
Now let's view the histogram.
Right click on the histogram node.
And choose View, Histogram View.
The x-axis shows the value for
each bin in the histogram.
And the y-axis is the count, or frequency.
We can see the most frequent
values are between 60 and 73.
On the right, we also see that
there's some with missing values.
Next close the window.
Now let's create a scatter plot to show
the relationship between two variables.
First, we will add the scatter
plot node to the work flow.
We'll connect the the output of
File Reader to the input of Scatter Plot.
Execute the workflow, right-click on
Scatter Plot and choose View Scatter Plot.
We'll click on the Column Selection and
choose air_temp_9am for the X Column.
And for the Y Column,
choose relative humidity 9 AM.
In this plot,
we can see a negative correlation
between temperature and humidity.
As the temperature increases,
the humidity goes down.
We'll close this window.
Next, we'll create a bar chart to show the
distribution of a categorical variable.
We'll visualize the wind
direction at 9 AM.
We will begin by creating the categorical
variable by using the numeric binner node.
Let's add numeric binner to the work flow.
We'll connect the output of file
reader to the input of numeric binner.
Double-click on Numeric Binner
to configure it.
Select max_wind_direction_9am and
click on add five times to add five bins.
Now let's give a name for
each of these bins.
Select a bin and now choose a name.
The first will be for the North direction.
So we'll call that 1-N.
Next, 2-E for East, 3-S for
South, 4-W for West and
finally 1-N for north again.
Now we need to specify the values for
each of these bins.
We'll select the first one and
set the endpoint to be 45 degrees.
Next, choose east and
set that maximum to be 135.
Select the third one and
choose the max to be 225.
Finally, select the fourth one and
select the max to be 315.
Next, click on a pin new column.
Set the name for categorical variable to
be categorical underscore max underscore.
Wind_direction_9AM.
Click OK.
Now add a histogram note to the work flow.
Connect the output of
Numeric Binner to histogram.
Double-click on Histogram to configure it.
Make sure they binning column is
categorical_max_wind_direction_9AM.
And also there are no aggregation columns.
Click OK and execute the work flow.
Let's view the chart.
Right click on Histogram and
choose View, Histogram View.
This tells us that most of the wind
comes from the east and the south.
And not many measurements from the north.
Next, close this.
Now lets create a box plot to
compare two different distributions.
We w'll examine the distribution,
air pressure for
low humidity days versus normal or
high humidity days.
To do this, we'll first need to creat
a categorical variable for humidity.
Lets add another numeric
binner actor to the workflow.
Connect the output,
a file reader to this actor.
Double click to configure.
Select relative humidity, 9 AM.
And click on add twice to add two bins.
Select the first bin and
we'll call that humidity_low.
Select the second bin and
we'll call that humidity_not_low.
Select the first bin, and
we'll set the maximum value to 25.
Check append new column.
And set the name to low_humidity_day,
click on OK.
Next, add the conditional box
plot node to the workflow.
Right click on conditional
box plot to configure it.
Make sure the nominal column
is low_humidity_day and
the numeric column is air_pressure_9am.
Click OK.
Run the workflow.
Right click on conditional box plot and
choose few additional box plot.
And the x axis, we see the two values or
a categorical variable, humidity low and
humidity not low.
The y axis shows the air pressure values.
I can see that on average,
lower humidity means higher air pressure.
Close this.
Finally, save the workflow when
we're done by clicking on the disk
at the top left of the toolbar.
In addition to cleaning your data
to address data quality issues,
data preparation also includes
selecting features to use for analysis.
After this video, you will be able to
explain what feature selection involves,
discuss the goal of feature selection,
and list three approaches for
selecting features.
Feature selection refers to
choosing the set of features to
use that is appropriate for
the subsequent analysis.
The goal of feature selection is to come
up with the smallest set of features
that best captures the characteristics
of the problem being addressed.
The smaller the number of features used,
the simpler the analysis will be.
But of course,
the set of features used must include
all features relevant to the problem.
So, there must be a balance
between expressiveness and
compactness of the feature set.
There are several methods to
consider in selecting features.
New features can be added,
some features can be removed, features can
be re-coded or features can be combined.
All these operations affect the final
set of features that will be used for
analysis.
Of course some features
can be kept as is as well.
New features can be derived
from existing features.
For example, a new feature to specify
whether a student is in state or
out of state can be added based on
the student's state of residence.
For an application such
as college admissions,
this new feature represents an important
aspect of an application and so
would be very helpful
as a separate feature.
Another example is adding a feature
to indicate the color of a vehicle,
which can play an important role
in an auto insurance application.
Features can also be removed,
candidates for
removal are features
that are very correlated.
During data exploration,
you may have discovered that
two features are very correlated,
that is they change in very similar ways.
For example,
the purchase price of a product and
the amount of sales tax paid
are likely to be very correlated.
The higher the purchase price
the higher the sales tax.
In this case, you might want
to drop one of these features,
since these features have
essentially duplicate information.
And keeping both features makes
the feature set larger and
the analysis unnecessarily more complex.
Features with a high percentage of
missing values may also be good
candidates for removal.
The validity and
usefulness of features with a lot
of missing values are in question.
So removing may not result
in any loss of information.
Again these features would have
been discovered during the data
exploration step.
Irrelevant features should also
be removed from the data set.
Irrelevant features are those that
contain no information that is useful for
the analysis task.
An example of this is employee
ID in predicting income.
Other fields used simply for
identification such as row number,
person's ID, etc.,
are good candidates for removal.
Features can also be combined if the new
feature presents important information
that is not represented by looking at
the original features individually.
For example, BMI, which is body
mass index is an indicator of
whether a person is underweight,
average weight, or overweight.
This is an important feature to have for
a weight loss application.
It represents information about how much
a person weighs relative to their height
that is not available by looking at just
the person's height or weight alone.
A feature can be re-coded as
appropriate for the application.
A common example of this is when you
want to turn a continuous feature in to
a categorical one.
For example for a marketing application
you might want to re-code customer's age
into customer categories such as teenager,
young adult, adult and senior citizen.
So you would map ages 13 to 19 to
teenager, ages 20 to 25 to young adult,
26 to 55 as adult and over 55 as senior.
For some applications you may want
to make use of finery features.
As an example, you might want a feature to
capture whether a customer tends to buy
expensive items or not.
In this case, you would want a feature
that maps to one for a customer with
an average purchase price over a certain
amount and maps to zero otherwise.
Re-coding features can also
result in breaking one feature
into multiple features.
A common example of this is to
separate an address feature
into its constituent parts street address,
city, state and zip code.
This way you can more easily
group records by state, for
example, to provide
a state by state analysis.
Future selection aims to select
the smallest set of features to best
capture the characteristics of
the data for your application.
Know from the examples represented
that domain knowledge once again place
a key role in choosing
the appropriate features to use.
Good understanding of the application is
essential in deciding which features to
add, drop or modify.
It should also be noted that feature
selection can be referred to as feature
engineering, since what you're doing here
is to engineer the best feature set for
your application.
Let's now discuss what
feature transformation is.
After this video you will be able
to articulate the purpose of
feature transformation, list three
feature transformation operations, and
discuss when scaling is important.
In addition to feature selection,
data pre-processing can also
include feature transformation.
Feature transformation involves
mapping a set of values for
the feature to a new set of values to
make the representation of the data more
suitable or easier to process for
the downstream analysis.
A common feature transformation
operation is scaling.
This involves changing
the range of values for
a feature of features to
another specified range.
This is done to avoid allowing
features with large values to
dominate the analysis results.
For example, if your dataset has
both width and height as features,
the magnitude of the weight values,
which are in pounds, will be much
larger than the magnitude of the height
values which are in feet and inches.
So scaling both features
to a common value range
will make the contributions from
both weight and height equal.
One way to perform scaling is to map all
values of a feature to a specific range
such as between zero and one.
For example,
let's say you have a feature for
income that ranges from 30,000 to 100,000.
And you have another feature for years
of employment that ranges from 0 to 50.
These features have very different scales.
If you want both features to have equal
weighting when you compare the data
samples, then you can scale the range
of both features to be between 0 and 1.
That way the income feature which is
on much largest scale than the years
of employment feature will not
dominate the compares result.
Alternatively, scaling can be perform
by transforming the features such that
the results have zero mean,
and unit standard deviation.
The steps to perform the scaling
is to first calculate the mean and
standard deviation values for
the feature to be scaled.
Then for each value, for this feature,
subtract the mean value from that value,
and divide by the standard deviation.
The transformed feature will end
up with a mean value of zero, and
standard deviation of one.
This effectively removes
the units of the features and
converts each future value to number
of standard deviations from the mean.
This scaling method is used when
the min and max values are known.
This is also useful when there are
outliers which will skew the calculation
for the range as the max value is
determined by the furthest outlier.
This scaling operation is often
referred to as zero-normalization or
as standardization.
Filtering is another feature
transformation operation.
This is commonly applied to time series
data, such as speech or audio signals.
A low pass filter can be
used to filter out noise.
Which usually manifests as the high
frequency component in the signal.
A low pass filter removes components
above a certain frequency
allowing the rest to
pass through unaltered.
Filtering can also be used
to remove noise in images.
Noise in an image is random variation
in intensity or color in the pixels.
For example, a noise can cause
an image to appear grainy.
A mean or median filter can be used to
replace the pixel value with the mean or
median value of its neighboring pixels.
This has the effect of
smoothing out the image,
removing the noise that causes
the graininess in the image.
Aggregation combines values for
a feature in order to summarize data or
reduce variability.
Aggregation combines values for a feature
in order to summarize the data or
to reduce variability.
Aggregation is done by summing or
averaging data values at a higher level.
For example, hourly values can be
aggregated to the daily level.
Or values within a city region can
be aggregated to a state level.
These plots show
the results of aggregation.
The left plot shows the wind
speed values in miles per hour
averaged every 10 minutes
over a period of seven days.
Notice that there's a lot of variability,
that is the values fluctuate a lot.
The right plot shows wind speed
values averaged every hour so
every 60 minutes instead
of every 10 minutes.
Notice that the line is much smoother
here because the values are aggregated at
a higher time scale level.
So aggregation can have
the effect of removing noise
to provide a clear representation
of the structure of your data.
Another example is tracking stock prices.
Hourly deviations of a stock
may be difficult to track but,
aggregated daily changes may better reveal
any upward or downward trend of the stock.
In summary, feature transformation
involves mapping the set of values for
a feature to a new set of values to
make the representation of the data
more suitable for the downstream analysis.
Feature transformation should be used with
cautions since they change the nature of
the data and unintentionally remove some
important characteristics of the data.
So it's important to look at the effects
of the transformation you're applying
to your data to make certain that
it has the intended consequences.
In this activity we will be using
KNIME to handle missing data.
First, we will create new workflow and
import our weather data.
Next, we will remove missing values for
specific measurement in the data.
We will then impute missing
values with the mean.
And finally,
remove all the rows with missing values.
Let's begin, first,
let's create a new workflow in KNIME.
We'll name it, Handling Missing Values.
Next, let's import the weather
data using the File Reader node.
We'll add the File Reader
node to the canvas.
We'll configure File Reader
to read daily_weather.csv.
Next, we'll connect the Histogram
node to File Reader.
Before we configure the Histogram node,
we need to run the File Reader node.
We can do this by clicking on File Reader,
and
clicking on the green
arrow in the toolbar.
Next, double-click on
Histogram to configure it.
We'll set both the binning column and
aggregation columns to air_temp_9am.
Next, we'll add a missing value node.
We'll connect this to
the file reader node.
Double click on missing
value to configuring it.
Go to column settings,
select air_temp_9am, and click on Add.
We'll then choose remove row.
This will remove the measurements of
air_temp_9am that had missing values.
Click OK.
Next, we'll add another histogram
node to the output of missing value.
We can do this easily by copying and
pasting the existing histogram node.
Now let's run the workflow by
clicking on the double green arrows.
Let's view the output in
the histogram nodes before and
after we remove missing values.
In this histogram view,
we can see that there are missing values.
If we go and
look at the second histogram node,
the one after we removed
the missing values.
We can see that there are no
missing values in this chart.
Next, instead of removing missing values,
let's impute the values to the mean.
We could do this by configuring
the missing value node.
And instead of remove row,
change that to mean.
Click OK, and rerun the work flow.
We could see the difference by comparing
the graphs and the two histogram nodes.
If we go to visualization settings.
And change labels to all elements, we'll
see the number of elements in each band.
In the histogram,
before we removed the missing values,
we can see the fifth column
has 216 measurements in it.
Where as the fifth column after we imputed
the missing values has 221 values in it.
Let's close these.
Next, let's remove all the rows that
have missing values in the data.
We can do this by double
clicking on missing value.
Removing air_temp_ 9am.
Clicking on the default tab.
Changing this to remove row.
I'll click OK, now we rerun the workflow.
Again, we'll look at the histograms before
and after we remove the missing values.
Again, we'll go to visualization settings
and change the labels to all elements so
we can see the number of
elements in each bin.
We can see the number of elements in
each bin in the different histograms
has changed.
In this activity we will see how
to handle missing values in Spark.
First, we will load weather
data into a Spark DataFrame.
We'll then examine the summary
statistics for air temperature, remove
the rows with missing values, and finally
impute missing values with the mean.
Let's begin.
First, we'll open the notebook
called handling missing values.
The first cell creates an SQLContext and
then loads the weather data
csv into a data frame.
Let's execute this,
we can view the summary statistics for
the DataFrame by running
df.describe().show().
Let's just look at the summary
statistics for the air temperature.
We'll run
df.describe(['air_score_9am']) .show.
This says that there are 1090 rows.
This does not include the rows of
missing values for the air temperature.
We can count the total number of rows
in the DataFrame by running df.count.()
Since there are 1095 total
rows in the DataFrame, but
only 1090 in the air_temp column,
that means there are five rows in
air_temp that have missing values.
Next, let's remove all the rows in
the DataFrame that have missing values.
We'll put these in a new data
frame called removeAllDF.
To drop the missing values
we'll run df.na.drop.
Let's look at the summary statistics for
air_temp 9AM with
the missing values dropped.
We'll run removeAllDF .describe([
air_temp_9am]) show.()
We can see that the mean and
standard deviation values
are close to the original values before
we removed the rows with missing values.
Additionally, the count of
the number of rows is 1064.
We can verify that this is the total
number of rows in the new DataFrame by
running removeAllDF.count.
Next, let's impute the missing
values with the mean,
instead of removing them
from the DataFrame.
First, we'll need to load
the average function from pyspark.
We'll do this by running from
pyspark.sql.functions import avg.
Next, we'll create a copy of the DataFrame
in which we will input the missing values.
We'll call the new DataFrame imputeDF.
To impute the missing values we'll
iterate through each column of
the original DataFrame, first computing
the mean value for that column and
then replacing the missing values
in that column with the mean value.
To move through the columns
in the data frame,
we'll enter for
x in imputeDF.columns: next,
we'll compute the mean value for
that column.
We'll use the data frame in which
we removed all the missing values,
we'll call the agg function
to compute an aggregate.
And the argument that we give it is avg.
The argument avg is x, which is the column
we are trying to compute the average of.
The agg function returns to DataFrame and
we want to get the first
row of that data frame.
We can do this by calling .first and
then you get the first value in
this row or say [0].
Next let's print the column
name in mean value.
print(x, meanValue)
Now let's update our new DataFrame,
replacing the missing
values with the mean value.
imputeDF = imputeDF.na.fill(meanValue,
[x]).
Let's run this.
We can see that the mean value for
air_temp 9am matches the mean value
computed in the summary statistics of
the data frame where the missing
values were removed.
Finally, let's print the imputed
data summary statistics.
First we'll show the summary
statistics for the original DataFrame.
And then the summary statistics for
the imputed DataFrame.
We'll enter df.describe([
air_temp_ 9am]) .show () and
imputeDF.describe(['air_temp_9am']).sho-
w().
Run this.
We can see that the number of rows
in the imputed DataFrame is larger
than the number of rows in
the original DataFrame.
There were five rows in the original
DataFrame with missing values.
And these have now been
replaced with the mean.
Let's talk about what it means to
build a classification model and
how building a model differs
from applying a model.
After this video,
you will be able to discuss what
building a classification model means.
Explain the difference between
building and applying a model.
And summarize why the parameters
of a model needs to be adjusted.
A machine learning model
is a mathematical model.
In the general sense, this means that
the model has parameters and uses
equations to determine the relationship
between its inputs and outputs.
The parameters are used by the model to
modify the inputs to generate the outputs.
The model adjusts its parameters
in order to correct or
refine this input, output relationship.
Here's an example of a simple model.
This mathematical model represents a line.
y is the output, x is the input,
m determines the slope of the line and
b determines the y-intercept or
where the line crosses the y-axis.
m and b are the model's parameters.
Given a specific value for
x, the model uses as parameters
along with x to determine y.
By adjusting the values for
the parameters m and b,
the model can adjust how the input
x matched to the output y.
Here we see how the output y changes for
the same value of input x,
when parameter b changes.
Recall that b is the y-intercept, or
where the line crosses the y-axis.
The value of b is +1 for
the red line and -1 for the blue line.
For the input x=1, the value of y is 3 for
the red line,
as indicated by the red arrow.
For the blue line, when the parameter
b changes from +1 to -1,
for x=1, the value of y is 1,
as indicated by the blue arrow.
So we see that with just a simple
change in one model parameter,
the input to output mapping changes.
A machine learning model
works in a similar way.
It maps input values to output values.
And it adjusts the parameters
in order to correct or
refine this input-output mapping.
The parameters of a machine
learning model are adjusted or
estimated from the data
using a learning algorithm.
This, in essence,
is what is involved in building a model.
This process is referred to by many terms,
such as model building,
model creation,
model training and model fitting.
In building a model,
we want to adjust the parameters in
order to reduce the model's error.
In the case of supervised tasks,
such as classification, this means getting
the model's outputs to match the targets
or desired outputs as much as possible.
Since the classification task is
to predict the correct category or
class, given the input variables,
you can think of the classification
problem visually as carving out the input
space as regions corresponding
to the different class labels.
In this diagram for example,
the classification model needs to form
the boundaries to define the regions
separating red triangles
from blue diamonds, from green circles,
from yellow squares.
In this example, if a sample falls within
the region in the upper right corner,
it will be classified as a blue diamond.
Classification decisions are based on
these regions, and the regions are defined
by the boundaries, as indicated by
the dashed lines in the diagram.
So these boundaries are referred
to as decision boundaries.
Building a classification then means using
the data to adjust the model's parameters
in order to form decision boundaries
to separate the target classes.
Note that the term classifier is often
used to mean classification model.
In general,
building a classification model,
as well as other machine learning models,
involves two phases.
The first is the training phase,
in which the model is constructed and
its parameters adjusted using as
what referred to as training data.
Training data is the data set
used to train or create a model.
The second is the testing phase.
This is where the learned
model is applied to new data.
That is,
data not used in training the model.
Here's another way to
look at the two phases.
In a training phase, the learning
algorithm uses the training data
to adjust the model's
parameters to minimize errors.
At the end of the training phase,
you get the trained model.
In the testing phase,
the trained model is applied to test data.
Test data is separate from training data
and is previously unseen by the model.
The model is then evaluated on
how it performs on the test data.
The goal in building a classifier
model is to have the model
perform well on training,
as well as test data.
We will discuss in more detail
the use of training and
test data sets in the next module,
when we discuss model evaluation.
To adjust a model's parameters,
we need to apply a learning algorithm.
We will discuss the specific algorithms
to build a classification model in
the next few lectures.
In this video, we will outline
some commonly used algorithms for
building a classification model.
After this video,
you will be able to describe the goal of
a classification algorithm and name some
common algorithms for classification.
Recall that a classification task is
to predict the category from the input
variables.
A classification model processes the input
data it receives and provides an output.
Since classification is a supervised task,
a target or
desired output is provided for
each sample.
The goal is to get the model outputs to
match the targets as much as possible.
A classification model
adjusts its parameters
to get its outputs to match the targets.
To adjust a model's parameters,
a learning algorithm is applied.
This occurs in a training phase
when the model is constructed.
There are many algorithms to
build a classification model.
In this course,
we will cover the algorithms listed here,
kNN or k Nearest Neighbors,
decision tree, and naive Bayes.
kNN stands for k Nearest Neighbors.
This technique relies on the notion that
samples with similar characteristics,
that is samples with similar values for
input, likely belong to the same class.
So classification of a sample is dependent
on the target values of
the neighboring points.
Another classification technique
is referred to as decision tree.
A decision tree is a classification
model that uses a treelike structure
to represent multiple decision paths.
Traversing each path leads to a different
way to classify an input sample.
A naive Bayes model uses a probabilistic
approach to classification.
Baye's Theorem is used to capture the
relationship between the input data and
the output class.
Simply put, the Baye's Theorem
compares the probability of an event
in the presence of another event.
We see here the probability
of A if B is present.
For example, probability of having
a fire if the weather is hot.
You can imagine event B depending
on more than one variable.
For example, weather is hot and windy.
We will cover kNN, decision tree and naive
Bayes in detail in the next few lectures.
There are many other classification
techniques, but we will focus on these
since they are fundamental algorithms
that are commonly used and
form the basis of other algorithms for
classification.
In this activity we will perform
classification in Spark is in
decision tree.
First, we will load weather
data into DataFrame and
drop unused and missing data.
We'll then,
create a categorical variable for
low humidity days and aggregate
features used to make predictions.
We will then split our data
into training and test sets.
And then create and
train the decision tree.
Finally, we will save our
predictions to a CSV file.
Let's begin, first, we'll open
the notebook called classification.
The first cell contains the classes
we need to load to run this exercise.
Let's run this.
Next we create SQL context and load
the weather data CSV into a data frame.
The second cell also prints all
the columns in this data frame.
Run this.
The third cell defines the columns
in the weather data we will use for
the decision tree classifier.
Let's run it.
We will now use the column name number.
So, let's drop that from the data frame,
df = df.drop Number.
Now, let's revolve the rows with
missing data, df = df.na.drop.
Now, let's print the number of rows and
columns in our resulting data frame,
df.count(), len(df.columns).
Next, let's create a categorical variable
to denote if the humidity is low.
We'll enter binarizer = Binarizer ().
The first argument specifies
a threshold value for the variable.
We want the categorical variable to be 1,
if the humidity is greater than 25%.
So we'll enter a threshold=24.9999.
The next argument specifies the column to
use to create the categorical variable.
We'll input,
inputCol = relative_humidity_3pm.
The final argument specifies the new
column name, outputCol = label.
Now, let's create a new data frame
with this categorical variable.
binarizeredDF = binarizer.transform df.
Let's run this.
Let's look at the first four
rows in this new data frame.
We'll run binarizedDF.select
('relative_humidity_3pm',
'label').show(4).
The relative humidity in the first row
is greater than 25% and the label is 1.
The relative humidity in the second,
third, and fourth rows are less than 25%,
and the label is 0.
Next, let's aggregate the features we will
use to make predictions into a single col,
assembler = VectorAssember( ).
The first argument is a list of
the columns to be aggregated.
inputCols=featureColumns, and
the second argument is the name
of the new column containing the
aggregated features, outputCol=features.
We can create the new
data frame by running
assembled=assembler.transform binarizedDF.
Let's run this.
Next we will split our data
set into two parts, one for
training data and one for test data.
You can do this by entering (training
Data,
testData)=assembled.randomSplit([0.8,
0.2], seed=13234).
We can see the size of the two
sets by running count,
trainingData.count(), testData.count ().
Next let's create and
train the decision tree.
We'll enter dt = DecisionTreeClassifier.
The first argument is the column we're
trying to predict, labelCol='label'.
The second argument is the name
of the column containing your
aggregated features,
featuresCol='features'.
The third argument is
the stopping criteria for
tree induction based on the maximum
depth of the tree, maxDepth=5.
The fourth argument is the stopping
criteria for tree induction based
on the minimum number of samples
in a node, minInstancesPerNode=20.
And finally, the last argument
specifies the impurity measure
used to split the nodes,
impurity="gini", let's run this.
Next, we can create a model by
training the decision tree.
We'll do this by executing
it in a pipeline.
We'll enter pipeline=Pipeline
(stages=[dt]).
We'll create them all by putting
a training data, model =
pipeline.fit trainingData.
Let's run this Now, we can make
predictions using our test data.
We'll enter predictions =
model.transform(testData).
You can look at the first 10 rows
of the prediction by running,
predictions.select('prediction', label')
show(10).
You can see in the first ten rows,
the prediction matches the label.
Now let's save our
predictions to a CSV file.
In the next Spark hands-on activity
we will evaluate the accuracy.
You can save it by running
predictions.select('prediction',
'label').write.save(path='file File:///
home/cloudera/downloads/big-data-4/predic-
tions.csv.
We'll specify the format to use Spark csv.
Format='com.databricks.spark.csv.
Finally, we'll enter header='true'.
Run this to save
the predictions to a .csv file.
In this activity, we will be
performing classification in KNIME,
first we will create a new workflow and
import our weather data.
Next, we will remove the missing data and
then create a categorical value for
the humidity measurements.
We will then examine summary
statistics of the data before and
after the missing data was removed, and
finally build a decision tree workflow.
Let's begin.
First, let's create a New Workflow.
We'll call it Classification.
Next, we'll import the daily weather data,
using the File Reader node.
Configure the file reader node,
to use daily_weather.csv.
Next, we'll add a missing value node,
to remove the missing values
in the daily weather data.
We'll configure missing value to
remove all the missing values.
Next we'll use a numeric binner node
to create a categorical variable for
the humidity at 3pm.
We'll add the numeric binner node,
we'll connect it to missing value.
We'll select the relative
humidity 3pm column.
We'll create two bins,
the first bin we'll call humidity_low.
And that value will go up to 25.
The second bin, we'll
call humidity_not_low.
We'll check the Append new column and
we'll call the new
column low_humidity_day.
Next, we'll examine some summary
statistics, both before, and
after we've removed the missing values.
We'll add the statistics
node to the canvas.
We'll connect the first one to
the output of the File Reader actor.
We'll add another one to
the output of Numeric Binner.
We'll change the name of the first
one to be BEFORE filtering.
And change the name of the second
one to AFTER filtering.
Lets configure the first one.
We'll change the maximum number of
possible values per column to 1500.
We'll also add all the columns.
Let's configure the second statistics now.
Again, we'll change the maximum number of
possible values per column to 1500, and
we'll add all the columns.
Now let's run our workflow.
Let's view both Statistic
nodes to compare the outputs.
In the BEFORE filtering statistics,
we can see that there are missing values.
However, there are no missing values
in the AFTER filtering statistics.
We can also compare the summary
statistics, for different measurements,
to see that they are similar values.
For example,
let's take a look at air_temp_9am.
We could see that most of
the statistics are the same.
As well as the distribution of values.
In the AFTER filtering statistics,
click on the Nominal tab,
and we'll look at the low humidity
day categorical variable we created.
We can see that the samples are equally
distributed between the two values.
Let's close these Statistics views.
Next, let's add a Column Filter node.
We'll connect this to
the output of Numeric Binner.
Double-click to configure the node.
And we will exclude
relative_humidity_9am and
relative_humidity_3pm columns, click OK.
Next, we'll add a Color Manager
node to the canvas.
Will connect this to the output of Column
Filter, double-click to configure it.
We will make sure the humidly_low is red,
and humidity_not_low is blue.
Click OK to close.
Next, we'll add the Partitioning
node to the campus.
We'll connect this to
the output of Color Manager.
Double-click to configure.
We want to split the data
into two partitions.
The first partition should
have 80% of the data.
The second partition should have 20%.
To do this click on Relative[%] and
change this to 80.
We'll make sure Draw randomly is selected.
And check Use random seed and
change the seed to 12345.
Normally we would not
specific the random seed.
However, since we want repeatable results,
we use a specific seed value here.
Click OK to continue.
Next, we'll add a Decision Tree Learner
to the work flow.
We'll connect this to the top
output of the Partitioning node.
Double-click to configure, and
change the Min number of
records per node to 20.
Click OK.
Next, we'll add a Decision Tree Predictor
node to the canvas, and we will connect
the bottom output of Partitioning to
the bottom input of the predictor.
Next we'll connect the output
of Decision Tree Learner
to the top input of
Decision Tree Predictor.
Now let's execute our workflow.
We can view the resulting
classification rules
by right clicking on
Decision Tree Predictor.
And choosing either View: Decision Tree
View or View: Decision Tree View (simple).
Let's do the first one.
This shows the first two
splits in our decision tree.
We can expand each branch
by clicking on the plus.
Let's close this.
Now let's look at the simplified view.
Again, we can expand the branches to
see the splits in the Decision Tree.
Close this,
finally let's save this workflow.
We'll analyze the results of the Decision
Tree model in the next KNIME Hands On.
Save the workflow by
clicking on the disk icon.
Welcome back, we already discussing
Classification models and techniques for
next few lectures.
Let's first define what
the classification task is,
after this video you will be able
to define what classification is.
Explain whether classification is
supervised or unsupervised and
describe how binomial classification
differs from multinomial classification.
Classification is one type of
machine learning problems.
In the classification problem, the input
data is presented to the machine learning
model and the task is to predict the
target corresponding to the input data.
The target is a categorical variable,
so the classification task is
to predict the category or
label of the target given the input data.
For example, the classification
problem illustrated in this image
is to predict the type of weather.
The target that the model has to predict
is the weather and the possible values for
weather in this case is Sunny,
Windy, Rainy, or Cloudy.
The input data can consist of measurements
like temperature, relative humidity,
atmospheric pressure,
wind speed, wind direction, etc.
So, given specific values for temperature,
relative humidity, atmospheric pressure,
etc., the task for the model is to
predict if the weather will be sunny.
Windy, rainy, or cloudy for the day,
this is what the data set might look like
for the weather classification problem.
Each row is a sample with input
variables temperature, humidity, and
pressure and target variable weather.
Each row has specific values for
the input variables and
a corresponding value for
the target variable.
The classification task is to predict
the value of the target variable
from the values of the input variables.
Since a target is provided,
we have labeled data and so
classification is a supervised task.
Recall that in a supervised task,
the target or
desired output for each sample is given.
Note that the target variable goes
by many names such as target,
label, output, class variable,
category, and class.
A classification problem can be binary or
multi-class with binary
classification the target variable has two
possible values, for example yes and no.
With multi-class classification
the target variable has more than
two possible values.
For example, the target can be short,
medium and tall.
Multi-class classification is
also referred to multinomial or
multi-label classification.
Remember though that the target is always
a categorical variable in classification.
Some examples of binary
classification are predicting
whether it will rain tomorrow or not,
here there are two possible outcomes,
yes it will rain tomorrow or
no, it will not rain tomorrow.
Identifying whether a credit card
transaction is legitimate or fraudulent,
again, there are only two possible values
for the target, legitimate or fraudulent.
Some examples of multi-class
classification include
predicting what type of product
that a customer will buy.
The possible values for
the target variables would be product
categories such as kitchen,
electronics, clothes, etc.
There is more than one
category of products, so
this is a multi-class
classification problem.
Another example is categorizing a tweet
as having a positive, negative, or
neutral sentiment, again,
the number of possible values for
the target is more than two here.
So, this is also a multi-class
classification task
to summarize in classification,
the model has to predict the category
corresponding to the input data.
Since the target is provided for each
sample, classification is a supervised
task, the target variable is always
categorical in classification.
In this lecture,
we will look at the decision tree model,
a popular method used for classification.
After this video, you will be able to
explain how a decision tree is used for
classification.
Describe the process of constructing
a decision tree for classification.
And interpret how a decision tree comes
up with a classification decision.
The idea behind decision trees for
classification is to split the data
into subsets where each subset
belongs to only one class.
This is accomplished by dividing
the input space into pure regions,
that is regions with samples
from only one class.
With real data completely pure
subsets may not be possible.
So the goal is to divide the data into
subsets that are as pure as possible.
That is each subset contains as many
samples as possible from a single class.
Graphically this is equivalent to dividing
the input space into regions that are as
pure as possible.
Boundaries separating these regions
are called decision boundaries.
And the decision tree model
makes classification decisions
based on these decision boundaries.
A decision tree is a hierarchical
structure with nodes and directed edges.
The node at the top is
called the root node.
The nodes at the bottom
are called the leaf nodes.
Nodes that are neither the root node or
the leaf nodes are called internal nodes.
The root and
internal nodes have test conditions,
each leaf node has a class
label associated with it.
A classification decision is made
by traversing the decision tree
starting with the root node.
At each node the answer to the test
condition determines which
branch to traverse to.
When a leaf node is reached
the category at the leaf node
determines the classification decision.
The depth of a node is the number of
edges from the root node to that node.
The depth of the root node is 0.
The depth of a decision
tree is the number of edges
in the longest path from
the root node to the leaf node.
The size of a decision tree is
the number of nodes in the tree.
This is an example of a decision tree.
It can be used to classify an animal
as a mammal or not a mammal.
According to this decision tree,
if an animal is warm-blooded,
gives live birth, and
is a vertebrate, then it is a mammal.
If an animal does not have all
of these three characteristics,
then it is not a mammal.
A decision tree is built by starting
with all samples at a single node,
the root node.
Additional nodes are added when
the data is split into subsets.
At a high level, constructing a decision
tree consists of the following steps.
Start with all samples and a node,
partition the samples into subsets
based in the input variables.
The goal is to create subsets of
records that are purest, that is
each subset contains as many samples as
possible, belonging to just one class.
Another way to say this is that
the subsets should be as homogeneous or
as pure as possible.
Repeatedly partition data into
successively purer subsets
until some stopping
criterion is satisfied.
An algorithm for
constructing a decision tree model is
referred to as an induction algorithm.
So you may hear the term tree induction
used to describe the process of
building a decision tree.
Note that at each split
the induction algorithm
only considers the best way to split
that particular portion of the data.
This is referred to as a greedy approach.
Greedy algorithms solve a subset
of the problem at a time, and
as a necessary approach when solving
the entire problem is not feasible.
This is the case with decision trees.
It is not feasible to determine
the best tree given a data set, so
the tree has to be built
in piecemeal fashion
by determining the best way to split
the current node at each step.
And combining these decisions together
to form the final decision tree,
in constructing a decision tree
how is the data partitioned?
How does a decision tree
determine the best way to split
the set of samples at a node?
Again the goal is to partition data
at a node into subsets that are as
pure as possible.
In this example,
the partition shown on the right
results in more homogeneous subsets.
Since these subsets contain more
samples belonging to a single class
than the resulting subsets
shown on the left.
So the partition on the right
results in purer subsets and
is the preferred partition.
Therefore, we need a way to
measure the purity of a split
in order to compare different
ways to partition a set of data.
It turns out that it works out better
mathematically if we measure the impurity
rather than the purity of a split.
So the impurity measure of a node
specifies how mixed
the resulting subsets are.
Since we want the resulting subsets
to have homogeneous class labels,
not mixed class labels, we want the split
that minimizes the impurity measure.
A common impurity measure used for
determining the best
split is the Gini Index.
The lower the Gini Index the higher
the purity of the split.
So the decision tree will select
the split that minimizes the Gini Index.
Besides the Gini Index, other
impurity measures include entropy, or
information gain, and
misclassification rate.
The other factor in determining
the best way to partition a node
is which variable to split on.
The decision tree will test all variables
to determine the best way to split a node
using a purity measure such as
the Gini index to compare the various
possibilities.
Recall that the tree induction algorithm
repeatedly splits nodes to get more and
more homogeneous subsets.
So when does this process stop?
When does the algorithm
stop growing the tree?
There's several criteria that can be used
to determine when a node should no longer
be split into subsets.
The induction algorithm can
stop expanding a node when
all samples in the node
have the same class label.
This means that this set of data
is as pure as possible, and
further splitting will not result in
any better partition of the data.
Since getting completely pure subsets
is difficult to achieve with real data,
this stopping criterion can be modified.
To when a certain percentage of
the samples in the node, say 90% for
example, have the same class labels.
The algorithm can stop expanding a node
when the number of samples in the node
falls below a certain minimum value.
A this point the number of
samples is too small to make
much difference in the classification
results with the further splitting.
The induction algorithm can stop expanding
a node when the improvement in impurity
measure is too small to make much of
a difference in classification results.
The algorithm can stop expanding a node
when the maximum tree depth is reached.
This is to control the complexity
of the resulting tree.
There can be other criteria that can be
used to determine when tree induction
should stop.
Let's take a look at an example to
illustrate the tree induction process.
Let's say that we want to classify loan
applicants as being likely to repay a loan
or not likely to repay a loan
based on their income and
amount of debt they already have.
Building a decision tree for
this classification problem
could proceed as follows.
Consider the input space of this
problem as shown in the left figure.
One way to split this
data set into homogeneous
subsets is to consider the decision
boundary where income equals t1.
To the right of this decision
boundary are mostly red samples and
to the left are mostly blue samples.
The subsets are not
completely homogeneous but
that is the best way to split the original
data set based on the variable income.
This decision boundary is represented
in the decision tree by the condition
Income is greater than
t1 at the root node.
This is the condition used to
split the original data set.
Samples with income greater
than the threshold value
of t1 are placed in the right subset and
samples with income less than or
equal to t1 are placed in the left subset,
just as shown in the right diagram.
The right subset is now labeled as red,
meaning that the loan applicant
is likely to be paid alone.
The second step then is to determine how
to split the region outlined in red.
As shown in the left diagram, in input
space, the best way to split this data
is specified by the second decision
boundary with debt equals t2.
This is represented in
the decision tree on the right
with the addition of the node with
condition debt greater than t2.
Samples with the value of debt greater
than t2 are shown in the region
above the decision boundary.
This region contains all blue samples and
so the corresponding node is labeled blue.
Meaning that the loan applicant
is not likely to repay the loan.
The third and final split looks at how
to split the region outlined in red
in the left diagram.
The best split is specified by
the boundary with income equals T3.
This splits the red region
into two pure subsets.
This split is represented in the decision
tree by adding a node with condition,
Income is greater than t3.
The left resulting node is labeled blue,
and
the right resulting node is labeled red,
corresponding to the resulting subsets
within the red border in the left diagram.
We end with the final
decision tree on the right,
which implements the decision boundaries
shown as dash lines in the left diagram.
These decision boundaries
partition the data set as shown.
The label for each region is determined by
the label of the majority of the samples.
These labels are reflected in
the leaf nodes of the decision tree.
Shown on the right.
You may have noticed that the decision
boundaries of a decision tree are parallel
to the axes formed by the variables,
this is referred to as being rectilinear.
The boundaries are rectilinear
because each split considers only
a single variable.
There are variance of the tree induction
algorithm that consider more than one
attribute when splitting a note.
However, each split has to consider all
combinations of combined variables and
so such induction algorithms are much
more computationally expensive.
There are a few important things to
note about the decision tree classifier.
The resulting tree is often simple
to understand and interpret.
This is one of the biggest advantages
of decision trees for classification.
It is often possible to look
at the resulting tree to see
which variables are important to
the classification problem and
understand how
the classification is performed.
For this reason, many people will start
out with the decision tree classifier
to get a feel for
the classification problem.
Even if they end up using more
sophisticated models later on.
The tree induction algorithm
as described in this lesson
is relatively computationally inexpensive.
So training a decision tree for
classification can be relatively fast.
The greedy approach used by tree induction
algorithm determines the best way to split
the portion of the data at a node but
does not guarantee the best solution
overall for the entire data set.
Decision boundaries are rectilinear.
This can limit the expressiveness
of the resulting model which means
that it may not be able to solve
complicated classification problems that
require more complex decision
boundaries to be formed.
In summary, the decision tree classifier
uses a tree like structure to specify
a series of conditions that are tested to
determine the class label for a sample.
The decision tree is constructed by
repeatedly splitting a data partition
into successively more
homogeneous subsets.
The resulting tree can
often be easy to interpret.
We will start with a very simple
classification technique called k-Nearest
Neighbors.
After this video, you will be able
to describe how kNN is used for
classification.
Discuss the assumption behind kNN and
explain what the k stands for in kNN.
kNN stands for k-Nearest Neighbors.
This is one of the simplest techniques
to build a classification model.
The basic idea is to classify
a sample based on its neighbors.
So when you get a new sample as shown by
the green circle in the figure, the class
label for that sample is determined by
looking at the labels of its neighbors.
KNN relies on the notion
of the so-called duck test.
That is if it looks like a duck,
swims like a duck and quacks like a duck,
then it probably is a duck.
In the classification context,
this means that samples with similar input
values likely belong to the same class.
So, samples with similar input values
should be labeled with the same
target label.
This means that classification
of a sample is dependent
on the target labels of
the neighboring points.
In more detail then,
this is how kNN works.
Given a new sample, look for
the samples in the training data
that are closest to the new sample.
These are the neighbors.
Use the labels of this neighboring points
to determine the label for the new sample.
This figure illustrate how kNN works.
The problem here is to determine if
a sample should be classified as
a blue square or red triangle.
The green circle is the new sample.
To determine a class label for this new
sample, look at its closest neighbors.
These neighbors are the samples
within the dashed circle.
Two blue squares and one red triangle.
The class labels of the neighboring
samples determine the label for
the new sample.
The value of k determines the number
of nearest neighbor to consider.
So if k equals 1,
then only the closest neighbor is examined
to determine the class of the new
sample as shown in the left figure.
If k equals 2,
then the 2 nearest neighbors are
considered as seen in the middle figure.
If k equal 3, then the 3 nearest
neighbors are considered as
in the right figure and so on.
If k equal 1 and only 1 neighbor is used,
then the label for
the new sample is simpler
the label of the neighbor.
This is shown in the left figure.
The label of the new sample is then A,
since that is the label of
its one nearest neighbor.
When multiple neighbors are considered,
then a voting scheme is used.
Majority of vote is commonly used,
so the label associated with
the majority of the neighbors is
used as the label of the new sample.
This is what we see in the right figure.
With k equals 3,
3 nearest neighbors are considered.
With two neighbors labeled as A and
one as B,
the majority of vote determines that
the new sample should be labeled as A.
In case of a tie which could be
possible if the value of k is even,
then some tight breaking rule is needed.
For example, the label of
the closer neighbor is used or
the label is chosen randomly
among the neighbors.
This is seen in the middle figure.
With two nearest neighbors and each with
a different class label, the label for
the new sample is randomly
chosen here to be B.
With kNN, some measure of similarity
is needed to determine how
close two samples are together.
This is necessary to determine which
samples are the nearest neighbors.
Distance measures such as
distance are commonly used.
Other distance measures that can be used,
include Manhattan and hemming distance.
To summarize, kNN is a very
simple classification technique.
Note that there is no
separate training phase.
There is no separate part where a model is
constructed and its parameter is adjusted.
This is unlike most other
classification algorithms.
KNN can generate complex
decision boundaries allowing for
complex classification
decisions to be made.
It can be susceptible to noise,however,
because classification decisions
are made using only information about
a few neighboring points
instead of the entire dataset.
KNN can be slow, however, since
the distance between a new sample and
all sample points in the data must
be calculated in order to determine
the k-Nearest Neighbors.
In this lecture, we will discuss
the Naive Bayes classifier.
After this video, you will be able
to discuss how a Naive Bayes model
works fro classification,
define the components of Bayes' Rule and
explain what the naive
means in Naive Bayes.
A Naive Bayes classification model uses a
probabilistic approach to classification.
What this means is that the relationships
between the input features and
the class is expressed as probabilities.
So given the input features for
a sample, the probability for
each class is estimated.
The class with the highest probability
then, determines the label for the sample.
In addition to using a probabilistic
framework for classification,
the Naive Bayes classifier also uses
what is known as Bayes' theorem.
The application of Bayes' theorem makes
estimating the probabilities easier.
In addition, Naive Bayes assumes that
the input features are statistically
independent of one another.
This means that, for a given class,
the value of one feature does not
affect the value of any other feature.
This independence assumption is
an oversimplified one that does not always
hold true, and so
is considered a naive assumption.
The naive independence assumption and
the use of Bayes theorem gives this
classification model its name.
We will cover Bayes theorem and
the independence assumption in
more detail in this lecture.
Before we look at naive
Bayes in more detail,
let's first start with some
background on probability.
Probability is the measure
of how likely an event is,
the probability of an event A occurring
is denoted P and in parenthesis A.
It is calculated by dividing
the number of ways event A can occur,
by the total number of possible outcomes.
For example, what is the probability
of rolling a die and getting six?
When you roll a die you can get
a number from one to six, so
the number of possible outcomes is six.
The number of ways fro getting six is one,
since the way you can get six is if
the die shows six when it stops rolling.
That means that the probability of getting
the number six when you roll a die
is one over six.
This is denoted p of six and
that's equal to one over six and
is read as probability
of six is one over six.
There's also a joint probability,
the joint probability specifies
the probability of event A and
event B occurring together.
In this diagram, the probability of event
A occurring is shown as the blue circle
and the probability of event B
occurring is shown as the green circle.
Then the joint probability,
that is the probability of A and
B occurring together is shown as
the overlap of these two circles.
The joint probability of A and
B is denoted,
P(A,B) for
an example of joint probability,
let's consider rolling 2 dice together.
What is the probability in getting
2 sixes or a six from each die.
If the two events are independent, then
the joint probability is simply the result
of multiplying the probabilities
of the individual events together.
In this case then, we have
the probability of rolling a six for
each die is one over six so
the joint probability is one over 36,
this leads us to conditional probability.
The conditional probability is
the probability of event A occurring
Given that event B has already occurred.
Another way to say this is that
event A is conditioned on event B.
The conditional probability is
the noted P and in parentheses A,
vertical line B and is read as,
probability of A Given B.
This diagram gives a graphical
definition of conditional probability.
As before, the blue circle is
the probability of event A occurring,
the green circle is the probability
of event B occurring.
The overlap is a joint
probability of A and B.
The conditional probability,
P(A given B) then is
calculated as the join probability
divided by the probability of B.
The conditional probability is
an important concept in classification
as we will see later.
It provides the means to specify
the probability of a class label,
given the input values.
The relationship between conditional
probabilities P of B given A and
P of A given B can be expressed
through Bayes' Theorem.
This theorem is named after a reverend
named Thomas Bayes who lived in the 1700s.
It is a way to look at how the probability
of a hypothesis is affected by
new evidence gathered from data.
Bayes' theorem expresses the relationship
between probability of B
given A and probability of A given
B as shown in this equation.
Bayes' Theorem is also known
as Bayes' Rule or Bayes' Law.
Now that we have reviewed some
background on probability
let's see how all this relates
to the classification problem.
With the probabilistic framework the
classification task is defined as follows.
Capital X is the set of values for
the input features in the sample,
given a sample with features X,
predict the corresponding class C.
Another way to state this is,
what is the class label associated with
the feature vector X or how should
the feature vector x be classified?
To find the class label C we need to
calculate the conditional probability of
class C, given X for all classes and
select a class with
the highest probability.
So for classification,
we want to find the value of C that
maximizes the probability of C given X.
The problem is that it is difficult
to estimate this probability,
because we would need to enumerate every
possible combination of feature values and
to know the conditional probability.
For each class given every
possible feature combination and
here is where Bayes'
theorem comes into play.
The classification problem can be
reformulated using Bayes' theorem
to simplify the classification problem.
Specifically, using Bayes' theorem, the
probability of c given x, can be expressed
using other probability quantities,
which can be estimated from the data.
Here's Bayes' theorem again, but
some additional terms defined.
Probability of C I X is referred to
as the posterior probability since
it is the probability of the class label
being C after observing input features X.
Probability of X given
C is the probability of
observing input features X given
that c is the class label.
This is the class conditional probability
since it is conditioned on the class.
Probability of c is the probability
of the class label being C,
this is the probability of each class
prior to observing any input data.
And so
is referred to as the prior probability.
The probability of X is the probability
of observing input features X
regardless of what the class label is.
So for classification we want
to calculate the posterior
probability P(C | X) for each class C.
From Bayes' theorem P(C | X) is related to
the P(X | C) P(C And probability of X.
Probability of X does not depend
on the class C, therefore,
it is a constant value, given the input X.
Since it the same value for
all classes, the probability
of X can be removed from the calculation
of probability of C, given X.
What's left then are probability of
X given C and the probability of C.
So estimating the probability
of C given X boils down to
estimating the probability of X
given C and probability of C.
The nice thing is that
probability of X given C and
probability of C can be
estimated from the data.
So now we have a way to calculate probably
of C given X which is what we need for
classification.
To the estimate the probability of C
which is the probability of the class
of C before observing any input data.
We simply calculate the fraction
of samples with that class label
C in the training data.
For this example, there are four samples
labeled as green circles out of 10
samples, so probability of green
circle is 4 out of 10, or 0.4.
Similarly, the fraction of samples labeled
as red triangles is 6 out of 10, or 0.6.
So estimating the prior
probabilities is a simple count
of number of samples with each class label
divided by the total number of
samples in the training data center.
In estimating probability of X
given C which is the probability
of observing feature factor
X given that the class is C,
we can use the independent
assumption to simplify the problem.
The Independence Assumption of
the Naive Bayes classifier assumes
that each feature X sub I
in the featured vector X
is conditionally independent of every
other feature, given the class C.
This means that we only need to
estimate the probability of X
sub i given C, instead of having to
estimate the probability of
the entire feature X given C.
For every combination of values for
the features in X then we would simply
multiply these individual probabilities
together to get the probability
of the entire feature vector X.
Given the class C to estimate
the probability of X sub I,
given C, we count up the number
of times a particular input
value is observed for
the class c in the training data.
For example, the number of times that we
see the value of yes for the future home
owner, when the class label is no it's
three as indicated by the green arrows.
This is divided by the number of samples
with no as the class label which is seven.
This fraction, three out of seven,
is the probability that home owner
is Yes given that the class is No.
Similarly, the samples with
the value of Single for
the feature Marital Status when it crosses
Yes are indicated by the red arrows.
And the probability that
Marital Status is Single,
given that the class label
is Yes is 2/3 or 0.67.
Some things to know about the Naive Bayes
classification model are it is a fast and
simple algorithm.
The algorithm boils down to calculating
counts for probabilities and
performing some multiplication, so
it is very simple to implement.
And the probabilities that are needed
can be calculated with a single
scan of the data set and
stored in a table.
Either two processing of the data
is not necessary as with many other
machine learning algorithms.
So model building and
testing of both task, it scales well.
Due today independent assumption,
the probability for
each feature can be
independently estimated.
These means that featured probability
is can be calculated in parallel,
this also means that the data set size
does not have to grow exponentially
with a number of features.
This avoids the many problems associated
with the curse of dimensionality,
this also means that you do not need
a lot of data to build the model.
The number of parameters scales
linearly with the number of features.
The Independence assumption does
not hold true in many cases.
In practice however, the Naive Bayes
classifier still tends to perform very
well this is because even
though Naive Bayes may
not provide good estimates of
the correct class probabilities.
As long as the correct class is
more probable than any other class,
the correct classification
results will be reached.
The independence assumption also prevents
the naive base classifier to model
interactions between features which
limits its classification power.
The increased risk of smoking in a history
of cancer would not be captured,
for example.
The Naive Bays classifier has been
applied to many real world problems
including spam filtering, document
classification, and sentiment analysis.
To summarize, the Naive Bayes classifier
uses a probabilistic framework for
classification.
It applies Bayes Theorem and
the Feature Independence Assumption,
to simplify the problem of estimating
probabilities for the classification task.
In addition to the evaluation
matrix covered n the last lecture.
The performance of a classification
model can also be evaluated
using a Confusion Matrix.
We will introduce the Confusion Matrix,
in this lecture.
After this video you will be able to,
describe how a confusion matrix can
be used to evaluate a classifier.
Interpret the confusion matrix of a model.
And relate accuracy to values
in a confusion matrix.
Let's use our example again of predicting
whether a given animal is a mammal or not.
Recall that this is a binary
classification task, with the Class Label
being either Yes, indicating mammal or
No indicating non-mammal.
Now let's review the different Types
of Errors that you can get with
Classification.
If the True Label is Yes and
the Predicted Label is Yes, then this
is a True Positive, abbreviated as TP.
This is a case where the label is
correctly predicted as positive.
If the True Label is No and
the Predicted Label is No, then this
is a True Negative, abbreviated as TN.
This is the case where the label is
correctly predicted as negative.
If the True Label is No and
the Predicted Label is Yes, then this
is a False Positive, abbreviated as FP.
This is the case where the label is
incorrectly predicted as positive
when it should be negative.
If the True Label is Yes and
the Predicted Label is No,
then this is a False Negative
abbreviated as FN.
This is the case where the label is
incorrectly predicted as negative,
when it should be positive.
A Confusion Matrix can be used to
summarize the different types of
classification errors.
The True Positive cell corresponds to the
samples that are correctly predicted as
positive by the model.
The True Negative cell corresponds to
the samples that are correctly predicted
as negative.
The False Positive cell corresponds to
samples that are incorrectly predicted
as positive.
The False Negative cell corresponds to
samples that are incorrectly predicted
as negative.
Each cell has the count, or percentage
of samples, with each type of errors.
Let's look at an example to see how
a Confusion Matrix is filled in.
The table on the lists True Labels
along with the models prediction for
a data set of ten samples.
We'll summarize this results
in a Confusion Matrix.
First let's figure out
the number of true positives.
We call that a true positive occurrence
when the output is correctly predicted
as positive.
In other words, the true label is Yes and
the model's prediction is also Yes.
In this example, there are three true
positives as indicated by the red arrows.
We enter three and the true positive
cell in the Confusion Matrix.
Now let's look at the true negatives.
A true negative occurs when the output
is correctly predicted as negative.
In other words, the true label is No and
the models prediction is also No.
In this example,
there are four true negatives as
indicated by the green arrows.
We enter four in the true negative
cell in the Confusion Matrix.
What about false negatives?
A false negative occurs when the output
is incorrectly predicted as negative,
when it should be positive.
That is the true label is Yes,
and the model's prediction is No.
In this example,
there are two false negatives as
indicated by the purple arrows.
We enter two in the false negative
cell in the Confusion Matrix.
Finally we need to look
at false positives.
A false positive occurs,
when the input is incorrectly predicted
as positive, when it should be negative.
That is the true label is No and
models prediction is Yes.
In this example there is one false
positive as indicated by the yellow arrow.
We enter one in the false positive
cell in the Confusion Matrix.
This is our complete Confusion Matrix for
this example.
We see that the sum of the numbers
in the cells add up to ten,
which is the number of
samples in our dataset.
Note that the diagonal values,
true positives and
true negatives are samples
with Correct Predictions.
In our example, these values sum up to 7.
Meaning that 7 out of 10 samples were
correctly predicted by the model.
The higher the sum of the diagonal values,
the better the performance of the model.
The off diagonal values capture
the misclassified samples.
Where the model's predictions
do not match the true labels.
In this example these values indicate
that there were three misclassifications.
Smaller values for
the off diagonal cells in the confusion
matrix indicate better model performance.
Note that the diagonal values,
true positives and
true negatives are samples
with correct predictions.
In our example,
these values sum up to 7 meaning
that 7 out of 10 samples were
correctly predicted by the model.
The higher the sum of the diagonal values,
the better the performance of the model.
You may have noticed that the diagonal
values are related to Accuracy Rate.
Recall that accuracy is defined
as the sum of two positives and
true negatives, divided by all samples.
The sum of two positives and
two negatives is the sum of the diagonal
values in a confusion matrix.
The sum of the diagonal
values in a confusion matrix,
divided by the total number of
samples gives you the Accuracy Rate.
Similarly, the off diagonal values
are related to the Error Rate.
Recall that the Error Rate is
the opposite of the Accuracy Rate.
The sum of the off diagonal
values in a confusion matrix,
divided by the total number of samples,
gives you the Error Rate.
Looking at the values in the Confusion
Matrix can help you understand
the kind of Misclassifications
that your model is making.
A high value for
this cell indicated by the yellow arrow,
means that classifying the Positive
class is problematic for the model.
A high value for the cell indicated by
the orange arrow on the other hand,
means that classifying the Negative
class is problematic for the model.
In summary,
the Confusion Matrix is a table
used to summarize the different
types of errors for a classifier.
The values in a Confusion Matrix can
be used to evaluate the performance of
a classifier and are related to evaluation
metrics, such as accuracy and error rates.
They also indicate what other types of
misclassifications the model is making.
Note that in some implementations
of a Confusion Matrix, the true and
predictive labels are switched.
Be sure to review the documentation for
the software you're using to generate
a Confusion Matrix to understand
what each cell specifies.
In this activity, we will be
evaluating the decision tree model
we created in the KNIME
classification hands-on.
First, we will create a confusion
matrix to determine the accuracy
of the decision tree model.
Next, we will use highlighting and
a scatter plot to analyze
the classification errors.
Let's begin.
First, let's open the Classification
workflow that we built in the previous
hands-on.
In the top-left of KNIME
is a KNIME Explorer.
Double-click on the Classification,
under LOCAL.
Next, we'll create a confusion
matrix to analyze the accuracy
of our decision tree model.
To do this,
we'll add the Scorer node to the canvas.
Connect the output of Decision Tree
Predictor, to the input of Scorer.
Double-click on Scorer.
We'll use the default values, so click OK.
Next, run the workflow.
Now, let's view the confusion matrix.
I can see the accuracy as 80.282%.
At the top, I can see that it
accurately predicted 76 values for
humidity_low and 95 for humidity_not_low.
It inaccurately predicted 24 values for
humidty_low and
18 for humidty_not_low,
for an error of 19.718%.
Close this.
Next, we use an interactive table to
look at the values that were incorrectly
predicted.
We'll add the Interactive Table
to the canvas.
We'll connect this to the output
of Decision Tree Predictor,
run the workflow and view the table.
The right two columns have the real value
for low_humidity and the prediction.
For some of these rows, we can tell
that the prediction was not correct.
For example, in row ten, And in row 17.
Let's leave the table view open,
and go back to the workflow.
Next, we'll add the Scatter Plot
nodes to the workflow.
Connect this to the output
of Decision Tree Predictor.
Execute the workflow, and
view the scatter plot.
We'll select row 17, and
choose, Hilite Selected.
Go back to the scatter plot,
and we see this particular value
is highlighted in the plot.
We could choose another
row from the table, and
highlight it again to see
its place in the plot.
Let's choose row ten.
We can do this for
values that were incorrectly predicted,
to find any patterns for further analysis.
In this activity we will use Spark
to evaluate our decision tree.
First, we load
the classification predictions,
created during the last
Spark hands on activity.
We then compute the accuracy
of these predictions.
And then, generate a confusion matrix.
Let's begin.
First, let's open the model
evaluation notebook.
Next, let's execute the first
cell to load the classes.
Then, execute the second cell
to load the predictions we saved
during the previous hands on.
We could then complete
the accuracy of these predictions
by using a multi-class
classification evaluator.
Let's enter evaluator =
MulticlassClassificationEvaluator(labelCo-
l="label", predictionCol="prediction") and
finally metricName="precision" and
execute this.
We can then compute the accuracy by
calling evaluate on the evaluator.
We'll enter
evaluator.evaluate[predictions].
This says that the accuracy is about 81%.
Next, let's use multi-class metrics
to compute a confusion matrix.
Multi-class metrics takes
an RDD of numbers, and
our data is currently in a data frame.
We can access the RDD of the underlying
data frame by using the RDD
attribute of predictions.
If we look at predictions.rdd.take(2)
we see the RDD
is the RDD of rows, or
each row has a prediction and label.
However multi-class metrics
wants an RDD of numbers.
We could do this using a map.
We'll enter predictions.rdd.map and
we'll use a key word,
tuple, and we'll look at the first
two elements in this RDD.
Run this.
We can see now this RDD is just numbers.
Now we'll create a new instance of
a multiclass metrics using this RDD.
Metrics =
MulticlassMetrics(predrictions.rdd.map(tu-
ple)).
We can then display
the confusion matrix by running
metrics.confusionMatrix().toArray().trans-
pose().
We can see these results are similar
to the confusion matrix in nine.
Generalization and overfitting are very
important concepts in machine learning.
We will cover them in
the next three lectures.
After this video you will be able
to define what overfitting is,
describe how overfitting is
related to generalization, and
explain why overfitting should be avoided.
Before we look at generalization and
overfitting, let's first define some terms
that we will need to know to
discuss errors in classification.
Recall that a machine learning model
maps the input it receives to an output.
For a classification model, the model's
output is the predicted class label for
the input variables and
the true class label is the target.
Then if the classifier predicts
the correct classes label for
a sample, that is a success.
If the predicted class label is
different from the true class label,
then that is an error.
The error rate, then, is the percentage
of errors made over the entire data set.
That is, it is the number of errors
divided by the total number of samples
in a data set.
Error rate is also known as
misclassification rate, or simply error.
In our lesson on classification we discuss
that there is a training phase in which
the model is built, and a testing phase in
which the model is applied to new data.
The model is built using training data and
evaluated on test data.
The training and
test data are two different data sets.
The goal in building a machine learning
model is to have the model perform well
on training, as well as test data.
Error rate, or simply error, on the
training data is refered to as training
error, and the error on test data
is referred to as test error.
The error on the test data is
an indication of how well the classifier
will perform on new data.
This is known as generalization.
Generalization refers to how well
your model performs on new data,
that is data not used to train the model.
You want your model to
generalize well to new data.
If your model generalizes well, then
it will perform well on data sets that
are similar in structure
to the training data, but
doesn't contain exactly the same
samples as in the training set.
Since the test error indicates how well
your model generalizes to new data,
note that the test error is also
called generalization error.
A related concept to
generalization is overfitting.
If your model has very
low training error but
high generalization error,
then it is overfitting.
This means that the model has learned to
model the noise in the training data,
instead of learning the underlying
structure of the data.
These plots illustrate what
happens when a model overfits.
Training samples are shown as points, and
the input to output mapping that the model
has learned is indicated as a curve.
The plot on the left shows that the model
has learned the underlying structure of
the data, as the curve follows
the trend of the sample point as well.
The plot on the right,
however, shows that the model has learned
to model the noise in a data set.
The model tries to capture
every sample point,
instead of the general trend
of the samples together.
The training error and
the generalization error are plotted
together, during model training.
What is the connection between
overfitting and generalization?
A model that overfits will not
generalize well to new data.
So the model will do well on just
the data it was trained on, but
given a new data set,
it will perform poorly.
A classifier that performs well
on just the training data set
will not be very useful.
So it is essential that the goal of good
generalization performance is kept in mind
when building a model.
A problem related to
overfitting is underfitting.
Overfitting occurs when the model is
fitting to the noise in the training data.
This results in low training error and
high test error.
Underfitting on the other hand,
occurs when the model has not
learned the structure of the data.
This results in high training error and
high test error.
Both are undesirable,
since both mean that the model will
not generalize well to new data.
Overfitting generally occurs when
a model is too complex, that is,
it has too many parameters relative
to the number of training samples.
So to avoid overfitting, the model needs
to be kept as simple as possible, and yet
still solve the input/output mapping for
the given data set.
We will discuss methods for
avoiding overfitting in
the next couple of lectures.
In summary, overfitting is when your model
has learned the noise in the training data
instead of the underlying
structure of the data.
You want to avoid overfitting so that your
model will generalize well to new data.
How do you evaluate
your model performance?
In this lecture, we will look at
different metrics that can be used to
evaluate the performance of
your classification model.
After this video, you will be able to
discuss how performance metrics
can be used to evaluate models.
Name three model evaluation metrics, and
explain why accuracy may be misleading.
For the classification task, an error
occurs when the model's prediction of
the class label is different
from the true class label.
We can also define the different types
of errors in classification depending on
the predicted and true labels.
Let's take the case with the task is
to predict whether a given animal is
a mammal or not.
This is a binary classification task
with the class label being either yes,
indicating mammal, or
no indicating non-mammal.
Then the different types
of errors are as follows.
If the true label is yes and
the predicted label is yes,
then this is a true positive,
abbreviated as TP.
This is the case where the label is
correctly predicted as positive.
If the true label is no and
the predicted label is no,
then this is a true negative,
abbreviated as TN.
This is the case where the label is
correctly predicted as negative.
If the true label is no and
the predicted label is yes,
then this is a false positive,
abbreviated as FP.
This is the case with the label is
incorrectly predicted as positive,
when it should be negative.
If the true label is yes and
the predicted label is no, then this
is a false negative abbreviated as FN.
This is the case where the label is
incorrectly predicted as negative,
when it should be positive.
These definitions can take a while to sink
in, so feel free to hit the pause button
and replay button several times
here to review this part.
These four different types of errors
are used in calculating many evaluation
metrics for classifiers.
The most commonly used evaluation
metric is the accuracy rate, or
accuracy for short.
For classication,
accuracy is calculated as the number of
correct predictions divided by
the total number of predictions.
Note that the number of correct
predictions is the sum of the true
positives, and the true negatives, since
the true and predicted labels match for
those cases.
The accuracy rate is an intuitive
way to measure the performance
of a classification model.
Model performance can also be
expressed in terms of error rate.
Error rate is the opposite
of accuracy rate.
Let's look at an example to see how
accuracy and error rates are calculated.
The table on the left, lists the true
label along with the model's prediction
for a data set of ten samples.
First, let’s figure out
the number of true positives.
Recall that a true positive occurs when
the output is correctly predicted as
positive.
In other words the true label is yes,
and the model's prediction is yes.
In this example there are three true
positives as indicated by the red arrows.
So, TP=3, remember that value
as we'll need it later.
Now, let's figure out
the number of true negatives.
A true negative occurs when the output
is correctly predicted as negative.
In other words, the true label is no and
the model's prediction is no.
In this example there are four true
negatives as indicated by the green
arrows.
So TN = 4,
we'll need to remember this value as well.
Now we use the values for TP and
TN to calculate the accuracy rate.
Using the equation for accuracy rate,
we plug in three for TP and four for TN.
We get seven correct predictions for
the numerator.
The denominator is simply the total number
of samples in our data set, which is ten.
So the accuracy rate for
example is 7 out of 10 which is 0.7 or
70%.
The error rate is the exact
opposite of the accuracy rate.
To calculate the error rate, we simply
subtract the accuracy rate from 1.
For our example that is
1- 0.7 which is 0.3.
So the error rate for
this example is 0.3 or 30%.
There's a limitation with accuracy and
error rates when you have
a class imbalance problem.
This is when there are very few
samples of the class of interest, and
the majority are negative examples.
An example of this is identifying
if a tumor is cancerous or not.
What is of interest is identifying
samples with cancerous tumors, but
these positive cases where the tumor
is cancerous are very rare.
So, you end up with a very small
fraction of positive samples, and
most of the samples are negative.
Thus the name, class imbalance problem.
What could be the problem with using
accuracy for a class imbalance problem?
Consider the situation where only 3%
of the cases are cancerous tumors.
If the classification model
always predicts non-cancer,
it will have an accuracy rate of 97%,
since 97% of the samples will
have non-cancerous tumors.
But note that in this case, the model
fails to detect any cancer cases at all.
So the accuracy rate is
very misleading here.
You may think that your model is
performing very well with such
a high accuracy rate.
But in fact it cannot identify any of
the cases in the class of interest.
In these cases we need evaluation
metrics that can capture how
well the model classifies positive,
versus negative classes.
A pair of evaluations metrics that
are commonly used when there is a class
imbalance are precision and recall.
Precision is defined as the number of
true positives divided by the sum of
true positives and false positives.
In other words, it is the number of true
positives divided by the total number
of samples predicted as being positive.
Recall is defined as the number of
true positives divided by the sum of
true positives and false negatives.
It is the number of true positives
divided by the total number of samples,
actually belonging to the true class.
Here's an illustration that
shows precision and recall.
The selected elements indicated by the
green half circle are the true positives.
That is samples predicted as positive and
are actually positive.
The relevant elements indicated
by the green half circle and
the green half rectangle, are the true
positives, plus the false negatives.
That is samples that are actually
positive, but some are correctly predicted
as positive, and some are incorrectly
predicted as negative.
Recall then is the number of samples
correctly predicted as positive,
divided by all samples that
are actually positive.
The entire circle indicated
by the green half circle and
the pink half circle, are the true
positives plus the false positives.
That is samples that were
predicted as positive
although some were actually positive and
some were actually negative.
Then precision is the number of samples
correctly predicted as positive,
divided by the number of all
samples predicted as positive.
Precision is considered a measure
of exactness because it calculates
the percentage of samples
predicted as positive,
which are actually in a positive class.
Recall is considered a measure of
completeness, because it calculates
the percentage of positive samples
that the model correctly identified.
There is a trade off between precision and
recall.
A perfect precision score of one for
a class C means that every sample
predicted as belonging to class C,
does indeed belong to class C.
But this says nothing about the number of
samples from class C that were predicted
incorrectly.
A perfect recall score of one for
a class C, means that every sample
from class C was correctly labeled.
But this doesn't say anything
about how many other samples were
incorrectly labeled as
belonging to class C.
So they are used together.
For example, precision values can be
compared for a fixed value of recall or
vice versa.
The goal for classification is to
maximize both precision and recall.
Precision and recall can be combined into
a single metric called the F-measure.
The equation for that is 2 times
the product of precision and
recall divided by their sum.
There are different
versions of the F-measure.
The equation on this side is for
the F1 measure which is the most
commonly used variant of the F measure.
With the F1 measure, precision and
recall are equally weighted.
The F2 measure weights recall
higher than precision.
And the F0.5 measure weights
precision higher than recall.
The value for
the F1 measure ranges from zero to one,
with higher values giving better
classification performance.
In summary, there are several metrics for
evaluating the performance
of a classification model.
They are defined in terms of
the types of errors you can get in
a classification problem.
We covered some of the most commonly
used evaluation metrics in this lecture,
namely accuracy and error rates,
precision and recall and F1 measure.
In this lecture, we will discuss how
overfitting occurs with decision trees and
how it can be avoided.
After this video,
you will be able to discuss overfitting
in the context of decision tree models.
Explain how overfitting is addressed
in decision tree induction.
Define pre-pruning and post-pruning.
In our lecture on decision trees, we
discussed that during the construction of
a decision tree, also referred to as
tree induction, the tree repeatedly
splits the data in a node in order to
get successively paired subsets of data.
Note that a decision tree classifier can
potentially expand its nodes until it can
perfectly classify samples
in the training data.
But if the tree grows nodes to fit
the noise in the training data,
then it will not classify
a new sample well.
This is because the tree has partitioned
the input space according to the noise in
the data instead of to
the true structure of a data.
In other words, it has overfit.
How can overfitting be
avoided in decision trees?
There are two ways.
One is to stop growing the tree
before the tree is fully grown
to perfectly fit the training data.
This is referred to as pre-pruning.
The other way to avoid overfitting in
decision trees is to grow the tree to its
maximum size and then prune the tree
back by removing parts of the tree.
This is referred to as post-pruning.
In general, overfitting occurs
because the model is too complex.
For a decision tree model,
model complexity is determined by
the number of nodes in the tree.
Addressing overfitting in decision trees
means controlling the number of nodes.
Both methods of pruning control
the growth of the tree and consequently,
the complexity of the resulting model.
With pre-pruning, the idea is to stop tree
induction before a fully grown tree is
built that perfectly
fits the training data.
To do this, restrictive stopping
conditions for growing nodes must be used.
For example, a nose stops expanding if
the number of samples in the node is less
than some minimum threshold.
Another example is to stop expanding
a note if the improvement in the impurity
measure falls below a certain threshold.
In post-pruning,
the tree is grown to its maximum size,
then the tree is pruned by removing
nodes using a bottom up approach.
That is, the tree is trimmed
starting with the leaf nodes.
The pruning is done by replacing
a subtree with a leaf node if
this improves the generalization error,
or if there is no
change to the generalization
error with this replacement.
In other words, if removing a subtree
does not have a negative effect
on the generalization error,
then the nodes in that subtree only
add to the complexity of the tree,
and not to its overall performance.
So those nodes should be removed.
In practice,
post-pruning tends to give better results.
This is because pruning decisions are
based on information from the full tree.
Pre-pruning, on the other hand, may stop
the tree growing process prematurely.
However, post-pruning is more
computationally expensive since the tree
has to be expanded to its full size.
In summary, to address overfitting in
decision trees, tree pruning is used.
There are two pruning methods,
pre-pruning and post-pruning.
Both methods control
the complexity of the tree model.
In this lecture, we will discuss
what a validation set is and
how it relates to overfitting and
model performance evaluation.
After this video, you will be able to
describe how validation sets can be
used to avoid overfitting.
Articulate how training,
validation, and test sets are used.
And list three ways that
validation can be performed.
In our lesson on classification,
we discussed that there is a training
phase in which the model is built, and
a testing phase in which
the model is applied to new data.
The model is built using training data and
evaluated on test data.
The training and
test data are two different datasets.
The goal in building a machine learning
model is to have the model perform well
on the training set, as well as generalize
well on new data in the test set.
Recall that a model that overfits
does not generalize well to new data.
Recall also that overfitting generally
occurs when a model is too complex.
So to have a model with good
generalization performance,
model training has to stop before
the model gets too complex.
How do you determine
when this should occur?
A validation set can be used to guide the
training process to avoid overfitting and
deliver good generalization performance.
We have discussed having a training
set and a separate test set.
The training set is used
to build a model and
the test set is used to see how
the model performs a new data.
Now we want to further divide up
the training data into a training set and
a validation set.
The training set is used to
train the model as before and
the validation set is used to determine
when to stop training the model
to avoid overfitting, in order to get
the best generalization performance.
The idea is to look at the errors
on both training set and
validation set during model
training as shown here.
The orange solid line on the plot
is the training error and
the green line is the validation error.
We see that as model building
progresses along the x-axis,
the number of nodes increases.
That is the complexity
of the model increases.
We can see that as the model complexity
increases, the training error decreases.
On the other hand, the validation
error initially decreases but
then starts to increase.
When the validation error increases, this
indicates that the model is overfitting,
resulting in decreased
generalization performance.
This can be used to determine
when to stop training.
Where validation error starts to increase
is when you get the best generalization
performance, so
training should stop there.
This method of using a validation set
to determine when to stop training
is referred to as model selection
since you're selecting one from
many of varying complexities.
Note that this was illustrated for
a decision tree classifier, but
the same method can be applied to
any type of machine learning model.
There are several ways to create and use
the validation set to avoid overfitting.
The different methods are holdout method,
random subsampling,
k-fold cross-validation,
and leave-one-out cross-validation.
The first way to use a validation
set is the holdout method.
This describes the scenario
that we have been discussing,
where part of the training data
is reserved as a validation set.
The validation set is
then the holdout set.
Errors on the training set and the holdout
set are calculated at each step
during model training and
plotted together as we've seen before.
And the lowest error on the holdout
set is when training should stop.
This is the just the process that
we have described here before.
There's some limitations to
the holdout method however.
First, since some samples are reserved for
the holdout validation set,
the training set now has less data
than it originally started out with.
Secondly, if the training and holdout sets
do not have the same data distributions,
then the results will be misleading.
For example, if the training data has
many more samples of one class and
the holdout dataset has many
more samples of another class.
The next method for using
a validation set is repeated holdout.
As the name implies,
this is essentially repeating
the holdout method several times.
With each iteration, samples are randomly
selected from the original training data
to create the holdout validation set.
This is repeated several times with
different training and validation sets.
Then the iterates on the holdout set for
the different iterations
are averaged together to get the overall
iterate for model selection.
A potential problem with repeated holdout
is that you could end up with some samples
being used more than others for training.
Since a sample can be used for either
testing or training any number of times,
some samples may be put in the training
set more times than other samples.
So you might end up with some
samples being overrepresented while
other samples are underrepresented
in training or testing.
A way to improve on the repeated
holdout method is use cross-validation.
Cross-validation works as follows.
Segment the data into k number
of disjoint partitions.
During each iteration, one partition
is used as the validation set.
Repeat the process k times.
Each time using a different partition for
validation.
So each partition is used for
validation exactly once.
This is illustrated in this figure.
In the fist iteration, the first
partition, specified in green, is used for
validation.
In the second iteration,
the second partition is used for
validation and so on.
The overall validation error is calculated
by averaging the validation errors for
all k iterations.
The model with the smallest average
validation error then is selected.
The process we just described is
referred to as k-fold cross-validation.
This is a very commonly used approach
to model selection in practice.
This approach gives you a more structured
way to divide available data up between
training and validation datasets and
provides a way to overcome the variability
in performance that you can get when
using a single partitioning of the data.
Leave-one-out cross-validation
is a special case of k-fold
cross-validation where k equals N,
where N is the size of your dataset.
Here, for each iteration the validation
set has exactly one sample.
So the model is trained to
using N minus one samples and
is validated on the remaining sample.
The rest of the process works the same
way as regular k-fold cross-validation.
Note that cross-validation is often
abbreviated CV and leave-one-out
cross-validation is in abbreviated
L-O-O-C-V and pronounced LOOCV.
We have described several ways to use
a validation set to address overfitting.
Error on the validation set is used
to determine when to stop training so
that the model does not overfit.
Note that the validation error that comes
out of this process can also be used
to estimate generalization
performance of the model.
In other words,
the error on the validation set provides
an estimate of the error on the test set.
With the addition of the validation set,
you really need three distinct
datasets when you build a model.
Let's review these datasets.
The training dataset is used to train the
model, that is to adjust the parameters of
the model to learn the input
to output mapping.
The validation dataset is used to
determine when training should stop
in order to avoid overfitting.
The test data set is used to evaluate
the performance of the model on new data.
Note that the test data set should never,
ever be used in any way to create or
tune the model.
It should not be used, for
example, in a cross-validation process
to determine when to stop training.
The test dataset must always remain
independent from model training and
remain untouched until the very end
when all training has been completed.
Note that in sampling the original dataset
to create the training, validation, and
test sets, all datasets must contain the
same distribution of the target classes.
For example, if in the original dataset,
70% of the samples belong to one class and
30% to the other class, then this same
distribution should approximately
be present in each of the training,
validation, and test sets.
Otherwise, analysis results
will be misleading.
To summarize, we have discuss the need for
three different datasets
in building model.
A training set to train the model,
a validation set to determine when to stop
training, and a test to evaluate
performance on new data.
We learned how a validation set can
be used to avoid overfitting and
in the process, provide an estimate
of generalization performance.
And we covered different
ways to create and
use a validation set such
as k-fold cross-validation.
Now that we have seen what
association analysis is,
let's go over the association
analysis process in more detail.
After this video, you will be able
to define the terms support and
confidence, describe the steps
in association analysis, and
explain how association rules
are formed from item sets.
Let's review the set in
association analysis.
They are create item the sets,
then identify the frequent item sets.
Finally, generate the rules.
We will continue with
this example dataset,
there are five transactions
in the dataset.
Each with a set of items
purchased together.
The goal is to come up with rules
describing associations between items.
The first step is to create item sets.
Item sets have different sizes
which need to be created.
We will color code the items so
that each one is easier to pick
out from the transactions table.
We start out with just 1-item sets,
that is, sets with just one item.
The left table is
the dataset of transactions.
The right table contains the 1-item sets
that can be created from this dataset.
As each item set is created, we also need
to keep track of the frequency at which
these item set occurs in the dataset.
This is referred to support for
the item set and
is calculated by dividing the number of
times the item set occurs in the dataset
by the total number of transactions.
This is what is in the Support
column in the right table.
For example, eggs the last
item in the right table occurs
just occurs just once in the dataset,
in the transaction two.
So if Support is 1/5 or
one fifth,the item set with
diaper occurs in all transactions,
so if Support is 5/5 or 1.
The Support for each item set will be
used to identify frequent item sets
in the next step, specifically,
the Support issues to prune, or
remove, item sets that
do not occur frequently.
The support of each item set
will be used to identify
frequent item sets in the next step.
Specifically, the support
is used to prune or
remove item sets that do
not occur frequently.
For example, the minimum support
threshold is set to 3/5.
So looking at the 1-item sets table
We can remove any item set with
the support of less than 3/5.
These item sets are highlighted in pink,
they will be removed before the sets for
two items are created.
The final one item sets are then the item
sets with bread, milk, beer and diaper.
We only consider items that were in
the one item sets, that were not pruned.
The two item sets are shown
in the right table.
We, again,
need to keep track of the support for
these item sets,
just as we did with the one item sets.
For example, for
the last item set, with beer, and
diaper, we see, by looking at
the left table, that beer and
diaper occur together three times In
transactions two, three and four.
So with support is 3/5.
Again, we need to prune
item sets with low support.
The ones highlighted in pink
in the two item sets table.
Those would be the item set with bread and
beer and the item set with milk and beer.
The remaining two items that end.
One item such or
then use to create the three item sets.
Let's look now at
creating three item sets.
The only three item sets that has a
support value greater than minimum support
is the one shown in the right table.
Namely the items start with bread,
milk and diaper.
The second step in association analysis
is to identify the frequent item sets.
But note that the process
that we just described for
creating item sets already
identifies frequent item sets.
A frequent item set is one whose
support is greater than or
equal to the minimum support.
So by keeping track of the support of
each item set as it is being created and
removing item sets with low support,
we are already identifying
frequent item sets.
For our example, the frequent one,
two and three item sets are shown here.
Now that we identified the frequent
item sets, the last step is to
generate the rules to capture
associations that we see in the data.
Let's first define some terms we'll
need to discuss association rules.
The format of an association
rule is shown at the top.
It's written as X arrow Y and
is read as if X, then Y.
The X part is called the antecedent and
the Y part is called
the consequent of the rule.
X and Y are item sets.
An important term in rule
generation is the rule confidence.
This is to find as a support for X and
Y together divided by the support for
X only.
So rule confidence
calculates the frequency of
instances to which the rule applies.
Recall that the support for
X is the frequency of item set X and
is defined as the number of
transactions containing items in X
divided by the total
number of transactions.
The rule confidence measures
how frequently items in
Y appear in the transaction
that contain X.
In other words, the confidence measures
the reliability of the rule by determining
how often, if X and
Y is found to be true in the data.
How is rule confidence
used in rule generation?
Association rules are generated from the
frequent item sets created from the data.
Each item in an item set can be
used as a part of the antecedent or
consequent of the rule.
And you can have many ways to combine
items to form the antecedent and
consequent.
So if we just simply generate
rules from each frequent item set,
we would end up with lots and
lots of rules.
Each item set with k items can
generate 2 to the k-2 rules.
That's a lot of rules.
And the majority of those rules
would not be found in the data.
This is where rule confidence comes in.
We can use rule confidence to
constrain the number of rules to keep.
Specifically, a minimum
confidence threshold is set and
only rules with confidence greater than or
equal to the minimum confidence are
significant and only those will be kept.
Let's look at how this works
with our example dataset.
We call that only one three item set
was created from the transactions.
That three items that contains
items bread, milk and
diaper as shown at the top.
With these three item set let's see
how we can generate rules from it and
determine which rules to keep and
which one to prune.
Let's set the minimum confidence to 0.95.
And here again is the definition for
confidence.
For candidate rule if bread and
milk then diaper,
we can calculate it's confidence
as follows the support for
both antecedent and consequent is
the number of times we see bread, milk and
diaper together in the data, divided
by the total number of transactions.
Items bread, milk and diaper appear
together in transaction 1, 4 and
5 so the support is 3/5.
The support for just the antecedent is
the number of times we see bread and
milk together divided by
the total number of transactions.
Items bread and milk appear together
also in transactions 1, 4, and 5.
So the support is 3/5.
The confidence of this rule is then 1,
or 100%.
This means that the rule is correct 100%.
Every time bread and milk are bought
together, diaper is bought as well.
For candidate rule if bread and
diaper than milk,
we calculate its confidence the same way.
The support for bread, diaper and
milk is 3/5 as before.
Items bread and diaper are paired
together in transactions 1, 2, 4 and 5.
So the support for
the items set with bread and milk is 4/5.
Then the confidence with
this rule is 0.75 or 75%.
Since the minimum confidence is 0.95 or
95%,
the first rule is kept and the second
rule is removed from consideration.
There are several algorithms for
association analysis.
Each uses a different set of methods
to make frequent items set creation and
rule generation efficient.
The more popular algorithms are Apriori,
FP Growth and Eclat.
As a summary, we just looked at the steps
in association analysis in more detail.
We saw how items sets can be created from
a dataset, how frequent items sets can be
identified, and how association rules can
be created from frequent item sets and
pruned using rule confidence.
We've looked at classification,
regression and cluster analysis.
Let's now discuss association
analysis as a machine learning task.
After this video, you will be able to
explain what association analysis entails,
list some applications of association
analysis, define what an item set is.
In association analysis, the goal is to
come up with a set of rules to capture
associations between items or events.
The rules are used to determine when
items or events occur together.
You may remember seeing these images
earlier in the course, where we introduced
the different categories of machine
learning tasks and techniques.
But do you remember what
the association is between these items?
Well, let's recap that story,
in case you don't remember.
The story goes like this.
A supermarket chain used
association analysis to discover
a connection between two
seemingly unrelated products.
They discovered that many
customers who go to the store
late on Sunday night to buy
diapers also tend to buy beer.
This information was then used to
place beer and diapers close together.
And they saw a jump in
sales of both items.
This illustrates that you
can uncover unexpected and
useful relationships with
association analysis.
This diaper and beer story has become
part of the data mining folklore.
It's unclear how much of it true, but it
has become the prime example of what you
can discover with association analysis and
machine learning in general.
A common application of association
analysis is referred to as
market basket analysis.
This is used to understand
the purchasing behavior of customers.
The idea is that you're looking into
the shopping basket of customers
when they are at the market, and
analyzing that data to understand
what items are purchased together.
This information can be used to
place related items together, or
to have sales on items that
are often purchased together.
Another application of association
analysis is to recommend items that
a customer may be interested in, based
on their purchasing or browsing history.
This is very commonly used
on companies' websites
to get customers to buy more items.
There are medical applications as well.
Analysis of patients and treatments may
reveal associations to identify effective
treatments for
patients with certain medical histories.
this diagram illustrates how
association analysis works.
The data set is a collection
of transactions.
Each transaction contains one or
more items.
This is referred to as the item set.
From the given items sets,
generate association rules that capture
which item tend occur together.
In our example, the data set
consists of five transactions.
In the first transaction,
the items are diaper, bread and milk.
The second transaction has items bread,
diaper, beer, and eggs, and so on.
Rules that could be generated from
this data set are shown at the bottom.
For example,
the first rule states that if bread and
milk are bought together,
then diaper is also bought.
The second rule state that if milk is
bought, then bread is also bought.
The association analysis process
consist of the following steps.
The first step is to create item sets.
Item sets are generated for sets with one
item, two items, three items and so on.
Then frequent item sets are identified.
Frequent item sets are those that occur
at least a minimum number of times.
From the frequent item sets,
association rules are generated.
We will take a more detailed look
at these steps in the next lecture.
Some things to note about
association analysis.
Like cluster analysis, each transaction
does not have a label to specify which
item set or rule it belongs to.
So, association analysis
is an unsupervised task.
You may end up with many rules
at the end of the analysis.
But, whether those rules are interesting,
useful,
or applicable, requires interpretation
using domain knowledge of the application.
In addition,
the association analysis process will
not tell you how to apply the rules.
This also requires knowledge
of the application.
So as with cluster analysis,
interpretation and analysis are required
to make sense of the resulting rules
that you get from association analysis.
In summary,
association analysis finds rules to
capture associations between items.
The association rules have intuitive
appeal because they are in the form of
if this, then that,
which is easy to understand.
The results of association
analysis require analysis and
interpretation using domain knowledge
to determine the usefulness and
applicability of the resulting rules.
Next we will cover the steps in
the association analysis process in
more detail.
In this activity, we will use
Spark to perform cluster analysis.
First, we will load
the minute weather data.
Next, we will remove the unused and
missing data and
then scale the data so
that the mean is zero.
We will then create an elbow plot,
a subset of the data,
to determine the optimal
number of clusters.
And then cluster the full
data set using k-means.
Finally, we will generate parallel plots
to analyze the individual clusters.
Let's begin.
First, let's open the clustering notebook.
Execute the first cell
to load the libraries.
Execute the second cell
to load the data set.
This data set contains weather station
measurements that were taken every minute.
So there's a lot of measurements.
We can count how many rows there are in
the data frame by running df.count.
This says that there are over 1.5
million rows in the data frame.
Clustering this much data on a single
Cloudera VM can take a lot of time.
So let's only work with
one-tenth of the data.
Let's subset the data
into the new data frame.
We'll enter filteredDF
= df.filter((df.rowID
% 10)) == 0.
We then count the rows of the new data
frame by calling filteredDF.count.
The new data frame has one-tenth as
many rows as the original data set.
Let's compute the summary
statistics using describe.
filteredDF.describe, and
to display it nicely,
we'll enter toPandas().transpose.
Run this.
These weather measurements were taken
during the period of a long drought.
As we can see from the mean values
of the two rain measurements,
rain accumulation, the rain duration,
the measurements are close to zero.
Let's count how many rain
values are equal to 0.
FilterDF.filter(filterDF.rain_accumulation
==
0.0).count().
Now let's do rain duration.
filteredDF.filter(filteredDF.rain_duration
==
0.0).count().
We can see from these counts that most
in these two measurements are zero.
So let's remove them from our data frame.
workingDF =
filterDF.drop('rain_accumulation').drop('-
rain_duration').
And we'll also drop the column
called hpwren_timestamp,
since we will not use it.
So .drop('hpwren_timestamp').
Next, let's drop rows with missing values,
and count how many rows were dropped.
before = workingDF.count() workingDF =
workingDF.na.drop() after
= workingDF.count(),
and finally, we'll print the difference,
before- after.
So only 46 rows had missing values and
were dropped.
Next, let's scale the data so that each
feature will have a value of 0 for
the mean and a value of 1 for
the standard deviation.
First, we need to combine the columns
into a single vector column.
We can look at the existing columns
by entering workingDF.columns.
We do not want to include rowID
since it is a row number.
Additionally, the minimum wind
measurements have a high correlation
to the average wind measurements,
so we will not include this either.
Let's create an array of
the columns we want to combine and
then use vector assembler to
create the vector column.
featuresUsed = [.
Now, let's copy and
paste the columns we want to use.
Assembler = VectorAssembler(inputCols
= featuresUsed,
outputCol = "features_unscaled").
And finally, assembled =
assembler.transform(workingDF).
Run this.
Now we'll use standard
scaler to scale the data.
Scaler = standard scaler
inputCol=”features _unscaler”,
outputCol=“features”, withStd = true,
withMean = True,
scalerModel = scaler.fit(assembled),
scaledData =
scalerModel.transform[assembled].
Next we will create an elbow plot
to determine the value k, for
the number of clusters.
To create the elbow plot,
we will calculate the within cluster,
sum of squared error, or WSSE,
for different values of k.
So since some valves running
K-means many times, let's do it for
a smaller subset of the data
since it'll be faster.
First, let's choose the data to work with.
Let's subset the data.
So scaledData =
scaledData.select("features"), ("rowID").
elbowset =
scaledData.filter((scaledData.rowID
%3) == 0).select("features").
And finally,
we'll call the persist method on elbowset.
Persist will keep it in memory,
and make the calculations faster.
Run this.
Now, let's compute the WSSE values for
different values of k.
We'll do for k, 2 to 30.
Clusters equals range(2,31).
wsseList = utils.elbow(elbowset,
clusters).
Run this, This will print out
the value of wsse for each value of k.
As you can tell, this'll take some
time to run, let's skip to the end.
Now let's display the plot of our data.
utils.elbow_plot(wsseList, clusters).
The x axis is k, the number of clusters,
and the y axis is the WSSE value.
You can see that the graph flattens
out between 10 and 15 for k.
So let's choose k equals 12 as
the midpoint for our number of clusters.
We'll now cluster the data into
12 clusters using k-means.
First, let's select the data
we want to cluster.
scaledDataFeat =
scaledData.select("features"),
scaledDataFeat.persist.
Now I'll perform
the clustering using kmeans.
kmeans = KMeans(k=12, seed=1).
model = KMeans.fit(scaledDataFeat),
and finally,
transformed =
model.transform(scaleDataFeat).
Run this.
We can now see the centre
measurement of each
cluster by calling model.clusterCenters.
It is difficult to compare the cluster
centers just by looking at these numbers.
So let's use parallel
plots to visualize them.
P = utils.pd_centers(featuresUsed,
model.clusterCenters).
Let's show the clusters for
dry days where the weather samples
have low relative humidity.
utils.parallel_plot(P[P['relative_humidi-
ty']
< -0.5], P).
The x axis of this chart shows
the different measurement types.
The y values show the standard deviations,
with zero being the mean.
Each line is a different cluster, and
there are five clusters in this graph.
We can see that they all have
a low relative humidity.
Notice that cluster four, the red one,
has a high average wind speed and
a high maximum wind speed.
Additionally, it has a low
average wind direction.
Which means it was coming from
the north and northeast directions.
So this cluster probably
represents Santa Ana conditions.
Next, let's show the plot for warm days,
the weather samples with
high air temperature.
utils.parallel_plot(P[P['air_temp'] >
0.5], P).
Other clusters in this plot have air
temperature greater than 0.5 standard
deviations away from the mean.
However, they have different values for
the other features.
Now let's show the clusters for cool days.
Weather samples with high relative
humidity and low air temperatures.
utils.parallel_plot(P[(P['relative_humidi-
ty']
> 0.5) & (P['air_temp']
< 0.5)], P).
All the clusters in this plot have
relative humidity greater than 0.5
standard deviations and air temp
less than 0.5 standard deviations.
These clusters represent cool
temperature with high humidity and
possibly rainy weather patterns.
So far we have seen all
the clusters except two.
Since it is not falling to any other
categories let's plot this cluster,
utils.parallel_plot(P.iloc[[2]],
P).
Cluster two captures
days with mild weather.
In addition to classification and
regression, machine learning tasks and
techniques can also fall into another
category known as cluster analysis.
After this video, you will be able to
articulate the goal of cluster analysis,
discuss whether cluster analysis
is supervised or unsupervised, and
list some ways that cluster
results can be applied.
In cluster analysis,
the goal is to organize similar items in
your data set into groups or clusters.
By segmenting your data into clusters, you
can analyze each cluster more carefully.
Note that cluster analysis is
also referred to as clustering.
A very common application of cluster
analysis that we have discussed before is
to divide your customer base into segments
based on their purchasing histories.
For example, you can segment customers
into those who have purchased science
fiction books and videos, versus those
who tend to buy nonfiction books,
versus those who have bought
many children's books.
This way, you can provide more targeted
suggestions to each different group.
Some other examples of cluster analysis
are characterizing different weather
patterns for a region,
grouping the latest news articles into
topics to identify the trending
topics of the day, and
discovering hot spots for different
types of crime from police reports
in order to provide sufficient
police presence for problem areas.
Cluster analysis divides all
the samples in a data set into groups.
In this diagram,
we see that the red, green, and
purple data points are clustered together.
Which group a sample is placed in is
based on some measure of similarity.
The goal of cluster analysis is to segment
data so that differences between samples
in the same cluster are minimized, as
shown by the yellow arrow, and differences
between samples of different clusters are
maximized, as shown by the orange arrow.
Visually, you can think of
this as getting samples in
each cluster to be as close
together as possible, and
the samples from different clusters
to be as far apart as possible.
Cluster analysis requires
some sort of metric to
measure similarity between two samples.
Some common similarity measures are
Euclidean distance, which is the distance
along a straight line between two points,
A and B, as shown in this plot.
Manhattan distance, which is
calculated on a strictly horizontal and
vertical path, as shown in the right plot.
To go from point A to point B, you can
only step along either the x-axis or
the y-axis in a two-dimensional case.
So the path to calculate the Manhattan
distance consists of segments
along the axes instead of along a diagonal
path, as with Euclidean distance.
Cosine similarity measures the cosine
of the angle between points A and
B, as shown in the bottom plot.
Since distance measures such as Euclidean
distance are often used to measure
similarity between samples
in clustering algorithms,
note that it may be necessary to
normalize the input variables so
that no one value dominates
the similarity calculation.
We discussed scaling and
normalizing variables in the lecture
on feature transformation.
Normalizing is one method
to scale variables.
Essentially, scaling the input variables
puts the variables on the same scale so
that all variables have equal
weighting in the calculation
to determine similarity between samples.
Scaling is necessary when you have
variables that have very different scales,
such as weight and height.
The magnitude of the height values,
which are in feet and inches,
will be much smaller than the magnitude of
the weight values, which are in pounds.
So scaling both variables to
a common value range will
make the contributions from
both weight and height equal.
Here are some things to note
about cluster analysis.
First, unlike classification or
regression, in general,
cluster analysis is an unsupervised task.
This means that there is no target
label for any sample in the data set.
In general,
there is no correct clustering results.
The best set of clusters
is highly dependent
on how the resulting
clusters will be used.
There are numerical measures to
compare two different clusters, but
since there are no labels to
determine whether a sample has
been correctly clustered,
there is no ground truth
to determine if a set of clustering
results are truly correct or incorrect.
Clusters don't come with labels.
You may end up with five different
clusters at the end of a cluster
analysis process, but you don't
know what each cluster represents.
Only by analyzing
the samples in each cluster
can you come out with reasonable
labels for your clusters.
Given all this, it is important to
keep in mind that interpretation and
analysis of the clusters
are required to make sense of and
make use of the results
of cluster analysis.
There are several ways that the results
of cluster analysis can be used.
The most obvious is data segmentation and
the benefits that come from that.
If you segment your customer base
into different types of readers,
the resulting insights can be used
to provide more effective marketing
to the different customer groups
based on their preferences.
For example, analyzing each segment
separately can provide valuable insights
into each group's likes, dislikes and
purchasing behavior, just like we see
science fiction, non-fiction and
children's books preferences here.
Clusters can also be used to
classify new data samples.
When a new sample is received,
like the orange sample here, compute
the similarity measure between it and
the centers of all clusters, and assign
a new sample to the closest cluster.
The label of that cluster,
manually determined through analysis,
is then used to classify the new sample.
In our book buyers' preferences example,
a new customer can be classified as being
either a science fiction, non-fiction or
children's books customer
depending on which cluster the new
customer is most similar to.
Once cluster labels have been determined,
samples in each cluster can be used as
labeled data for a classification task.
The samples would be the input
to the classification model.
And the cluster label would be
the target class for each sample.
This process can be used to provide much
needed labeled data for classification.
Yet another use of cluster results
is as a basis for anomaly detection.
If a sample is very far away, or
very different from any of the cluster
centers, like the yellow sample here,
then that sample is a cluster outlier and
can be flagged as an anomaly.
However, these anomalies
require further analysis.
Depending on the application, these
anomalies can be considered noise, and
should be removed from the data set.
An example of this would be a sample
with a value of 150 for age.
For other cases, these anomalous cases
should be studied more carefully.
Examples of this are in a credit
card fraud detection, or,
a network intrusion detection application.
In these applications, examples outside
of the norm are the interesting cases
that should be looked at to determine
if they represent potential problems.
To summarize, cluster analysis is used to
organize similar data items into groups or
clusters.
Analyzing the resulting clusters
often leads to useful insights
about the characteristics of each group,
as well as the underlying
structure of the entire data set.
Clusters require analysis and
interpretation to make
sense of the results,
since there are no labels associated with
samples or clusters in a clustering task.
In the next lecture, we will discuss
a specific algorithm for cluster analysis.
k-means clustering is a simple yet
effective algorithm for
cluster analysis that is
commonly used in practice.
After this video,
you will be able to describe
the steps in the k-means algorithm,
explain what the k stands for in k-means
and define what a cluster centroid is.
Recall a cluster analysis divides samples
in a data set into groups or clusters.
The idea is to group similar items in
the same cluster, where similar is defined
by some metric that measures
similarity between data samples.
So the goal of cluster analysis
is to divide data sample
such that sample within a cluster
are as close together as possible.
And samples from different clusters
are as far apart as possible.
k-means is a classic algorithm used for
cluster analysis.
The algorithm is very simple.
The first step is to select
k initial centroids.
A centroid is simply the center of
a cluster, as you see in the diagram here.
Next, assign each sample in
a dataset to the closest centroid.
This means you calculate
the distance between the sample and
each cluster center and assign a sample
to the cluster with the closest centroid.
Then you calculate the mean,
or average, of each cluster
to determine a new centroid.
These two steps are then repeated until
some stopping criterion are reached.
Here's an illustration
of how k-Means works.
(a) shows the original data
set with some samples.
And (b) illustrates centroids
initially selected.
(c) shows the first iteration.
Here, samples are assigned
to the closest centroid.
In (d), the centroids are recalculated.
(e) shows the second iteration.
Samples are assigned to
the closer centroid.
Note that some samples changed
their cluster assignments.
And in (f),
the centroids are recalculated again.
Cluster assignments and
centroid calculations are repeated until
some stopping criteria is reached.
And you get your final clusters,
as shown in (f).
How are the initial centroids selected?
The issue is that the final
cluster results are sensitive
to initial centroids.
This means that cluster results with
one set of initial centroids can be
very different from results with
another set of initial centroids.
There are many approaches to
selecting the initial centroids for
k-means varying in levels
of sophistication.
The easiest and most widely used approach
is to apply k-means several times
with different initial centroids
randomly chosen to cluster you dataset.
And then select the centroids that
give the best clustering results.
To evaluate the cluster results,
an error measure,
known as the within cluster sum
of squared error, can be used.
The error associated with a sample
within a cluster is the distance between
the sample and the cluster centroid.
The squared error of the sample then,
is the squared of that distance.
We sum up all the squared errors for
all samples for
a cluster to the get the squared error for
that cluster.
We then do the same thing for all
clusters to get the final calculation for
the within-cluster sum
of squared error for
all clusters in the results
of a cluster analysis run.
Given two clustering results, the one with
the smaller within-cluster sum of squared
error, or WSSE for short,
provides the better solution numerically.
However, as we've discussed before,
there is no ground truth
to mathematically determine which set of
clusters is more correct than the other.
In addition, note that increasing
the number of clusters,
that is, increasing the value for
k, always reduces WSSE.
So WSSE should be used with caution.
It only makes sense to use WSSE
to compare two sets of clusters
with the same value for k and
generate it from the same dataset.
Also the set of clusters with
the smallest WSSE may not
always be the best solution for
the application at hand.
Again, interpretation and
domain knowledge about what the cluster
should represent and how they will be used
are crucial in determining
which cluster results are best.
Now that there are several metrics that are
used to evaluate cluster results as well.
Choosing the optimal value for k is
always a big question in using k-means.
There are several methods to
determine the value for k.
We will discuss a few here.
Visualization techniques can be used
to determine the dataset to see if
there are natural
groupings of the samples.
Scatter plots and
the use of dimensionality reduction
are useful here, to visualize the data.
A good value for
k is application-dependent.
So domain knowledge of the application can
drive the selection for the value of k.
For example,
if you want to cluster the types of
products customers are purchasing,
a natural choice for k might be the number
of product categories that you offer.
Or k might be selected to represent the
geographical locations of respondents to
a survey.
In which case, a good value for
k would be the number of regions
your interested in analyzing.
There are also data-driven method for
determining the value of k.
These methods calculate symmetric for
different values of k to determine
the best selections of k.
One such method is the elbow method.
The elbow method for determining
the value of k is shown on this plot.
As we saw in the previous slide,
WSSE, or within-cluster sum of
squared error, measures how much
data samples deviate from their respective
centroids in a set of clustering results.
If we plot WSSE for different values for
k, we can see how this
error measure changes as a value
of k changes as seen in the plot.
The bend in this error curve indicates
a drop in gain by adding more clusters.
So this elbow in the curve provides
a suggestion for a good value of k.
Note that the elbow can not always be
unambiguously determined, especially for
complex data.
And in many cases, the error curve
will not have a clear suggestion for
one value, but for multiple values.
This can be used as a guideline for
the range of values to try for k.
We've discussed choosing
the initial centroids and
looked at ways to select a value for
k, the number of clusters.
Let's now look at when to stop.
How do you know when to stop
iterating when using k-means?
One obviously stopping criterion is when
there are no changes to the centroids.
This means that no samples would
change cluster assignments.
And recalculating the centroids
will not result in any changes.
So additional iterations will
not bring about any more changes
to the cluster results.
The stopping criterion can be relaxed to
the second stopping criterion listed here.
Which is when the number of
sample changing clusters is below
a certain threshold, say 1% for example.
At this point, the clusters
are changing by only a few samples,
resulting in only minimal changes
to the final cluster results.
So the algorithm can be stopped here.
At the end of k-means we have a set
of clusters, each with a centroid.
Each centroid is the mean of
the samples assigned to that cluster.
You can think of the centroid as
a representative sample for that cluster.
So to interpret the cluster
analysis results,
we can examine the cluster centroids.
Comparing the values of the variables
between the centroids will reveal
how different or alike clusters are and
provide insights into what
each cluster represents.
For example, if the value for age is
different for different customer clusters,
this indicates that the clusters
are encoding different
customer segments by age,
among other variables.
In summary, k-means is a classic algorithm
for performing cluster analysis.
It is an algorithm that is simple
to understand and implement, and
is also efficient.
The value of k, the number of clusters,
must be specified.
And final clusters are sensitive
to initial centroids.
Linear regression is a very common
algorithm to build regression models.
After this video you will be able to
describe how linear regression works,
discuss how least squares is used in
linear regression, define simple and
multiple linear regression.
A linear regression model captures the
relationship between a numerical output
and the input variables.
The relationship is modeled as
a linear relationship hence the linear
in linear regression.
To see how linear regression works, let's
take a look at an example from the Iris
flower dataset, which is a commonly
used dataset for machine learning.
This dataset has samples of
different species of iris flowers
along with measurements such as
petal width and petal length.
Here we have a plot with petal width
measurements in centimeters on the x axis,
and petal length
measurements on the y axis.
Let's say that we want to predict
petal length based on petal width.
Then the regression task is this,
given a measurement for
petal width predict the petal length.
We can build a linear regression model to
capture this linear relationship between
the input petal width and
the output petal length.
The linear relationship for this samples
is shown as the red line on the plot.
From this example we see that linear
regression works by finding the best
fitting straight line,
through the samples.
This is called the regression line.
In the simple case with
just one input variable,
the regression line is simply a line.
The equation for a line is y = mx + b,
where m determines
the slope of the line and
b is the y intercept or
where the line crosses the y axis.
M and b are the parameters of the model.
Training a linear regression model
means adjusting these parameters to
fit the regression line to the samples.
The regression line can be
determined using what's referred to
as the least squares method.
This plot illustrates how
the least squares method works.
The yellow dots are the data samples.
The red line is the regression line,
the straight line that
goes through the samples.
This line represents the model's
prediction of the output given the input.
Each green line indicates the distance
of each sample from the regression line.
So the green line represents
the error between the prediction,
which is the value of the red regression
line and the actual value of the sample.
The square of this distance is
referred to as the residual
associated with that sample.
The least squares method
finds the regression line
that makes the sum of
the residuals as small as possible.
In other words, we want to find
the line that minimizes the sum
of the squared errors of prediction.
The goal of linear regression then is
to find the best fitting straight line
through the samples using
the least squares method.
Once the regression model is built,
we can use it to make predictions.
For example,
given a measurement of 1.5 centimeters for
petal width, the model will predict
a value of 4.5 centimeters for
petal length base on the regression
line that it has constructed.
In linear regression, if there is only
one input variable then the task is
referred to as simple linear regression.
In cases with more than
one input variables,
then it is referred to as
multiple linear regression.
To summarize, linear regression
captures the linear relationship
between a numerical output and
the input variables.
The least squares method can be used
to build a linear regression model
by finding the best fitting
line through the samples.
We studied the machine learning process,
applied techniques to explore and
prepare data, discussed the different
categories of machine learning tasks,
looked at metrics and
methods for evaluating a model,
learned how to use scalable machine
learning algorithms for big data problems,
and worked with two widely used tools to
construct the machine learning models.
I hope that the lectures, along with
the hands-on activities, have given you
a sound and practical introduction to
machine learning tools and techniques.
I also hope that the course piqued
your interest in the exiting and
rapidly developing field of
machine learning for big data.
Keep in mind that the best
way to learn machine learning
is to do machine learning.
So I encourage you to go out and find
a problem or data set that interest you.
Apply the techniques you've learned in
this course to it and start analyzing.
Thank you for your time and effort on
this course, happy machine learning.
If you recall, we have previously
discussed that the main categories of
machine learning tasks are classification,
regression,
cluster analysis, and
association analysis.
We have discussed
classification in detail.
Now let's look at the other categories,
starting with regression.
After this video you will be able
to define what regression is,
explain the difference between
regression and classification, and
name some applications of regression.
Before we talk about regression,
let's review classification.
In a classification problem the input
data is presented to the machine learning
model, and the task is to predict the
target corresponding to the input data.
The target is a categorical variable.
So the classification task is to
predict the category or label of
the target, given the input data.
The classification example shown
here is one we have seen before.
The input variables are measurements
such as temperature, relative humidity,
atmospheric pressure,
wind speed, wind direction, etc.
The task for
the model is to predict the weather
category associated with the input data.
The possible values for
the weather category is sunny,
windy, rainy, or cloudy.
Since we're predicting the category,
this is a classification task.
With that context in mind,
let's now discuss regression.
When the model has to predict
a numeric value instead of a category,
then the task becomes
a regression problem.
An example of regression is to
predict the price of a stock.
The stock price is a numeric value,
not a category.
So this is a regression task
instead of a classification task.
Note that if you were to predict not
the actual price of the stock, but whether
the stock price will go up or go down,
then that would be a classification task.
That is the main difference between
classification and regression.
In classification,
you're predicting a category, and
in regression you're
predicting a numeric value.
Here are some examples where
regression can be used.
Forecast the high temperature for the next
day, estimate the average housing price
for a particular region, determine the
demand for a new product, a new book for
example, based on similar existing
products, predict the power usage for
a particular power grid.
This is what the data
set might look like for
the regression task of predicting
tomorrow's high temperature.
The input variables could
be the high temperature for
today, the low temperature for
today, and the month.
And the target is the high temperature for
tomorrow.
The model has to predict this
target value for each sample.
Recall that in a supervised
task the target is provided.
Well, for an unsupervised task the target
is not available or not known.
Since the target label is provided for
each sample here,
the regression task is a supervised one,
similar to classification.
As with classification building a
regression model also involve two phases.
A training phase in which
the model is built, and
a testing phase in which
the model is applied to new data.
The model is built using training data and
evaluated on test data.
Similar to classification, the goal in
building a regression model is also to
have a model perform well on training
data, as well as generalize to new data.
The use of three different datasets
that we have previously discussed
also apply to regression.
Recall that the three
datasets are used as follows.
The training dataset is used to train the
model, that is to adjust the parameters of
the model to learn the input
to output mapping.
The validation dataset is used to
determine when training should stop
in order to avoid over fitting.
And the test dataset is used to evaluate
the performance of the model on new data.
In summary, in regression the model
needs to predict the numeric value
corresponding to the input data.
Since a target is provided for each
sample, regression is a supervised task.
The target is always a numerical
variable in regression.
In the next lecture,
we will discuss a specific algorithm
to build a regression model.
Hello.
Welcome to the Graph Analytics module
in the Big Data specialization.
I'm Amarnath Gupta, a research scientist
at the San Diego Supercomputer Center.
What do I do research on?
Well, a number of different areas,
all generally related to data engineering.
But the area I'm recently very
excited about has to do with graphs.
Now, graphs or
networks has many people call them,
are about studying relationships and
relationship patterns on objects.
I became interested in graphs
when I was a graduate student and
the professor in our artificial
intelligence class showed us how a part of
human knowledge can be represented as
a kind of graphs called semantic networks.
She showed us how even
very simple things like
relationships somewhere in a family can
be represented and viewed as graphs.
Represent your knowledge huh?
Now, that got me really excited.
Someday, I thought this will be a really
interesting topic to research on.
What I didn't realize then is that
in just a few years graphs and
the need to model and analyze them would
become so dominant in both academia and
industry that graphs will
be found everywhere today.
Now we look at Facebook,
LinkedIn, Twitter, and many,
many more companies that
are thriving in the market with data
that are represented, modeled,
and processed as graphs.
Now, even the entire World Wide Web,
if you think about it,
is a giant graph that people analyze.
And that brings us to this course.
Now, in this course, I'll introduce you
to the wonderful world of Graph Analytics
specifically, I'd like
to show how different
kinds of real world data science problems
can be viewed and modeled as graphs.
And how the process of solving
them can apply analytical
techniques that used graph based methods,
that is Algorithms.
This course would have four models.
In model one, we'll introduce graphs and
different applications that use graphs.
In model two,
we'll cover a number of common techniques,
mathematical and algorithm techniques,
that are used in Graph Analytics.
In module three,
we'll look at a graph database.
And through some sort
of a hands on guidance,
we'll show you how to store and
query graph data with the database.
In module four, we'll cover some
strategies of handling very large
graphs and discuss how existing
tools that are currently used by
the community are actually prints.
Thank you for joining this course and
I sincerely hope that you'll find
it both exciting and useful.
Happy learning.
As we saw in these four examples
what graphs are used for
are kind of different but they all show
different viewpoints from which you
can use graphs for your analysis.
Since this course focuses
on graph analytics,
I'd like to briefly recap
what the term means.
Analytics is the ability to
discover meaningful patterns and
interesting insights into data using
mathematical properties of data.
It covers the process of computing
with mathematical properties, and
accessing the data itself efficiently.
Further, it involves
the ability to represent and
work with domain knowledge as we
saw in use case two with biology.
Finally, analytics often involves
statistical modeling techniques for
drawing inferences and
making predictions on data.
With analytics, we should be able
to achieve the goals shown here.
Take a minute to read.
Therefore, graph analytics is
a special case of analytics where
the underlying data can be
modeled as a set of graphs.
So in this video,
we'll going to talk about graph analytics
within the context of this
big data specialization.
So in the previous courses you know about
the three important V's of big data.
So the three well-known V's are volume,
velocity, and variety.
We will also talk about a lesser-known V,
which is called valence.
Okay, what we want to talk about is,
what impact these things
have on graph data.
So for volume, let's take a dataset like
the load network of the United States.
Well, that's a pretty large graph.
So when we say volume,
I mean that the size of the graph
is much larger than what you might have
in the memory of a reasonable computer or
real computing infrastructure.
Now, we will see what impact the size
of the graph has on analytic operations.
What we mean by velocity
when it comes to graphs?
Well, think of Facebook again.
So these little graphs are updates.
So you write a post, then like somebody
else's post, and make a comment.
That's a bunch of updates.
That comes and adds to your graph.
Well, then ten minutes later,
you do something similar, and
that also comes and adds to the graph.
Then your friend does the same thing,
it adds to your graph.
So as time goes by,
you are sending more edges to your graph.
And the speed at which
you are doing this for
at least like Facebook can be really,
really high.
So the rate of update in
Facebook is really high.
This is what is called
streaming edges into graphs.
And there can be multiple streams for
various reasons.
What do we mean by variety?
For graphs, it means that the graph is
collecting data from various places.
And all these different places are giving
different kinds of information to
the graph.
So in the end,
the graph has more non-uniform and
complex information potentially
coming from multiple sources.
That's what we mean by variety
when we refer to graphs.
That picture there, by the way, is
different kinds of protein interactions.
The next one,
the less-known one is valence.
Now, if you remember your chemistry,
this comes from valence electrons,
which are electrons in an atom
which are used for bonding.
The other electrons
are called core electrons.
So the idea is if we increase
the valence of the graphs,
you increase the connectiveness
of the graph.
How, we will see.
Now, graph size clearly impacts analytics.
Why, a, it takes more space, but more
importantly, it increases the algorithmic
complexity of any operation that
you want it to on the graph.
Now, we'll see an example of that,
but what happens as
a result is that the data-to-analysis
time becomes high.
So I put in some data, and
I wanted to do this analysis.
But there is so much data, that my
analysis takes way longer than it should.
Let's give a simple example,
an example we have seen before.
Remember, we had this little graph
from our biological example where we
were asking, find a simple path between
Alzheimer's Disease and Colorectal Cancer.
And in this case, the result is obvious.
Now, let's pause and ask.
There are two nodes that I mentioned,
in this case,
my Colorectal Cancer and
Alzheimer's Disease nodes.
And we are asking,
is there a simple path connecting them?
This is called a decision problem.
I give you a data, and I'm asking does
such a simple path exist or not exist?
But this is actually a very
hard decision problem.
And the computer scientists will tell you
that this is a very complicated problem
because it has a very high complexity.
Let's ask another question.
Well, how many simple paths,
now I want to count.
How many simple paths exist
between these two nodes?
Indeed, it is another
hard computing problem.
And if you really want to know,
the size of the result,
in the worst case is exponential
in the number of nodes.
So if we increase the number of nodes and
edges, if we increase the size of
the graph such a seemingly simple question
can take a very, very, very long time.
So that it's almost practically
impossible to compute it for
a really large graph if we have
no other information supporting.
That's the worst case.
But when we say algorithmic complexity
increases, that's what we mean.
Let's talk about velocity, and
I said our favorite example is Facebook.
So we are adding a bunch of updates, which
means we are adding a bunch of edges.
We are streaming the edges into the data,
and we want to compute a metric.
We want to see what is
the shortest distance
between person a and
person b or item a and item b.
Or I want to know that
Facebook has communities.
Twitter has communities like we saw.
And how many people out there,
in these communities, and
how many such communities are there,
like a Facebook group?
Now, if you want to compute this metric,
and you get this
edges very fast, it is very difficult
to know when you have the answer.
Because you are going to get an increasing
number of edges in the system,
and you keep computing this metric that
you want to find the answer for, and
it will turn out that your continuous
stream does not fit in memory.
Because your memory is limited
compared to the amount of
edges, or edge updates you
are streaming into the system.
So that's what's happened when you
have high velocity information.
Very soon, your memory runs out,
and you want to compute
your answer right now from
the data that you have.
Okay, let's look at variety,
also known as heterogeneity.
There are two aspects of heterogeneity.
One, we have already mentioned, graph data
is often created through integration,
like we saw in the case of the biology.
And therefore, the variety comes because
the nature of data is very different.
Also, they may not be all
the same kind of data.
For example, the data may come
from a relational database,
it may come from an XML database.
It may come from another graph.
It may come from a document.
It may even come from complex
things like social networks,
like citation networks between papers or
patents, between interaction networks,
between web entities,
which are connected through links.
And from human knowledge that has been
represented as graphs through ontologists.
So all of these graphs, the nodes and
the edges do not mean the same thing.
And somehow in there,
you need to capture what it means to have
an edge because that will determine
what you can do with the edge.
A simple example, in an ontology,
is something that says a is a b,
and b is a c, so a is a c.
The a is a c is an inference that you do,
given the other two relationships.
What would be an example?
My pet is a dog, and the dog is a mammal,
therefore, my pet is a mammal.
You want to do inferences for
some edges likes is a.
Now, you need to know this.
You do not do this with the biology
example where you are looking at genes and
proteins because that operation does
not make sense when you have genes and
proteins.
So therefore, every graph may
have a different semantics.
And what happens with variety is
the number of sub-semantics and
the number of valid
operations that you can do.
That changes, and
that becomes more complex.
Now, valence I said,
is about connectedness.
It is also about
interdependency among data.
So if I have a higher valence which means,
I have more data elements that
are more strongly related, and
these relationships can be exploited.
In most cases,
the part where valence becomes important,
is that it increases over time, which
means, parts of the graph becomes denser,
and the average distance
between node pairs decreases.
Let me show you, here is my Gmail.
And I have plotted my Gmail graphs
from 2006 to about two months back.
When I first started using it,
I had these users,
a very few users, and
they are not really related.
Now with time, more and
more people started communicating
with me through Gmail.
And more and more of these people were
also talking amongst themselves and
copying me and responding to me.
By the end, you would see that
you can find dense groups
within my Gmail because
the information and
the connectedness between people have
evolved and become more dense over time.
This is the phenomenon of valence, and
this is very important to study because
you want to study things like, what parts
of the graph have become more dense?
And why have they become more dense?
Maybe something was going on.
Maybe there was an event that
brought these people together,
and you want to analyze that and
find that out from your graph analytics.
That's why you want to understand
the effect of valence.
You also want to understand what do I do
if the graph becomes very, very dense
in a place, so that finding a path through
that dense space becomes very hard.
You will see in a later video that when
this happens, the computer system,
that is trying to process these graphs in
a parallel and distributed way has to do
something special to handle these
increasing density in parts of the graph.
So before we go into graph analytics,
the first question we want to ask is,
what is a graph?
Let's see.
This is a plot of the sales of
some items against time and
it gives you a nice visual representation
of the data, but is it a graph?
While you think about it,
let's try another one.
This is another common visual
representation of data.
If you go to Google and type pie graph,
you will see many results
that look like this.
But is this a graph?
In our research, this is not a graph.
We call it a chart.
Yes, you guessed it right this time.
This too is a chart, and not a graph.
So why do people call them graphs, then?
In a sense, they're abbreviating.
A chart depicts what's called
a graph of a function.
Let me explain.
Look at the two column table on the right.
The first column has information
about product category
with values like furniture,
office supplies, and technology.
The second column represents another set
of values called total containing 1724,
4610, and 2065.
Now we can define our mapping option.
Which means a correspondence
from Product Category to Total.
So we map Furniture to the value 1,724,
Office Supplies to the value 4,610,
and so forth.
If we visually portray this,
we can represent it like a bar chart or
a pie chart.
This is why both the previous diagram and
this diagram are charts and not graphs.
Graph analytics has its basis in a brand
of mathematics called graph theory.
What's more interesting,
however, is that graph theory was
born out of a very practical problem.
The problem started in a very old city
in Prussia which is now in Russia
called Konigsberg.
Even if we look at in in Google Maps
it would sort of look like this.
One of the interesting features of
Konigsberg is that it has two islands and
these islands are connected
by seven bridges.
Back in 1736, the city wanted to create
a walkway, and the criteria was,
this walkway would traverse all
seven bridges such that somebody
wanting to go from one part of the city
to another can cross a bridge only once.
Now this is sort of an urban
planning problem right?
Well in fact, it required
a mathematician to solve the problem.
The mathematician named Euler shown
on the left looked at this and
figured out that you really
cannot create such a walk.
Why?
He said, it cannot be done, because
there are an odd number of bridges, and
proved it mathematically.
From this problem, the whole field
called graph theory emerged.
On the right, you can see Edsger Dijkstra,
a well-known computer scientist who has
developed graph algorithms, one of which
we will study later in the course.
His work has had far further impact on
both the theoretical computer science and
practical applications.
What's the difference between
the mathematics view and
the computer science view?
Let's try to define
the mathematical view of graphs.
We start with a set of vertices.
Here we have a set of six nodes or
vertices.
Now, I'll add another set.
I'll call this the set of edges.
In our diagram there are only four edges,
but
there's something special
about these edges.
Each edge is just not
an ordinary atomic object.
An edge like e1, actually, is one term
from v and then a second term from v.
So this edge, e1, goes from v1 to v5.
Pictorially, we can draw and
arrow from v1 to v5.
Now if I had said v5 to v1,
the arrow would be reversed.
So what do we have so far?
We have a set of vertices and
a set of edges.
That is the mathematical
definition of a graph.
What about the computer
scientist's definition?
Of course a computer scientist needs to
adhere to the mathematical definition, but
they want to represent and
manipulate the same information.
So they need a data structure.
In other words,
something they can operate on.
So what kind of operations would they do?
Well, with a graph,
they can say add edge, or add a new
vertex, find the nearest neighbors of
the vertex where the term neighbor refers
to the nodes connected to the vertex.
We said a computer scientist needs to
represent graphs using data structures.
Here is one that you should recognize.
It's a matrix,
called the adjacency matrix of a graph.
Both the rows and
columns of this matrix represent notes.
If I go from v1 one along the row,
I see that there's one at v3,
which means there is
an edge from v1 to v3.
Similarly there is another from v1 to v5.
Let's look at some operation.
Let's say I first want to
add an edge from v3 to v2.
What should I do?
I'll start from the row v3,
go up to the column v2,
and add a 1 in that set.
So I've added an edge,
which is an operation on the matrix.
Another operation.
I want to get the neighbors a v3.
This will be a little more complicated.
I look at the row v3 and
paint that row and
I'll also look at the column v3 and
paint that column.
If we go down the row of v3,
we'll get v2, so v2 is neighbor.
And if we go down the column of v3,
we'll get v1 and v6.
So v1 and v6 have alternators.
What's the difference?
Since the matrix has the From along
the rows and the Tos along the columns,
following the row v3 gives us
the edges outgoing from v3.
And following the column v3 gives
us the edges coming into v3.
Is this the only
representation of the graph?
No it's not.
Here is another one,
in this representation there
are two kinds of data objects.
No data, which are the blue rectangles and
edge data which are the triangles.
To get a sense of this representation,
look at the note v1 and
follow the top yellow line.
It'll reach v3.
So this link structure directly captures
the graph diagram we created before.
Now, start from v1 again and
follow the blue link and
it will reach e1 and then v3.
So that tells you that e1 is
an edge object between v1 and v3.
Next, let's stand on the edge triangle e1,
and follow the red
dashed line to get to e2, which is
the next edge from the same starting node.
Is this possibly too complex?
Yes it is.
However, as we'll see down the road, many
graph database systems are using this kind
of data structure internally, so that the
database operations become more efficient.
In the first example
of graph analytics for
big data, we'll consider
the social media called Twitter.
And graphs representing tweets.
What types of objects and
relationships does a tweet have?
Well, in fact, tweets consist
of many of the same elements and
relationships as the Facebook posts.
Tweets have users, they contain text,
tweets can point to one another or
to URL's, they have hashtags, they can
include reference to various other types
of media, but what about relationships?
Well much like Facebook, relationships and
tweets are more reflective of
what the users do with tweets.
For example, people create tweets,
they respond to tweets,
they mention other users, and so forth.
Let's look at these
relationships in detail.
In this graph, all of the light
blue notes are tweets, and
all of the purple notes are users.
When a specific user
creates a specific tweet,
an entity is created in
the graph as a result.
We'll come back to this graph
in the next few slides.
So what we want to do with it?
Well to be very specific,
this graph was created from tweets
of a bunch of online gamers.
In this case, we were monitoring
the tweets of all people
who played particular online video game.
Typically, gamers are very
excited about their video games.
They're exited about their characters
of the video games and they want to
discuss the video games they're excited
about, when new versions are released.
So what are the data
science questions here?
People who look at these things, such as
behavioral psychologists, want to know.
If you are a war game user or
if you play any other violent game, where
there is a lot of fighting online, do
these people also show violent behavior?
Maybe they do, maybe they don't.
They also want to know whether as a result
of looking at somebody's tweets and
following them over time they can tell if
the person is addicted to the game or not.
So why use graphs for that?
One of the things you could
do is what we showed here,
from the graphs you can extract
certain elements like conversations.
If you look at it, you will see all of
them have somebody posting something.
Somebody responding to the post, and the
first person responding to the response.
They are retweeting, and
they are responding, and so forth.
You would see a conversation chain
going on which can be short or long,
like you see, and
other people would join in.
We don't know if it's violent or not, but
at least there is a lively
conversation going on about something.
Using graphs, we could find some
meaningful parts of a graph
that we can further analyze using
techniques like text analytics.
Another kind of thing people
would like to identify,
is which players are interacting
with which other players?
Who are these people?
Do they form a close community?
Can anybody join in?
Are there groups, what are the groups?
If you find a group,
who are the most influential users?
Who are the people that everybody
refers to, listens to and so on?
Graph analytics is used to answer all
these questions about a conversation
that's going on live in
social media stream.
Let's look at our next example.
Our second use case is about biology.
Interactions arise naturally in biology.
Genes produce proteins, proteins regulate
the functions of other proteins,
cells transmit signals to other cells.
These functional genes lead to
pathological conditions that
present themselves as
observable phenotypes.
Some of these interactions that are
observed and measured by experiment lists.
Another class of graph relations
represent human knowledge.
For example, an edge may denote
an anatomical association, such as
the nucleuses inside a cell, part of
the cerebral cortex is part of the brain.
Similarly, one can encode different
classifications of entities like
both humans and dogs and mammals.
Researchers also find these
relationships from literature
or by computational techniques
like bioinformatics algorithms.
There are many bioinformatics algorithms
that find statistical correlations between
genes and proteins.
Many biological networks are created by
creating edges between entities because
they are strongly correlated based on
measurements like gene expression level.
Yet, a third category of
computed relationships
associates terms by mining
scientific literature.
If two entities are co-mentioned
in scientific articles very often,
then there is a likelihood that
these two entities are related.
In this case, the edge between them does
not depict a specific relationship, but
the fact they are associated.
All these interactions can be assembled
into networks of graphs where the nodes
are biological entities and
edges represent different categories of
molecular interactions,
associations between diseases and.
Now there are two issues I
would like you to understand.
First, graphs like the one
we saw are assembled.
That is, integrated from many data sources
produced by many independent science
groups who have different research goals,
use different scientific techniques,
but the underlying biological entities
are common across many groups.
It is the commonality that helps us
stitch together these logic graphs.
Second, as more results get linked and
integrated, the size of the networks grow,
leading to big data problems and
the need for big data technology.
Now let's ask the same question.
Why graphs?
In bio medicine people are always
trying to discover new science, for
instance, they want to discover
unknown relationships.
For example, they can take two diseases,
very different diseases, colorectal
cancer and Alzheimers disease, and
they might want to ask are they related?
If so, can you connect the dots and
find out what the intervening
network between them is?
It turns out, as you can see,
there are several genes that directly or
indirectly connect these two diseases.
Thus, we can use path finding techniques
like this to discover previously
unknown connections in a network.
In addition,
researchers sometimes think to explore the
networks to help their discovery process.
I have collaborated with a group that
is using graph exploration techniques
to figure out how phenotypes of
undiagnosed diseases all fit together.
Our third use case is about
the human information network.
That means a personal information network.
The graphic you see there
is my LinkedIn network.
Everybody who is on my LinkedIn is a node.
And if they know each other,
there's an edge between them.
You can possibly see some groups or
clusters there.
One analytical question
we'll explore in module two
is how to discover these
groups automatically.
Now of course with LinkedIn we only
have professional information.
But it is prudent to ask whether
one can integrate the professional network
with other forms of personal information.
This would be other social media data like
my friendship network from Facebook or
Google, or it could be information
like my Outlook email network.
One can add even more information and
put that interpersonal relationships.
For example, Professor Norman who is
on my contact list is my director.
And if we add my calendar to this,
one can find events that I'll be attending
and people that I will be meeting.
Taking it even further, for
special applications you might
actually include financial and
business transactions, or
performance in activities,
or fitness information, or
the location from my GPS.
Now, if you add all of these questions, we
should ask what we do with these things?
Let's see.
One use of this kind of
information is matching.
For example, matching people with jobs
is not just a matter of screening
series based on job descriptions or
evaluating their job experience.
To recruit for high level positions,
like the board of directors of a company,
you need to evaluate the network of the
candidate to determine their relationships
with important organizations,
groups, and individuals.
For some tasks like choosing a surgeon,
you might also want inspect
their social media ratings.
In other classic applications,
we might want to look for
people who can influence a human network.
Suppose, we are in an election
campaign team, and
need our message to get to as many
people as possible in a city.
We can not go door to door ourselves,
we need to go to some people, and
these people will reach
others on our behalf.
Graph analytic techniques may help
identify the fewest number of people
who will have maximal reach into most
of the potential voters in the city.
A third category of application
is threat detection.
This network is created
by groups who study news.
For example,
they collect information about all
the militant groups in different countries
and all the reported acts of terrorism.
This creates a network as you can see.
We show only a part of the network.
In this graph view,
the green notes are groups and
the pink notes are deemed individuals.
It should be clear that some
of these individuals and
groups are more closely
associated than others.
Discovering and tracking these groups,
their current activities,
together with an analysis of details of
the events they're associated with might
help analysts to get deeper
insight into the networks and
perhaps anticipate their
future activities.
Our fourth and
last use case has to do with smart cities.
Now, a city is a geographically
bounded space, and
contains many different networks
operating within the same spatial domain.
What kind of networks?
Let's see.
It has transportation networks.
Water and sewage networks,
power transmission networks,
your IP broadband networks.
Some of these networks have
multiple subtypes, for
example transportation networks include
the bus networks, the subway network,
the surface street network, and
the railway network, and so on.
These networks form a physical
infrastructure and therefore
can be represented as graphs where
each node has a geographic coordinate.
But some of these networks can also be
thought of as a commodity flow network.
People flow through
transportation networks.
Sewage material flows through
a sewage network and so on.
For many of these networks,
a city planner would like to make
sure that they cover the entire city,
that commute time is optimized,
traffic congestions are well planned.
To accomplish this, they would need to
create what's called a network model.
For example, urban planners develop
city traffic model servicing.
A traffic model will use both
the geographic layout and
connectivity of the network along
with the flow parameters like
the number of commuters getting
on board at any station.
Well, if we're planning
to create a smart hub,
we need to make sure that all the right
things happen at the same place.
People who come out of a metro
station find nearby businesses.
They find nearby facilities.
Those facilities should
have broadband network for
people who are going to go
on their mobile phones.
The same places need to have
a water supply network, and
you have to plan it in such
a way that all these networks
who exist within a certain
distance of each other.
And all the facilities can
be planned accordingly.
Beyond normal operations,
we also need to model what would
happen if the network gets disrupted.
What are the kinds of congestion or
traffic that might disturb the network?
Therefore these graphs are no longer just
structures, but they represent things like
congestions, things like people's behavior
and materials behavior over the network.
One should also compute
energy use patterns for
the busy parts of the network in order to
figure out how the network structure or
the network flow can be altered to
enable energy optimal operations.
As we saw in these four examples,
what graphs are used for
are kind of different but
they all show different view points from
which you can use graphs for analysis.
So this course focuses on Graph Analytics.
I would like to briefly
recap what the term means.
Analytics is the ability to
discover meaningful patterns and
interesting insights into data using
mathematical properties of data.
It covers a process of computing
with mathematical properties and
accessing the data itself efficiently.
Further, it involves
the ability to represent and
work with domain knowledge as we
saw in use case two with biology.
Finally, analytics often involves
statistical modeling techniques for
drawing inferences and
making predictions on data.
With analytics, we should be able
to achieve the goals shown here.
Therefore, Graph Analytics
is a special piece of
analytics where the underlying data
can be modeled as a set of graphs.
In the previous video,
we learned what a graph is.
We gained insight into both
the mathematician's view and
the computer scientist's view.
Now we want to look at the big
picture of graph analytics.
Why are we doing what we are doing, and
why do I need a graph
representation on graph analytics?
Let's start with a graph network which you
may already be familiar with, Facebook.
Here is my Facebook page.
Let's look at it and
consider some of the elements it contains.
There is a primary user, and that's me.
There are my friends.
And typically there are some posts,
some of which may have media in them,
such as video.
What else does it have?
Well, let's consider what's inside a post.
The post contains text.
It has tags.
I tag some people,
some people comment on my post.
If somebody's commenting,
then that means there must be a commenter
who is also a user in the Facebook.
Other people like my post or
they like a comment and
they also respond to some of the comments.
Many posts have locations
associated with them as well.
When we consider all of these together,
do you see the graph?
Well if not, we'll show you.
Here, we see very much the same types of
information but now they're in a graph.
First, notice me on the far left.
If you look carefully at this graph you'll
also notice there are relations labeled
Friend-of and Created_post and parts
of the post and everything that you saw
before that are now organized in terms of
objects and relationship speaking objects.
The objects here on the post, comments on
the post, replies to the comments and so
forth, and the relationships also
include tagged in or refers to.
So this is sort of the big picture, right?
Next we will look at 4 specific
Use Cases in four different disciplines.
The first one will be on Social Media.
The second one will be on biology,
where we'll look at genes and diseases.
The third one will be Human Information
Network, which means personal information.
And the fourth one will
be on smart cities.
Let's go through these
examples one by one.
We will go over the logic of Dijkstra's
algorithm without writing code.
If you are an advanced student and
know the algorithm,
you can skip to the next lecture.
The basic plan is to start from node I and
progressively traverse
a sequence of notes.
When the method attempts to choose
the next node to traverse to,
it chooses a node for which the total rate
of the path to that node is the lowest.
In the beginning,
the algorithm is on the start node I.
The distance from I to I is 0.
And the distance to all
other nodes is infinity,
because the system doesn't know them yet.
A second table, called a priority queue,
is currently exactly the same as
the distance row of the first array.
The system starts with processing node I,
the source node.
That means it finds the nodes
that can reach from I, F and J.
Note that the respective total weights,
that is 5 for F,
and 15 for J,
to get to these nodes in the distance row.
Then it marks I as done.
We have made the node I agree,
because the node is processed.
Next it looks at row d to find
the least distance, which is 5.
The corresponding vertex is F.
So next, the method traverses to F.
Now the algorithm on node F and
has determined that out of its possible
destinations, E, G, and J,
J is the least expensive.
The total path, that is the weight
of the path to J, is 10.
5 from I to F, plus 5 from F to J.
This diagram shows that the priority
is now shorter because it has
popped out the already processed load, I.
At step three, we are processing node
J but face the following situation.
We can go back to F from J, but
that will cost 10 plus 15, that is 25.
25 is worse than the cost of the current
path to F, which is 5 directly from I.
Thus we do not go from F to J, and
do not update the distance shown.
The other option is to go from J to G,
which incurs a cost of 10 plus 5, 15.
Hm, this does not improve the current
cost to reach G through F,
which is now at 15 already.
Therefore, we do not
update the distance for G.
So at this point,
we see that while J is processed,
it had no impact on
the traversal process.
We consider the distance row again, and
find that the next node to expand is G,
which is reached through F.
Continuing as before, G's processed.
It opens up the possibility of
diverging to C, at a cost of 35.
Or to D, at the cost of 25.
But wait, we have an issue,
there are two competing nodes,
E coming form F or D coming from G,
that are both expansion candidates.
At this point,
the algorithm can make a random choice
because there is no other information.
Let's say we make an arbitrary choice,
we expand to E next.
In an optional video, we will see
how we can use the additional information
to make a more informed decision.
After expanding to E,
we can find that we have already
reached the node B, so we are done.
The other choice, that is to go to D from
G, costs less than the path through B, but
it doesn't matter now,
because the destination is reached.
Just for the sake of completeness, if we
did let the algorithm continue to operate,
it will terminate when all
reachable nodes are reached.
We say all reachable nodes,
become some nodes like H,
are not reachable because
it has no incoming edge.
Such a node, as we said before,
is called the root node of the graph.
In general,
a graph can have more than one root node.
Now that we have reached our destination,
we need to construct the shortest path.
We start by taking the destination B and
find its predecessor, E.
Then we find the node E, and
check its predecessor, which is F.
Finally, we find the predecessor
of F to obtain I,
which is a source node for the task.
So these nodes can then be
stretched together in reverse,
thus building I to F, to E, to B,
which is highlighted in the film.
So, how well does this algorithm work for
big graphs?
Actually, not very well.
We often measure
the performance of an algorithm
in terms of the size of the data.
So, we saw that the Dijkstra Algorithm
has a very high worst case complexity.
Despite the high complexity of
the algorithm, there are several
practical improvements that will
enhance the performance of the method.
One of them is
Bi-directional Dijkstra Algorithm.
The idea is very simple,
we will go forward from the source now and
backward from the target node and stop
when the two expanding frontiers meet.
We will briefly illustrate
the process without going deep into
the details of every step.
So the technique starts just
like the regular method.
The control moves from
I to F at a cost of 5.
But then, it switches and
starts from the target, and
moves backward along the edges.
So from A, it comes to D or C.
We'll chose D,
because an AD is a least weight part.
Now the forward step is performed again,
and we traverse from F to G.
We are skipping the expansion
to J because as we saw before,
it does not contribute to the path.
So the total rate of the IFG path is 15.
The backward process
then reaches G through D.
The cost of the IFG is 15.
And the cost of ADG is also 15.
We stop because a common node is reached.
We need to ensure that the weight
of the forward path and
that of the reverse path are added, and
the total combined rate is minimal.
At this point,
we can concatenate the partial paths
to construct the full shortest path,
which is IFGDA.
Now one point to remember is that
the length of the smallest weight path
can be longer than the shortest hop path.
Here the FCA path has 2 hops but
a weight of 20.
But the weight of the 3 hop path,
FGDA, is 15.
So just remember that.
The final type of analytics
we'll discuss in this module
is called Centrality Analysis.
We call something central if it's
in the middle of a larger entity.
We also call something central
if it's important and vital.
For graphs, we'll identify important
notes by looking at how central they are.
In the graph.
Look at the the six node graph,
you don't have to know a lot
to figure out that the orange
node is pretty important, Why?
Well, one reason could be it's
the most vulnerable node.
If you remove it the graph
will fall apart.
because this is clearly one way to
look at the centrality of the node.
But it's not the only way.
Another way of looking at the orange node,
is that it can reach all other
nodes quicker, than any other node.
So this is the idea behind influences.
People in a social network who
are connected enough to reach out and
possibly influence a lot more
people than others will be able to.
If the little graph represents
a transportation network.
And you were asked to build a restaurant
somewhere around this network.
You'll possibly choose an area
near the central node.
Because more traffic will flow
through this node than other nodes.
And some of them will get
out at the station and
bring business to your restaurant.
We can give many more examples.
In biological networks,
house-keeping genes are genes needed for
the maintenance of basic
cellular function, and
are expressed in all cells of
an organism under normal and
abnormal conditions, these genes
are central because they're vital and
they're connected to many other
nodes in the biological network.
So much so that they need to
be taken out of the network so
that the rest of
the network can be studied.
Out of all these examples,
we'll focus on a kind of problem
researchers have called
the key player problem.
The problem comes in two flavors.
Now take a little time to
read the two examples.
The first is sort of a negative piece.
We have a network and we are trying
to find a small subset of people
who's removal will maximally
disrupt the network.
The key operative word here is maximally.
So if there is a node which removal
breaks the network into two parts,
it is not what we want if
there's another two nodes
whose removal will break
the network into ten parts.
The second case, however,
is a lot more conventional.
The goal is to find a small set of nodes
with maximal combined reachability
to other nodes.
That means, taken together, these nodes
should reach almost all other nodes.
You should know that
people use two terms to
characterize a general concept
of network centrality.
The first one, centrality,
is about a node.
It measures how central the node
is with respect to the network.
So the orange node in the left
graph has high centrality, and
the blue nodes have low centrality.
The second term, centralization,
is about the network.
Now look at the graph on the right,
where the dark orange node is still very
central for the light orange node, and
between the other nodes, and
therefore has reasonable centrality.
As more nodes start
having higher centrality,
the centralization of the network drops
because there is less variation in
the centrality values of the network.
So for each type of centrality that we
discuss next we can compute the network
centralization by considering the sum
of the difference between the maximum
centrality and the centrality of the node
divided by the maximum centrality.
There are thirty different
measures of centrality.
We will consider only a few of them and
explore the conceptual
principles supported here.
The first and the most intuitive
measure is degree centrality.
Quick measures, the degree of a node
divided by the possible edges it
could have if it connected to each of
the other N- 1 nodes in the graph.
Now, we have seen this before.
This measure gives us a sense
of the hubness of the node.
The higher the number is,
the more hub-like the node is.
Thinking of our second key player problem.
One way to approach this is to
find a hub-like measure for
a group with multiple nodes.
Instead of measuring the degree
centrality of individual nodes,
the measure simply counts the number of
edges coming into the group as a whole
compared to the number of outsiders.
In our example two red nodes here
together connect to all blue nodes.
Although there is just one
node neighboring both of them.
Closeness centrality takes a different
approach to the centrality problem.
It acts the shortest distance
of a node to all other nodes and
divides it by a minus one.
So in our graph, a node like I,
which is on the periphery of the graph,
will be quite far from
all nodes in general, and
therefore will have a very high
closeness centrality value.
On the other hand, nodes like F, C and
H are much closer to all other nodes.
Know that we define this measure
in terms of shortest paths.
So if a moving object, like information,
flows to the shortest path
in the network, F is more likely to
receive them earlier than other nodes.
And therefore can process into
other nodes more quickly.
Therefore.
If we look to inject a new piece of
information into the network with the idea
that it should read every other node
quickly, I should possibly inject it at F.
Recall however, that node information
flow is two shortest routes.
An example is gossip, that tends to
travel through centrality nodes.
Closeness centrality does not work well
for these types of information nodes.
Another very popular centrality measure
is called betweenness centrality.
For any node it measures the fraction of
shortest paths flowing through that node.
Compared to the number of
shortest paths in the graph.
Since B is at one end,
its between a centrality is 0.
But let's look at A.
A is in the path from B to E.
So is D.
Therefore, A's score for
the B to E path is 0.5.
Similarly, its score for the C to E path
is also 0.5, making the total score 1.
E is in the path from A to D,
for there is one more
path from A to do through C,
so E's score is 0.5.
Now can you verify why C's score is 3.5?
Betweenness centrality
is typically used for
problem where a commodity is
flowing through the network.
As in the case of closeness centrality.
Any quantity that does not flow in
shortest path channels like infection or
rumor on the internet doesn't work
well with betweeness centrality.
This lesson on graph analytics,
is about identifying and
tracking groups of interacting
entities in a network.
We call these groups communities.
Let's try to provide a more concrete
definition of communities in a network.
We multiply the definition
by this diagram,
showing a research study
on the Santa Fe Institute.
A theoretical research institute
located in Santa Fe, New Mexico, US.
They performed multidisciplinary
studies on fundamental principles
of complex adaptive systems.
The nodes in the graph are researchers.
And an edge exists
between two researchers,
if they collaborate with each other.
As you can see, there are distinct
groups among researchers.
A mathematically college researcher,
does not collaborate with researchers
who work on structure of the RNA.
So the graph,
is essentially a set of separate groups,
thinly connected through a handful
of cross-disciplinary researchers,
who collaborate across groups.
These groups are then the communities
in this collaboration graph.
What does this tell us?
It tells us that communities are highly
interacting clusters in a graph.
That is, they form pockets of
denser subgraphs that are more
connected to each other,
than to members of the other clusters.
Communities of humans, or otherwise,
are interesting things to study,
because it gives us an insight
into the interaction patterns.
And how they change with time.
Here, are some analytics
questions about communities.
We have divided them
into three categories.
Analytics questions that do not
depend on time, are called static.
Here, we ask questions about
the composition of the community,
how tight-knit members are connected,
and so forth.
In the second category, we involve the
formation, and evolution of the community.
Communities can form temporal,
for example,
around an event like a school shooting.
Or some communities,
despite the comings and
goings of members,
sustain themselves well.
A Facebook group, a political party,
fans of a music band,
are likely to continue over time,
and hence are non-transient.
One can also be interested in
the history of formation of a community,
like a criminal network.
The third category is about predictions.
Analysts would like to predict
how a community would grow.
Whether it's composition
of members might change.
Or whether there are emerging
power shifts within the community.
Now before we ask these questions,
however,
we need to first identify
communities in a large network.
To find communities, we need to
formalize the idea that there are more
connections within the community, and
fewer connections between two communities.
One way to achieve this, is to think
of dividing the degree of a node,
into an internal and
an external component.
The internal component is the count
of edges within community.
And the external degree, is the count
of edges outside the community.
An example,
will be to consider that my community
is where I live, that is San Diego.
And then count the number of my friends
within San Diego versus outside San Diego.
In the figure, the highlighted node
has four internal connections and
one external connection.
The next step, would be to think
of the internal degree, and
the external degree of an entire cluster.
We can sum up the internal degrees
of all nodes in a cluster.
And call it the internal
degree of the whole cluster.
And similarly,
sum the external degrees of the nodes,
to compute the external
degree of the cluster.
Now, we can define intra-cluster
density to be the ratio of the number
of internal edges of the cluster,
divided by the number of possible
connections inside the box.
The denominator is N cues 2.
Which is the number of pairwise
combination of nodes within the cluster.
We call this delta int.
Similarly, inter-cluster density,
delta x is the number
of inter-cluster edges divided by
the possible pairings between nC,
a node in the cluster, to n- nC,
the number of nodes outside the cluster.
There are two kinds of methods used for
finding communities in the network.
One of them focuses on local properties,
that is,
properties for which one only
looks at a node and its neighbor.
For the most ideal community
in a network is a subgraph,
where every node is connected to
every other node in the subgraph.
Such a structure is called a clique.
To find a perfect community
structure as a clique,
one can try to find the largest
clique within a graph, return cell.
That is a computationally
challenging problem.
It's much simpler to find cliques
if we know the value of k.
That means the number of
members in the clique.
We're going to show a simple
version of this in model three.
The more general problem has been
solved by complex algorithms,
that are beyond the scope of this course.
In the real world, perfect cliques larger
than three or four are harder to find.
So we need to relax the definition of it.
Now, there are two types of relaxations,
those based on distance,
and those based on density.
Two distance based definitions
are n-clique and n-plan.
We'll illustrate this over
a friendship graph shown here.
n-clique, is a subgraph,
such that the distance between each
node pair in that subgraph is n or less.
By this definition, Holly, Paul,
and Gary form a two clique.
That's a little awkward, isn't it?
Yeah.
They are within two
distance of each other.
But the two clique does not
include intermediate nodes that
connect the member nodes.
So, Mike, is not in the two clique.
This situation is corrected in n-clan.
Where, to belong to the n-clan,
the shortest part between any members,
without involving outsiders, is n or less.
Now, Holly, Mike,
Bill, Don, Harry, and
Gary form a two-clan.
Clearly, this group is more cohesive
than the two-clique we saw before.
n-clique and n-clan
are distance based measures for
finding cohesive groups of communities.
K-core is a density based method for
finding communities.
Let's look at the dark, orange subgraph.
Every node is connected to at least
three other nodes within the subgraph.
They form a 3-core.
Let's include the medium light
orange nodes in the subgraph now.
Each node is connected to at least two
other members within the subgraph,
they form a 2-core.
Relaxing further, we can add the light
orange nodes and the graph as a 1-core.
We have already defined
the degree of the node
as the number of edges connected to it.
Thus specifying if a node is
more connected than another.
Looking closer we can separate out
that two components denotes
degrees into in degree and out.
Which are the counts of the incident and
the outgoing edges of a node respectively.
In the example graph G has an indegree and
outdegree of three making
the total degree equal to six.
We first construct this degree table for
each node.
It's a simple procedure where we count
the number of nodes with degree.
0, 1, 2, and so forth.
The degree versus count table is
a degree histogram of the graph.
We can compare two graphs by computing
the vector distance between them.
One simplistic measure is
just the Euclidean distance.
For our case, the degree
histogram based on comparisons of
the histograms find the graphs
to be very similar.
The more sophisticated
methods are available but
are outside the scope of this course.
We can also compute histograms
of just the in degree or
just the out degree of the graph.
But perhaps more interesting is the joint
two dimensional histogram of the graph,
the colorful histogram of the graph
can be interpreted here as follows.
The graph has a maximum in degree of
three and a maximum out degree of three.
This creates a two-dimensional
histogram with four times four
equal to 16 different joined values.
The actual value for any combination
is computed from the graph and
color coded in the ratings.
For example, there is no node with
in degree 0 and out degree 0.
So the lower-left square of the graph
has value zero and color-coded blue.
On the other hand, there are two nodes
with in-degree three and out-degree three.
Thus, the top-right corner has the value
twp, which is 20% of the nodes.
Color coded as light green.
The 2D histogram provides
an interesting insight.
The nodes with more incident
edges than outgoing edges
represent entities that take
in more than they put out.
In a social networking setting,
they represent members who are listeners.
They receive a lot of posts,
but send much fewer posts.
On the opposite side of the spectrum,
there are talkers whose out-degrees
exceed their in-degrees.
The entities that are in between,
we have both large values of in-degree and
out-degree.
These are communicators.
In this graph, there seems to
be more talkers than listeners.
Not surprising though.
My social media friends
show similar statistics.
In this video we will explore
another fundamental property
of graphs called Connectivity.
We list two important kinds
of graph analytic questions
that are based on connectivity.
In the first case we are asking
about the robustness of the network.
Suppose we have a computer
network with many servers and
a hacker is trying to
bring the system down,
you set a small set of servers that the
hacker can target to disrupt the network.
What we mean by disrupt is to disconnect
a part of the network from the rest.
A similar problem may occur in
the power distribution network.
In that case, an attacker may be able to
attack one or two central components so
that large portions of
the network loses power.
I have a geneticist colleague at
Tech Graduate Institute who studied
the robustness of biological networks.
He told me that many biological
networks have built in redundancy, so
that even if you disrupt one important
gene, there are other genes in the network
which will support the biological
function, possibly through other routes.
Therefore a network is robust,
if removing one or
more edges or
nodes still keeps it connected.
The second category is about network
comparison in terms of their
overall connectivity.
The two graphs shown here are very
different in their structure.
What are some parameters by
which we can compare them?
That to talk about connectivity, we must
first define the concept of connectivity.
Very simple.
A graph is connected if we can
reach any node from any other node.
Let's look at the crypto graph in
the picture, clearly we cannot
reach from all nodes to all nodes here
because this graph is not connected.
However, we can identify four parts of
the graph that are themselves connected.
These islands of connected
parts are called components or
connected components of a graph.
For directed graphs, we need to be
a little more specific about connectivity.
We say that the directed graph is strongly
connected, if we follow the direction of
the edges and still reach every
node from every other node.
A weaker form of connectivity is if we do
not care about the direction of the arrows
and can reach every node
from every other node.
Another way of saying it is that
the undirected version of the graph
is connected,
this is called Weak Connected.
Look at the graph that we have seen so
many times in this course.
Is it strongly connected or
weakly connected?
This leads to some big graph challenge.
Given an arbitrarily large graph,
can I find the connected components
of the graph efficiently?
Second given an arbitrarily large graph,
can we find its sub graphs
that are strongly connected?
We'll touch upon these
questions in Module Four.
So there are two ways to break a graph.
Identifying the smallest node set which
if removed will disconnect the graph.
Here, if we remove F, D and
H or H, F, G,
we have disconnected the graph.
So the separating set is either H,
F and G, or H, F and D.
So the connectivity is three.
Similarly, removing C-F, D-G, D-F and
H-E edges will also disconnect the graph.
Therefore, the edge connectivity is four.
So this is how network
robustness is defined.
Now, let's ask, is this network robust?
Suppose the attacker removed node F.
Why remove F?
Because F is the most connected node.
That is, F has the highest degree.
If we remove F, five paths are disrupted.
For example,
there is no way to go from C to G, or
from I to E,
because these paths went through F.
Let's try this exercise.
Suppose the attacker
has already removed F.
And would like to cause more
damage to the rest of the network.
Which node should be targeted next?
The answer is C,
because C is the next most connected node.
Higher degree nodes make
the network more vulnerable.
So far, the centrality of a node
is defined using the degree and
the shortest distance to other nodes.
Now, we introduce a different idea.
We would like to say that
if you are important and
I'm connected to you,
then I must be somewhat important too.
In other words, my centrality
is proportional to the combined
centrality values of my neighbors.
Now, if we write that down mathematically
it would look like the top formula.
The centrality of (Vi) is
the sum of its neighbors.
Now, we can write that as an equation
where Lambda is
a proportionality constant.
The resulting equation looks exactly
like the Eigenvector equation we have
seen before.
Now again, you really do not
have to understand how it works.
It's fine to know that if
we solve that equation,
we will get the Eigen values lambda.
Now, let's take the largest lambda and
find the corresponding Eigenvector, which
will give you the centrality of each note.
Notice the difference between
the degree centrality and
the Eigenvector centrality
in the same graph.
The yellow node in the middle
has a low degree centrality
compared to its neighbors.
However, with the Eigenvector centrality,
the node becomes comparably more important
because the neighbor centrality status
boost some of the centrality of this node.
In contrast,
consider the second highlighted note.
It had the same on normalize degree
centrality as the previous node.
But because the neighbors
are low centrality nodes,
the eigenvector centrality goes down.
So, this is the intended consequence
of the eigenvector centrality measure.
Speaking of consequences,
Eigenvector centrality essentially says
if you know the right people,
your importance will go up.
Well, that's kind of risky proposition.
Here is me in a social network,
and let's say I'm connected to
this somewhat dubious character, and
I think it doesn't really matter.
What I don't know is that my connection
has it's own set of connections, and
look at who they are.
So, on the one hand, these shady
characters that are now connected to
indirectly does raise my
eigenvector centrality, but
it also has quite a damaging
effect on my reputation.
My EV centrality almost makes
me look like a suspect.
Now, think about that.
Now Brin and Page, the founders of Google
had an interesting way to think
about the eigenvector centrality.
They thought about a server.
Well no, not that kind of server.
This kind of server.
The kind that surfs the web.
But, this is a special web
surfer called a random surfer.
And here is what he does, he picks
a web page and looks at the links.
Then he chooses a random link, goes to
that page and does the same thing again.
Except sometimes when you kind of get
bored and goes to totally new page.
How often does he do this random jump?
Let's say, there's always sort
of a 15% chance that he will.
Or more generally,
with the probability of 1 minus alpha.
So, Page and Brin's idea was to figure out
that this surfer will visit a page with
a high chance, if the page is central.
They came up with a measure for
this stationary probability of a page
being visited by the random surfer.
They did not call it centrality,
they called it pagerank.
Let's see a YouTube video to
understand how pagerank behaves.
Okay, now we are talking about
the World Wide Web which is a huge graph.
How do we of such a graph?
The answer is iteratively using
a method called power iteration.
This method can be used because we
are looking for the largest eigenvalue.
Let me show you.
Let's take a small graph.
Let's initialize the still unknown
page rank as zero for all nodes.
Now, page rank A is a 0.15 chance,
that I was at A already.
And 0.85 chance that I come to A from B,
or I come to A from C.
However, at this point,
the page rank of B and C are at zero.
So, in the first iteration,
page rank of A is 0.15.
Now for B, I can only come to B from A,
but we cannot claim all of pagerank of A,
because there is always a half chance
that the surfer will come to B
from A because he could
also get to here from C.
This, plus the 0.15 chance that
the surfer is already at B,
makes Bs pagerank 0.21.
Now after doing a few rounds of this
computation, between 50 and 100 iteration,
let's say.
The values will converge.
Now, this computation has been
demonstrated to perform well
in the MapReduce framework.
In module four, we'll talk about
another way of computing this metric.
Welcome back to the second
module of the course.
In this module, we will cover
a number of basic principles and
techniques of graph analytics.
As we mentioned in the last module,
the goal of graph analytics
is to utilize the mathematical
properties of data and provide
efficient algorithmic solutions for large
and complex graph structure problems.
As I said, in this module, we'll learn a
number of basic graph analytic techniques.
After this module,
you'll be able to identify the right
class of techniques to apply for
a graph analytics problem.
To be more specific,
in this module we will consider
the mathematical and
algorithmic aspects, and not so
much the computing frameworks
to implement these methods.
In Modules 3 and 4, we will look at
two different kinds of computing
platforms that are used for implementing
the techniques discussed in this module.
Here is the lesson plan for the module.
First, we'll discuss a few basic terms and
their definition which we'll use for
the rest of the course.
Of course, they are not the only terms and
concepts we will learn.
As we go through each technique,
we will add more terms and
definitions in our vocabulary.
Now following these definitions we
will consider four categories of
graph analytic procedures.
The first, called Path Analytics,
is centered around the Analytic Techniques
where the primary objective involves
traversing to the nodes and
edges of the ground.
The second analytic technique inquires and
explores the connectivity
pattern of the gaps.
Where the term connectivity pattern
refers to the structure and
organizations of the edges of the graph.
The third analytics category
involves the discovery and
behavior of communities which are closely
interacting entities in a network.
The fourth category, termed Centrality
Analytics, detects and characterizes
significant nodes of a network with
respect to a specific analysis problem.
Of course there are many more types of
graph analytic techniques that we'll cover
in the course.
We'll provide some additional reading
material for those who are interested.
But we start by recapitulating
our definition of graphs
as a collection of vertices and edges,
which represent ordered pairs of nodes.
While this mathematical
definition is indeed correct,
in practice it needs to be extended to
give you other information elements.
Let us consider a single Tweet.
As we have mentioned previously,
a Tweet is a complex information output
because it is a graph in itself
with several nodes and edges.
But over and about the structure, a Tweet
actually contains much more information
and code inside the nodes and edges.
First, there several kinds
of nodes in a Tweet.
For example it has a Tweet node,
a User node, a Media node,
a URL node, a hashtag node and so forth.
This assignment of kinds or labels to
nodes is often called node typing.
Every graph application will
have its own set of types.
And it'll assign one or more types to
a node but it is not mandatory for
an application to use node types.
Mathematically we can extend our original
definition with two more elements.
The set of node types and the mapping
function that assigns types to nodes.
That means it associates
a type to every node.
However, not all nodes need to have
a type but in many applications they do.
In addition to types,
a node also has attributes and values.
In our Tweet example,
text is the name of an attribute that
refers to the textual body of the Tweet
whose value is a character string
written by the author of the Tweet.
For a specific kind of data like a Tweet,
one has a fixed set of attributes
as decided by Twitter.
This collection of attributes
is called a node schema.
For a general graph,
a node schema may have an arbitrary
number of attribute value pairs.
We will revisit this in module 3
when we discuss graphing the models.
Similarly, at edge of a graph, we have
an edge type, also called an edge label.
Also just like a node,
an edge may have an edge schema
consisting of attribute value pierce.
Here, Interaction Type is
an attribute in our biological
network that describes the modality of
interaction between a pair of genes.
For the specific edge we have highlighted,
the genes interact through
biochemical activity.
Because they are party to
some biochemical process.
Clearly, there are different kinds
of interaction between these
genes or proteins.
That means an attribute called
interaction type can have a set of
possible values like physical,
genetic and so on.
This set of possible values is
called the domain of the attribute.
Putting these elements back
into our mathematical model,
we get a more concrete specification of
what a real live graph would contain.
We have already discussed edge types
as well as node and edge properties.
Take a minute to look through this again.
Whenever you consider an application that
needs graph analytics, the first task
should be to determine the informational
model of the graph your application needs.
It's always a good exercise to
document the information model,
in terms of the elements
described on the slide.
Let's see a little more on
the topic of edge properties.
Many application encode different
kids of numeric knowledge
into edges of a graph in
the form of edge points.
If we do not put weights
in an adjacency metrics,
an edge is just represented by
placing a one in the appropriate cell.
However, if we do use a weight,
the weight value can be placed in
the adjacency matrix to facilitate
down stream computation as
we'll show in the next lesson.
What do the weights mean?
That depends on the application.
Let's see some examples.
The most obvious example is a road map
where the nodes are road intersections and
the edges represent
stretches of the street or
highway between these intersections.
The edge weight can represent the distance
of a particular segment of the road.
In a personal communication network,
for example an email network,
we can count the average number of emails
per week sent from John to Jill and
use it as a proxy for
the strength of their connection.
So more emails means
a stronger connection.
In a biological network, one often has
to assess whether an interaction that
can occur is actually likely to occur
given the concentration of the reactants,
the chemical environment at the site
of the reaction and so forth.
This is represented as a weight that
designates the likelihood of interaction.
Finally, consider a knowledge network
where nodes represent entities
like people, places and events.
And edges represent relationships
like a person visited a place or
movie actor Tom is dating
movie actress Kim.
Now this kind of information may
be important for some news media.
However, if the information does
not come from an authentic source,
itself, it is more prudent to
put a certainty value on it.
This certainty value may be
treated as a weight on the edge.
Moving on from the information
model of the graph,
the structure of the graph often
contains valuable insights to a graph.
Many of the graph analytic techniques
we will discuss in this section
will consider these structural
properties of graphs.
One such structure is a loop,
which is an edge from a node to itself.
In the example here,
you can see that a protein can interact
with another protein of the same kind.
Many other examples abound.
People send emails to themselves.
A road segment circles back
to the same intersection.
A website has a link to its own URL.
The existence of loops and the nodes that
have such loops can be very informative
in some applications and
can be problematic for other applications.
Another structure property of a graph
is the occurrence of multiple
edges between the same node pair.
The graphs with this feature
are called multi-graphs.
In this example, the two map kinase
genes have five edges between them.
Why multiple edges?
It's because each edge has
a different information content.
In this case,
these two genes can have five different
types of interactions between them.
Where each interaction has a different
value for the attribute interaction type.
We see this all the time
in human networks too.
A person can be my spouse,
a co-performer in music and
my financial adviser,
all at the same time.
Many analytics algorithms
are not natively designed for
multigraphs, and often need a little
customization to handle them.
We will mention some of these
customizations as we go forward and walk
through the different kinds of analytics
applications preformed on graphs.
So we talked about local properties.
In this lecture,
we'll cover a global property based
method of [INAUDIBLE] finding.
The specific property we focus on,
is called modularity.
It tries to estimate
the quality of clusters of
communities in the [INAUDIBLE].
The intuition is as follows.
If we consider the edges in a group and
try to see whether it's different
from what you'd see if the edges
were assigned randomly with
some probability distribution.
If there is a community, there will be
more edges than would happen at random.
If there is no community in some part
of the graph, the number of edges in
that part will either be close to
the random case or even lower than that.
The modularity measure thus estimates
the quality of the clusters in
the graph by evaluating this difference of
the actual minus the random edge fraction.
So this is the mathematical
formulation of what I just described.
The adjacency matrix, A,
gives us the actual edges.
The Pij provides a probability
of a random edge.
The m in the denominator gives
us the fractional edges.
And the delta function's
task is to evaluate if i and
j should be in the same cluster.
If they are,
the contribution will be added to Q,
the quality metric,
which is multi-layered.
Well, we have not defined what
the probability model looks like.
There are many ways to figure
out what Pij should look like.
One simple model says, that the chance
that there is an edge between nodes i and
j, is proportional to the degree of
node i times the degree of node j.
That means if nodes i and
j are already well connected, there is
a high chance that they share an edge.
So if you're a mathematical person,
you might be thinking, okay,
let's find clusters in the graph so
that Q is maximum and then we're done.
Well sadly, maximizing Q is very hard.
So we need to find
an approximate solution.
So we will illustrate a very
popular method of finding this
modularity based community detection.
Well, the best way to describe
this is through a YouTube video.
That's the URL.
Now, the next slide and
the following slide,
describes it, but
I think it's better to explain the method
through screenshots off
the video as it happens.
We will show you some
snapshots of this video.
There are 309 nodes in this graph.
Initially, they all have different colors.
That is,
they belong to different communities.
This screenshot shows the graph at
iteration 144 of the algorithm.
The number of communities now is 286.
The chart on the right side plots time on
the x-axis and modularity on the y-axis.
As you see,
the modularity's on the rights.
Roughly, at each iteration,
the system is trying to change the color
of a node to that of its neighbors.
But it actually changes the color
only if the modularity value of
the whole graph changes as
a result of that color change.
After a few more iterations,
the number of communities has become 241.
The three arrows show some parts of the
graph where the nodes have changed colors.
Modularity is on the rise.
After 1,437 iterations, the modularity
of the graph is still going up.
Now, there are 113 communities.
The errors show some new areas where
the neighboring nodes have the same color.
At 1,842 iterations,
the modulary gains slows down.
Meanwhile, the number of
communities have reduced to 75.
At 4,179 iterations, the modularity
growth has started becoming flat.
But in the meantime, the number of colors,
that is communities, has reduced to 48.
At around 5,196 iterations, the algorithm
decides that there is not enough
reduction in the number of communities,
which is reduced to only 45 in
the last 1,000 iterations or so.
Now it collapses each community that
is clustered to a single node, and
creates a cluster to cluster edges.
The orange box,
an arrow shows this contraction.
Now compared to the previous slide,
this collapsing or
contraction of the plastic creates
a skeleton of the original draft.
Now the algorithm starts again
with this reduced graph.
You will find many graph
analysis software,
where you can run the Louvain
method of community detection.
[INAUDIBLE].
I took my Linked-in network,
which has me at the center, and
all my connections as nodes.
If two of my contacts are also
connected in Linked-in,
there is an edge between them.
This kind of mean-centric network
is often called an ego network.
When I [INAUDIBLE] the community direction
algorithm here, I found six communities,
with one set of parameters and
seven communities with another.
I could clearly see my
connections in San Diego.
My connections in my professional network,
my friends in India, and so forth.
There's always one false community,
which stands for
others, nodes that do not clearly
belong to any specific group.
Perhaps more interesting and
important than the static
analysis of communities is to track
communities over a length of time.
And determine how they evolve and why.
There are six large
categories of evolution steps
that can happen within a community.
A community like a new
Facebook group can be born.
A community, like a group of
people who gathered for an event,
would dissolve because the event and
the mutual interest around it has ended.
A community can grow because the members
rally around a common cause.
Typically, new cross-community
edges start getting
formed before the communities
actually merge.
The communities can
shrink like my book club.
Where do you see this in real life?
Well, how about company mergers?
Surely enough, the [INAUDIBLE] results
will happen when a community splits.
Going along with the previous example,
a closely working group in a company may
at some point create their own product and
form a new company with very
little ties to the old company.
One standard symptom of a group splitting
is that the nodes in the subgroup
show an increase in the number of
edges just amongst themselves.
So far we have seen two versions
of the Dijkstra Algorithm.
Both these versions assume that the edge
weights provided by the network
must be used as is.
Now that can lead to some
interesting problems.
We saw one such problem before.
Remember we were trying to decide
whether we should go from G to D or
from F to E because both options
had the same total weight?
Now had we chosen to go from G to D,
it would take us a few extra steps
to arrive at correct solution.
One way of handling this problem
is to use additional knowledge.
So intuitively, we want to say that
we know that we want to go to B.
So traversing through
D is not a good idea.
Because it will take us away from B.
In other words we use the knowledge
of the destination of B's location
to steer the direction of search.
This variant is called
Goal-Directed Dijkstra Algorithm because
it is using the information about the
target known at any point in the search.
The trick to use this information is to
change the edge weights as we diverse.
How do we change the weight?
We use a formula, where the new weight
is the original weight together with
a function called the potential function.
Now we'll show this in our example.
Since our graph is a proxy for
a road network, we can assume that we
know the coordinates of every node.
Therefore, we can compute
the distance between any two nodes.
In practice, we will choose a few nodes so
that we can compute the distance of every
other node from these chosen nodes.
These chosen nodes are called landmarks.
Let's assume B, which is our target,
is a landmark node, and
let's rewind to the state where
we are trying to choose between
the GD expansion or the FE expansion.
So we calculate the distance of F,
G and E from B.
BF is 20, BG is 80, and BE is 15.
Now we'll apply the formula like this.
For the FG case,
we subtract the BF distance
from the weight and
add the BD distance to the weight.
This gives us 70 because G is far from B.
Similarly for the FE case,
we subtract the BF distance and
add the BE distance to the weight and
it gives us 15.
Now, with these modified weights
we choose the FE expansion.
In practice this significantly improves
the actual performance of the algorithm.
So, this technique is used by many online
mapping services when they give you
directions.
So now let's bring back the constraints
that we have ignored so far.
There are two constraints here,
parts of the graph to include and
parts of the graph to exclude.
In this example we have to go to B, but
we should go to J first, and
then travel from B to J.
Also, we cannot use any
of the paths through E.
This really means two things.
First, we split the problem into two
independent shortest path problems
that we can solve in parallel if needed.
Second, when we go from J
to B We need to extract
the useful subgraph that
we need to consider.
For a large network and
a complex exclusion condition,
we will essentially operate
over a smaller graph,
thereby reducing the effective
size of the problem.
As we'll see in module three,
this kind of subgraph extraction operation
can be done effectively and
efficiently with a graph database system.
This concludes our short
tour of path analytics.
So, in this optional module, we'll look
at the two key player problems again.
The goal of the first problem is
to identify a small set of nodes,
whose removal will create
maximum disruption.
Now, in this case, a traditional
centrality algorithm may not work,
because the optimization goal
is to break up the network.
So we need a quantitive
measure of the breakage.
If dij is the distance between nodes i and
j, then 1 over dij is
the closeness of these two nodes.
If we add the closeness of all nodes and
normalize it by the number of node pairs,
we'll get a measure of
cohesiveness as a fraction.
So, 1 minus this value is
a measure of fragmentation.
Our goal is to maximize
this fragmentation metric.
In the model terrorist network shown here,
removing the red nodes A,
B, and C will break up the network
into seven components,
with F reaching a value of 0.59.
The second key player problem, is trying
to find a group of S influencers,
which can reach a maximum
number of nodes within K steps.
The number of unique nodes reachable from
a starting node is called the reach,
of the starting node.
For this we need to adapt the concept
of reach to limit it to k steps.
We also need to adapt it to measure
the distance of an arbitrary node
from a group of nodes
between our influences.
The distance from one node to a group
of nodes can be defined as a maximum,
or average, or minimum distance,
of the node from the members of the group.
Often, the minimum
distance is a good choice.
So the distance, we could reach,
can then be through of, as the proportion
of all nodes reached by the group,
where the nodes are weighted
by the distance from the set.
And only nodes at distance
1 are given full rate.
Hence, a distance we could reach
that use a maximum value of 1,
where every outside node is adjacent to at
least one member of the set of influences.
In the network shown,
just three nodes, A, C, and D,
are sufficient to reach every other
member within just four steps.
Now this concludes this module, where we
looked at several analytic techniques and
measures to extract different
kinds of insights from a network.
We saw how a community
in a graph can evolve.
To track the nature of evolution,
we need to measure how
the community changes over time.
So here are three cases.
One, two and three of a community
changing between two observation points.
The goal is to figure out whether these
are normal fluctuations in the network or
are more drastic changes occurring.
Look at them for a second.
Just visually, the first case
seems to show just minor changes.
Whereas case two shows a merger,
and case three shows a split.
Now, to come up with a quantitative
measure of change over time, we need to
take two observations from two consecutive
time points and fuse the graph.
If you do it for case one,
you'll find one new node,
one living node, and
the rest will come on over time.
For case two, you will see
that two previous communities,
colored differently, are internally
connected the same way as before.
But some members of the two communities
have created new crosslinks.
Now can you tell me what
you observe in case three?
Well I see one join node, color purple.
Apart from it, there are just two
edges connecting the two groups.
Now with these observations,
we can now compute the autocorrelation
between the graphs across time t and
t plus 1.
This is just a measure of
the number of common nodes
divided by the number of
nodes in the combined graph.
If the community does not change at all,
this number is 1.
If a community has only a few connection,
the number is lower.
After computing autocorrelation
over every pair of time steps,
we can then compute stationarity,
which measures the overall change in
the autocorrelation over a period of time.
So if we measure over 100 time steps,
we will add the 99 correlation values
from the steps and then divide it by 99.
This will tell us what fraction
of members remain unchanged
on an average over these 100 time steps.
Therefore, the 1 minus zeta tells
us the average ratio of members
that are changed in a time step.
Let's take three cases.
In the first plot,
the size of the graph is small and
nothing much is happening here.
A note occasionally joins or leaves,
keeping the stationarity pretty flat.
In the second case, the graph is small,
but there are a lot of changes, especially
at time step seven a whole bunch of purple
nodes have joined and then they went away.
The size of the graph
clearly reflects this
with a purple spike that you see
on the size versus the time graph.
This spike on the time series
by the way is called a burst.
The third plot shows a large graph
with many nodes joining and leaving.
The stationarity of this graph will be
quite low given the abrupt changes we
observe over time.
In this video,
we'll discuss what paths are and
how to find your way as it travels
along the nodes and edges of the graph.
Let's start with an example.
For this example,
we'll consider an edge weighted
graph with no loops as shown here.
Term edge weighted means
the edges have weights.
The weight of the edge I to J is 15.
We can think of this graph as a small road
network, where the nodes are cities, and
the edge weights are highway
distances between them.
To walk, or traverse, through this
graph we'll define what a walk is.
A walk is an arbitrary
sequence of nodes and
edges that starts from some node and
ends on some node.
Here we can go from H to F
to G to C to
F to E to B.
Notice that in this walk,
we went through the node F twice.
In many applications, we do not want
to consider arbitrary walks but
consider a walk where
we do not repeat nodes
unless we need to come back
to the starting point.
Such a constrained walk is called a path.
The green arrows indicate
a path from J to B.
We said on the last slide that a path
can start from a node and end on it.
Such a path is called a cycle when
the path has a three or more nodes.
The J, G, C,
F, J, is a four node cycle,
sometimes called a four cycle.
C, F, E is a three cycle.
However, although there is an edge from
F to J and another from J back to F,
this two node path is not
a cycle by our definition.
A network with no cycles
is called acyclic.
A graph that is both directed and
acyclic is called a directed
acyclic graph, in short, a deck.
A trail is a concept similar to a path,
it is a walk with no repeating edges.
In the graph shown in the walk,
H, F, G, C, F, E,
C, F, J, is not a trail.
Because C, F Is traversed twice.
Remember the seven bridges of
the Konigsberg problem that we described
in module one?
In that problem,
we had the constraint that one
cannot cross the same bridge twice.
Often we see such constraints
in path planning problems.
A common notion in directive
graphs is called reachability.
If there is a path from node U to node V,
V is reachable from U.
Reachability is not symmetric.
Even if V is reachable from U,
U may or may not be reachable from V.
As we can see in this graph,
I is not reachable from A.
Look at A more carefully.
There is no outgoing edge from A at all.
So no node in this graph
is reachable from A.
A is a terminal, a leaf node of the graph.
Where do we see this in real life?
Think of road network with one way streets
and road blocks through the construction.
This can make some areas
unreachable by cars.
In biology,
there are gene regulation networks,
in which the nodes represent genes and
edges represent the fact that gene
A regulates gene B and not visa verse.
This makes it a directed graph.
We can easily think of a case where
A regulates B, and B regulates C, but
C does not regulate B or A.
That's making A unreachable from C.
The final concept you will
explore in this graph,
in this lecture,
is that of a graph diameter.
The diameter of a graph measures the
maximum number of steps, also called hops,
want us to traverse to go to
the most distant node in the graph.
That means,
if you go from an arbitrary node
to any other arbitrary node in the graph,
following only the shortest paths roots,
what is the maximum number
of steps you have to take?
Let's see how this is computed.
For this task, we'll create a matrix
called the shortest hop distance matrix.
Just like the adjacency matrix, the rows
and columns here represent graph nodes.
And each cell contains the distance
from the I eighth node,
to the G eighth node
via the shortest path.
The distance from any
node to itself is zero.
So all diagonal elements
of the matrix are zero.
If a node I cannot reach
node J through any path,
the distance is marked as infinity.
Thus, the distance from
B to C is infinity.
You can go from E to F in two steps,
E to C to F.
Therefore, the wait at the C cell is two.
If you fill this matrix, you will
notice that the largest reachable value
is 4 in doing the infinite distance.
Thus, the diameter of this graph is
4 where It represents the part from I
to A, through J, G and D.
There are a few noteworthy
items in this Distance Matrix.
The row of A has a value of 0 with itself
and infinity for every other node.
This happens because A is a leaf node.
Similarly, except for
the 0 distance with itself,
the H column has infinity for
all of the nodes.
This happens because H
has no incoming edges and
therefore no other node can reach H.
So we have seen how to compute
degree histograms of a graph.
While degree histograms are useful
to characterize a graph,
it is usually a means to an end.
It's a known practice in statistics to
compute a mathematical expression for
a statistical distribution
Using histograms.
For graphs, we often look for a function
to describe the degree distribution.
But this is expressed as
a distribution of the probability
that a random vertex will
have exactly k neighbors.
Now, this problem has been
investigated by many.
One popular, well known model,
is a Power Law.
A graph follows a Power Law if,
the best probability is given by k,
erased to a negative
exponent called alpha.
The value of alpha, for many practical
networks, is between two and three.
More recently,
people have suggested other distributions
that look like the power law graph.
One of them is a log-normal graph.
Here, the logarithm of k has
a Gaussian distribution.
So this log-normal distribution
seems to have the better fit to
natural graphs that are observed.
So, why are power law graphs important?
Interestingly, many very,
very different real life graphs in
the world seem to follow the power law.
If a graph does follow the power law, it
would have one large connected component
with a very high proportion of notes
connected to it In a power law graph,
most nodes have a low degree and
some nodes will be disconnected.
The low degree nodes belong to
a very dense sub graphs and
those sub graphs are connected
to each other through hubs.
In the center of the graph
has a high density,
power law graphs can be
difficult to compute with.
For example, the shortest path
algorithm operating in the dense part
will possibly be very inefficient, not
because of the size of the network, but
because there are too many paths to
explore inside the denser pieces.
The more interesting reason why
people study power-law graphs
is because power-law graphs
are supposed to be robust.
So in nature, all biological networks
show power-law graphs because
It gives you a high rate of redundancy
against failure and attacks.
The most primitive path analytics
question one can ask is to find the best
path from node one to node two.
What does best mean?
Well, that depends on the actual
needs of the application.
But in general, to specify the best path,
we need to define when one
path is better than another.
This is usually expressed in
terms of an optimization problem.
Where we need to minimize and maximize
our subfunction subject to constraints.
What kind of constraints?
Two common criteria for graphs are,
inclusion and exclusion conditions.
Inclusion criteria may specify which
nodes we have to include in the path.
And exclusion criteria
specifies which nodes and
edges should be excluded from the path.
In addition,
one specify a preference criteria
that act as a softer or
less strict constraint.
For example, we would like to
minimize highways on my trip.
Or avoid condition.
These are soft because although
the users would like to have them
enforced completely, it is all right
if they are not fully enforced.
A good practical use case occurs when I'm
trying to drive to work in the morning.
Ideally, I would like to take a path
having the shortest distance from my home.
For example, node I, to my workplace,
which is node B in the graph.
But I have to drop off my son at school.
So my path must include his school,
the J here.
However, I would like to avoid roads
around the new construction that's
happening about five miles from my
workplace, like the node E in the graph.
Because there is usually a huge traffic
delay around that construction site.
I could also add
a preference criteria like
I don't prefer to drive on the highway.
But for this discussion,
we'll skip the preference idea.
Too complicated?
Okay, let's start with a simpler problem.
To start with, let's drop the constraints
and look at the problem with just
the optimization part of the problem,
having a single variable.
In our case, that variable is the sum
of edge weights from the source,
that is the starting node I,
to the target, which is B.
This problem is handled by all mapping and
road direction software.
Here is a Google map screenshot,
in which I am trying to go from my home
in North San Diego,
to a collision center in a nearby city.
Google Maps shows three different routes,
and
highlights one as a preferred solution.
You should readily see that the real
shortest path of 26.6 miles
will take the longest time at the time of
the day when I was looking at the map.
So this means the weights here are not
raw distances but estimated travel time.
You should also notice the blue, red, and
orange segments in the preferred
path are presented by Google.
The orange and red street segments
clearly represent congestion areas and
therefore have higher weight
than the blue segments.
Therefore, the weights of the street
segments are not really static but
change with many other factors,
like weather or the time of the day.
This is why the least weight path problem
is an important problem to solve for
the benefit of the commuter.
A widely applied algorithm
that is applied for
shortest path problems is
called Dijkstra's algorithm.
Originally, Dijkstra considered a variant
of the problem where the task is
to find the shortest path from a single
source node to all other nodes.
We'll go through the algorithm here.
However, there are many good online
resources including tutorials and
YouTube videos describing the algorithm.
For our discussion, we'll confine
ourselves to the case where both
the source and
the target nodes are known in advance.
As you probably already know, Cypher is
the scripting language used in Neo4j and
it's what we have been using
already in the previous lectures.
In this lecture, we're going to go through
a series of basic queries using Cypher
with the focus on the data sets
that we've already been using.
Here's a listing of the basic queries
we will go through step by step.
So let's get started.
To keep things simple we will be using a
text file containing the basic queries and
we'll make this file available for
download as a reading in the module.
I will briefly review the queries and
then we'll toggle to the browser to view
the results of the queries in Neo4j.
Neo4j has a very nice feature which
allows us to retain individual queries
in multiple panels as we're going through
the process of exploring each query.
So for the first few queries we'll be
using the simple road network data set
that we used in previous demonstrations.
And here we've already loaded
the data set into Neo4j.
So let's look at our first query.
Our first query is a very a simple one,
in which we're counting the number
of nodes in the network.
So the first line of code simply matches
all of the nodes with the label MyNode and
it returns a count of those nodes.
So let's look at the results.
The results are very simple,
the value of eleven.
And we can visually confirm this
by inspecting the graph itself and
see it has 11 nodes and
we can see that up here.
The next query is almost as simple,
we want to count the number of edges.
Now, first thing to keep in mind
is in order to count edges,
we also need to declare nodes that
are associated with those edges.
So this first line of codes
includes a declaration
of the nodes associated with the edges.
Here we're identifying
with thevariable r and
then we're returning
a count of those edges.
So let's take a look in Neo4j and the
results of this query are a value of 14.
And once again we can confirm this
visually by looking at our network and
counting the number of edges.
The next query involves finding all
of the leaf nodes in the network.
Now as you may remember
from a previous lecture,
leaf nodes are defined as those
nodes which have no outgoing edges.
Notice that we're returning the node
represented by the variable M,
which is the target node in this query.
So here we're matching all nodes
associated with edges having the label two
and we want to place
a constraint on those nodes,
such that they have no outgoing edges.
And then we return all those nodes.
So let's take a look at the results.
We're going to see a single node returned,
the node with the label p.
And if we inspect our graph, we can
see over here on the right the node p,
and sure enough it has no outgoing edges,
only one incoming edge.
The next query is also similar,
we're looking for
root nodes instead of leaf notes.
And as you may also remember,
root nodes are defined as a node
which has no incoming edges.
You may notice that this segment of
the first line of code is sort of a mirror
image of the same segment in the first
line of code from the previous query.
We also want to place the constraint
on the nodes that we want to return
by specifying that they can
have no incoming edges.
And then, we return all of those nodes
When we look at our results in Neo4j.
Once again,
we see we only get a single node
return it's the node with the label H.
And if we inspect our graph,
we see over here the node H and
sure enough it has no incoming edges.
Only a single outgoing edge which
means it's a root node of the network.
The next query can be described
as a pattern matching query.
We're looking for a pattern that
we're describing as triangles.
This is a pattern that's
a bit more complex than
the patterns we've been looking for
in our previous queries.
A triangle can also be described as a
three cycle, consisting of three nodes and
three edges where the beginning and
end node are the same.
So here we're matching a node A which
goes through an edge to node B
which goes through a second
edge to a second node C and
through a third edge back
to the original node A.
And then we return all of those notes.
Let's look at our results.
And here we see we have five
distinct nodes returned.
And we have two triangles or
two three cycles.
From D to E to G and from D to C to B.
Finally the last query we're going
to execute with this data set,
is going to explore the neighborhood
of a particular node.
In this case, the node with the label d.
And we're going to be looking for
what we're calling second neighbors of D.
This means nodes that
are two nodes away from d.
So the first line of code matches
all nodes that are two nodes away
from a specific node.
And then the second line of codes
specifies the actual node that we
we want to consider by constraining
its name to have the label d,
and then we return those nodes.
And here we're using the command distinct
because we want to make sure that we
don't return any duplicate nodes.
All of our nodes must be unique.
So let's look at the results.
And here we have a network that
consists of nine nodes and 11 edges and
we can see that each node is
two nodes away from the node D.
Some nodes appear to be only one
node away from the node D but
we can get to those nodes indirectly
through another node, which means that
they're not only a first neighbor but
they're also a second neighbor.
So we encourage you to play
around with these queries,
and make minor changes with them,
and see what the results might be.
For our next three queries,
we're going to switch to the terrorist
data set that we had used in
our previous demonstration.
Our first query involves finding
the types of a particular node.
So, as you may recall in the terrorist
data set there were node types
corresponding to a country.
So, in this case we
want to match all nodes,
where the name is equal to Afghanistan.
And we will return the labels for
that particular match.
And the results for
this query are relatively simple.
The label for the node named Afghanistan
is country, as you might expect.
Next, we're going to do something
similar but with an edge.
In this case, we want to find the label
of a edge associated with
a node named Afghanistan.
And also, if you can recall from that
particular network, the label for
an edge associated with a country named
Afghanistan would be an IS_FROM label.
And the final query, we would like to
demonstrate with this terrorist data set,
involves finding all of
the properties of a node.
Now, based on how we defined
our data import script,
we defined all of our
nodes to be of type Actor.
So in this query, we're going to
search for all nodes of type Actor and
then, we're going to return all of the
properties associated with those nodes.
But, since there are thousands of nodes,
we're going to limit
the results to the first 20.
So, let's go ahead and submit our query.
And here are the results.
Each node represents a terrorist and
if we look at the rows data
behind the scenes we can see the various
properties associated with each node.
Each node has a name.
Each node has aliases,
one or more aliases.
And they have a type property.
Now, depending on how we defined our
import script in the first place,
these nodes could have
different types of properties.
In this case, we only defined them
to have three different properties.
For our next two queries,
we're going to use a different data set,
it's a biological data set consisting
of genetics data representing
interactions between genes.
We will be providing the data for
you to download.
In fact, there are two separate data sets.
One is a complete data set
consisting of 250,000 rows,
and the other data set consists
of the first 50,000 rows,
and that's what we'll be using for
this demonstration.
So, let's take a look at
a small sample of the data.
Here you see a graph network
in which each node is a gene.
And each edge represents
the association between genes.
To load this data set, this is the smaller
data set, required 1446 seconds,
and it consists of 9656 labels and
46621 relationships.
So, the first query involves finding
loops in the data which represent genes
that have associations
with there own types.
So, it's a very simple query
in which the source node and
the target node are the same and we'll
be returning those along the edges and
we'll limit our results to the first ten.
So, here are the results of our query.
We can see a few different loops.
If we look at the rows, our query returned
not only the node but the edge type.
So, on the left we see the particular
gene and on the right,
we see the type of association.
And there are a range of different types.
So, this data set also
contains multigraphs.
If you recall from a previous lecture,
the definition of a multigraph
is any two nodes which have two or
more edges between them.
So in this case, we'll be matching
two separate node edge relationships.
And we'll apply a constraint in which
the edges must be different for
the same pairs of nodes.
And then we will return those nodes and
those edges.
We'll limit our results to the first ten.
And here's the results.
Here we see a set of four genes, and
there are two pairs that have three
edges between them and another pair
that has four edges between them.
Our final query addresses something that
is not necessarily been fully covered
in previous lectures, but
it is useful enough to address here and
you'll get an understanding of it by
going through this query example.
We're going to essentially
extract a subset of nodes and
edges from the graph that
we've been working with.
And this is called an induced subgraph.
In which, if we provide a set of nodes,
we want to return
the network that consists only of those
nodes and their associated edges.
So, my first line of code is very
familiar, we're matching nodes and
edges, it's a very basic node and
edge match.
The second line of code is where
the constraints are explicitly stated.
A resulting network must consist
of edges in which the source node
must be constrained to this
subset of node labels.
And the target node must also be
constrained to be a part of the subset of
nodes with just these labels.
And then we return the nodes and
the edges.
So, let's see the resulting graph.
And here it is.
So, as we would expect,
we're seeing the five nodes that were
defined in our query constraints.
And the edges corresponding to them,
retain the network structure.
So, this concludes our review of
some of the basic queries you can do
with Neo4j using the cipher
scripting language.
Next, we will talk about
connectivity analytics with Cypher.
If you remember in module two,
we talked about connectivity analytics
in terms of network robustness.
In other words, a measure of how resistant
a graph network is to being disconnected.
Specifically, we used
two kinds of methods.
One computed the eigenvalues, and the
second computed the degree distribution.
For these examples, we're going to use
the second one, degree distributions.
And we will use the same graph
network we've used previously.
A simple graph representing
a road network.
And here's a listing of the query examples
we're going to be applying to our network.
My first query example finds all
of the outdegrees of all nodes.
Now, if you'll notice, this query consists
of two parts, because there's a specific
type of node, a leaf node, which does not
conform to this particular constraint.
So our first match statement finds
all nodes with outgoing edges,
as you can see here,
this is a directed edge.
And then,
we returns the names of the nodes and
the count as the variable outdegree.
And for convenience,
we order by outdegree.
And we need to combine that with
a specific query dealing with leaf nodes.
We're familiar with how to
do that from past examples.
And so, we'll match all leaf nodes and
return the name and
the value zero for its outdegree.
So when we submit this query we
get this listing right here.
The node P has 0 for its outdegree and
all of the other nodes are as we might
expect and they're ordered
by their value of outdegree.
Our next query finds
the indegree of all nodes,
which is very similar to
our previous example.
But, in this case, as you might expect,
we're going to take into account
root nodes instead of leaf nodes.
And so, our match involves incoming edges.
Indegree is a measure of all nodes
connected to a specific node with
incoming edges.
And we return similar results and
we union that with the specific query
commands to find all of the root nodes,
and then we return those names and
0 as the value of indegree.
So when we submit this query,
here's our results as we might expect.
In this case, H is our only root node.
So it has a value of 0 for indegree, and
all the other nodes
are as we might expect.
And our third query example
finds the degree of all nodes,
which is a combination of outdegree and
indegree.
So in this case we're not including any
specific direction in our match statement.
And we're returning the name and
the count for all of our edges.
But we're using the distinct statement,
otherwise we would be
counting some nodes twice.
And then, for convenience,
we order this by the value of degree.
And when we submit this query,
we get the results as shown here.
We have 1 column with the name and
the other column with the degree and
the values are as we would expect, we have
a leaf node P with the degree of 1 and
a root node H with a degree of 1.
Our next query example generates a degree
histogram of the graph since we're able to
calculate the degree of each node, we can
sort those into actual values of degree.
So if we look at the distribution
of degree among our nodes,
we see there's 2 nodes with the degree 1,
there's 3 nodes with degree 2,
there's 4 nodes with degree 3, and
there's 2 nodes with degree 4.
So we're going to group those
in the form of a histogram.
So when we submit this query,
we get this table.
The first column list the degree
value in ascending order and
the second column list the counts of
the nodes that have that degree value.
So for those of you who are familiar with
SQL you might recognize this as similar
to the group by command,
it performs a similar function
Our next query example saves the degree
of the node as a new node property.
This provides an added convenience so that
we don't have to calculate the degree of
a node every time we're
performing some sort of analysis.
So we match all nodes with edges, and
there's no direction in this
particular edge definition.
And then, we return distinct
counts of each node's degree, and
then we create a new property, called deg,
and assign the value of degree to it.
Then, we return the names and
the degree values, and so
when we submit this query,
we see this distribution right here,
with the names in the left column, and
the values of degree in the right column.
And we can verify that if we issue a
command to return all of the properties of
the specific node.
So in this case I issued a command
to match the node named D and
return all of its properties.
And sure enough we see that it has
a property name and a property degree.
Before we go to the last two examples,
there's a philosophical issue that we
need to remember with all databases.
Every database will allow you some
analytical computation and the remainder
of the analytical computations must
be done outside of the database.
However, it is always a judicious
idea to get the database to
achieve an intermediate result formatted
in a way that you would need for
the next computation.
And then, you use that intermediate result
as the input to the next computation.
We've seen that a number of
computations in graph analytics
start with the adjacency matrix.
So we should be able to force Cypher
to produce an adjacency matrix.
And this is what we're doing here.
So think of a Matrix as a three column
table, in which, here's one column,
here's another column, and the third
column will be the values that we
are calculating when we determine whether
two nodes have an edge between them.
And we're introducing a new
construct in Cypher called case.
This allows us to evaluate conditions and
return one result, or
a different result
depending on the condition.
Here, we're specifying that when
there is an edge between nodes n and
m, then we return a value of 1,
otherwise return a value of 0.
And we'll output those results as a value.
And so, when we submit this query,
we get our three column table in which
the first column is
the name of our first node.
The second column is the name of our
second node and the value is either a 1 or
a 1 depending on whether the nodes
have an edge between them.
So in this case we see node A and
C have an edge,
A and L have an edge and
so on as we would expect.
So if we can calculate the adjacency
matrix then we can calculate any matrix.
You might remember from our
module two lecture where we
learned about this complex structure
called the Normalized Laplacian Matrix.
So let's go ahead and calculate that.
We'll perform something very similar
to what we did in the previous example.
We'll match all nodes for
the first column, and all nodes for
the second column.
We'll return the names of those nodes and
then we'll use the case structure again
to compare the names of each node and
determine whether we have the same node.
If we do have the same node then
that is a diagonal of the matrix and
should get a value of 1.
If they are different nodes and
contain an edge between them,
then we calculate the normalized
Laplacian with this equation here.
And you'll also want to notice that here
we're using the actual degree property
that we assigned to the nodes
in a previous example.
This is an example of how that
can become a convenient option.
So when the calculation is performed,
the value would be returned.
If there's no edge between the 2 nodes,
then the value of 0 will be returned.
And these values will end
up in the value column.
So when we submit this query,
here's the table that get returned.
This is the first column
with the source node.
The second column with the target node and
the values.
So in the first row, the first node
is P and the second node is P, so
it's identical, which means it's
on the diagonal of the matrix.
Likewise, for A in this row down here.
And then the first value of the Laplacian
is calculated between nodes A and
C, and so on.
So that concludes our examples of how
to perform connectivity analytics
in Neo4j with Cypher.
Hello everyone and welcome to a series of
lessons on graph analytics with Neo4j.
In this first tutorial we are going to go
briefly through the process of downloading
and installing Neo4j, and
then we'll go ahead and run Neo4j and
provide a brief review of
the Neo4j graphical interface.
So, let's get started.
To download Neo4j,
you'll want to browse to neo4j.com, and
once you're at that URL,
you should see a webpage similar to this.
Neo4j typically will detect which
operating system you're running, but
if you want to download
other versions of Neo4j,
click this link in the upper
right-hand corner to download Neo4j.
We're going to use the community edition,
so we'll click this link right here.
But if you'd like to
explore other releases,
you can click the link down here.
When we click
the Download Community Edition link,
Neo4j should automatically
begin the download.
There are versions of Neo4j for
Windows, Mac, and Linux.
Neo4j is developed with the Java
programming language, so
you'll want to be sure you have the
minimum system requirements to run Neo4j.
We'll provide a link to those system
requirements in the resources of
this video.
This example is with
the Mac OS X operating system.
And we've downloaded the .dmg file and
we can click to open that.
And as is the case with the Mac
applications to install is very
straightforward.
We'll just click and drag this icon
into the Applications folder and
that should automatically install.
Once the application is installed,
we should see it listed in
the Applications folder.
So let's go ahead and run Neo4j.
To run Neo4j, you'll just double-click
on the application's icon.
Neo4j is browser-based, so
it launches a web server, and
it launches a URL specific to Neo4j.
So to activate that server
we'll click the Start button.
If it's your first time using Neo4j
then you probably won't have any graph
databases available to open,
so Neo4j makes it easy for
you by providing a default
graph database of movie data.
To run Neo4j, you click this link and
that should launch your default browser.
Installation on Windows should be
just as straightforward as OS X.
You'll click the same
Download Neo4j button and
when the download page opens,
you'll click Download Community Edition.
Neo4j should recognize you're running
Windows and should download an executable.
Once that downloads we can run it and
we'll step through the same steps
which are typical for
a Windows operating system.
Now I already have Neo4j
installed in my Windows system so
I will be updating my
existing installation.
And Neo4j downloads a Java jar file.
Once the application's installed
it will open the dialog box and
we can start up our web server.
And the same URL is available and
when we click that, our default
browser should be launched and we should
see the same interface we see In OS X.
You should be able to subsequently
run neo4j by accessing the executable
in the Windows Start menu.
So let's take a look at
the neo4j interface.
As I mentioned previously,
neo4j is a browser-based application.
So once the application launches it
should open your default browser and
in my case, I'm using the Chrome browser.
And you should see a URL like
this in the address bar.
Most browsers provide a full-screen
viewing mode, so I'm going to go ahead and
activate that, in this case,
what Chrome calls presentation mode.
The interface for
neo4j consists of three main areas.
There's the command line along the top
where you can issue commands and you can
paste content into the command line and
execute multiple lines at one time.
You can specify these commands
to be one of your favorites.
You can clear the command box.
And you can run, or execute,
the commands with the Play button.
On the left-hand side is an expandable and
collapsible panel that provides
supplementary information about the
database you're currently working with.
There's an option to list your favorites,
and
Neo4j provides an initial
default listing of favorites.
And there's supplementary information and
links to references and
examples and tutorials and so on.
You can also modify the configuration
of your Neo4j installation for
your particular user.
And there's additional information
about the application.
The third area is the main panel in
the middle where the results of all of
the commands that you
execute are displayed.
In fact, this panel itself has been
generated by issuing a command,
which is displayed in
the very top of the panel.
The command is ;play start.
In fact, if I type that command into my
command line I should be able to generate
a duplicate of that panel,
and sure enough, there it is.
The upper right-hand corner of these
panels I can pin the panel to my webpage,
and I can do this with as
many panels as I want and
the window will simply allow
me to scroll up and down.
I can view this particular
panel full screen.
Or it can cancel or close it,
which is what I'm going to do.
Now you can see neo4j makes it very
easy to learn all about graph analytics.
So let's go ahead and get started
with learning how to create and
modify our first graph network.
Next we're going to get started with Neo4j
by creating our first graph network.
To do this,
first we will review a graphical or
a diagrammatic representation
of a graph network.
Then, we'll introduce you to an equivalent
text representation of that network.
Then, we will build on those text
representations in the form of pseudocode,
with the ultimate goal being
to develop an actual script
to create our network in Neo4j.
Then, we'll go ahead and run the script to
create the network, and we'll explore it,
and confirm it structure and content.
You're looking at a simple graph network,
consisting of five nodes and five edges.
Each node represents a person,
an individual.
And, the edges represent
relationships between those people.
Each node has a number associate with it,
N1 through N5.
And, each edge has a corresponding number
associated with it, E1 through E5.
Edges are relationships such
as Harry is known by Tom,
or Julian is coworker of Harry.
We could have more or less edges, but we
wanted to keep things relatively simple,
while still maintaining
a reasonable degree of complexity.
What we want is a script that we can
process with Neo4j in order to
create an actual graph network.
So, let's look at a text
representation of this network.
So, here we list our five nodes and
five edges, and we're going to begin
the process of extending the text
descriptions of our graph network.
I'm going to scroll down briefly,
and just show you the end result, so
you have a better idea of what
the final goal is going to be.
This is the actual code that we're going
to submit to Neo4j in order to create
our network.
But, we're going to back
up a little bit and
look at some simplified
versions of this syntax, so
we can better understand how simple the
graph network relationships really are.
Here, we list the five nodes and
five edges, as you saw just a moment ago.
And down below,
we have a simple notation structure,
which attempts to describe
the five edge relationships.
The first line represents the edge E1.
We can see that the nodes N1 and
N2 are included,
because Harry is known by Tom, and
Tom is node N1 and Harry is node N2.
The same goes for the second line,
the relationship between Julian and Harry.
Julian is co-worker of Harry, and so on.
So, let's take this a step further
by defining our graph network,
so that each node is
a particular type of node.
In this case, we're going to define a node
type as what we're calling a ToyNode.
As we introduce each node and
its relationship with other nodes,
we'll define the node
to be of type ToyNode.
So, on this first line,
N1 goes through e1 to N2.
And, both of those are introduced for
the first time, so
we'll define them as type ToyNode.
But, on the next line, since we
already introduced N2 as type ToyNode,
we don't need to repeat that statement.
And, so we continue in the same manner
with the remaining edge relationships.
Taking this even further, we'll apply
a similar kind of constraint to our edges.
In this case, we'll define our network
such that each edge is a particular type,
which we're calling ToyRelation.
Next, we're going to add
properties to our nodes and edges.
Our nodes can have properties
such as name or job,
so in this case, our first node,
N1, will have the name Tom.
And, the appropriate syntax for this
includes curly braces surrounding the key
value pairs, a colon separating
the key value pairs, and
the values defined within single quotes.
Likewise, each edge may have
a specific type of relationship,
including co-worker, wife, and friend.
So, finally this brings us to the actual
code we're going to use to create our
graph network.
So, let's go ahead and copy this,
and paste it into Neo4j, so
we can take a look at our network.
Here we are, running Neo4j in our browser.
So, I'm going to paste the code that
I just copied from my text file
into the command line
in the Neo4j interface.
And, I'll click the Play button
to execute those commands, and
we'll see the results returned
in this newly displayed panel.
We can see that we have 5 labels added,
5 nodes were created, 13 properties were
set, 5 relationships were created, and the
entire process required 31 milliseconds.
However, we still can't actually view our
graph unless we issue yet another command.
So, let's shuffle to our text file,
and take a look at that command.
What this command does,
is it tries to identify a match
in which a particular node has
a relationship with any other node.
And, then we'll return those nodes and
relationships.
So, we'll go ahead and copy this, and
we'll paste it in to our command line,
and we'll execute.
And, there's our graph.
When we mouse over the nodes, we can see
information displayed on the bottom.
And, when we select those nodes, that
information is displayed permanently along
the bottom,
likewise with edge relationships.
So, we would expect to see things such
as Michelle is the wife of Harry,
Julian is a co-worker of Harry, and so on.
So, it looks like our network
has been created successfully.
We can also display
information in a tabular format
by clicking the Rows icon on the left.
And, we'll see that this information
is not constrained by the directed
nature of our graph.
For example, we see that Harry
has a relationship with Tom,
in which Harry knows Tom.
But likewise, down here,
Tom has a relationship with Harry,
in which Tom knows Harry.
Next, we're going to learn
how to add to this graph and
modify some of the properties
of the nodes and edges.
In this segment, we're going to
learn how to import data into Neo4j.
We will begin by using a fairly simple
spreadsheet consisting of only a few
rows and three columns in a format
that's fairly typical for
importing into a graph database.
We will review the Neo4j CYPHER
script used to perform this import.
And then we'll run the script and
validate the resulting graph.
Then we'll demonstrate
a similar process but
with a more challenging dataset,
consisting of terrorist network data.
We will review this dataset and
the script commands necessary for
performing the import.
And we'll run the script and
explore the resulting graph.
And finally, we will review a third
dataset that you will use yourself to
perform similar data inport operations.
First, let's take a look
at our sample dataset.
This spreadsheet consists of just
a few rows and three columns.
Each column has a heading.
The first column heading is Source,
the second column heading is Target, and
the third column heading is distance.
You can imagine that this might represent
data from a simple road network in which
the Source and
Target values represent towns, and
the distance values represent the actual
distance in miles between the towns.
So let's take a look at
the Neo4j CYPHER script and
see what we will need to do to
import our spreadsheet data.
The first line of code
performs the actual import.
The other three lines of code provide
constraints to the formatting
of that data.
Since our data file is
a comma separated values or
CSV file,
we will need to specify that in our code.
Our file also contains headers.
And if you're using
a Windows operating system,
your file path will look
something like this.
Since we're running Neo4j in a browser,
the file path needs
to conform to the HTTP address
conventions of the word file,
followed by a colon,
followed by three forward slashes and
then the hard disk letter where the file
is located, plus the path to that file.
If you're using Mac OSX,
your command will be similar, but
the file path will probably
look something more like this.
The next three lines specify which
nodes will be the source nodes and
which nodes will be the target nodes.
And the properties will attach to them as
well as defining the relationships and
the properties we will
attach to the relationships.
As we read each line of data n,
we're going to use keyword line,
to specify the individual line
we're currently working on.
We use that here at the end
of our load command and so
we'll have to continue to use it
in the subsequent merge commands.
Our source node variable
is going to be n and
we'll use the MyNode type,
which we've made up ourselves.
We're going to add a Name property
to each of our source nodes.
And we're going to attach the value in
the Source column to that particular node.
Likewise for our target nodes,
we'll use a variable m.
We'll define them as the same type,
MyNode.
We will give them a Name and we will
extract that name from the Target column
on the particular line we're working with.
Finally, we need to define
our edge relationships.
We're going to give each
edge a label of the word TO,
and we're going to add a property called
dist, which represents the distance.
And we'll attach the values
in the distance column
from the particular line
we're currently working on.
So let's go ahead and copy this code and
paste it into Neo4j, and see what happens.
Now, I'm working on a Mac OSX machine, so
I'm going to copy this code down here and
perform the import operation.
So I've pasted the line
of code into Neo4j and
I'll click Execute.
And it takes a few moments to run.
There's not too much data so it shouldn't
take more than just a few seconds.
And now we get the results in which
11 labels, 11 nodes have been added,
25 properties have been set and
14 relationships have been created.
So let's take a look
at this graph network.
We can see that the nodes are listed
all as MyNode and there's our graph.
The edge relationships should all
have different distance values and
each node should be named
a different letter.
Okay, so
let's try a more difficult dataset.
Here is the spreadsheet
containing terrorist data.
The spreadsheet consists of seven
columns with headings such as Country,
ActorName, ActorType, AffiliationTo,
AffiliationStartDate,
AffiliationEndDate, and any aliases
associated with that particular terrorist.
This dataset consists of
over 100,000 rows of data.
Since that could take a very long
time to load into Neo4j, we will be
working with a subset of this dataset
consisting of the first 1,000 rows.
That much data will still
include three countries,
which should be plenty of data for
our purposes.
So here is the script we're going to use
to import the subset of terrorist data,
which shares similarities with
the script we used previously.
But since there are more
columns in our dataset,
we're going to include some additional
properties into our graph network.
The first line of code is very similar
to the load command we've
used in previous datasets.
The second line of code will use
a variable c and a label Country for
the particular nodes representing
the individual countries in the dataset.
In this particular case, we're going to
use the keyword row instead of line to
read our data n, but
it really doesn't matter.
We could use either word as long we
are consistent from command to command.
So we're using the term row and
associating the value in the Country
column with the node that we're
working on in that particular row.
We will do something similar with
nodes that are intended to represent
the actors or
the actual individual terrorists.
We're going to use a variable a and
we will associate a property
called Name, and associate
the ActorName with that property.
We'll also associate
a property named Aliases, and
associate the value in the Aliases
column with that property.
And finally,
we will define a property called Type and
associate the values in the ActorType
column with that property.
We're going to create nodes
representing organizations as well and
we will use the variable o, and
the label Organization for those nodes.
We will attach a single property
to these nodes called Name and
we'll assign the values in
the AffiliationTo column to that property.
Then we're going to define
relationships between the Actors and
the Organizations they're affiliated with.
The relationship label is
going to be AFFILIATED_TO and
we'll define a property called Start.
And we'll assign the values in the
AffiliationStartDate with that property.
Likewise, we will define
a property called End and
assign the values in
the AffiliationEndDate with that property.
And finally, we're going to create
relationships between the countries and
the actors.
In this case, we will define relationships
with the label IS_FROM that will
describe the fact that a particular
actor is from a particular country.
So if all this makes sense,
let's go ahead and copy this script and
paste it into Neo4j, and see the results.
So here we are in Neo4j, and
I'm going to go ahead and
paste that script into the command line,
and we will execute it.
We loaded 1,000 rows of data, which
consists of 658 labels and 658 nodes.
3,464 properties and
1,403 relationships and
it took about two and a half seconds.
So let's look at a small
subset of this network.
Here, we see the equivalent of
the first 25 rows of the dataset.
There's only enough data
such that 1 Country,
8 Actors and 15 Organizations are visible.
Let's go ahead and
change this command to 250.
By clicking on the line of
code in the top of our panel,
it automatically gets pasted
into the command line above.
So all we need to do is add a zero on the
end of our command and execute that again.
Now we have a much larger,
more complex graph,
but we still only have one country.
In order to see more than one country,
we'll need to render the entire 1,000
rows of our terrorist data subset.
But in so doing, we will have a difficult
time viewing the entire graph.
The community edition of Neo4j
is limited in its ability to
navigate a graph network.
But I'm going to show you
a little trick by editing
the HTML behind the scenes to
scale the view of our graph.
So let's go ahead and
render all 1,000 rows.
So most recent versions of the major
browsers provide the ability to go behind
the scenes and edit the HTML.
So the trick is to find a place on
the viewing panel that does not have
any objects.
So that when you right-click and
inspect the element,
you'll be inspecting the viewing area.
Neo4j uses SVG graphics, or
Scalable Vector Graphics to
render its graph networks.
And SVG uses a g element,
which can be seen here on the right.
So in order to change the scale of our
view, we simply need to double-click and
add scale, open parentheses, and
the scale factor that we'd like.
We hit Return and
the graph network now is zoomed out.
I'm going to try to position it so
we can see at least two countries,
and I'll close my HTML panel.
And so now we can view two countries.
We can see Albania in the upper region,
and Afghanistan in the lower right.
And we can see that there are actors and
organizations that have
relationships with both countries.
Now there are add ons to Neo4j that
make navigating a graph network a little
easier, but
this trick is convenient for those of you
who have not added any Neo4j extensions.
The last thing that we're going to do
is take a look at the sample dataset of
gene-disease associations, and give you
an idea what's going to be expected of
you in the accompanying assignment for
this module.
This data consists of
information associating
different genes with different diseases.
The spreadsheet consists of
columns with headings for geneId,
geneSymbol, geneName, diseaseId,
the diseaseName, the score that
represents the extent to which that gene
is associated with that
particular disease.
The NumberofPubmed articles
containing that information.
The associationTypes,
there are up to three different types of
associations between a gene and a disease.
And then the sources of data and
information that confirm this
gene disease relationship.
Now this dataset contains
over 400,000 rows of data.
So if you have difficulty
importing this entire dataset,
then you'll be better off extracting
the first few thousand rows.
So you're goal will be to
define the load statement,
which includes a CSV with headers,
that will allow you to import enough
data into Neo4j to give you an idea
that you've done it successfully.
We've already learned a little
about the Neo4j interface.
And we've learned how to create
a relatively simple graph with it.
In this lecture,
we're going to learn how to add
another node and an edge to the graph.
We'll also go through
the process of adding a node and
edge incorrectly to the graph.
And we'll learn how to
correct that mistake.
And finally we'll learn how to modify
an existing node's information.
Okay, so here's our network that we
created in the previous lecture.
The first modification
that we want to make,
is adding a single node to the network.
So let's say that Julian has a fiance and
her name is Joyce and
she works as a store clerk.
So let's look at the code that we're
going to use to make that modification.
So this process involves two steps or
two separate commands.
First command requires you to find the
node that you want to add the new node to.
So we use the match command and
we specify the ToyNode named Julian.
Once that command is issued then
we'll use the merge command and
define the relation between Julian and
the new node.
And it's going to be fiancee.
And then the new node
will also be a ToyNode.
And the name is Joyce, and
her job is store clerk.
So let's go ahead and
copy both these lines of code.
And we'll paste them into our command
line, and we'll run these commands.
And the results that
are returned look good.
Neo4j says that it has added 1 label,
created 1 node, set 3 properties,
created 1 relationship, and
it's required 55 milliseconds to execute.
So let's look at that network.
Maybe the easiest way to
view an existing network,
if it's the only one you're working on and
you know the constraints involved,
just ToyNodes, is to expand the panel on
the left and just click the ToyNode node.
And you'll easily see the new network.
And we can confirm that Joyce
has been successfully added, and
when we select that,
we can see that her job is store clerk.
The command that was issued automatically
by clicking the ToyNode button in
the panel Is a little different than what
we've been using to view our networks.
But they both work essentially
the same with this particular network.
So next let's see what happens if
we do something incorrectly, and
how to correct the mistake.
So to do this,
we'll need to get back to our original
network without the added node.
And maybe the easiest way to do
this is to delete everything and
recreate our original network.
So first I'm going to copy and
paste command to delete all
of the nodes and edges.
You'll find this command in the getting
started video supplementary resources.
It involves the match command and
I'm matching all nodes and
all relationships and I'm deleting
those nodes and relationships.
So let's issue that command,
which should say it's deleted 6 nodes and
6 relationships, and sure enough.
Neo4J's command line has a nice feature of
maintaining a history of the commands and
so in OSX we can use the command+up
arrow to cycle through the commands and
find the original create command
that created our network.
On Windows, it's a CTRL+up arrow command.
So here I've found that command and
I'm going to re-execute it.
And we have our original
network back again.
Let's view that network.
And there it is.
So let's say for whatever reason I am
not quite fully understanding how to add
an additional node to an existing network,
and I want to use the create command.
For example, I might be thinking that
this statement right here will
accomplish the same kind of thing.
By using the create command and
by specifying a ToyNode named Julian.
Well, if we go ahead and
give that a try let's see what happens.
So I'll copy this command and I will paste
it into my command line and execute it.
And it says it's added 2 labels and
created 2 nodes and set 4 properties.
And if we look at this, We
see we've actually got another node named
Julian who has a relationship with Joyce.
So that much is correct, but it's not
the same Julian from the original network.
So how do we undo this?
Well, we'll need to specify the Julian
that has a relationship with Joyce and
delete both the Julian and
the Joyce notes.
So here we'll use the match
command once again.
And we'll identify the node, the ToyNode,
with the name Joyce and any relationship
she has with any other node should be
deleted in addition to that other node.
Let's go ahead and copy this.
And we'll paste it into our
command line and execute.
And it says it deleted 2 nodes and
deleted 1 relationship.
Let's view our network again.
And it's back to normal.
So that's one example of how you can
intuitively figure out how to correct
certain mistakes.
Next we're going to modify
information of an existing node.
So if you remember when we first created
our network, Harry didn't have a job.
So let's go ahead and add a job to Harry.
First of all,
we'll need to actually select
the node by using the match command.
So we'll issue that here and
we'll specify that that node
name must be equal to Harry.
And then we're going to
use the set command and
specify that job will be equal to drummer.
So let's go ahead and copy that.
And we'll paste it and execute it.
And the results that are returned
says that one property has been set.
But let's say that Harry does
more than just play drums.
Let's say that he can
also play lead guitar.
So in this case we will be
adding an additional property
to a property that already exists and
we'll see how Neo4J handles that.
It's a relatively simple modification
we make, in which we're setting
the job key equal to the existing job key
+ an additional value to that key,
in this case, lead guitarist.
So let's copy that statement.
And we'll paste it and execute it.
And we get a similar result returned and
then let's look at our network.
And when we select Harry, sure enough
now we see that he has two jobs.
They're separated by a comma.
One is drummer and one is lead guitarist.
There's much more you can do with Neo4j,
but
we'll want to move on and
learn some more advanced capabilities
that work us closer towards
managing our big data challenges.
Next, we will talk about
Path Analytics using Cypher,
the query language for Neo4j.
Here's the listing of the various
queries we will be demonstrating.
There are some things that Cypher
is capable of doing very well.
And there are other things that
require a little bit of creativity
in order to get the results
that you're looking for.
And we'll show you some examples of that.
It's also important to keep in mind
that because we're working with paths,
which are an official
structure in graph networks,
each one of these examples
includes a new variable.
Which in this case,
we're using the letter p to represent for
the actual path objects that
we're going to be returning.
You may also see the complete word
path instead of just the single letter
p to represent these objects.
We're going to continue to use the data
set of a simple road network that we've
already been using in previous
demonstrations that contains 11 nodes and
14 edges.
So the first query we're
going to demonstrate
is finding a path between specific nodes.
So this would be very much like trying
to find a root between two different
locations in our road network.
In this case, we're going to find
a path between the node named H and
the node named P.
To do this,
we'll use the match command and
we'll say match p which is a variable
we're using to represent our path,
= node a, going through an edge to node c.
There's something slightly different about
this edge, and that is that we're using
a star to represent an arbitrary number
of edges in sequence between a and c, and
we'll be returning all of those edges
that are necessary to complete the path.
And in this case we only want
to return a single path.
So when we submit this query,
we see this path.
It consists of eight nodes and
seven edges.
And it begins with H and ends with P.
Now, another common function we
will use frequently with paths
is finding the length
between two specific nodes.
So we'll issue the same two lines of code
and then we'll use this new command,
length, to return an actual value.
We want to be returning an actual path.
And we just want a single value.
And when we submit this query,
we get the result seven.
And we can see that by visually
inspecting the graph or our seven edges.
But because most networks
are much more complex than this,
we would need to understand the necessary
query to return the length.
And ideally,
in the case of our road network,
we would want to find the shortest
path between those two nodes.
So in this case we're introducing yet
another new command specific
to paths called shortestPath.
We will use the same variable key, and
the same descriptions in our syntax,
in connecting node a with node c.
And in this case, were going to look for
the shortest path between node a and
node p, and we're going to return that
path as well as the length of that path.
And we're just going to
return a single path.
And when we submit this query,
we get a path that's five nodes and
four edges long and if we look at
the text results that are returned,
we'll see a length displayed
in the length column.
And that value is 4, and we can see
that by visually inspecting our graph.
The next query we are going to demonstrate
is intended to illustrate that
there may be more than one shortest path.
And so, we may want to know all of the
possible shortest paths in order to make
a choice between which one we prefer.
So we'll be using a command that is built
into Neo4j called, allShortestPaths.
We'll be issuing a similar query
to what we issued previously,
we're going to try to find all of the
shortest paths between node a and node p.
And instead of the letters a and c, we're
using the terms source and destination.
But the results that we're going to return
will actually be in the form of an array.
We're using a new term, extract,
which is based on the following.
Assuming we have matched our path p,
we want to identify
all of the nodes in p and
extract their names.
And we'll return these names as a listing,
which we'll call the variable paths.
If there's more than one shortest path,
we'll get multiple listings of node names.
So when we submit this query, the results
are listed in the rows display and
we see there are actually
two shortest paths.
They each have five nodes and four edges.
Now, we may want to issue a query
that finds the shortest path but
with particular constraints or
conditions that we place on them.
So in this case we still want
to find the shortest path, but
in this case we may want to constrain
the path length to be greater
than a particular value, in this case 5.
And then, we want to return essentially
the same results that we returned in
the previous query.
But we'll also want to return the length
of the resulting path just so
we have that information conveniently.
So when we issue this command
we get a path with length six
between node A and node P.
So it's clearly longer than the shortest
path that we had found earlier.
Now that we are somewhat familiar
with the two shortest path commands,
the shortest path, or a single path and
the all shortest paths command or multiple
shortest paths, we're going to use
that in a little bit of a creative way
to return the diameter of the graph.
And if you remember from
a previous lecture,
the definition of
the diameter of the graph
is actually the longest continuous
path between two nodes in the graph.
So by using the shortest path command, but
returning all possible shortest paths,
we're actually going to get the longest
path included in those results returned.
Now, if we look carefully at this script,
it is a little different
than our previous scripts.
In this case our match command is
matching all nodes of type MyNode.
We'll assign those to the variable end.
We're also matching the all nodes of type
MyNode and assigning that to variable m.
So these matches are the same.
But we want to place a constraint
such that the nodes in n are not
the same as the nodes in m, and
then we want to find all of the shortest
paths between unique nodes in n and m.
And return the names of those nodes as
well as the length of that resulting path.
And the trick is to use
the command order by.
And so for those of you who are familiar
already with SQL query language,
you'll recognize order by.
You'll also recognize the descend command.
So if we order the resulting paths
by their length in descending order,
and only return 1, that path should
actually be the longest path.
And that's equal to
the diameter of the graph.
So when we submit this query,
here's the results that we get.
We get a path between node e and
node l with length severn.
Or maybe it occurs to you that maybe this
is not the only diameter of the graph,
the only path with length of seven.
So we can modify our query just a little
bit and change the limit from one to five.
And we'll see the results.
And sure enough,
we actually get five paths.
And 3 of those have length 7.
So there are actually three
distinct paths which qualify as
a diameter of this particular graph.
So up until now we've been
calculating path length
based on the number of hops between
our beginning node and our end node.
This is roughly equivalent to counting
the number of towns between one town and
another town.
But it doesn't really get at
the value that is usually of
greatest importance to us.
And that is the actual distance between
one location and another location.
Which is found in the values that we've
assigned to the edges between the nodes.
So in this next example, we're going
to perform that kind of a calculation.
So the first two lines of code
we're already fairly familiar with.
We're matching a path between node a and
node c,
where the first node is H,
and the second node is P.
And this third line of code
is also fairly familiar.
We're extracting the names of the nodes
and the path that's been returned, and
we're returning a listing of those
names as well as a length of the path.
All of that is being returned
as the variable pathLength.
We've added a third element
to our return statement, and
that is using the reduce statement.
So what we're doing here is,
the purpose of the reduce statement,
takes a set of values and
reduces them down to a single value.
So in this line of code we begin by
setting a variable s equal to 0.
And then we define a variable E, which
represents the set of relationships in
a path that's returned, or
in other words, the edges.
And we pass that into this variable s,
and add to it,
the value of the distance that
we've assigned to that edge.
So we're performing
an aggregate calculation.
And returning the final results
to a variable called pathDist.
And we're limiting that
results to a single value.
And so when we do this, we should
get a value that is more indicative
of the actual distance between
our source and our destination.
And so here's the results.
The path itself, as we know,
begins in H and ends in P.
And it has a pathLength of 7,
but it has a pathDist of 39.
So we could interpret this to mean
that even though there are 6 towns
between the source town and
the destination town, or
a pathLength of 7, the actual distance
in miles would be a value of 39.
So with that we can apply
Dijkstra's algorithm.
So here I'm going to match the node with
the name A, and the node with the name P.
And we're going to find the shortest
path in terms of hops from A to P.
And we'll set that equal
to the variable path.
Then we'll perform a reduce command,
and set the variable dist = 0.
And we'll go through, and
sum all of the distances of each
of the edges in our shortest path.
And return that value as a distance.
And we'll also return the path variable.
So remember, this is not the path in
our network with the least weights.
It is the weight of the shortest
path based on numbers of hops.
Now that's an inherent feature of
the shortest path command in Cipher.
So here is the path that's returned.
It's a five node path with four edges and
the total sum of the weights of
those edges sums to a value of 22.
So in our previous query,
we specified that we wanted a match for
the source node and the destination node.
But if I don't specify my destination
node, I can apply Dijkstra's single
source shortest path algorithm
from node A to any other node.
So when we apply this query,
the results displayed consist of
the actual original path from
A to P with a distance of 22.
And we'll see a display of all of
the intermediate paths generated in
the process, all the way down to
a single edge path between A and C.
So just to reiterate, what we've
calculated is the shortest hop path
with the weights added, the sum of
the weights of the edges in that path.
This is not the least weight
path of the entire network.
Okay, so let's switch gears for a moment.
As we learned in one of our previous
lectures, we can extract a subset
of nodes and edges from a particular
graph for various reasons.
Let's say for example that we want
to avoid a particular town or
a particular area where
there might be congestion.
And this would be represented
by one of our nodes.
So we're going to perform a similar
match as we've done in the past,
where we're going to match any node n with
any node m, with a two edge between them.
But we want to apply an additional
constrained in which none of the n nodes
are going to include the node D.
And none of the m nodes are going
to include the node D as well.
And then we'll return the resulting graph.
So when we do that, we get a graph but
looks very much as we might expect.
Very similar to our previous graph,
but it is missing node D, so
it only has ten nodes and
it's now been reduced to ten edges.
So now let's say we want to calculate
the shortest path over there graph that we
just returned in the previous query.
So in this case, we're going to match the
shortest path between node A and node P.
But in the second line, we want to
issue sort of a negative statement
in which the resulting list of
node names that we extract using
the extract statement
cannot contain the node D.
And then we'll return that path and
the length of that path.
So when we issue this command,
here's our resulting path.
It's a five node path of length four.
As we recall from one of our earlier
queries where we were trying to calculate
all of the shortest paths,
we returned two paths.
One path that contained D, and this is
the second path, which did not contain D.
So we can make this a little complicated.
Instead of avoiding a single node in
our resulting path, we're looking for
a graph that doesn't contain the immediate
neighborhood of a specific node.
This means all of the nearest, or
the first neighbors of a specific node.
So in this case we're going
to match the same node D, and
all edges between D, and any other node.
And then we are going to issue
a collect command to collect all of
the distinct neighbors of D.
And we'll apply a constraint to that,
in which the returned
list of neighbors cannot contain
the node with the name D.
Likewise, the neighbors list for
the target nodes,
can also not contain the node D.
And when we submit this command,
we see a network that looks like this.
Five nodes and four edges.
And that seems to makes sense.
Node D isn't in the network,
nor are its first neighbors.
But if you recall the original network,
there may be a peculiar result that you
might find a little bit disconcerting.
So let's look at our original network.
Now here's the node D, and
here are all it's nearest neighbors.
So these are the forbidden
neighbors that we want to
remove from our resulting graph.
And we seemed to have
done that successfully.
These are the five nodes that
are retained in the resulting graph, but
there's a node out here.
The node p, which seems to be neglected or
not handled in the results.
It's not a first neighbor of D.
So it, in some ways arguably should
be returned in our results, but
it's not part of the connected
graph that we saw returned.
This is one area in which Cipher does
not handle these situations by default.
So we'll need to supplement our
query with an additional query.
In this case, the node P was a leaf node,
so we want to make sure that
not only matching the nodes that
conform to these constraints above.
But we also want to include the node or
any nodes which are leaf nodes,
which may also be arguably part of the
results that you expect to be returned.
Now in our network,
we do have one root node,
but it doesn't impact the results
in this particular query.
In the interests of being complete, for
any network, most networks being much more
complex than the one we're working with.
We'd want to take into account not only
those leaf nodes that might be left out,
but also any root notes
that might be left out.
And finally, our last query
example extends the previous query
to find the graph which doesn't
contain a selective neighborhood,
in this case,
the two neighborhood of a particular node.
In this example we're
going to use the node F.
And we want to eliminate all of
the second neighbors of that node.
So initially we match all of those
nodes that are second neighbors of F,
including F itself.
And we'll place those in
a variable called MyList.
Then we go back through the network and
match all of the nodes and
edges, where the source nodes are not
part of the nodes in the MyList and
the target nodes are not
contained in MyList.
And then we return those nodes and edges.
And here's the resulting graph.
It does not contain F or
its first or second neighbors.
If we scroll down to look at the original
graph, here's node F, nodes H,
J, C, A and L are all the first and
second neighbors of F.
So those should be eliminated from the
graph that gets returned from our results.
And sure enough,
this subset of nodes represents the
results that were returned from our query.
It consists of nodes B, D, E, G, and P.
And so this concludes our review
of some of the more advanced
path analytics queries.
We were using a simple network, but
we're providing additional data
sets that are much larger and
present a more realistic challenge
in applying pathanalythics queries.
Hello everyone and welcome to this week's
module on graph analytics with Neo4j
using the Cypher query language.
I'm Jeff Sale and I'll be your
instructor for this series of lessons.
I've been an instructional designer at
the San Diego Supercomputer Center for
more than ten years, but I've also had
a passion for scientific visualization and
visual analytics in one form or
another for over two decades.
And I'm very excited about this
opportunity to introduce you to this
free and very powerful graph
analytics tool called Neo4j.
First we realized that many of you
may not have the systems capable of
pushing the boundaries of
Neo4j's performance limits.
Plus the fact that many of you are fitting
this course into your already busy
schedules means we'll be working with data
sets, which will load into Neo4j and can
be analyze in a reasonable length of time,
on the order of minutes not hours or days.
However you can be sure that Neo4j
is capable of processing and
analyzing extremely complex graph networks
consisting of millions of nodes and
relationships.
This module consists of a series of
hands-on demonstrations with Neo4j,
which begin with examples of
some basic cypher queries
that soon progress to some of
the more advanced cypher queries.
We'll begin by using a relatively simple
graph representing a road network, but
we'll also use much larger and
more complex data sets,
including sociological data on
global terrorist groups and
genetics data on associations and
interactions between genes.
These data sets are in fact sub
sets of much larger data sets and
we're making both of the sub sets and
complete data sets available for download.
Once you become comfortable working
with the smaller data sets,
we encourage you to explore
the larger sets on your own.
Finally you'll notice that each
video is accompanied by a text file
containing all of the code used
in the video demonstrations.
These files include dozens of sample
scripts, written in cypher, designed to
make it easy for you to learn, not only
basic cypher cards, but also queries which
focus on more advanced methods such
pathenoids and connectivity analytics.
When you're finished with this module
you'll be able to write cypher scripts to
import and
analyze your own data using Neo4j.
So thank you for
enrolling in this course and let's get
started doing some real graph analytics
with Neo4j and the Cypher query language.
A parallel computation is at
the heart of big data computing.
However, to specify what becomes parallel,
we usually think of a conceptual model
of parallel computation often called,
a programming model.
A parallel programming model is
a way to specify abstractly,
how a parallel program will run.
Naturally for a program to be parallel,
there must be a number of
concurrently operating processes.
But how do these processes communicate and
exchange data?
How do they decide,
when to communicate with each other?
Further, what exactly is done in parallel?
To think of the first question.
Two processes communicate
data by sharing memory.
Indeed, there are architectures in which
all memory in multiple machines can be
made to virtually look like,
one large addressable memory space.
However, two processes,
we also communicate by passing
messages to one another.
Either, directly from one
process to another, or
through a common message carrying pipe,
often called a message bus.
The second question can
also have multiple answers.
Two of the most common ways of achieving
parallelism are pass parallelism and
data parallels.
In task parallelism, a large task can
be decomposed into multiple sub-tasks,
each of which can be run concurrently.
In data parallelism, the data can be
partitioned into many smaller fragments
and operation can run on each partition,
independent of the others.
Typically, these partial operations
have then synchronized and
partially process data combined
to produce a full answer.
Many parallel data management systems,
operate a partition due
to parallel manner.
We need to remember that task
parallelism is somewhat independent of
data parallelism.
And it is possible to have both problems
of parallelism in a programming model.
It is important to emphasize
the issue of a programming model,
should be not be confused with
the issue of a programming language.
A programming language is independent
of the programming model.
And therefore,
a programming model can be implemented
in several different languages.
As I mentioned, the programming model
we are going to consider is BSP.
BSP wasn't initially created for
graph computation.
It was thought of as
a parallel computing model,
that will bridge the gap between software
models of parallel computation, and
hardware capabilities for
supporting parallelism.
The basic idea of BSP is as follows.
There are number of processors.
Each processor can perform local
computation, using its own local memory.
There's a router, which can serve to pass
a message from any processor to any other.
When one pair of nodes
are exchanging messages,
another third node can
still perform computation.
There's a facility that can
synchronize the state of
all auto-substative processes.
This synchronize may either
happen periodically,
at intervals of L time units or
there may be another way of specifying,
when this synchronization
is going to happen.
But when it does, all processors affected
by it, will come to a consistent state.
When synchronization is performed,
a fresh round of computation can start.
We call this.
Synchronization point.
Barrier synchronization.
Because all executed processes
must reach this barrier point,
before the next step of
processing can continue.
A BSP program is broken up into
a sequence stop supersteps.
In each superstep, each processor
will get the data, if needed.
Performance computation if needed and
then, exchange data
with the right partner.
Once all the nodes are done,
the system helps to synchronize.
Then, the next round starts.
Each processor can determine,
if it needs to compute or exchange data.
If not, it will make itself inactive.
If required later, a processor can
be woken up to be active again.
When all processors are inactive,
the computation stops.
In applying BSP model to graphs,
we make a few assumptions.
We assume that a processor
is synonymous with a vertex.
So for
a processor can only send messages to or
receive from, its neighboring processes.
We also assume, a vertex has an ID and
possibly a complex value.
And an edge,
we also have an idea and fact.
Each vertex knows,
which edges it's connected to.
We cannot think of a computation
as a vertex centered task.
We shall [INAUDIBLE] what this means.
In a now famous paper from Google.
This programming model was called,
think like a vertex.
Well to think like a vertex,
we need to know what a vertex can do.
Here's a list of actions,
a vertex can take.
The first one is easy.
A vertex can find its own identifier.
The second operation is to get or
set the value of the node.
This operation may be a little involved,
if the value is a complex data object.
For our purposes,
we'll assume the value is a scalar.
Next, a node can ask for
its own edges, the result of
the operation is a set of edge objects.
A node may also count its edges.
Since we are referring to
outgoing edges throughout,
this is the out degree of the vertex.
Recognize that,
this means a vertex does not natively
have access to its incident notes.
However, it does have control
of the outgoing edges.
So it can get inside the edge values.
There may be two different
ways of specifying an edge.
The edge we have an ID
that the node can get.
Passively, more commonly, an edge is
identified the vertex of targets.
So in our diagram V1 lasts for
the edge, targeting V4.
So in the situation like v3 and v5, we're
there are multiple edges between v3 and
v5, the source v3 can ask for
the values of all edges going to v5.
The operate operation can add or
remove an edge of a vertex.
Finally, since the vertices are processes,
they can start or stop computing.
Typically a node wakes up, if it
receives a message from another node.
Now in comparison to a vertex,
an edge can do far less.
It can get its own ID if the system
allows edge ID's, it can set and
retrieve its own values, and it can get
the ID of the node its pointing to.
That's it.
Now, we still have not defined,
how to think like a vertex.
That's what we'll do next,
using an example that we have
seen several times before.
It's Dijkstra's single source
shortest path, SSSP, algorithm.
We have seen this algorithm before.
But now, we'll show how to compute
it in a parallel setting using BSP.
Here is the edge value,
that's the weight of the edge.
This is known before the algorithm starts.
Each vertex,
runs the exact same routine concurrently.
Each vertex asks.
1, is it super step zero?
2, if yes,
then if this is a source vertex,
it sets the value to zero.
Else, it sets the value to infinity,
which is a large number.
The source vertex,
propagates its edge value to the nodes
at the other end of the edges.
Just the source vertex.
All other vertices are quiet.
The propagation process works like this.
A vertex gets its own value,
which for the source vertex is zero.
It gets its edges, for each edge,
it gets the value of the edge,
adds it to its own value and sends
the result to the end point of the edge.
The blue numbers indicate
that the messages are sent.
All vertices go to halt.
That is, they now have hit
a synchronization barrier.
Notice, that the receiving nodes
do not look at the messages yet.
It's the system's job to ensure that
the messages are available to these nodes
at the next superstep.
All nodes who have received messages
wake up and read the messages.
If a node receives multiple messages,
it picks the minimum.
In our case, the two active nodes
have received only one value each.
We have for the sake of convenience,
colored the processed edges in yellow.
This is just for
visualization purposes in this example.
Now, it compares this band for
a minimum value, to its own value.
And if its own value is greater, it sets
its own value with the minimum value.
In our case, both notes set their value
to that, of the incoming message.
The same propagation routine works again.
So, each note completes the new distance.
And sends the message along an edge
to the other endpoint, then halts.
The same step is repeated
in the next superstep.
At this point,
the nodes have updated their values.
The node with the value 6,
has received our message,
just along one of the three edges on it.
Continuing.
At the end of superstep 2,
all nodes are ready to receive messages
from all their incident edges.
The node with a value 6, received a value
which is lower than its current value.
Now the active nodes,
have no more messages to send.
So each vertex, votes to halt.
The vertex ID and the value
are read out from each vertex, and
then the process starts.
If these nodes are in different
machines of a cluster,
the system will rely on
the underlying platform like YARN.
Or sparks underlying
infrastructure to ensure,
that the edges going across machines can
send and receive messages effectively.
This should give you a sense of the speed
of this process for a large scale network.
As we said earlier,
while the Giraph paradigm implements BSB,
it must also be pragmatic.
One such point of pragmatism is
the computation of aggregate values.
In the think like a vertex paradigm,
operations local to a vertex can
be performed in parallel, and
each vertex only has to work
with its immediate neighborhood.
This is very useful, but
it isn't sufficient at times.
For example, we need to know and use
the total number of edges in the graph.
This will be computed by adding
edges connected to each vertex, but
once aggregated,
it does not belong to any specific vertex.
So whom does this vertex
send the aggregate to?
Also suppose, a vertex creates some
edges as part of its compute step.
When does this information get sent out?
Let's answer the first question first.
The class in charge of these aggregates
is called the DefaultMasterCompute class.
This class specializes MasterCompute.
How does the DefaultMasterCompute
relate to the basic vertex computation?
We have seen that all vertex programs are
created by first defining a vertex class.
This class has a compute function that
performs like the think like a vertex
logic.
Now let's add to it a basic vertex
function and an aggregate function.
Now this function, for
our example of all the total number
of aggregate edges looks like this.
The name of the function is aggregate.
As you can see in yellow, it just gets
the number of edges off this vertex.
What's a little strange is that the first
argument of this aggregation has
an id of something whose
name is total number edges.
What really happens is as follows.
The defaltMasterCompute class, which
is in charge of this global aggregate
operations, is specialized
by your aggregate class.
This class has an ID, and
the aggregator gets registered with
Giraph's defaultMasterCompute class.
The ID we saw before refers to your
registered aggregator's classes ID.
The MasterCompute class performs
the centralized computation between
supersteps.
This class is initiated
on the master node and
will run every superstep
before the workers do.
Communication with the workers
should be performed via aggregators.
The values of the aggregators
are broadcast to the workers before
the vertex compute is called.
And collected by the master before
the master compute is called.
This means the aggregator values
used by the workers are consistent
with the aggregator values from
the master from the same superstep.
And the aggregator used by
the master are consistent
with the aggregator values from
the workers from the previous superstep.
Now let's go back to the big picture for
a second.
Giraph is a big data software.
Why not implement the Giraph system
with a set of MapReduce jobs?
Too much disk requirement.
No in-memory caching.
Every superstep becomes a job.
So all intermediate steps
are written to files, and
that is not a very scalable solution for
iterative operations.
However, it will be incorrect
to think that Giraph works
only in an in memory process.
It can always have less
memory than it needs.
There are two broad categories of
what's called out-of-core computation.
The first situation occurs when the graph
is really large compared to the capacity
of the cluster it's running on.
Each worker stores the vertices assigned
to it inside a set of partitions.
Inside a partition are a subset of
vertices together with their data.
During a superstep, the worker node
processes multiple partitions
concurrently, one per thread.
If a graph is large, then not all
partitions are stored in memory.
Typically only N partitions
are kept in memory at all times and
the rest of the partitions
are swapped into disk.
The second situation occurs when
the number of messages becomes high.
Normally, vertices are processed
in the order of their IDs.
A large number of messages
is handled by creating
temporary message stores which
are sorted by their destination IDs.
All messages going to the same
vertex are placed together.
To do this, messages are sorted
in memory periodically.
The message store files
are accessed based on
which vertices are being
processed at this moment.
This whole system is managed by
Giraph's out of core message processor.
In this lesson, we'll talk about
two dominant systems developed for
large scale graph processing.
The first one, called Giraph,
is from Apache and
implements a BSP model on Hadoop.
The second system is called Graphx,
is developed on the Spark platform,
which as you know, emphasizes on
interactive in memory computations.
While BSP is a popular
graph processing model,
the actual implementation of
BSP in an infrastructure needs
additional programmability beyond
what we have discussed so far.
In Giraph, several additional capabilities
are added to make it more practical.
A thorough coverage of the Giraph platform
is beyond the scoop of these lectures.
However, we'll touch upon
a few of these capabilities.
We'll first consider graph IO,
that is how graphs can come into a system
represented inside the system, and
when completed are written out.
Next, we'll describe how Giraph
interacts with external data sources.
Some of these data sources
use a different data model,
other sources include databases.
Once a graph is imported,
it is important to make sure that
the system runs efficiently.
We will look at a method that uses a
special kind of global aggregate operation
which saves time by reducing
the amount of messaging
to compute aggregate functions
like sum and products.
Finally, we'll recognize that
even if Giraph is designed for
performing iterative,
in memory computation,
there are times where it is absolutely
necessary to store data on disk.
We'll briefly touch upon Giraph's
ability to handle out of core graphs and
out of core messages.
A graph can be written in many ways.
For Neo4J, we saw how graphs can be
important to the database from a CSV file.
In Giraph, two of the most common input
formats are Adjacency List and Edge List.
For an Adjacency List,
each line has the node ID, a node value
which is a single number here, and
a list of destination, weight pairs.
Thus, in line one,
A has a value of 10 and 2 neighbors B and
F with edge weights 2 and 5, respectively.
Since G has no outgoing edge,
the adjacency list is empty.
The current way of representing
graphs is in terms of triplets.
Containing the source and destination
nodes followed by an [INAUDIBLE].
Notice the way we have shown it here.
And the node values is not represented.
Let us simplify the Adjacency List
representation of it.
We remove the colons, commas, braces, and
parenthesis, and
get a space separated set of lines.
One line for each vertex.
We further replace the node IDs A,
B, C, etc., with 1, 2, 3, etc.,
so that these IDs are integers.
So what do we need to specify
to parse this for Giraph?
One, the graph is a text subject and
not, let's say, a database subject.
Two, it is a vertex based representation,
each line is a vertex.
This splitter here is a space.
The idea of the node is a first value for
each line.
The value is a second token.
The next pair of items you find an edge
with the target and the weight,
respectively.
And lastly, there is a list of these
pairs until the end of the line.
Therefore, each line would typically
lead to the creation of both notes and
a set of edges.
This shows a typical reader formula
decency matrix written in Java.
Again, you don't have to know Java
to get the elements of this program.
Our reader is clearly customized for
your specific input.
Very often the starting point is
a basic reader provided by Giraph.
Like the reader that knows how to read
vertices from each line of a text swipe.
To customize it, you extend it and
create your own version.
Now, you need to define
how to get the ID and
value of the vertex by writing
separate message for them.
Notice that the ID comes from
the zeroth item of each line after
the split by white space, and
the value comes from the next open,
the second term, marked by 1 for
the 0 base of the light.
The next code element is this block here.
This specifies how to create edges
by iterating through every line.
To keep the short, we'll remove
the part that gets the edges here.
As Giraph as mature it has
included many specialized
to interoperate with compatible resources.
This diagram is from Giraph where
the show some of these sources.
We can group them into
three different categories.
Group one interoperates with Hive and
HBase.
You possibly remember these
systems from a prior course.
These systems are designed to give
a higher level of data access on
interface on top of MapReduce.
Group two accesses relational
systems like MySQL and Cassandra.
But these systems have accessed indirectly
through a software module called Gora.
Gora uses a JSON schema to map
the relation schema of the SQL database
to a structure that Giraph can read.
Group three accesses graph
databases like Neo4J and DEX,
which is now called Sparksee.
These systems are all taxes indirectly.
Using the [INAUDIBLE]
service of Tinkerpop.
Which is a graph API layer that can use
many different Giraph stores including
[INAUDIBLE] graph and Titan.
Consider a relational
table stored in Hive.
The table shown here is extracted
from the bio grid data source that
we mentioned in module two.
Each row of the table represents
a molecule interaction.
We can create a network from here just
by considering the first two columns.
The first column represents the source
node of an edge colored red.
And the second column represents
the target node of the edge colored blue.
The label on the edge comes from
the fifth column of the table
which is a black bold font.
Let's assume that these predict items,
these are items that we want to
pick up from the Hive table.
The simplest way to get a record from hive
to Giraph is to extend the class
called SimpleHiveRowToEdge.
For this class, we need to specify
the source node, the target node, and
the edge value using three
methods as shown here.
My extension is called MyHiveRowToEdge.
It shows the implementation of these
methods where we just pick up the first,
second, and fifth columns,
as we described before.
Now, as mentioned before,
Giraph interacts with Neo4J through
the Gremlin API provided by Tinkerpop.
One can think of Gremlin as
a traversal API, which means,
it allows one to start from some node and
walk the graph step by step.
To show this,
consider disease gene graph on the right.
Let's call this graph G.
So g.V represents all the vertices of G.
Therefore g.V has name
MC4R selects the node that
has a property called
name whose value is MC4R.
Let's add to this path the condition .out,
which chooses the out
edges of the MC4R node and
then traverses the associatedWith edge
to the orange node called obesity.
For this call, returns the vertex only.
Now, adding the path to values
means gives us obesity.
We can also expand differently
from the obesity node.
When we say inV() we refer
to all nodes that have
incoming edges to the current node.
In this case, there is only one.
The LEPR node.
To this, we add the traversal out beam and
thus we get back the out going edge from
the LEPR node highlighted in together.
We can also look at the Giraph Gremlin
near project connection
from Tinkerpop's viewpoint.
Tinkerpop is trying to create
a standard language for graph reversal,
just like Neo4J is trying to create Open
Cypher as a standard query language for
graph databases.
In trying to create the standard,
Tinkerpop recognizes that the actual
storage management for graph databases
should be provided by another vendor.
The vendor needs to implement
the Gremlin API for access.
Similarly for graphic processing,
including expensive analytic operations
should be performed by what
they call a graph computer.
This is the role played by
Giraph as well as Spark.
Both of which interface with Tinkerpop.
Next, we'll count the number of
vertices and edges, define a min and
max function for Spark's reduce method,
computer the min and max degrees,
and compute the histogram data
of the degree of connectedness.
In this hands on,
we will cover the degree distribution of
the metros graph from
the first hands on exercise.
This will help you practice finding
the degrees of connectedness in a graph.
These numbers will be used for
plotting the visualizations in
the next hands on exercises.
The degree of a vertex is
the number of edges or
connections the vertex has to
other vertices in the graph.
In directed graphs,
each vertex has an in degree,
the number of edges
directed to the vertex.
In and out degree, the number of
edges directed away from the vertex.
The metros graph is an example
of a directed graph.
Each metropolis vertex has one
outgoing edge to a country vertex.
Each country vertex has one or more
incoming edges from metropolis vertices.
This will be a quiz question.
Starting again where we left off from
the previous hands-on exercise, first,
ensure your Cloudera VM is started, and
that you downloaded the dataset
examples of analytics.
The link is in the content for this week.
Use the numEdges attribute to print
the number of edges in metrosGraph.
As you can see the result is 65,
which matches the number of
lines in metro_country.csv.
Now use the numVertices
attribute to print the number
of vertices in metrosGraph.
As you can see the result is 93,
which matches the number of
lines in metro.csv65 plus the number
of lines in country.csv, 28.
Define the max and the min reduce
operation to compute the highest and
lowest degree vertex.
Let us find the vertex with
the most outgoing edges or
the vertex with the largest
out degree by passing the max
function to a reduced operation on
the out degrees of metrosGraph.
The result in this case is vertex
ID five with one outgoing edge.
The result could have been any metropolis
because every metropolis in this graph
has one outgoing edge to its country.
Let us find the vertex with
the most incoming edges, or
the vertex with the largest inDegree.
This is done the same way
as the previous example,
except you'll run the reduce operation
on the inDegrees of metrosGraph.
The result is VertexId 108
with 14 incoming edges.
Apply a filter to the metrosGraph
vertices to find out which vertex is 108.
The answer is the United States.
This means that the United States has
14 metropolises in the metros.csvfile.
We can also compute how many vertices have
one out going edge by applying a filter of
one to the outgoing degrees and
counting the results.
The result is 65 because there are 65
metropolises with one outgoing degree.
None of the countries have
any outgoing degrees.
Let us ignore whether or
not the edge is in or out, and
just find which vertex has the most edges.
Again, we will run the reduce
operation with the max function.
But this time we will run it on
metrosGraph's degrees attribute.
The result is 108 again
with 14 connections.
This means that the United States is
the most connected vertex in metrosGraph.
Finally, let us calculate
the histogram data of the degrees for
the countries in metrosGraph.
First, create a map that
only includes countries.
So create a filter to only include
the vertices with the vertex ID that is
greater than or equal to 100.
Then you will group the map
by the size of the degree and
sort the map from lowest
to highest degree.
The output shows six pairs in an array.
The first number is the number of edges,
and
the second number is the number of
vertices that have that number of edges.
In other words, the result of
the query shows that there are 18
countries with 1 metropolis,
4 countries with 2 metropolises,
2 countries with 3 metropolises,
2 countries with 5 metropolises,
1 country with 9 metropolises, and
1 country with 14 metropolises.
Next, we'll import the GraphX libraries,
import the Vertices, import the Edges,
create a Graph, and use Spark's filter
method to return Vertices in the graph.
Hi, this is Cristine Kirkpatrick,
division director for
Information Technology Systems and
Services at
the San Diego Super Computer Center.
I'll guide you through
the hands-on exercises.
I recommend you follow
along with the video once.
Then, either using the video or
the hands-on reading, go through the
hands-on exercise on your own computer.
This hands-on exercise will show you
how to build a graph using GraphX,
Spark's API for graphs, and
graph-parallel computation.
We'll start with importing the data and
then build a simple graph.
Note that the first four hands on
assignments are meant to be completed
sequentially.
That is, you will need to have your
Cloudera VM running continuously.
If you must shut down your VM and
restart, you will need to run the commands
from this first hands on assignment again.
Otherwise you may receive error messages
because the data has not been imported.
The data references metro areas.
In an effort to disambiguate or
distinguish between metropolitan areas and
an English word also used
to refer to a train or
light rail, when we mean metro
area we will say metropolis.
First, ensure your
cloudera vm is started and
that you've downloaded the data set,
examples of analytics.
The link is in the content for this week.
The download process might name
the zip file something very long.
Copy the examples of analytics.zip
file to the cloudera's home folder.
If the zip file is on the desktop,
simply drag it to the Cloudera's
home folder on the desktop.
If the file is saved elsewhere,
then you will need to navigate
to the folder where it is saved before
dragging it to the Cloudera's home folder.
Open the terminal window by clicking the
terminal icon at the top of the screen.
Use the unzip command to extract the zip
file to the cloudera home directory.
You can copy and
paste the name of the zip file.
Let it extract with the default name,
ExamplesOfAnalytics.
Go into the ExamplesOfAnalytics
directory and
list the contents of
the EOA data directory.
You should see five .csv files and
one .txt file.
In order to access the CSV and TXT files,
we have to first copy the files to HDFS.
Rally HDFS foot command to copy
the EOA data directory to HDFS
then less the contents of
the EOA data directory on HDFS.
Start the spark shell and include the
graph stream and breeze fizz libraries.
Don't worry about copying
the full command from the video.
A text version will be included within
the course reading that contains the full
command for you to copy and paste.
Import the log for j classes and
suppress the notice in info messages.
Import sparks graphx and
rdd classes along with scala source class.
The data set we are going to use in
this hands on is from three files.
The metro.csv file and the country.csv
file contain the vertices for
the graph and
metro underscore country.csv.
contains the edges that make up the
relationships between the metro areas and
the country they belong too.
Before importing any of the CSV files, we
are going to list the first five lines of
each file to verify that
they are indeed CSV files.
Notice that the metric.csv contains an ID,
the metropolis name and the population.
The country.csv file contains
only an ID and the country name.
The metro_country.csv file
contains the metro ID and
the ID of the country that
the metropolis belongs to.
Create a class called PlaceNode to store
the information about the vertices.
Then extend the PlaceNode class
with case classes specifically for
the metro's and the countries vertices.
Create attributes for
the metro class to store the name and
the population from the CSV file.
The country class only needs
an attribute to store the name.
To import the metro.csv file, create
a spark resilient distributive data set or
rdd named metros made up of
a vertex id in the metro class.
An rdd represents an immutable
partition collection
of elements that can be
operated on in parallel.
When the contents of
the .csv files printed,
the line with the column names
started with the symbol #.
So create a filter to ignore any
line that starts with a # so
that the column names
don't import into the RDD.
The .csv files being imported
contain values separated by commas.
So you will need to split each line
in the metro.csv file into rows,
by using a comma as a delimiter.
Map the first row to the vertex ID.
The second row is the metro
name attribute, and
the third row is the population attribute.
You're going to import the country's .csv
feed file the same way as the metro.csv
feed file.
However this time since the ids in both
the metro.csv file and the country.csv
file start with one you will add 100
to the vertex id of the countries.
So that the vertex ids are unique
between both data sets.
If the ids are not unique
that will prevent us from
creating an accurate graph.
This will be on the quiz.
Import the edges into
an RDD named mclinks.
This is done the same way as
the previous two examples.
Remember to add 100 to
the countries vertex ID.
Concatenate the metros and countries
vertices into a single variable and
use GraphX's graph function to
create a graph of the metros and
countries vertices with
the MC links edges.
Let us take a look at
what is in the graph.
Use the vertices and edges attributes
to print five vertices and
five edges from the metros graph.
Query the graph to find
how the metropolises and
the countries are related.
Let us find which country Tokyo is in.
Tokyo has a vertex ID of 1.
Use RDD's filter method to filter
all of the edges in metro's graph
that have a source for text ID of one and
create a map of destination vertex ID's.
The result is 101 which is Japan.
You can verify this by looking at
the metro.csv and country.csv files.
Remember, we added 100 to
the IDs in country.csv.
Now, let us do the opposite and
find all of the metropolises that are in
China which has a vertex ID of 103.
This time we're going to filter
all of the edges in metro's graph
that have a vertex ID of 103 and
create a map of all of the source IDs.
The result is 3,4, 7, 24, and 34.
You can look in metrostats.csv and verify
that those metropolises are in China.
Next, we'll create a new dataset,
join two datasets with JoinVertices,
join two datasets with outerJoinVertices,
and create a new return type for
the joined vertices.
In this hands-on exercise,
we will create a new graph made
up of five airline flights.
The vertices will represent the airports,
and the edges will represent
the departures and the arrivals.
Once the graph has been created
we will add a second dataset
with additional airport information and
practice using GraphX's join methods to
create new graphs by joining the datasets.
We will start a new spark shell session,
so
we will be opening a new terminal window.
Open the new terminal window by
clicking the terminal icon at the top
of the screen.
Start the spark shell.
Import the log for j classes and
suppress the notice and info messages.
Import sparks graphics and rdd classes.
Now we will create the vertices
ourselves from a list.
The list will contain the vertex ID and
the name of the airport.
Now we will create the edges.
The edges will represent a flight
departing from one airport and
arriving at another.
We will set the edge property
to a fake flight number.
Create the flights graph
by joining the vertices and
the edges using graph
flexes graph functions.
Let us explore the graph so far.
Look through each triplet in flights graph
and print the contents of the graph.
We will specify which airport
the flight departs from,
which airport the flight arrives at,
and the flight number.
You'll just put all of
the vertices in the graph.
Now we are willing to create an additional
dataset to store additional information
about each airport.
First, we will create a case class called
airport information with the city and
airport code properties.
Then we are going to create the airport
information vertices from a list
as we did earlier.
We will make sure the vertex ID for
the airport information matches the vertex
ID of the airport defined earlier.
Note, there does not have to be a one
to one relationship between the airport
vertices and
the airport information vertices.
Los Angeles International Airport is
present in the airport vertices, but
it is missing from the airport
information vertices.
The airport information vertices contains
information about airports in London and
Hong Kong.
But we don't have any flights departing or
arriving from those airports.
Let us complete our first join.
A mapping function has to be defined in
order to join vertices with graphics join
vertices method.
We are going to define a map function that
will join the name of the airport from
the airport vertices with the city name
from the airport information vertices.
In order to create a new graph with
the vertices that has the airport name
colon city name.
After the map function in defined,
then we will use the joined vertices
method to create the new graph.
Vertices without a matching value in
the RDD, retain their original value.
Now, print out the vertices
of the new graph.
Notice all of the vertices contain
the airport and city names,
except Los Angeles International Airport,
which retained its original value.
Now we will join the vertices using
GraphX's outerJoinVertices method.
OuterJoinVertices is
similar to JoinVertices,
except that the user-defined map
function is applied to all vertices and
it can change the vertex property type.
Here, we are using the OuterJoinVertices
method to create a new graph where
the vertices contain a property
with the name of the airport and
a property makeup of
the airport information class.
Print the vertices once
the new graph is made.
Notice that the type of the second
vertex property is sum.
This is because
Los Angeles International Airport
does not have a corresponding
vertex in airport information.
Therefore GraphX assigned all of
the properties the sum type so
that all of the vertex
property types are the same.
We can use the get or
else method to assign a default
value if one does not exist.
Now, let us rerun
the outer join vertices but
this time use the get, get or
else method to create an airport
information class with NA as the values
for the city and the airport code.
Print the vertices once
the new graph is made.
Now, the type of the second vertex
property is airport information in
Los Angeles International Airport,
airport information class,
has the properties NA and NA.
Finally, in this last exercise, we will
create a new case class called Airport
that contains property for the name,
city, and code of the airport.
First, we will define the new Airport
case class with the name, city, and
code properties.
Then use the outer join vertices
method to join the data sets, and
create the new graph.
Create a mapping so if the airport has an
airport information vertex, the city and
code are taken from the instance
of the airport information class.
Otherwise, only include the airport name.
Finally, print the vertices
of the new graph.
The new graph has only one vertex property
which is an instance of the airport class.
GraphX has lots of methods for
joining graph datasets.
This hands on example only scratched
the surface of GraphX's power.
Next, we'll create a new graph by
adding the continents dataset,
import the GraphStream library,
import the countriesGraph into
a GraphStream SingleGraph,
visualize the countriesGraph,
and visualize the Facebook graph.
In this hands-on exercise we
will use the GraphStream library
to visualize countries graph.
The metros graph that we have been
working with in the previous exercises.
This time with the continent vertices and
edges added.
Starting again where we left off
from the previous hands-on exercise,
ensure your [INAUDIBLE] has started and
that you've imported the data.
First, in order to make
the graph more interesting,
we are going to import additional
vertices from the continent.csv, and
additional edges from
country_continent.csv to create
a relationship between the country and
the continent it belongs to.
We will show the steps for
importing the datasets, but
we do not cover the steps in detail.
If you aren't sure how to
import a dataset, go back and
view the video called
hands-on building a graph.
Now, we are going to concatenate the
metros, countries, and continents vertices
into a single variable and concatenate
the metros to countries edges, and
countries to continent edges
into another single variable.
Finally, you will create a new
graph called countriesGraph.
Now, import the GraphStream library.
We will not go over in detail how
to use the GraphStream library.
You can review its documentation and
other online resources on your
own if you are interested.
First, create a new instance of
GraphStreams SingleGraph class,
using the countriesGraph.
Next, we will set some attributes for
the graph we are going to visualize,
including setting a style for the graph.
GraphStream uses cascading style sheets or
CSS just like ordinary web pages,
to control the appearance of the graph.
The zip file that you downloaded from
Coursera contain the CSS file that we will
use in this hands-on exercise.
Now, load the countries graph
vertices into the visualization
using GraphStreams add node method.
Notice that we are setting
the style UI.class of each vertex
depending on if the vertex is an instance
of the metro, country or continent class.
Add the edges of country's graph to
the visualization using GraphStreams
add edge method.
Finally, call the display
method to visualize the graph.
The graph will look similar to this.
The small blue dots are the metropolises,
the medium sized red dots
are the countries, and
the large green dots are the continents.
By looking at the clusters
you can easily identify which
continent in the visualization
is Antarctica.
It is the green dot that
has no connections or
it is the least connected
cluster in the network.
I hope your paying attention,
because this will be on the quiz.
The large cluster of dots at the bottom is
Asia because it has the most countries and
metropolises in the graph.
The Asia cluster is the most
connected cluster in the network.
Can you identify which clusters
are the other continents
by looking at the visualization?
Let's look at the visualization
of a much larger dataset,
the Facebook dataset with 90,000 vertices.
You've seen these techniques
before with the metro dataset, but
that graph had only around 90 vertices.
Because we want you to learn the concepts,
not be bogged down with repetitive tasks,
we've supplied this Cloudera file in order
to create the visualization of the graph.
All you need to do is open
a new terminal window.
Go into the examples of
analytic directory and
run the spark shell with
the Facebook.Cloudera file.
Don't worry about copying
the full command from the video.
A text version will be included
within the course reading
that contains the full command for
you to copy and paste.
What do you see?
My first reaction is that
it looks like broccoli.
A green vegetable reviled by many
American children, unjustly.
Social networks are made up of
several clusters of communities or
pockets of people who interact densely
that are brought together by people who
are members of multiple communities.
This interlinking of clusters
gives the social network
a broccoli like shape when visualized.
I hope you heard the last thing I said
because that will be on the quiz.
Next we'll import the BreezeViz library,
define a function to calculate the degree
histogram, calculate the probability
distribution for the degree histogram, and
graph the results.
In this hands on exercise,
we will plot the degree histogram created
in the previous hands on exercise
using the BreezeViz library.
Starting again where we left off
in the previous hands-on exercise,
ensure your is started.
First we will import
the BreezeViz library.
Next, we will define a function to
calculate the degree histogram of Metro's
graph, so we can plot it with BreezeViz.
The definition of the degree histogram
function is nearly identical
to the code from the previous
exercise that helped us create.
The histogram data array.
Now we will calculate the probability
distribution of the vertex degrees over
the whole graph by normalizing the vertex
degree by the total number of vertices so
that the degree probabilities add up to 1.
The output of the first command is 28,
the number of countries in country.csv.
The output of the second command
is an array of numbered pairs.
The first number is the vertex degree,
and the second number is
the probability distribution.
Notice that the sum of all
the probability distributions equals one.
Now we will plot two graphs to
visualize the degree histogram.
The first graph will be a line
graph of the degree histogram and
the second will be
the degree histogram itself.
We will not go over in detail how to use
the BreezeViz library to create graphs.
The project is well documented and there
are many resources online if you want to
explore the BreezeViz library on your own.
For the first graph we will define
the X axis as the vertex degree and
the Y axis as the degree probability.
For the second graph we will
just pass the metro graph
degree attribute to
BreezeViz's histogram function
You should see two graphical
representations of the data.
The bottom one is the histogram.
The top shows the degrees
distribution plotting the histogram.
As we saw in the previous exercise's
array most countries have one metropolis.
Welcome back to the fourth and
final module of the course.
In this module, we'll cover the underlying
principles of large scale graph processing
and the software infrastructure
that supports it.
So, in this module,
you'll learn a programming model for
graph computation and
systems that implement this model.
After this model, you'll be able to
formulate graph analytics computations
in terms of the programming model.
This module will consist of three lessons.
The first lesson, will revisit
the concept of the programming model and
introduce a programming model
called Bulk Synchronous Parallel or
BSP that is designed specifically for
graph oriented computation.
I will discuss two well known versions of
the central idea, Pregel from Google, and
Graphlab from Carnegie Mellon University.
The second lesson,
we'll discuss two software systems,
Giraph that operates on Hadoop,
and GraphX that operates on Spark.
We'll compare the basic architecture
of these two systems and
point out their differences.
The final lesson will show example
computations, using graphics platform.
Since graphics come with Spark,
we've created these examples on the
virtual machine, which you have access to.
The code and
some data sets are available for
those who wish to play with the system.
Now we are going to
introduce you to Graphx,
which we'll primarily cover
as a hands-on presentation.
Graphx was developed by the Amp
lab at UC Berkeley, and
has now become an Apache product.
In this brief introduction, we are using
a few slides from Amp lab presentations.
Like [INAUDIBLE] graphic
uses a property graph model.
That means both nodes and
edges can have attributes and values.
In Graphx, the node properties
are stored in a Vertex Table.
And edge properties
are stored in an Edge Table.
The connectivity information, that is
which edge connects to which nodes,
is stored separately from the nodes and
edge properties.
Since Graphx is based on spark,
whose central information representation
is based on resilient data sets or RDDs.
You may recall that RDDs are typically
in memory information objects.
These objects can be used to perform
an action, which returns a value.
Or they can perform a transformation,
which can produce another RDD.
Graphx is built on special RDDs for
vertices and edges.
Note that VertexIDs are defined
to be unique by design.
VertexRDD A represents a set of vertices
all of which have an attribute called A.
The Edge class is an object with a source
vertex, a destination vertex, and
edge attribute.
The EdgeRDD extends this
basic edge by storing
edges in a columnar format on
each partition of performance.
Very often, it's easier to operate
on a data structure that has both
node properties and edge properties.
If you are familiar with this schema, you
will readily see that this is a three-way
join operation between the node set,
the edge set and the second node set.
Finally, GraphX implements
it's own version of BSP.
This implementation,
not surprisingly, is called Pregel.
It allows a user to write a vertex
program, a send message routine,
and a message combiner routine,
just like BSP.
However, this implementation also performs
vertex partitioning like
we saw in graph lab.
Also, similarly to graph lab,
it enables the message sending computation
to reach the attributes of both vertices.
The code limit shown here
is written in Scala.
The hands on code after this you'll
see are all certain in scatter.
Will have a notice here in no scatter.
We would like to show you
here an example which uses
the Pregel runtime object in GraphX
to implement the simple BSP desk.
We would like to show here how Pregel
runtime objects in Graphx works.
We point out all the functions
that are defined by users
in running the Pregel operation.
The vprogf function,
which takes a vertex and a message and
returns a new attribute value for
that vertex.
The sendMsgr function, which computes
the new message along each edge.
The Option[M] construct says that it is
optional for a vertex to send the message.
That is,
the system should not show an error
if your message is not sent for
the vertex.
The combinef function is
a message combiner that we
mention in passive for graph.
Finally, the user can also specify
the number of reiterations that
the GraphX BSP process will run for.
In 2010, Google
published a paper outlining a system
that they had been working on.
This publication about a system called
Pregel, has been one of the most
influential publications on
large scale graph computing.
The Pregel system essentially implemented
the BSB model that we covered in
the last lecture.
To show how the Pregel
system is programmed,
we present the published code of Google's
most famous algorithm, the PageRank.
Recall that PageRank's task is
to compute note centrality.
The basic philosophy of PageRank is
that a note that is connected to an more
important note gains more importance.
In the filler on the right, B is a very
important node with a high page rank
because a lot of other nodes directly or
indirectly point to it.
So C being his direct neighbor
that receives an edge from B,
also has a high page rank.
All the C itself,
there's not have too many incident edges.
On the left side we have
Google's published C++ code
that implements PageRank method
on the Pregel infrastructure.
You don't have to know C++ to understand
the basic essence of the code.
We will explain the basic elements of
the Vertex program in the next few slides.
Remember from the last lecture
that the VSP technique considers
a vertex to be a process.
Every vertex implements
a method called compute.
This method, implements the logic of what
a vertex should do during the super steps.
The program starts by creating a special
kind of vertex called the PageRank vertex
for which this compute
method is specified.
You will notice that the compute
method starts by saying what happens
when the super step is one or more.
But what happens in super step zero?
Usually, superstep 0 is used for
initialization.
Every vertex, initialization
PageRank value to a same number
which is one divided by the total
number of vertices in the graph.
Computationally, a PageRank of a vertex is
a number calculated by adding two terms.
The first term, depends on the total
number of vertices in the graph, and
is therefore the same every time.
And the second term depends on the page
rank of the neighbors of the vertex.
How does the vertex
compute the second term?
It gets the PageRank values of
the neighbors in its messages,
and adds them up.
As we saw for SSSP,
after a vertex computes its value,
it goes to the propagate step and
sends a message to its outgoing edges.
For PageRank, the message it sends out
is just computed value divided
by the number of outgoing edges.
When this is done, the node halts for
the next superstep, and waits for
some other node to wake it up.
At this point, we have seen two
examples of graph analytic operations
executed on the BSB programming model.
Now, we'll look at the same problem
from a slightly different viewpoint.
GraphLab, originally a project from
Carnegie Mellon University, now turned
into a company called Dato, took a similar
yet different approach to the problem.
In GraphLab, any kind of data can be
associated with a vertex or an edge.
This information is stored in
what is called a data graph.
Let's look at the same
page like I already did.
The syntax is a bit different but
the logical blocks are identical.
These are the same blocks
that we highlighted before.
GraphLab breaks up these blocks into
three different user specified functions
called Gather, Apply,
Scatter, or GAS, for short.
Okay, so what's different?
Let's mention a few important differences.
First, let's consider gather.
Rather than adopting a message passing or
data flow model like Pregel,
GraphLab allows the user defined update
function complete freedom to read and
modify any of the data on
adjacent vertices edges.
In GraphLab, a receiving vertex has
access to the data on adjacent vertices
even if the adjacent vertices did
not schedule the current update.
In contrast, for Pregel the control
is with descending nodes.
An update can happen only when
a node sends out messages.
For some graph analytics operations
like a dynamic version of PageRank,
this is very important.
Further, if vertex can update
its value asynchronously.
That is, as soon as it receives
an update without having to wait for
all nodes like we do in VSP.
This often helps some intuitive algorithms
like page rank converge faster.
When the graph is large and
must be split across machines,
BSP cuts the graph along edges,
as we see on this slide.
So every cut edge results in
a machine to machine communication.
If we increase the number
of across machine edges,
we increase communication cost.
This has an interesting
practical consequence.
As we have mentioned,
many graph applications have communities.
And central nodes that have high degree.
Many young people today have
over 500 Facebook friends.
So when an analytical
operation like Page Rank,
that goes through multiple
iterations until convergence, for
these graphs, the communication
cost can become very high.
In the cluster graph shown here, every
color represents a different machine.
Let's look at that red vertex.
What would happen if we
split it like this instead?
The red node gets split.
And different vertices of different
machines work with their own copy
of the red vertex.
In the diagram,
the primary red vertex is marked zero and
copies are marked one through five.
Now the gather phase happens for
each copy.
Followed by a second operation from
the copies to the primary red vertex.
And this is followed by new user
defined operation called merge
that combines the partial results from
the copies to the primary vertex.
So for PageRank, the merge operation
boils down to computing the total
summation of the partial summation
of the edges computed at the copies.
Thus in this lesson,
we have seen two of the most influential
paradigms of large scale graph
computation when the number of nodes and
edges run into tens of millions and more.