in this short video we ll talk about how meltwater
helped danone using sentiment analysis
meltwater is a company that helps other companies
analyze what people are saying about them and manage their online reputation
one of the case studies on their website is about danone baby nutrition
meltwater helped danone to monitor the opinions through social media for
one of their marketing campaigns
they were able to measure what was impactful and what was not
through such monitoring
meltwater also helped danone manage a potential reputation issue
when a crisis occurred related to horse dna
being in some meat products across europe
while danone was confident that they did not have an issue with their products
having the information a couple of hours before news hit the uk press
allowed them to check and
reassure their customers that their products were safe to consume
you can imagine millions of mothers having been reassured and happy for
danone efforts on this
this is an excellent story about how big data helped manage public opinion
and i am sure meltwater was able to help them to measure the opinion impact through
social media as well
big data is now being generated all around us
so what
it the applications
it is the way in which big data can serve human needs that makes it valued
let look at a few examples of the applications big data is allowing us to
imagine and build
big data allows us to build better models which produce higher precision results
we are witnessing hugely innovative approaches in how companies
market themselves and sell products
how human resources are managed
how disasters are responded to
and many other applications that evidenced based data is being
used to influence decisions
what exactly does that mean
here is one example
many of you might have experienced it i do
data amazon keeps some things i have been looking at
allows them to personalize what they show me
which hopefully helps narrow down the huge raft of options i might get
than just searching on dinner plates
now businesses can leverage technology to make better informed decisions
that are actually based on signals generated by actual consumers like me
big data enables you to hear the voice of each consumer as
opposed to consumers at large
now many companies including walmart and target
use this information to personalize their communications with their costumers which
in turns leads to better met consumer expectations and happier customers
which basically is to say big data has enabled personalized marketing
consumers are copiously generating publicly accessible data through
social media sites like twitter or facebook
through such data the companies are able to see their purchase history
what they searched for what they watched where they have been and
what they are interested in through their likes and shares
let look at some examples of how companies are putting this information to
build better marketing campaigns and reach the right customers
one area we are all familiar with are the recommendation engines
these engines leverage user patterns and product features
to predict best match product for enriching the user experience
if you ever shopped on amazon
you know you get recommendations based on your purchase
similarly netflix would recommend you to watch
new shows based on your viewing history
another technique that companies use is sentiment analysis or in simple terms
analysis of the feelings around events and products
remember the blue plates i purchased on amazon com
i not only can read the reviews before purchasing them
i can also write a product review once i receive my plates
this way other customers can be informed
but more importantly amazon can keep a watch on the product reviews and
trends for a particular product
in this case blue plates
for example they can judge if a product review is positive or negative
in this case while the first review is negative
the next two reviews are positive
since these reviews are written in english using a technique called natural
language processing and other analytical methods
amazon can analyze the general opinion of a person or public about such a product
this is why sentiment analysis often gets referred to as opinion mining
news channels are filled with twitter feed analysis every time
an event of importance occurs such as elections
brands utilize sentiment analysis to understand how customers
relate to their product positively negatively neutral
this depends heavily on use of natural language processing
mobile devices are ubiquitous and
people almost always carry their cellphones with them
mobile advertising is a huge market for businesses
platforms utilize the sensors in mobile devices
such as gps and provide real time location based ads
offer discounts based on this deluge of data
this time let imagine that i bought a new house and
i happen to be in a few miles range of a home depot
sending me mobile coupons about paint shelves and
other new home related purchases would remind me of home depot
there a big chance i would stop by home depot
bingo !
now i would like to take a moment to analyze what kinds of big data are needed
to make this happen
there definitely the integration of my consumer information and
the online and offline databases that include my recent purchases
but more importantly the geolocation data that falls under
a larger type of big data spacial big data
we will talk about spacial data later in this class
let now talk about how the global consumer behavior can be used for
product growth
we are now moving from personalize marketing
to the consumer behavior as a whole
every business wants to understand their consumer s collective
behavior in order to capture the ever - changing landscape
several big data products enable this by developing models to capture user
behavior and allow businesses to target the right audience for their product
or develop new products for uncharted territories
let look at this example
after an analysis of their sales for weekdays
an airline company might notice that their morning flights are always sold out
while their afternoon flights run below capacity
this company might decide to add more morning flights based on such analysis
notice that they are not using individual consumer choices but
using all the flights purchased without consideration to who purchased them
they might however
decide to pay closer attention to the demographic of these consumers
using big data to also add similar flights in other geographical regions
with rapid advances in genome sequencing technology
the life sciences industry is experiencing an enormous draw in biomedical big data
this biomedical data is being used by many applications in research and
personalized medicine
did you know genomics data is one of the largest growing big data types
between 100 million and 2 billion human genomes could be sequenced by year 2025
impressive
this inaudible sequence data demands for
between 2 exabytes and 40 exabytes in data storage
in comparison all of youtube only requires 1 to 2 exabytes a year
an exabyte is 10 to the power 18 bites
that is 18 zeros after 40
of course analysis of such massive volumes of sequence data is expensive
it could take up to 10 000 trillion cpu hours
one of the biomedical applications that this much data is enabling
is personalized medicine
before personalized medicine most patients without a specific type and
stage of cancer received the same treatment
which worked better for some than the others
research in this area is enabling development of methods to analyze
large scale data to develop solutions that tailor to each individual
and hence hypothesize to be more effective
a person with cancer may now still receive a treatment plan that is standard
such as surgery to remove a tumor
however the doctor may also be able to recommend
some type of personalized cancer treatment
a big challenge in biomedical big data applications like many other fields
is how we can integrate many types of data sources to gain further insight problem
in one of our future lectures my colleagues here at
the supercomputer center will explain how he and his colleague have
used big data from a variety of sources for personalized patient interventions
another application of big data comes from interconnected mesh of large
number of sensors implanted across smart cities
analysis of data generated from sensors in real time
allows cities to deliver better service quality to inhabitants
and reduce unwanted affect such as pollution traffic congestion
higher than optimal cost on delivering urban services
let take our city san diego
san diego generates a huge volumes of data from many sources
traffic sensors satellites camera networks and more
what if we could integrate and
synthesize these data streams to do even more for our community
using such big data
we can work toward making san diego the prototype digital city
not only for life - threatening hazards but
making our daily lives better such as managing traffic flow more efficiently or
maximizing energy savings even as we will see next wildfires
if you want to read more here a link to the at kearney report
where they talk about other areas using big data
as a summary big data has a huge potential
to enable models with higher precision in many application areas
and these highly precise models are influencing and transforming business
big data generated by people how is it being used
we listed a number of challenges for
using unstructured data generated by human activities
now let look at some of the emerging technologies to tackle these challenges
and see some examples that turn unstructured data into valuable insights
although unstructured data specially the kind generated by people has
a number of challenges
the good news is that the business culture of today is shifting
to tackle these challenges and take full advantage of such data
as it is often said a challenge is a perfect opportunity
this is certainly the case for big data and
these challenges have created a tech industry of it own
this industry is mostly centered or as we would say layered or
stacked around a few fundamental open source big data frameworks
need big data tools are designed from scratch
to manage unstructured information and analyze it
a majority of these tools are based on an open source
big data framework called hadoop
hadoop is designed to support the processing of large data sets
in a distributed computing environment
this definition would already give you a hint that it tackles the first challenge
namely the volume of unstructured information
hadoop can handle big batches of distributed information but
most often there a need for
a real time processing of people generated data like twitter or facebook updates
financial compliance monitoring is another area of our central time processing is
needed in particular to reduce market data
social media and market data are two types of what we call high velocity data
storm and spark are two other open source frameworks
that handle such real time data generated at a fast rate
both storm and
spark can integrate data with any database or data storage technology
as we have emphasized before unstructured data
does not have a relational data model so it does not generally
fit into the traditional data warehouse model based on relational databases
data warehouses are central repositories of integrated data from one or
more sources
the data that gets stored in warehouses gets extracted from multiple sources
it gets transformed into a common structured form and
it can slow that into the central database for
use by workers creating analytical reports throughout an enterprise
this exact transform load process is commonly called etl
this approach was fairly standard in enterprise data systems until recently
as you probably noticed it is fairly static and
does not fit well with today dynamic big data world
so how do today businesses get around this problem
many businesses today are using a hybrid approach in which their smaller
structured data remains in their relational databases and
large unstructured datasets get stored in nosql databases in the cloud
nosql data technologies are based on non - relational concepts and
provide data storage options typically on computing clouds
beyond the traditional relational databases centered rate houses
the main advantage of using nosql solutions is their ability
to organize the data for scalable access to fit the problem and
objectives pertaining to how the data will be used
for example if the data will be used in an analysis to find connections
between data sets then the best solution is a graph database
neo4j is an example of a graph database
graph networks is a topic that the graph analytics course
later in this specialization we will explain in depth
if the data will be best accessed using key value pairs like a search engine
scenario the best solution is probably a dedicated key value paired database
cassandra is an example of a key value database
these and
many other types of nosql systems will be explained further in course two
so we are now confident that there are emerging technologies for
individual challenges to manage people generated unstructured data
but how does one take advantage of these to generate value
as we saw big data must pass through a series of steps before it generates value
namely data access storage cleaning and analysis
one approach to solve this problem is to run each stage as a different layer
and use tools available to fit the problem at hand and
scale analytical solutions to big data
in coming lectures we will see important tools that you can use
to solve your big data problems in addition to the ones you have seen today
now let take a step back and remind ourselves what some of the value was
remember how companies can listen to the real voice of customers using big data
it is this type of generated data that enabled it
sentiment analysis analyzes social media and other data to find
whether people associate positively or negatively with you business
organizations are utilizing processing of personal data to
understand the true preferences of their customers
now let take a fun quiz to guess how much twitter data companies analyze
every day to measure sentiment around their product
the answer is 12 terabytes a day
for comparison you would need to listen continuously for
two years to finish listening to 1 terabyte of music
another example application area for
people generated data is customer behavior modeling and prediction
amazon netflix and a lot of other organizations
use analytics to analyze preferences of their customers
based on consumer behavior organizations suggest better products to customers
and in turn have happier customers and higher profits
another application area where the value comes in the form of societal impact and
social welfare is disaster management
as you have seen in my wildfire example
there are many types of big data that can help with disaster response
data in the form of pictures and tweets helps facilitate
a collective response to disaster situations such as evacuations through
the safest route based on community feedback through social media
there are also networks that turn crowd sourcing and
big data analytics into collective disaster response tools
the international network of crisis mappers
also called crisis mappers net is the largest of such networks and
includes an active international community of volunteers
crisis mappers use big data in the form of aerial and satellite imagery
participatory maps and live twitter updates to analyze
the data using geospatial platforms advanced visualization
live simulation and computational and statistical models
once analyzed the results get reported to rapid response and humanitarian agencies
in the form of mobile and web applications
in 2015 right after the nepal earthquake crises mappers crowd source the analysis
of tweets and mainstream media to rapidly access disaster damage and
needs and to identify where humanitarian help is needed
this example is amazing and shows how big data can have huge impacts for
social welfare in times of need
you can learn more about this story at the following link
as a summary although there are challenges in working with unstructured
people generated data at a scale and speed that applications demand
there are also emerging technologies and solutions that are being
used by many applications to generate value from the rich source of information
big data generated by people the unstructured challenge
people are generating massive amounts of data every day through their activities on
various social media networking sites like facebook twitter and linkedin
or online photo sharing sites like instagram flickr or picasa
and video sharing websites like youtube
in addition an enormous amount of information gets generated via
blogging and commenting internet searches more via text messages
email and through personal documents
most of this data is text - heavy and unstructured
that is non - conforming to a well - defined data model
we can also consider this data to be content with
occasionally some description attached to it
this much activity leads to a huge growth in data
did you know that in a single day facebook users produce
more data than combined us academic research libraries
let look at some similar daily data volume numbers
from some of the biggest online platforms
it is amazing that some of these numbers are in the petabyte range for
daily activity
a petabyte is a thousand terabytes
the sheer size of mostly unstructured data generated by humans
brings a lot of challenges
unstructured data refers to data that does not conform to a predefined data model
so no relation model and no sql
it is mostly anything that we do not store in a traditional
relational database management system
consider a sales receipt that you get from a grocery store
it has a section for a date a section for
store name and a section for total amount
this is an example of structure
humans generate a lot of unstructured data in form of text
there no given format to that
look at all the documents that you have written with your hand so far
collectively it is a bank of unstructured data you have personally generated
in fact 80 to 90 of all data in
the world is unstructured and this number is rapidly growing
examples of unstructured data generated by people includes texts images
videos audio internet searches and emails
in addition to it rapid growth major challenges of unstructured data
include multiple data formats like webpages images pdfs
power point xml and other formats that were mainly built for human consumption
think of it although i can sort my email with date sender and subject
it would be really difficult to write a program
to categorize all my email messages based on their content and
organize them for me accordingly another challenge of human generated data
is the volume and fast generation of data which is what we call velocity
just take a moment to study this info graphic and observe what happens in one
minute on the internet and consider how much to contribute to it
moreover confirmation of unstructured data is often time consuming and costly
the costs and time of the process of acquiring storing
cleaning retrieving and processing unstructured data can add up to quite and
investment before we can start reaping value from this process
it can be pretty hard to find the tools and
people to implement such a process and reap value in the end
as a summary although there is an enormous amount of
data generated by people most of this data is unstructured
the challenges of working with unstructured data should not
be taken lightly
next we will look at how businesses are tackling these challenges to gain insight
and thus value out of working with people generated data
as we have already seen there are many different exciting applications
that are being enabled by the big data era
as part of my core research here at the san diego supercomputer center
i work on building methodologies and
tools to make big data useful to dynamic data driven scientific applications
my colleagues and i work on many grand challenge data science applications
in all areas of science and engineering including genomics geoinformatics
metro science energy management biomedicine and personalized health
what is common to all these applications is their unique way of bringing
together new modes of data and computing research
let me tell you the one i am passionate
about wildfire analytics
which breaks up into two components
prediction and response
why is this so important
on may 2014 in san diego county where
the instructors of this specialization live and work
there were 14 fires burning as many as nine at one time
which burned a total of 26 000 acres 11 000 hectares
an area just less than the size of the city of san francisco
six people were injured and one person died
and these wildfires resulted in a total cost of
over 60 million us in damage and firefighting
these wildfires can become so severe that we actually call them firestorms
although we cannot control such fire storms
something we can do is to get ahead of them by predicting their behavior
this is why disaster management of ongoing wildfires relies
heavily on understanding their direction and rate of spread
as these fires are a part of our lives
we wanted to see if we can use big data to monitor predict and manage a firestorm
why can big data help
as we will see in this video indeed wildfire prevention and
response can benefit from many streams in our data torrent
some streams are generated by people through devices they carry
a lot come from sensors and satellites things that measure environmental factors
and some come from organizational data including area maps
better service updates and field content databases which archive how much
registers vegetation and other types of fuel are in the way of a potential fire
what makes this a big data problem
because novel approaches and responses can be taken if
we can integrate this many diverse data streams
many such data sources have already existed for quite some time
but what is lacking in disaster management today is a dynamic system
integration of real time sensor networks satellite imagery
near real time data management tools wildfire simulation tools
connectivity to emergency command centers and
all these before during and after a firestorm
as you will see the integration of diverse streams and
novel ways is really what is driving our ability to see new things and
develop predictive analytics which may help improve our world
what are these diverse sources
one of the most important data sources is sensor data streaming in from weather
stations and satellites such sensed data include temperature
humidity air pressure
we can also include image data streaming from
mountaintop cameras and satellites in this category
another important data source comes from institutions
such as the san diego supercomputer center
which generate data related to wildfire modeling
these include past and current fire perimeter maps put together by
the authorities and fuel maps that tell us about the vegetation
and other types of fuel in a fire path
these types of data sources are often static or updated at a slow rate
but they provide valuable data that is well - curated and verified
a huge part of data on fires is actually generated by the public
on social media sites such as twitter which support photo sharing resources
these are the hardest data sources to streamline during an existing fire but
they can be very valuable once integrated with other data sources
imagine synthesizing all the pictures on twitter about an ongoing fire or
checking the public sentiment around the boundaries of a fire
once you have access to such information at your fingertips
there are many things you can do with such data
you can simply monitor it or maybe you can visualize it
but it not until you bring all these different types of data sources together
and integrate them with real time analysis and predictive modeling that you can
really make contributions in predicting and responding to wildfire emergencies
so now i will like you to take a moment and
imagine how big data might help with firefighting in the future
all these streams of data will come together in 3d displays that can show
all the related information along with weather and fire predictions
just like the way tornadoes are managed today
let look at a 2nd example where big data can have a big impact on saving lives
i mean literally saving lives one life at a time
i collaborated with a number of world - class researchers in san diego and
an industrial group who are dedicated to improving human health through research
and practice of precision medicine
what is precision medicine
it is an emerging area of medicine targeted toward an individual person
analysing her genetics her environment her daily activities so
that one can detect or predict a health problem early
help prevent disease and in case of illness provide the right drug
at the right dose that is suitable just for her
very recently the white house and the national institute of health here
in the american have declared it to be a top priority area for research and
development for the next decade
the expected learning outcome of this video is for
you to give example of sensor organizational and
people - generated data used in precision medicine
and explain why the integration of different kinds of data is critical
in advancing healthcare
for any technology to succeed in real life we need
not only a certain level of maturity of the technology itself but a number of
enabling factors including social economic environment market demands
consumer readiness cost effectiveness all of which must work together
why is big data for precision medicine important now
let see
an important aspect of precision medicine is to utilize
an individual genetic profile for his or her own diagnoses and treatment
analyzing the human genome
which holds the key to human health is rapidly becoming more affordable
today cost to sequence a genome is less
than 10 of what it cost just back in 2008
but human genomic data is big
how big
in a perfect world just the three billion letters of your genome
would require about 700 megabytes to store
in the real world meaning the kind of data generated from genome sequencing
machines we need 200gb to store a genome
and it takes now about a day to sequence a genome
we are finally beginning to create more electronic records that can be stored and
manipulated in digital media
most doctors offices and hospitals now use electronic health record systems
which contain all details of a patient visit and lab test
how big is this data
as a quick example the samaritan medical center watertown new york at 294 that
community hospital reported 120 terabytes as of 2013
the data value more than double in just the last two years
so clearly just in a past two years dramatic changes have prepared the health
care industry to produce and analyze larger mounts of complex patient data
to summarize what we have seen so far the key components of these changes are :
reduced cost of data generation and analysis increased availability of cheap
large data storage and they increased digitization of previously paper records
but we need one more capability to advance toward the promised land of individualized
health care practices
we need to combine various types of data produce by different groups in
a meaningful way
let look at this issue from the same point of view as ilka did
with her discussion of how big data can help with wildfire analytics
the key is the integration of multiple types of data sources
data from sensors organizations and people
in the next few slides we look at each of these and
then i will share a story about some of the new and really exciting ways people data
especially has the potential to change healthcare big data landscape
let start with sensor data
sure digital hospital equipment have been producing sensor data for
years but it was unlikely that the data was ever stored or
shared let alone analyzed retrospectively
these were intended for
real - time use to inform healthcare professionals and then got discarded
now we have many more sensors and deployment
and many more places that are capturing and
explicitly gathering information to be stored and analyzed
let just take a new kind of data
that increasingly becoming common in our daily lives
fitness devices are everywhere now
their sales have skyrocketed in the last few years
they are in wristbands watches shoes and vests directly communicating with your
personal mobile device tracking several activity variables like blood pressure
different types of activities blood glucose levels etc at every moment
their goal is to improve wellness
by having you monitor your daily status and
hopefully improve your lifestyle to stay healthy
but the data they generate can be very useful medical information
because this data is about what happens in your normal life and
not just when you go to the doctor
how much data do they generate
the device called fitbit can produce several gigabytes a day
could this data be used to save healthcare costs effect a healthier lifestyle
that a question mark
it safe to guess that this data alone would not drive the dream of
precision medicine
but what if we consider integrating it with other sources of data
like electronic health records or a genomic profile
this remains an open question
this is an open arena for research that my colleagues at scripts are doing
it also a potentially significant area for product and business development
let look at some examples of health related data being generated by
organizations
many public databases including those curated and
managed by ncbi the national center for biotechnology information
had been created to capture the basic scientific data and knowledge for
humans and other model organisms at the different building blocks of life
these databases carry both experimental and computed data that are necessary to
observations for unconquered diseases like cancer
in addition many have created knoweledge - bases
like the geneontology and the unified medical language system
to assemble human knowledge in a machine processable form
these are just a few examples of organizational data sources and
governmental data gathered by health care systems around the world
could also be used as a massive source of information
but really some of the most interesting and
novel opportunities seem likely to come from the area of people generated data
mobile healths apps is an area that is growing significantly
there are apps now to monitor heart rates blood pressure and
test oxygen saturation levels
apps we might say record data from sensors but
are also obviously generated from people
but there is more people generated data that interesting beyond censure
measurements
in 2015 the webby people voice award
went to an app which supports meditation and mindfulness
rather than an electronic sensing device
a human would indicate how many minutes per day they spent meditating
if they interact with the app which reminds them to be mindful
then we have human generated behavior that we could not get from a sensor
there are well over 100 000 health apps today in either itunes or google play
and by some estimates the mobile health app market
may be worth 27 billion dollars by 2017
so really we are just seen the beginning of what data might be generated here
from what is being called human sensors but to really understand where the power
of people generated data might take us in the era of big data for healthcare
let imagine how things stand now
in general a patient goes to see their doctor and
maybe their doctor asks if they have had any side effects from their medications
the accuracy and
hence the quality of data patients provide in this kind of setting is very low
not that it really the patients fault
it might have been days or weeks ago that they experienced something
they may be unsure whether something they experienced was actually a reaction
to then report it
and there might be details about exactly when they took a medication that
are meaningful but they have forgotten it after the fact
today people are self reporting reactions and experiences they are having
we are on twitter on blog sites online support groups
online data sharing services : these are sources of data that we have
never had before that can be used to understand in a far more detailed and
personal rate the impact of drug integrations are responses to certain
if applications were designed to integrate doctor and
hospital records with information on when drugs were taken and
then to further mine social media or collect self reports from patients
who knows what kinds of questions we will be able to answer
or new questions we may be able to ask