in this short video we ll talk about how meltwater
helped danone using sentiment analysis
meltwater is a company that helps other companies
analyze what people are saying about them and manage their online reputation
one of the case studies on their website is about danone baby nutrition
meltwater helped danone to monitor the opinions through social media for
one of their marketing campaigns
they were able to measure what was impactful and what was not
through such monitoring
meltwater also helped danone manage a potential reputation issue
when a crisis occurred related to horse dna
being in some meat products across europe
while danone was confident that they did not have an issue with their products
having the information a couple of hours before news hit the uk press
allowed them to check and
reassure their customers that their products were safe to consume
you can imagine millions of mothers having been reassured and happy for
danone efforts on this
this is an excellent story about how big data helped manage public opinion
and i am sure meltwater was able to help them to measure the opinion impact through
social media as well
big data is now being generated all around us
so what
it the applications
it is the way in which big data can serve human needs that makes it valued
let look at a few examples of the applications big data is allowing us to
imagine and build
big data allows us to build better models which produce higher precision results
we are witnessing hugely innovative approaches in how companies
market themselves and sell products
how human resources are managed
how disasters are responded to
and many other applications that evidenced based data is being
used to influence decisions
what exactly does that mean
here is one example
many of you might have experienced it i do
data amazon keeps some things i have been looking at
allows them to personalize what they show me
which hopefully helps narrow down the huge raft of options i might get
than just searching on dinner plates
now businesses can leverage technology to make better informed decisions
that are actually based on signals generated by actual consumers like me
big data enables you to hear the voice of each consumer as
opposed to consumers at large
now many companies including walmart and target
use this information to personalize their communications with their costumers which
in turns leads to better met consumer expectations and happier customers
which basically is to say big data has enabled personalized marketing
consumers are copiously generating publicly accessible data through
social media sites like twitter or facebook
through such data the companies are able to see their purchase history
what they searched for what they watched where they have been and
what they are interested in through their likes and shares
let look at some examples of how companies are putting this information to
build better marketing campaigns and reach the right customers
one area we are all familiar with are the recommendation engines
these engines leverage user patterns and product features
to predict best match product for enriching the user experience
if you ever shopped on amazon
you know you get recommendations based on your purchase
similarly netflix would recommend you to watch
new shows based on your viewing history
another technique that companies use is sentiment analysis or in simple terms
analysis of the feelings around events and products
remember the blue plates i purchased on amazon com
i not only can read the reviews before purchasing them
i can also write a product review once i receive my plates
this way other customers can be informed
but more importantly amazon can keep a watch on the product reviews and
trends for a particular product
in this case blue plates
for example they can judge if a product review is positive or negative
in this case while the first review is negative
the next two reviews are positive
since these reviews are written in english using a technique called natural
language processing and other analytical methods
amazon can analyze the general opinion of a person or public about such a product
this is why sentiment analysis often gets referred to as opinion mining
news channels are filled with twitter feed analysis every time
an event of importance occurs such as elections
brands utilize sentiment analysis to understand how customers
relate to their product positively negatively neutral
this depends heavily on use of natural language processing
mobile devices are ubiquitous and
people almost always carry their cellphones with them
mobile advertising is a huge market for businesses
platforms utilize the sensors in mobile devices
such as gps and provide real time location based ads
offer discounts based on this deluge of data
this time let imagine that i bought a new house and
i happen to be in a few miles range of a home depot
sending me mobile coupons about paint shelves and
other new home related purchases would remind me of home depot
there a big chance i would stop by home depot
bingo !
now i would like to take a moment to analyze what kinds of big data are needed
to make this happen
there definitely the integration of my consumer information and
the online and offline databases that include my recent purchases
but more importantly the geolocation data that falls under
a larger type of big data spacial big data
we will talk about spacial data later in this class
let now talk about how the global consumer behavior can be used for
product growth
we are now moving from personalize marketing
to the consumer behavior as a whole
every business wants to understand their consumer s collective
behavior in order to capture the ever - changing landscape
several big data products enable this by developing models to capture user
behavior and allow businesses to target the right audience for their product
or develop new products for uncharted territories
let look at this example
after an analysis of their sales for weekdays
an airline company might notice that their morning flights are always sold out
while their afternoon flights run below capacity
this company might decide to add more morning flights based on such analysis
notice that they are not using individual consumer choices but
using all the flights purchased without consideration to who purchased them
they might however
decide to pay closer attention to the demographic of these consumers
using big data to also add similar flights in other geographical regions
with rapid advances in genome sequencing technology
the life sciences industry is experiencing an enormous draw in biomedical big data
this biomedical data is being used by many applications in research and
personalized medicine
did you know genomics data is one of the largest growing big data types
between 100 million and 2 billion human genomes could be sequenced by year 2025
impressive
this inaudible sequence data demands for
between 2 exabytes and 40 exabytes in data storage
in comparison all of youtube only requires 1 to 2 exabytes a year
an exabyte is 10 to the power 18 bites
that is 18 zeros after 40
of course analysis of such massive volumes of sequence data is expensive
it could take up to 10 000 trillion cpu hours
one of the biomedical applications that this much data is enabling
is personalized medicine
before personalized medicine most patients without a specific type and
stage of cancer received the same treatment
which worked better for some than the others
research in this area is enabling development of methods to analyze
large scale data to develop solutions that tailor to each individual
and hence hypothesize to be more effective
a person with cancer may now still receive a treatment plan that is standard
such as surgery to remove a tumor
however the doctor may also be able to recommend
some type of personalized cancer treatment
a big challenge in biomedical big data applications like many other fields
is how we can integrate many types of data sources to gain further insight problem
in one of our future lectures my colleagues here at
the supercomputer center will explain how he and his colleague have
used big data from a variety of sources for personalized patient interventions
another application of big data comes from interconnected mesh of large
number of sensors implanted across smart cities
analysis of data generated from sensors in real time
allows cities to deliver better service quality to inhabitants
and reduce unwanted affect such as pollution traffic congestion
higher than optimal cost on delivering urban services
let take our city san diego
san diego generates a huge volumes of data from many sources
traffic sensors satellites camera networks and more
what if we could integrate and
synthesize these data streams to do even more for our community
using such big data
we can work toward making san diego the prototype digital city
not only for life - threatening hazards but
making our daily lives better such as managing traffic flow more efficiently or
maximizing energy savings even as we will see next wildfires
if you want to read more here a link to the at kearney report
where they talk about other areas using big data
as a summary big data has a huge potential
to enable models with higher precision in many application areas
and these highly precise models are influencing and transforming business
big data generated by people how is it being used
we listed a number of challenges for
using unstructured data generated by human activities
now let look at some of the emerging technologies to tackle these challenges
and see some examples that turn unstructured data into valuable insights
although unstructured data specially the kind generated by people has
a number of challenges
the good news is that the business culture of today is shifting
to tackle these challenges and take full advantage of such data
as it is often said a challenge is a perfect opportunity
this is certainly the case for big data and
these challenges have created a tech industry of it own
this industry is mostly centered or as we would say layered or
stacked around a few fundamental open source big data frameworks
need big data tools are designed from scratch
to manage unstructured information and analyze it
a majority of these tools are based on an open source
big data framework called hadoop
hadoop is designed to support the processing of large data sets
in a distributed computing environment
this definition would already give you a hint that it tackles the first challenge
namely the volume of unstructured information
hadoop can handle big batches of distributed information but
most often there a need for
a real time processing of people generated data like twitter or facebook updates
financial compliance monitoring is another area of our central time processing is
needed in particular to reduce market data
social media and market data are two types of what we call high velocity data
storm and spark are two other open source frameworks
that handle such real time data generated at a fast rate
both storm and
spark can integrate data with any database or data storage technology
as we have emphasized before unstructured data
does not have a relational data model so it does not generally
fit into the traditional data warehouse model based on relational databases
data warehouses are central repositories of integrated data from one or
more sources
the data that gets stored in warehouses gets extracted from multiple sources
it gets transformed into a common structured form and
it can slow that into the central database for
use by workers creating analytical reports throughout an enterprise
this exact transform load process is commonly called etl
this approach was fairly standard in enterprise data systems until recently
as you probably noticed it is fairly static and
does not fit well with today dynamic big data world
so how do today businesses get around this problem
many businesses today are using a hybrid approach in which their smaller
structured data remains in their relational databases and
large unstructured datasets get stored in nosql databases in the cloud
nosql data technologies are based on non - relational concepts and
provide data storage options typically on computing clouds
beyond the traditional relational databases centered rate houses
the main advantage of using nosql solutions is their ability
to organize the data for scalable access to fit the problem and
objectives pertaining to how the data will be used
for example if the data will be used in an analysis to find connections
between data sets then the best solution is a graph database
neo4j is an example of a graph database
graph networks is a topic that the graph analytics course
later in this specialization we will explain in depth
if the data will be best accessed using key value pairs like a search engine
scenario the best solution is probably a dedicated key value paired database
cassandra is an example of a key value database
these and
many other types of nosql systems will be explained further in course two
so we are now confident that there are emerging technologies for
individual challenges to manage people generated unstructured data
but how does one take advantage of these to generate value
as we saw big data must pass through a series of steps before it generates value
namely data access storage cleaning and analysis
one approach to solve this problem is to run each stage as a different layer
and use tools available to fit the problem at hand and
scale analytical solutions to big data
in coming lectures we will see important tools that you can use
to solve your big data problems in addition to the ones you have seen today
now let take a step back and remind ourselves what some of the value was
remember how companies can listen to the real voice of customers using big data
it is this type of generated data that enabled it
sentiment analysis analyzes social media and other data to find
whether people associate positively or negatively with you business
organizations are utilizing processing of personal data to
understand the true preferences of their customers
now let take a fun quiz to guess how much twitter data companies analyze
every day to measure sentiment around their product
the answer is 12 terabytes a day
for comparison you would need to listen continuously for
two years to finish listening to 1 terabyte of music
another example application area for
people generated data is customer behavior modeling and prediction
amazon netflix and a lot of other organizations
use analytics to analyze preferences of their customers
based on consumer behavior organizations suggest better products to customers
and in turn have happier customers and higher profits
another application area where the value comes in the form of societal impact and
social welfare is disaster management
as you have seen in my wildfire example
there are many types of big data that can help with disaster response
data in the form of pictures and tweets helps facilitate
a collective response to disaster situations such as evacuations through
the safest route based on community feedback through social media
there are also networks that turn crowd sourcing and
big data analytics into collective disaster response tools
the international network of crisis mappers
also called crisis mappers net is the largest of such networks and
includes an active international community of volunteers
crisis mappers use big data in the form of aerial and satellite imagery
participatory maps and live twitter updates to analyze
the data using geospatial platforms advanced visualization
live simulation and computational and statistical models
once analyzed the results get reported to rapid response and humanitarian agencies
in the form of mobile and web applications
in 2015 right after the nepal earthquake crises mappers crowd source the analysis
of tweets and mainstream media to rapidly access disaster damage and
needs and to identify where humanitarian help is needed
this example is amazing and shows how big data can have huge impacts for
social welfare in times of need
you can learn more about this story at the following link
as a summary although there are challenges in working with unstructured
people generated data at a scale and speed that applications demand
there are also emerging technologies and solutions that are being
used by many applications to generate value from the rich source of information
big data generated by people the unstructured challenge
people are generating massive amounts of data every day through their activities on
various social media networking sites like facebook twitter and linkedin
or online photo sharing sites like instagram flickr or picasa
and video sharing websites like youtube
in addition an enormous amount of information gets generated via
blogging and commenting internet searches more via text messages
email and through personal documents
most of this data is text - heavy and unstructured
that is non - conforming to a well - defined data model
we can also consider this data to be content with
occasionally some description attached to it
this much activity leads to a huge growth in data
did you know that in a single day facebook users produce
more data than combined us academic research libraries
let look at some similar daily data volume numbers
from some of the biggest online platforms
it is amazing that some of these numbers are in the petabyte range for
daily activity
a petabyte is a thousand terabytes
the sheer size of mostly unstructured data generated by humans
brings a lot of challenges
unstructured data refers to data that does not conform to a predefined data model
so no relation model and no sql
it is mostly anything that we do not store in a traditional
relational database management system
consider a sales receipt that you get from a grocery store
it has a section for a date a section for
store name and a section for total amount
this is an example of structure
humans generate a lot of unstructured data in form of text
there no given format to that
look at all the documents that you have written with your hand so far
collectively it is a bank of unstructured data you have personally generated
in fact 80 to 90 of all data in
the world is unstructured and this number is rapidly growing
examples of unstructured data generated by people includes texts images
videos audio internet searches and emails
in addition to it rapid growth major challenges of unstructured data
include multiple data formats like webpages images pdfs
power point xml and other formats that were mainly built for human consumption
think of it although i can sort my email with date sender and subject
it would be really difficult to write a program
to categorize all my email messages based on their content and
organize them for me accordingly another challenge of human generated data
is the volume and fast generation of data which is what we call velocity
just take a moment to study this info graphic and observe what happens in one
minute on the internet and consider how much to contribute to it
moreover confirmation of unstructured data is often time consuming and costly
the costs and time of the process of acquiring storing
cleaning retrieving and processing unstructured data can add up to quite and
investment before we can start reaping value from this process
it can be pretty hard to find the tools and
people to implement such a process and reap value in the end
as a summary although there is an enormous amount of
data generated by people most of this data is unstructured
the challenges of working with unstructured data should not
be taken lightly
next we will look at how businesses are tackling these challenges to gain insight
and thus value out of working with people generated data
as we have already seen there are many different exciting applications
that are being enabled by the big data era
as part of my core research here at the san diego supercomputer center
i work on building methodologies and
tools to make big data useful to dynamic data driven scientific applications
my colleagues and i work on many grand challenge data science applications
in all areas of science and engineering including genomics geoinformatics
metro science energy management biomedicine and personalized health
what is common to all these applications is their unique way of bringing
together new modes of data and computing research
let me tell you the one i am passionate
about wildfire analytics
which breaks up into two components
prediction and response
why is this so important
on may 2014 in san diego county where
the instructors of this specialization live and work
there were 14 fires burning as many as nine at one time
which burned a total of 26 000 acres 11 000 hectares
an area just less than the size of the city of san francisco
six people were injured and one person died
and these wildfires resulted in a total cost of
over 60 million us in damage and firefighting
these wildfires can become so severe that we actually call them firestorms
although we cannot control such fire storms
something we can do is to get ahead of them by predicting their behavior
this is why disaster management of ongoing wildfires relies
heavily on understanding their direction and rate of spread
as these fires are a part of our lives
we wanted to see if we can use big data to monitor predict and manage a firestorm
why can big data help
as we will see in this video indeed wildfire prevention and
response can benefit from many streams in our data torrent
some streams are generated by people through devices they carry
a lot come from sensors and satellites things that measure environmental factors
and some come from organizational data including area maps
better service updates and field content databases which archive how much
registers vegetation and other types of fuel are in the way of a potential fire
what makes this a big data problem
because novel approaches and responses can be taken if
we can integrate this many diverse data streams
many such data sources have already existed for quite some time
but what is lacking in disaster management today is a dynamic system
integration of real time sensor networks satellite imagery
near real time data management tools wildfire simulation tools
connectivity to emergency command centers and
all these before during and after a firestorm
as you will see the integration of diverse streams and
novel ways is really what is driving our ability to see new things and
develop predictive analytics which may help improve our world
what are these diverse sources
one of the most important data sources is sensor data streaming in from weather
stations and satellites such sensed data include temperature
humidity air pressure
we can also include image data streaming from
mountaintop cameras and satellites in this category
another important data source comes from institutions
such as the san diego supercomputer center
which generate data related to wildfire modeling
these include past and current fire perimeter maps put together by
the authorities and fuel maps that tell us about the vegetation
and other types of fuel in a fire path
these types of data sources are often static or updated at a slow rate
but they provide valuable data that is well - curated and verified
a huge part of data on fires is actually generated by the public
on social media sites such as twitter which support photo sharing resources
these are the hardest data sources to streamline during an existing fire but
they can be very valuable once integrated with other data sources
imagine synthesizing all the pictures on twitter about an ongoing fire or
checking the public sentiment around the boundaries of a fire
once you have access to such information at your fingertips
there are many things you can do with such data
you can simply monitor it or maybe you can visualize it
but it not until you bring all these different types of data sources together
and integrate them with real time analysis and predictive modeling that you can
really make contributions in predicting and responding to wildfire emergencies
so now i will like you to take a moment and
imagine how big data might help with firefighting in the future
all these streams of data will come together in 3d displays that can show
all the related information along with weather and fire predictions
just like the way tornadoes are managed today
let look at a 2nd example where big data can have a big impact on saving lives
i mean literally saving lives one life at a time
i collaborated with a number of world - class researchers in san diego and
an industrial group who are dedicated to improving human health through research
and practice of precision medicine
what is precision medicine
it is an emerging area of medicine targeted toward an individual person
analysing her genetics her environment her daily activities so
that one can detect or predict a health problem early
help prevent disease and in case of illness provide the right drug
at the right dose that is suitable just for her
very recently the white house and the national institute of health here
in the american have declared it to be a top priority area for research and
development for the next decade
the expected learning outcome of this video is for
you to give example of sensor organizational and
people - generated data used in precision medicine
and explain why the integration of different kinds of data is critical
in advancing healthcare
for any technology to succeed in real life we need
not only a certain level of maturity of the technology itself but a number of
enabling factors including social economic environment market demands
consumer readiness cost effectiveness all of which must work together
why is big data for precision medicine important now
let see
an important aspect of precision medicine is to utilize
an individual genetic profile for his or her own diagnoses and treatment
analyzing the human genome
which holds the key to human health is rapidly becoming more affordable
today cost to sequence a genome is less
than 10 of what it cost just back in 2008
but human genomic data is big
how big
in a perfect world just the three billion letters of your genome
would require about 700 megabytes to store
in the real world meaning the kind of data generated from genome sequencing
machines we need 200gb to store a genome
and it takes now about a day to sequence a genome
we are finally beginning to create more electronic records that can be stored and
manipulated in digital media
most doctors offices and hospitals now use electronic health record systems
which contain all details of a patient visit and lab test
how big is this data
as a quick example the samaritan medical center watertown new york at 294 that
community hospital reported 120 terabytes as of 2013
the data value more than double in just the last two years
so clearly just in a past two years dramatic changes have prepared the health
care industry to produce and analyze larger mounts of complex patient data
to summarize what we have seen so far the key components of these changes are :
reduced cost of data generation and analysis increased availability of cheap
large data storage and they increased digitization of previously paper records
but we need one more capability to advance toward the promised land of individualized
health care practices
we need to combine various types of data produce by different groups in
a meaningful way
let look at this issue from the same point of view as ilka did
with her discussion of how big data can help with wildfire analytics
the key is the integration of multiple types of data sources
data from sensors organizations and people
in the next few slides we look at each of these and
then i will share a story about some of the new and really exciting ways people data
especially has the potential to change healthcare big data landscape
let start with sensor data
sure digital hospital equipment have been producing sensor data for
years but it was unlikely that the data was ever stored or
shared let alone analyzed retrospectively
these were intended for
real - time use to inform healthcare professionals and then got discarded
now we have many more sensors and deployment
and many more places that are capturing and
explicitly gathering information to be stored and analyzed
let just take a new kind of data
that increasingly becoming common in our daily lives
fitness devices are everywhere now
their sales have skyrocketed in the last few years
they are in wristbands watches shoes and vests directly communicating with your
personal mobile device tracking several activity variables like blood pressure
different types of activities blood glucose levels etc at every moment
their goal is to improve wellness
by having you monitor your daily status and
hopefully improve your lifestyle to stay healthy
but the data they generate can be very useful medical information
because this data is about what happens in your normal life and
not just when you go to the doctor
how much data do they generate
the device called fitbit can produce several gigabytes a day
could this data be used to save healthcare costs effect a healthier lifestyle
that a question mark
it safe to guess that this data alone would not drive the dream of
precision medicine
but what if we consider integrating it with other sources of data
like electronic health records or a genomic profile
this remains an open question
this is an open arena for research that my colleagues at scripts are doing
it also a potentially significant area for product and business development
let look at some examples of health related data being generated by
organizations
many public databases including those curated and
managed by ncbi the national center for biotechnology information
had been created to capture the basic scientific data and knowledge for
humans and other model organisms at the different building blocks of life
these databases carry both experimental and computed data that are necessary to
observations for unconquered diseases like cancer
in addition many have created knoweledge - bases
like the geneontology and the unified medical language system
to assemble human knowledge in a machine processable form
these are just a few examples of organizational data sources and
governmental data gathered by health care systems around the world
could also be used as a massive source of information
but really some of the most interesting and
novel opportunities seem likely to come from the area of people generated data
mobile healths apps is an area that is growing significantly
there are apps now to monitor heart rates blood pressure and
test oxygen saturation levels
apps we might say record data from sensors but
are also obviously generated from people
but there is more people generated data that interesting beyond censure
measurements
in 2015 the webby people voice award
went to an app which supports meditation and mindfulness
rather than an electronic sensing device
a human would indicate how many minutes per day they spent meditating
if they interact with the app which reminds them to be mindful
then we have human generated behavior that we could not get from a sensor
there are well over 100 000 health apps today in either itunes or google play
and by some estimates the mobile health app market
may be worth 27 billion dollars by 2017
so really we are just seen the beginning of what data might be generated here
from what is being called human sensors but to really understand where the power
of people generated data might take us in the era of big data for healthcare
let imagine how things stand now
in general a patient goes to see their doctor and
maybe their doctor asks if they have had any side effects from their medications
the accuracy and
hence the quality of data patients provide in this kind of setting is very low
not that it really the patients fault
it might have been days or weeks ago that they experienced something
they may be unsure whether something they experienced was actually a reaction
to then report it
and there might be details about exactly when they took a medication that
are meaningful but they have forgotten it after the fact
today people are self reporting reactions and experiences they are having
we are on twitter on blog sites online support groups
online data sharing services : these are sources of data that we have
never had before that can be used to understand in a far more detailed and
personal rate the impact of drug integrations are responses to certain
if applications were designed to integrate doctor and
hospital records with information on when drugs were taken and
then to further mine social media or collect self reports from patients
who knows what kinds of questions we will be able to answer
or new questions we may be able to ask
where does big data come from
the first thing i would like to say before talking about big data
is that it is not new
most of the big data sources existed before but the scale we use and
apply them today has changed
just look at this image of open link data on the internet
i thought this image was so cool
it shows not only there are so many sources of data but
they are also connected
if you want to check it out yourself
we will give you the link at the end of this video
big data is often boiled down to a few varieties of data generated by machines
people and organizations
with machine generated data we refer to data generated from real time sensors in
industrial machinery or vehicles that logs that track user behavior online
environmental sensors or
personal health trackers and many other sense data resources
the large hadron collider generates 40 terabytes of data
every second during experiments
but human generated data we refer to the vast amount of social media data
status updates tweets photos and medias
with organizational generated data we refer to more traditional types of data
including transaction information in databases and
structured data open stored in data warehouses
note that big data can be either structured semi - structured or
unstructured which is a topic we will talk about more later in this course
in most business use cases any single source of data on its own is not useful
real value often comes from combining these streams of big data sources
with each other and analyzing them to generate new insights
which then goes back into being big data themselves
once you have such insights
it then enables what we call data enabled decisions and actions
let now look into these different types of big data in more detail
why is big data generated by machines useful
let go back for a second to our first example for
machine generated big data planes
what is producing all that data on the plane
if you look at some of the sensors that contribute
to the half terabyte of data generated on a plane
we will find that some of it comes from accelerometers that measure turbulence
there are also sensors built into the engines for temperature pressure
many other measurable factors to detect engine malfunctions
constant real - time analysis of all the data collected provides help
monitoring and problem detection at 40 000 feet
that approximately 12 000 meters above ground
we call this type of analytical processing in - situ
previously in traditional relational database management systems
data was often moved to computational space for processing
in big data space in - situ means bringing the computation
to where data is located or in this case generated
a key feature of these types of real - time notifications is
that they enable real - time actions
however using such a capability would require you to approach your
application and your work differently
if you are using an activity tracker you should probably come up with a strategy
for how you will incorporate the usage of these useful gadgets into your lifestyle
just like that if you are planning to incorporate big data driven insights into
your organization you need to define a new strategy and a new way of working
most big data centric businesses have updated their culture to be more real - time
action oriented refining real - time processes to handle anything from customer
relations and fraud detection to system monitoring and control
in addition such volumes of real - time data and analytical operations that need
to take place requires an increased use of scalable computing systems
which need to be a part of the planning for an organizational big data strategy
they see affects of such changes also in scada system
scada stands for supervisory control and data acquisition
scada is a type of industrial control system for remote monitoring and
control of industrial processes that exists in the physical world
potentially including multiple sites many types of sensors
in addition to monitoring and control scada system can be used to define
actions for reduced waste and improved efficiency in industrial processes
including those of manufacturing and power generation public or
private infrastructure processes including water treatment oil and
gas pipelines and electrical power transmission and
facility processes including buildings airports ships and space stations
they can even be used in smart building applications to monitor and
control heating ventilation air conditioning systems like hvac
access and energy consumption
again the management of these processes once the trends patterns and
anomalies are identified in real - time needs to be decided in the big data case
as a summary as the largest and fastest type of big data machine generated
data can uniquely enable real - time actions in many systems and processes
however a culture shift is needed for its computing and real - time action
big data generated by machines
it everywhere and there a lot
do big planes require big data
absolutely !
did you know that a boeing 787 produces
half a terabyte of data every time it flies
really almost every part of the plane updates both the flight and
the ground team about its status constantly
where all this data coming from
this is an example of machine - generated data coming from sensors
if you look at all sources of big data
machine data is the largest source of big data
additionally it is very complex
in general we call machines that provide some type of sensing capability smart
have you ever wondered why you call your cell phone a smartphone
because it gives you a way to track many things
including your geolocation and connect you to other things
so what makes a smart device smart smart
generally speaking there are three main properties of smart devices
based on what they do with sensors and things they encapsulate
they can connect to other devices or
networks they can execute services and collect data autonomously
that means on their own they have some knowledge of the environment
the widespread availability of the smart devices and their interconnectivity
led to a new term being coined the internet of things
think of a world of smart devices at home in your car in the office
city remote rural areas the sky even the ocean
all connected and all generating data
let look at an example of a device that has some of these things in it
an activity tracker is a device or application for monitoring and
tracking fitness - related metrics such as distance walked or run
calorie consumption and in some cases heartbeat and quality of sleep
what if everyone in new york city wore an activity tracker
what if everyone wore several
i personally have three activity trackers that i use on a daily basis
one to track my sleep another one to track my physical activity and
a third my smartphone that goes everywhere with me
so it is not that unusual to imagine that this will be the case for many people
as you have already heard from in a previous lecture on personalized data
such activity trackers have enabled a new way
of doing patient intervention via personalized medicine
similarly the sensors in planes have generated a new way of looking at
fleet management and flight safety
as a summary machines collect data 24 7 via
their built - in sensors both at personal and industrial scales
and thus they are the largest of all the big data sources
organization - generated data
benefits come from combining with other data types
how are some organizations benefiting from big data
let look at real world examples to see the advantages these organizations
are getting out of big data
one of these companies is ups
ups delivers 16 million shipments per day
they get around 40 million tracking requests
that huge
an estimate of how much data ups has on its operations is 16 petabytes
can you guess how much money ups can save by reducing each driver route
by just one mile
if they can reduce distance traveled by each truck by even one mile
ups can save a whopping 50 million american per year
this is where big data steps in
utilizing complex optimization over large datasets
can lead to route optimizations that were previously not visible to the company
big data together with smart processing
enables ups to manage thousands of route optimizations
let travel from package delivery to the retail domain
an organization from the retail shopping domain
that heavily utilizes big data is walmart
walmart is a big organization that gets 250 million customers in 10 000 stores
did you know they collect 2 5 petabytes of data per hour
they collect data on twitter tweets local events local weather
in - store purchases online clicks and
many other sales customer and product related data
they use this data to find patterns such as which products are frequently
purchased together and what is the best new product to introduce in their stores
to predict demand at the particular location
and to customize customer recommendations
overall by leveraging big data and
analytics walmart has maintained its position as a top retailer
ups and walmart examples were just two out of a number of companies using big data
big data is producing results for companies in all sectors
studies forecast spending on big data technologies to go up
drastically in the next five years
a study by bane and company suggests that early adopters of big
data analytics have gained a significant lead over the rest of the corporate world
for graphics referenced here
we see that companies that use analytics are twice as likely
to be in the top quartile of financial performance within their industries
five times as likely to make decisions much faster than market peers
three times as likely to execute decisions as intended
and twice as likely to use data very frequently when making decisions
this points to the growth and demand of people and
technology centered around or specializing in big data applications
as a summary organizations are gaining significant benefit from integrating
big data practices into their culture and breaking their silos
some major benefits to organizations are operational efficiency improved marketing
outcomes higher profits and improved customer satisfaction
big data generated by organizations structured but often siloed
the last type of big data we will discuss is big data generated by organizations
this type of data is the closest to what most businesses currently have
but it considered a bit out of fashion or
traditional compared to other types of big data
however it is at least as important as other types of big data
so how do organizations produce data
the answer to how an organization generates data
is very unique to the organization and context
each organization has distinct operation practices and
business models which result in a variety of data generation platforms
for example the type and source of data that a bank gets is very different from
what a hardware equipment manufacturer gets
some common types of organizational big data come from commercial transactions
credit cards government institutions e - commerce banking or
stock records medical records sensors transactions clicks and so on
almost every event can be potentially stored
organizations store this data for current and
future use as well as for analysis of the past
let say you are an organization that collects sales transactions
you can use this data for pattern recognition to detect correlated products
to estimate demand for products likely to go up in sales and
capture fraudulent activity
moreover when you know your sales record and can correlate it
with your marketing records you can find which campaigns really made an impact
you are already becoming a data savvy organization
now think of bringing your sales data together with other
external open public data such as major world events in the news
you can ask was it savvy marketing or
a consequence of external events that triggered your sales
using proper analytics
you can now build inventories to match your predicted growth and demand
in addition organizations build and apply processes to record and
monitor business events of interest such as registering a customer
manufacturing a product or taking an order
these processes collect highly structured data
that include transactions reference tables and
relationships as well as the metadata that sets its context
usually structured data is stored in relational database management systems
however we call any data that is in the form of
a record located in a fixed field or file structured data
this definition also includes spreadsheets
as i have mentioned before traditionally this type of
highly structured data is the vast majority of what it managed and
processed in both operational and business intelligence systems
let look at the sales transaction data in our previous example
if you look at the data in the relational table on the right
as the name structured suggests
the table is organized to store data using
a structure defined by a model
each column is tagged to tell us what data that column intends to store
this is what we call a data model
a data model defines each of these columns and
fields in the table and defines relationships between them
if you look at the product id column you will see that it includes only
identifiers that can potentially be linked to another table defining these products
the ability to define such relationships easily make structured data
or in this case relational databases highly adopted by many organizations
there are commonly used languages like sql
the structured query language to extract data of interest from such tables
this is referred to as querying the data
however it could even be a challenge to integrate such structured data
this image shows us a continuum of technologies to model
collect and query unstructured data coming from software and
hardware components within an organization
in the past such challenges led to information being stored
in what we call silos even within an organization
many organizations have traditionally captured data at the department level
without proper infrastructure and policy to share and integrate this data
this has hindered the growth of scalable pattern recognition
to the benefits of the entire organization
because no one system has access to all data that the organization owns
each data set is compartmentalized
if such silos are left untouched organizations risk having outdated
unsynchronized and even invisible data sets
organizations are realizing the detrimental outcomes of this rigid
structure
and changing policies and infrastructure to enable integrated processing of
all data to the entire organization benefit
cloud - based solutions are seen as agile and
low capital intensive solutions in this area
as a summary while highly structured organizational data is very useful and
trustworthy and thus a valuable source of information
organizations must pay special attention to breaking up
the silos of information to make full use of its potential
the key integrating diverse data
whatever your big data application is and
the types of big data you are using the real value will come from integrating
different types of data sources and analyzing them at scale
so how do we start getting this value
sometimes all it takes
is looking at the data you already collect in a different way
and it can mean a big difference in your return on investment
this new story from june 2015 mentions that carnival cruises
is using structured and unstructured data from a variety of sources
carnival turns it into profit
using price optimization techniques on the integrated data
for you to achieve such a success story
you will need to include data integration into your big data practice
however there are some unique challenges when attempting to integrate these
diverse data sources and scaling the solutions
course two on on the specialization we will teach you more about these issues
but let take a moment to define why effect of data integration is useful
data integration means bringing together data from diverse sources and
turning them into coherent and more useful information
we also call this knowledge
the main objective here is taming or more technically managing data and
turning it into something you can make use of programmatically
a data integration process involves many parts
it starts with discovering accessing and monitoring data and
continues with modeling and transforming data from a variety of sources
but why do we need data integration in the first place
let start by focusing on differences between big data sets
coming from different sources
you might have flat file formatted data relational database data
data encoded in xml or json both common for internet generated data
these different formats and models are useful
because they are designed to express different data in unique ways
in a way different data formats and
models make big data more useful and more challenging all at the same time
when you integrate data in different formats you make the final
product richer in the number of features you describe the data with
for example by integrating environmental sensor and
camera data with geographical information system data such as in
my wildfire prediction application i can use the spacial data capabilities
with non - spacial data to more accurately run fire simulations
in the past although we were able to see the images of the fire
from mountain top cameras just like this image we were still
not able to tell what the exact location of the fire is automatically
now when a fire is detected from a mountain top camera
viewsheds are used to estimate the location of the fire
this location information can be fed into the fire simulator
as early as it detected to predict the size and
location of the fire in the next hour more accurately and faster
similarly i can use real time data with eye curve data sets and
use them all together
additionally by bringing the data together and
providing programmable access to it i am now making each data set more accessible
moreover integration of diverse datasets significantly
reduces the overall data complexity in my data - driven product
the data becomes more available for use and unified as a system of its own
one advantage of such an integration is not often mentioned
such a streamlined and integrated data system
can increase the collaboration between different parts of your data systems
each part can now clearly see
how their data is integrated into the overall system
including the user scenarios and the security and privacy processes around it
overall by integrating diverse data streams you add value to your big data and
improve your business even before you start analyzing it
next we will focus on the dimensions of the scalability and
discuss how we can start tackling some of these challenges
what launched the big data era
in this video you will learn about two new opportunities that have
contributed to the launch of the big data era
opportunities are often a signal of changing times
in 2013 an influential report by a company called mckinsey claimed that
the area of data science will be the number one catalyst for economic growth
mckinsey identified one of our new
opportunities that contributed to the launch of the big data era
a growing torrent of data
this refers to the idea that data seems to be coming continuously and at a fast rate
think about this today you can buy a hard drive to store
all the music in the world for only 600
that an amazing storage capability over any previous forms of music storage
in 2010 there were 5 billion mobile phones in use
you can be sure that there are more today and
as i am sure you will understand these phones and
the apps we install on them are a big source of big data
which all the time every day contributes to our core
and facebook which recently just set
a record of having one billion people login in a single day
has more that 30 billion pieces of content shared every month
well that number from 2013
so i am sure that it much higher than that now
does it make you think how many facebook share you made last month
all this leads to projections of serious growth
40 in global data per year and 5 in global it spending
this much data has sure pushed the data science field
to start remaining itself and the business world of today
but there something else contributing to the catalyzing power of data science
it is called cloud computing
we call this on demand computing
cloud computing is one of the ways in which computing
has now become something that we ca do anytime and anywhere
you may be surprised to know that some of your favorite
apps are from businesses being run from coffee shops
this new ability combined with our torrent of data
gives us the opportunity to perform novel dynamic and scalable data analysis
to tell us new things about our world and ourself
to summarize a new torrent of big data combined with computing capability
anytime anywhere has been at the core of the launch of the big data era
asking the right questions
the first step in any process is to define what it is you are trying to tackle
what is the problem that needs to be addressed or
the opportunity that needs to be ascertained
without this you wo not have a clear goal in mind or
know when you have solved your problem
an example question is how can sales figures and
call center logs be combined to evaluate a new product
or in a manufacturing process how can data from multiple
sensors in an instrument be used to detect instrument failure
how can we understand our customers and
market better to achieve effective target marketing
next you need to assess the situation with respect to the problem or
the opportunity you have defined
this is a step where you need to exercise caution analyzing risks
costs benefits contingencies
regulations resources and requirements of the situation
what are the requirements of the problem
what are the assumptions and constraints
what resources are available
this is in terms of both personnel and capital
such as computer systems instruments etc
what are the main costs associated with this project
what are the potential benefits
what risks are there in pursuing the project
what are the contingencies to potential risks and so on
answers to these questions will help you get a better overview of the situation
and better understanding of what the project involves
then you need to define your goals and objectives
based on the answers to these questions
defining success criteria is also very important
what do you hope to achieve by the end of this project
having clear goals and and
success criteria will help you to assess the project throughout its life cycle
once you know the problem you want to address and understand the constraints and
goals then you can formulate the plan to come up with the answer
that is the solution to your business problem
as a summary defining the questions you are looking to find answers for
is a huge factor contributing to the success of a data science project
by following the explained set of steps you can formulate better questions
to solve using analytical skills and link them to business value
building a big data strategy
before we focus on big data strategy let look at what strategy means
although it is associated with a military term
a dictionary search on strategy shows the meaning as a plan of action or
policy designed to achieve a major or overall aim
this definition calls out the four major parts that need to be in any strategy
namely aim policy plan and action
now we are talking about a big data strategy
so what do these four terms mean for us
when building our big data strategy we look at what we have
what high level goals we want to achieve what we need to do to get there
and what are the policies around data from the beginning to the end
a big data strategy starts with big objectives
notice that i did not say it starts with collecting data
because in this activity we are really trying to identify what
data is useful and why by focusing on what data to collect
every organization or team is unique
different projects have different objectives
hence it important to first define what your team goals are
have you ever had the scenario where you see the temperature on the weather report
and someone else highlights the humidity instead
to find problems relevant to solve and
data related to it it might be useful to start with your objectives
once you define these objectives or
more generally speaking questions to turn big data into advantage for your business
you can look at what you have and analyze the gaps and actions to get there
it is important to focus on both short term and
long term objectives in this activity
these objectives should also be linked to big data analytics with business
objectives
to make the best use of big data each company needs to evaluate how
data science or big data analytics would add value to their business objectives
once you have established that analytics can help your business
you need to create a culture to embrace it
the first and foremost ingredient for
a successful data science program is organizational buy - in
a big data strategy must have commitment and
sponsorship from the company leadership
goals for using big data analytics should be developed with all stakeholders and
clearly communicated to everyone in the organization
so that its value is understood and appreciated by all
the next step is to build your data science team
a diverse team with data scientists information technologists
application developers and business owners is necessary to be effective
as well as the mentality that everyone works together as partners with
common goals
remember one for all
no one is a customer or service provider of another
rather everyone works together and delivers as a team
since big data is a team game and multi - disciplinary
a big part of a big data strategy is constant training
of team members on new big data tools and analytics
as well as business practices and objectives
this becomes even more critical if your business depends on deep expertise
on one or more subject areas with subject matter experts working on problems
utilizing big data
such businesses might have subject matter experts who can be trained to add big
data skills and provide more value added support than a newcomer would have
similarly any project member would be trained to understand what
the business objectives and products are and how he or
she can utilize big data to improve those objectives using his or her skills
many organizations might benefit by having a small data science team whose main job
is do data experiments and test new ideas before they get deployed at full scale
they might come up with a new idea themselves
based on the analysis they perform
they take more research level role
however their findings can drastically shape your business strategy
almost on a daily basis
the impact of such teams becomes evident over time
as other parts of your organization starts to see the results of their finding and
analysis affecting their strategies
they become strategic partners of all verticals in your business
once you see that something works
you can start collecting more data to see similar results at organizational scale
since data is key to any big data initiative it is essential
that data across the organization is easily accessed and integrated
data silos as you know are like a death knell on effective analytics
so barriers to data access must be removed
opening up the silos must be encouraged and supported from the organization
leaders in order to promote a data sharing mindset for the company
another aspect of defining your big data strategy
is defining the policies around big data
although it has an amazing amount of potential for your business
using big data should also raise some concerns in long term planning for data
although this is a very complex issue
here are some questions you should think of addressing around policy
what are the privacy concerns
who should have access to or control data
what is the lifetime of data which is sometimes defined as volatility
anatomy of big data
how does data get curated and cleaned up
what ensures data quality in the long term
how do different parts of your organization communicate or
interoperate using this data
are there any legal and regulatory standards in place
cultivating an analytics driven culture is crucial
to the success of a big data strategy
the mindset that you want to establish is that analytics
is an integral part of doing business not a separate afterthought
analytics activities must be tied to your business objectives and
you must be willing to use analytics in driving business decisions
analytics and business together bring about exciting opportunities and
growth to your big data strategy
finally one size does not fit all
hence big data technologies and
analytics is growing rapidly as your business is an evolving entity
you have to iterate your strategy to take advantage of new advances and
also make your business more dynamic in the face of change
as a summary when building a big data strategy
it is important to integrate big data analytics with business objectives
communicate goals and provide organizational buy - in for
analytics projects
build teams with diverse talents and establish a teamwork mindset
remove barriers to data access and integration
finally these activities need to be iterated to respond to new business
goals and technological advances
in this video we will talk about a new that is usually not covered much
it called valence
simply put valence refers to connectedness
the more connected data is the higher it valences
the term valence comes from chemistry
in chemistry we talk about core electrons and valence electrons of an atom
valence electrons are in the outer most shell have the highest energy level and
are responsible for bonding with other atoms
that higher valence results in greater boding that is greater connectedness
this idea is carried over into our definition of the term valence
in the context of big data
data items are often directly connected to one another
a city is connected to the country it belongs to
two facebook users are connected because they are friends
an employee is connected to his work place
data could also be indirectly connected
two scientists are connected because they are both physicists
for a data collection valence measures the ratio of actually connected data items
to the possible number of connections that could occur within the collection
the most important aspect of valence
is that the data connectivity increases over time
the series of network graphs comes from a social experiment where scientists
attending a conference were asked to meet other scientists they did not know before
after several rounds of meetings
they found new connections shown by their red edges
increase in valence can lead to emergent group behavior in people networks
like creation of new groups and coalitions that have shared values and goals
a high valence data set is denser
this makes many regular analytic critiques very inefficient
more complex analytical methods must be adopted to account for
the increasing density
more interesting challenges arise due to the dynamic behavior of the data
now there is a need to model and
predict how valence of a connected data set may change with time and volume
the dynamic behavior also leads to the problem of event detection
such as bursts in the local cohesion in parts of the data
and emergent behavior in the whole data set
such as increased polarization in a community
now we will talk about a form of scalability called variety
in this case scale does not refer to the largeness of data
it refers to increased diversity
here is an important mantra you need to think about
when we as data scientists think of data variety we think of the additional
complexity that results from more kinds of data that we need to store process
and combine
now many years ago when i started studying data management
we always thought of data as tables
these tables could be in spreadsheets or databases or just files but somehow
they will be modeled and manipulated as rows and columns of of tables
now tables are still really important and dominant however today a much wider
variety of data are collected stored and analyzed to solve real world problems
image data text data network data geographic maps computer
generated simulations are only a few of the types of data we encounter everyday
the heterogeneity of data can be characterized along several dimensions
we mentioned four such axes here
structural variety refers to the difference in
the representation of the data
for example an ekg signal is very different from a newspaper article
a satellite image of wildfires from nasa is very different from tweets
sent out by people who are seeing the fire spread
media variety refers to the medium in which the data gets delivered
the audio of a speech versus the transcript of the speech
may represent the same information in two different media
data objects like news video may have multiple media
an image sequence an audio and closed captioned text
all time synchronized to each other
semantic variety is best described two examples
we often use different units for quantities we measure
sometimes we also use qualitative versus quantitative measures
for example age can be a number or
we represent it by terms like infant juvenile or adult
another kind of semantic variety comes from different
assumptions of conditions on the data
for example if we conduct two income surveys on two different groups of people
we may not be able to compare or
combine them without knowing more about the populations themselves
the variation and availability takes many forms
for one data can be available real time
like sensor data or it can be stored like patient records
similarly data can be accessible continuously for
example from a traffic cam
versus intermittently for
example only when the satellite is over the region of interest
this makes a difference between what operations one can do with data
especially if the volume of the data is large
we will cover this in more detail in course two
when we explore the different genres of data and how we model them
we should not think that a single data object or
a collection of similar data objects will be all uniform in themselves
emails for example is a hybrid entity
some of this information can be a table like shown here
now the body of the email usually has text in it
however some of the text may have ornaments around them
for example
the part highlighted in yellow represents something called a markup on text
we will get to markups later in the course
emails contain attachments
these are files or embedded images
or other multimedia objects that the mailer allows
this screenshot from my outlook shows the image of a scanned image
of a handwritten note
when you take a collection of all emails from your mailbox or
that from an organization you will see that senders and
receivers form a communication network
in 2001 there was a famous scandal around a company called enron that engaged in
fraudulent financial reporting practices
their email network partly shown here has been studied by data scientist to find
usual and unusual patterns of connections among the people in the organization
an email collection can also have it own semantics
for example an email cannot refer to that means cannot copy or
forward a previous email
finally an email server is a real - time data source
but an email repository is not
does email and email collections demonstrate significant
internal variation in structure media semantics and availability
characteristics of big data - velocity
velocity refers to the increasing speed at which big data is created and
the increasing speed at which the data needs to be stored and analyzed
processing of data in real - time to match its production rate as it gets generated
is a particular goal of big data analytics
for example this type of capability allows for
personalization of advertisement on the web pages you visit
based on your recent search viewing and purchase history
if a business cannot take advantage of the data as it gets generated or
at the speed analysis of it is needed they often miss opportunities
in order to build a case for the importance of this dimension of big data
let imagine we are taking a road trip
you are looking for some better information to start packing
in this case the newer the information
the higher its relevance in deciding what to pack
would you use last month weather information or
data from last year at this time
or would you use the weather information from this week yesterday or
better today
it makes sense to obtain the latest information about weather and
process it in a way that makes your decisions easier
if the information is old it does not matter how accurate it is
being able to catch up with the velocity of big data and
analyzing it as it gets generated can even impact the quality of human life
sensors and smart devices monitoring the human body can detect abnormalities
in real time and trigger immediate action potentially saving lives
this type of processing is what we call real time processing
real - time processing is quite different from its remote relative
batch processing
batch processing was the norm until a couple of years ago
large amounts of data would be fed into large machines and
processed for days at a time
while this type of processing is still very common today decisions based on
information that is even few days old can be catastrophic to some businesses
organizations which make decisions on latest data
are more likely to hit the target
for this reason it important to match the speed of processing
with the speed of information generation and get real time decision making power
in addition today sensor - powered
socioeconomic climate requires faster decisions
hence we can not wait for all the data to be first produced
then fed into a machine
there are many applications where new information is streaming and
needs to be integrated with existing data to
produce decisions such as emergency response planning in a tornado or
deciding trading strategies in real time or getting estimates in advertising
we have to digest chunks of data as they are produced and give meaningful results
as more data comes in
your results will need to adapt to reflect this change in the input
decisions based on processing of already acquired data such as batch processing
may give an incomplete picture
and hence the applications need real time status of the context at hand
that is streaming analysis
fortunately with the event of cheap sensors technology
mobile phones and social media we can obtain the latest information
at a much rapid rate and in real time in comparison with the past
so how do you make sure we match the velocity of the expectations
to gain insights from big data
with the velocity of the big data
rate of generation retrieval
or processing of data is application specific
the need for real time data - driven actions within a business case is
what in the end dictates the velocity of analytics over big data
sometimes precision of a minute is needed
sometimes half a day
let look at these four paths and discuss when to pick the right one for
your analysis
the dollar signs next to the numbers in this example indicate how costly
the operation is
the more dollars the higher the cost
when the timeliness of processed information plays no role in decision
making the speed at which data is generated becomes irrelevant
in other words you can wait for as long as it takes to process data
days months weeks
and once processing is over you will look at the results and
probably share them with someone
when timeliness is not an issue you can choose any of the four paths
you will likely pick the cheapest one
when timeliness of end result is an issue
deciding which of the four paths to choose is not so simple
you will have to make a decision based on cost of hardware
time sensitivity of information future scenarios
in other words this becomes a business driven question
for example if speed is really important at all costs you will pick path four
as a summary we need to pay attention to the velocity of big data
streaming data gives information on what is going on right now
streaming data has velocity meaning it gets generated at various rates
and analysis of such data in real time gives agility and
adaptability to maximize benefits you want to extract
characteristics of big data veracity
veracity of big data refers to the quality of the data
it sometimes gets referred to as validity or
volatility referring to the lifetime of the data
veracity is very important for making big data operational
because big data can be noisy and uncertain
it can be full of biases abnormalities and it can be imprecise
data is of no value if it not accurate
the results of big data analysis are only as good as the data being analyzed
this is often described in analytics as junk in equals junk out
so we can say although big data provides many opportunities to make
data enabled decisions the evidence provided by data
is only valuable if the data is of a satisfactory quality
there are many different ways to define data quality
in the context of big data
quality can be defined as a function of a couple of different variables
accuracy of the data the trustworthiness or reliability of the data source
and how the data was generated are all important factors
that affect the quality of data
additionally how meaningful the data is with respect to the program that
analyzes it is an important factor and makes context a part of the quality
in this chart from 2015 we see the volumes of data increasing
starting with small amounts of enterprise data to larger
people generated voice over ip and social media data and
even larger machine generated sensor data
we also see that the uncertainty of the data increases as we go from
enterprise data to sensor data
this is as we would expect it to be
traditional enterprise data in warehouses have
standardized quality solutions like master processes for extract
transform and load of the data which we referred to as before as etl
as enterprises started incorporating less structured and unstructured people and
machine data into their big data solutions
the data become messier and more uncertain
there are many reasons for this
first unstructured data on the internet is imprecise and uncertain
in addition high velocity big data leaves very little or no time for
etl and in turn hindering the quality assurance processes of the data
let look at these product reviews for a banana slicer on amazon com
one of the five star reviews say that
it saved her marriage and compared it to the greatest inventions in history
another five star reviewer said that his parole officer recommended
the slicer as he is not allowed to be around knives
these are obviously fake reviewers
now think of an automated product assessment going through such
splendid reviews and estimating lots of sales for the banana slicer and
in turn suggesting stocking more of the slicer in the inventory
amazon will have problems
for a more serious case let look at the google flu trends case from 2013
for january 2013 the google friends actually
estimated almost twice as many flu cases as was reported by cdc
the centers for disease control and prevention
the primary reason behind this was that google flu trends used a big data on
the internet and did not account properly for uncertainties about the data
maybe the news and social media attention paid to the particularly
serious level of flu that year effected the estimate
and resulted in what we call an over estimation
this is a perfect example for
how inaccurate the results can be if only big data is used in the analysis
imagine the economical impact of making health care preparations for
twice the amount of flu cases
that would be huge
the google flu trends example also brings up the need for
being able to identify where exactly the big data they used comes from
what transformation did big data go through up
until the moment it was used for a estimate
this is what we refer to as data providence
just like we refer to an artifacts provenance
as a summary the growing torrents of big data pushes for
fast solutions to utilize it in analytical solutions
this creates challenges on keeping track of data quality
what has been collected where it came from and
how it was analyzed prior to its use
this is akin to an art artifact
having providence of everything it has gone through
but even more complicated to achieve with large volumes of data coming
in varieties and velocities
characteristics of big data - volume
volume is the big data dimension that relates to the sheer size of big data
this volume can come from large datasets being shared or
many small data pieces and events being collected over time
every minute 204 million emails are sent
200 000 photos are uploaded and 1 8 million likes are generated on facebook
on youtube 1 3 million videos are viewed and 72 hours of video are uploaded
but how much data are we talking about
the size and the scale of storage for big data can be massive
you heard me say words that start with peta exa and
yotta to define size but what does all that really mean
for comparison 100 megabytes will hold a couple of encyclopedias
a dvd is around 5 gbs and
1 tb would hold around 300 hours of good quality video
a data - oriented business currently collects data in the order of terabytes
but petabytes are becoming more common to our daily lives
cern large hadron collider generates 15 petabytes a year
according to predictions by an idc report sponsored by a big data company called
emc digital data will grow by a factor of 44 until the year 2020
this is a growth from 0 8 zetabytes
in 2009 to 35 2 zettabytes in 2020
a zettabyte is 1 trillion gigabytes that 10 to the power of 21
the effects of it will be huge !
think of all the time cost energy that will be used to store and
make sense of such an amount of data
the next era will be yottabytes
ten to the power of 24 and brontobytes ten to the power of 27
which is really hard to imagine for most of us at this time
this is also what we call data at an astronomical scale
the choice of putting the milky way galaxy
in the middle of the circle is not just for aesthetics
this is what we would see if we were to scale up 10 to
the 21 times into the universe
cool is not it
please refer to the reading in this module called
what does astronomical scale mean for a nice video on the powers of ten
all of these point to an exponential growth in data volume and storage
what is the relevance of this much data in our world
remember the planes collecting big data
our hope as passengers is data means better flight safety
the idea is to understand that businesses and organizations are collecting and
leveraging large volumes of data to improve their end products
whether it is safety reliability healthcare or governance
in general in business the goal
is to turn this much data into some form of business advantage
the question is how do we utilize larger volumes of data
to improve our end product quality
despite a number of challenges related to it
there are a number of challenges related to the massive volumes of big data
the most obvious one is of course storage
as the size of the data increases so
does the amount of storage space required to store that data efficiently
however we also need to be able to retrieve that large amount of
data fast enough and
move it to processing units in a timely fashion to get results when we need them
this brings additional challenges such as networking bandwidth
cost of storing data
in - house versus cloud storage and things like that
additional challenges arise during processing of such large data
most existing analytical methods wo not scale to such sums of
data in terms of memory processing or io needs
this means their performance will drop
you might be able to get good performance for data from hundreds of customers
but how about scaling your solution to 1 000 or 10 000 customers
as the volume increases performance and cost start becoming a challenge
businesses need a holistic strategy to handle processing of
large scale data to their benefit in the most cost effective manner
evaluating the options across the dimensions mentioned here
is the first step when it comes to continuously increasing data size
we will revisit this topic later on in this course
as a summary volume is the dimension of big data related to its size and
its exponential growth
the challenges with working with volumes of big data include cost scalability
and performance related to their storage access and processing
data science
getting value out of big data
we have all heard data science turned data into insights or even actions
but what does that really mean
data science can be thought of as a basis for
empirical research where data is used to induce information for observations
these observations are mainly data in our case
big data related to a business or scientific case
insight is a term
we use to refer to the data products of data science
it is extracted from a diverse amount of data through a combination of
exploratory data analysis and modeling
the questions are sometimes more specific and sometimes it requires
looking at the data and patterns in it to come up with the specific question
another important point to recognize is that data science is not static
it is not one time analysis
it involves a process where models generated to lead to insights
are constantly improved through further empirical evidence or simply data
for example a book retailer like amazon com can constantly improve
the model of a customer book preferences using the customer demographic
his or her previous purchases and the book reviews of the customer
the book retailer can also uses information to predict
which customers are likely to like any book
and take action to market the book to those customers
this is where we see insights being turned into action
as we have seen in the book marketing example using data science and analysis
of the past and current information data science generates actions
this is not just an analysis of the past but
rather generation of actionable information for the future
this is what we can call a prediction like the weather forecast
when you decide what to wear for the day based on the forecast of the day
you are taking action based on insight delivered to you
just like this business leaders and decision makers
take action based on the evidence provided by their data science teams
we set data science teams
this comes from the breadth of information and skill that it takes to make it happen
you have probably seen diagrams like this one that describe data science
data science happens at the intersection of computer science
mathematics and business expertise
if we zoom deeper into this diagram and
open the sets of expertise we will see a variation of this figure
even at this level all of these circles require deeper knowledge and skills
in areas like domain expertise data engineering statistics and computing
an even deeper analysis of these skills will lead you to skills like
machine learning statistical modeling relational algebra
business passion problem solving and data visualization
that a lot of skills to have for a single person
these wide range of skills and definitions of data scientists having them
all led to discussions like are data scientists unicorns
meaning they do not exist
there are data science experts who have expertise in more than one of these
skills for sure
but they are relatively rare and
still would probably need help from an expert on some of these areas
so in reality data scientists are teams of people who act like one
they are passionate about the story and the meaning behind data
they understand they problem they are trying to solve and
aim to find the right analytical methods to solve this problem
and they all have an interest in engineering solutions to solve problems
they also have curiosity about each others work and have communication
skills to interact with the team and present their ideas and results to others
as a summary a data science team often comes together to analyze situations
business or scientific cases which none of the individuals can solve on their own
there are lots of moving parts to the solution
but in the end all these parts should come together to provide
actionable insight based on big data
being able to use evidence - based insight in business decisions is more
important now than ever
data scientists have a combination of technical business and
soft skills to make this happen
getting started characteristics of big data
by now you have seen that big data is a blanket term that is used to refer to any
collection of data so large and complex that it exceeds the processing
capability of conventional data management systems and techniques
the applications of big data are endless
every part of business and society are changing in front our eyes due to that
fact that we now have so much more data and the ability for analyzing
but how can we characterize big data
you can say i know it when i see it
but there are easier ways to do it
big data is commonly characterized using a number of v
the first three are volume velocity and variety
volume refers to the vast amounts of data that is generated every second
minutes hour and day in our digitized world
variety refers to the ever increasing different forms that data can come in
such as text images voice and geospatial data
velocity refers to the speed at which data is being generated and
the pace at which data moves from one point to the next
volume variety and
velocity are the three main dimensions that characterize big data
and describe its challenges
we have huge amounts of data in different formats and
varying quality which must be processed quickly
more vs have been introduced to the big data community
as we discover new challenges and ways to define big data
veracity and valence are two of these additional v we
will pay special attention to as a part of this specialization
veracity refers to the biases noise and abnormality in data
or better yet it refers to the often unmeasurable uncertainties and
truthfulness and trustworthiness of data
valence refers to the connectedness of big data in the form of graphs
just like atoms
moreover we must be sure to never forget our sixth v value
how do big data benefit you and your organization
without a clear strategy and
an objective with the value they are getting from big data
it is easy to imagine that organizations will be sidetracked by all these
challenges of big data and not be able to turn them into opportunities
now let start looking into the first five of these v in detail
how does data science happen
five p of data science
now that we identified what data science is and how companies can strategize around
big data to start building a purpose let come back to using data science
to get value out of big data around the purpose or questions they defined
our experience with building and
observing successful data science projects led to a method around the craft with
five distinct components that can be defined as components of data science
here we define data science as a multi - disciplinary
craft that combines people teaming up around
application - specific purpose that can be achieved through a process
big data computing platforms and programmability
all of these should lead to products where the focus really
is on the questions or purpose that are defined by your big data strategy ideas
there are many technology data and analytical research and
development related activities around the questions
but in the end everything we do in this phase is to reach to that
final product based on our purposes
so it makes sense to start with it and
build a process around how we make this product happen
remember the wild fire prediction project i described
one of the products we described there was the rate of spread and
direction of an ongoing fire
we have identified questions and
the process that led us to the product in the end to solve it
we brought together experts around the table for fire modeling
data management time series analysis scalable computing
geographical information systems and emergency response
i asked them let not dive into the techniques yet
what is the problem at large
how do we see ourselves solving it
a typical conversation around the process starts with this question
then from then on drilling down to many areas of expertise
often we blur lines between the steps
my wildfire team would start listing things like we do not have an integrated
system or we do not have real - time access to data programmatically
so we cannot analyze fires on the fly
or they can say i cannot integrate sensor data with satellite data
all of this leads me to challenges i can then use to define problems
there are many dimensions of data science to think about within this discussion
let start with the obvious ones people and purpose
people refers to a data science team or the projects stakeholders
as you know by now they are expert in data and
analytics business computing science or big data management
like all the set of experts i listed in my wildfire scenario
the purpose refers to the challenge or set of challenges defined by your
big data strategy like solving the question related to the rate of spread and
direction of the fire perimeter in the wildfire case
since there a predefined team with a purpose a great place for
this team to start with is a process they could iterate on
we can simply say people with purpose will define a process to collaborate and
communicate around
the process is conceptual in the beginning and
defines the set of steps an how everyone can contribute to it
there are many ways to look at the process
one way of looking at it is as two distinct activities
mainly big data engineering and
big data analytics or computational big data science
as i like to call it as more than simple analytics is being performed here
a more detailed way of looking at the process reveals five distinct steps or
activities of this data science process
namely acquire prepare
analyze report and act
we can simply say that data science happens
at the boundary of all these steps
ideally this process should support experimental work and
dynamic scalability on the big data and computing platforms
this five step process can be used in alternative ways in real life big data
applications if we add the dependencies of different tools to each other
the influence of big data pushes for
alternative scalability approaches at each step of the process
just like you would scale each step on its own
you can scale the whole process as a whole in the end
one can simply say all of these steps have reporting needs in different forms
or there is a need to draw all these activities as an iterating process
including build explore and scale for big data as steps
big data analysis needs alternative data management techniques and
systems as well as analytical tools and methods
multiple modes of scalability is needed based on dynamic data and computing loads
in addition change in physical infrastructure
streaming data specific urgencies arising from special events
can also require multiple modes of scalability
in this intro course for simplicity
we will refer to the process as a set of five sequential activities that iterate
however we will touch on scalability as needed in our example applications
as a part of building your big data process
it important to simply mention two other p
the first one is big data platforms like the ones in the hadoop framework
or other computing platforms to scale different steps
the scalability should be in the mind of all team members and
get communicated as an expectation
in addition the scalable process should be programmable through
utilization of reusable and reproducible programming interfaces
to libraries like systems middleware analytical tools
visualization environments and end user reporting environments
thinking of big data applications as a process
including a set of activities that the team members can collaborate over
also helps to build metrics for accountability to be built into it
this way expectations on cost time
optimization of deliverables and time lines can be discussed
between the the members starting with the beginning of the data science process
sometimes we may not be able to do this in one step
and joint explorations like statistical evaluations of intermediate results or
accuracy of sample data sets become important
as a summary data science can be defined as a craft of using the five p
identified in this lecture leading to a sixth p the data product
having a process within the more business - driven ps like people and
purpose and the more technically driven p like platforms and
programmability leads to a streamlined approach that starts and
ends with the product team accountability and collaboration in mind
data science process provides guidelines for
implementing big data solution as it helps to organize efforts and
ensures all critical steps taken conforms to pre - define and agreed upon metrics
step one acquiring data
the first step in the data science process is to acquire the data
you need to obtain the source material before analyzing or acting on it
the first step in acquiring data is to determine what data is available
leave no stone unturned when it comes to finding the right data sources
you want to identify suitable data related to your problem and
make use of all data that is relevant to your problem for analysis
leaving out even a small amount of important data
can lead to incorrect conclusions
data comes from many places local and
remote in many varieties structured and un - structured
and with different velocities
there are many techniques and technologies to access these different types of data
let discuss a few examples
a lot of data exists in conventional relational databases
like structure big data from organizations
the tool of choice to access data from databases is structured query language or
sql which is supported by all relational databases management systems
additionally most data base systems come with a graphical application
environment that allows you to query and explore the data sets in the database
data can also exist in files such as text files and excel spreadsheets
scripting languages are generally used to get data from files
a scripting language is a high level programming language
that can be either general purpose or specialized for specific functions
common scripting languages with support for processing files are java script
python php perl r and matlab and are many others
an increasingly popular way to get data is from websites
web pages are written using a set of standards approved by
a world wide web consortium or shortly w3c
this includes a variety of formats and services
one common format is the extensible markup language or xml
which uses markup symbols or tabs to describe the contents on a webpage
many websites also host web services which produce program access to their data
there are several types of web services
the most popular is rest because it so easy to use
rest stand for representational state transfer
and it is an approach to implementing web services with performance
scalability and maintainability in mind
web socket services are also becoming more popular
since they allow real time modifications from web sites
nosql storage systems are increasingly used to manage a variety of data
types in big data
these data stores are databases that do not represent data
in a table format with columns and rows as with conventional relational databases
examples of these data stores include cassandra mongodb and hbase
nosql data stores provide apis to allow users to access data
these apis can be used directly or in an application that needs to access the data
additionally most nosql systems provide data access
via a web service interface such a rest
now let discuss our wildfire case study
as a real project that acquires data using several different mechanisms
the wifire project stores sensor data from weather stations in a relational database
we use sql to retrieve this data from the database to create
models to identify weather patterns associated with santa anna conditions
to determine whether a particular weather station is currently experiencing
santa anna conditions we access real time data using a web socket service
once we start listening to this service
we receive weather station measurements as they occur
this data is then processed and compared to patterns found by our models
to determine if a weather station is experiencing santa ana conditions
at the same time tweets are retrieved
using hashtags related to any fire that is occurring in the region
the tweet messages are retrieves using the twitter rest service
the idea is to determine the sentiment of these tweets to see if people
are expressing fear anger or are simply nonchalant about the nearby fire
the combination of sensor data and tweet sentiments helps
to give us a sense of the urgency of the fire situation
as a summary big data comes from many places
finding and evaluating data
useful to your big data analytics is important before you start acquiring data
depending on the source and
structure of data there are alternative ways to access it
step 2 - a : exploring data
after you have put together the data that you need for your application
you might be tempted to immediately build models to analyze the data
resist this temptation
the first step after getting your data is to explore it
exploring data is a part of the two - step data preparation process
you want to do some preliminary investigation
in order to gain a better understanding of the specific characteristics of your data
in this step you will be looking for
things like correlations general trends and outliers
without this step you will not be able to use the data effectively
correlation graphs can be used to explore the dependencies
between different variables in the data
graphing the general trends of variables will show you if there is
a consistent direction in which the values of these variables are moving towards
like sales prices going up or down
in statistics an outlier is a data point that distant from other data points
plotting outliers will help you double check for
errors in the data due to measurements
in some cases outliers that are not errors might make you find a rare event
additionally summary statistics provide numerical values to describe your data
summary statistics are quantities that capture various characteristics
of a set of values with a single number or a small set of numbers
some basic summary statistics that you should compute for
your data set are mean median range and standard deviation
mean and median are measures of the location of a set of values
mode is the value that occurs most frequently in your data set
and range and standard deviation are measures of spread in your data
looking at these measures will give you an idea of the nature of your data
they can tell you if there something wrong with your data
for example if the range of the values for age in your data includes
negative numbers or a number much greater than 100
there something suspicious in the data that needs to be examined
visualization techniques also provide a quick and effective and
overall a very useful way to look at data in this preliminary analysis step
a heat map such as the one shown here
can quickly give you the idea of where the hotspots are
many other different types of graphs can be used
histograms show that the distribution of the data and
can show skewness or unusual dispersion
boxplots are another type of plot for showing data distribution
line graphs are useful for seeing how values in your data change over time
spikes in the data are also easy to spot
scatter plots can show you correlation between two variables
overall there are many types of graph to visualize data
they are very useful in helping you understand the data you have
in summary what you get by exploring your data is a better
understanding of the complexity of the data you have to work with
this in turn will guide the rest of your process
step 2 - b : pre - processing data
the raw data that you get directly from your sources are never in the format that
you need to perform analysis on
there are two main goals in the data pre - processing step
the first is to clean the data to address data quality issues and
the second is to transform the raw data to make it suitable for analysis
a very important part of data preparation
is to address quality of issues in your data
real - world data is messy
there are many examples of quality issues with data from real applications including
inconsistent data like a customer with two different addresses duplicate customer
records for example customers address recorded at two different sales locations
and the two recordings do not agree
missing customer agent demographics or studies
missing values like missing a customer age in the demographic studies
invalid data like an invalid zip code for example a six digit code
and outliers like a sense of failure causing values to be much higher or
lower than expected for a period of time
since we get the data downstream
we usually have little control over how the data is collected
preventing data quality problems as the data is being collected is not
often an option
so we have the data that we get and
we have to address quality issues by detecting and correcting them
here are some approaches we can take to address this quality issues
we can remove data records with missing values
we can merge duplicate records
this will require a way to determine how to resolve conflicting values
perhaps it makes sense to retain the newer value whenever there a conflict
for invalid values the best estimate for
a reasonable value can be used as a replacement
for example for a missing age value for an employee
a reasonable value can be estimated based on the employee length of employment
outliers can also be removed if they are not important to the task
in order to address data quality issues effectively
knowledge about the application such as how the data was collected
the user population and the intended uses of the application is important
this domain knowledge is essential to making informed
decisions on how to handle incomplete or incorrect data
the second part of preparing data
is to manipulate the clean data into the format needed for analysis
the step is known by many names
data manipulation data preprocessing data wrangling
and even data munging some operations for
this type of operation i mean data munging wrangling preprocessing
include scaling transformation feature selection
dimensionality reduction and data manipulation
scaling involves changing the range of values to be between a specified range
such as from zero to one
this is done to avoid having certain features that large values from
dominating the results
for example in analyzing data with height and weight
to magnitude of weight values is much greater than of the height values
so scaling all values to be between zero and
one will equalize contributions from both height and weight features
various transformations can be performed on the data to reduce noise and
variability
one such transformation is aggregation
aggregate data generally results in data with less variability
which may help with your analysis
for example daily sales figures may have many serious changes
aggregating values to weekly or monthly sales figures will result in similar data
other filtering techniques can also be used to remove variability in the data
of course this comes at the cost of less detailed data
so these factors must be weighed for the specific application
future selection can involve removing redundant or irrelevant features
combining features and creating new features
during the exploring data step
you might have discovered that two features are correlated
in that case one of these features can be removed
without negatively affecting the analysis results
for example the purchase price of a product and
the amount of sales tax paid are likely to be correlated
eliminating the sales tax amount then will be beneficial
removing redundant or
irrelevant features will make the subsequent analysis much simpler
in other cases you may want to combine features or create new ones
for example adding the applicant education level
as a feature to a loan approval application would make sense
there are also algorithms to automatically determine the most relevant features
based on various mathematical properties
dimensionality reduction is useful when the data set has a large number of
dimensions
it involves finding a smaller subset of dimensions that
captures most of the variation in the data
this reduces the dimensions of the data
while eliminating irrelevant features and makes analysis simpler
a technique commonly used for
dimensional reduction is called principle component analysis or pca
raw data often has to be manipulated to be in the correct format for analysis
for example from samples recording daily changes in stock prices
we may want the capture price changes for
a particular market segments like real estate or health care
this would require determining which stocks belong to which market segment
grouping them together and perhaps computing the mean range
standard deviation for each group
in summary
data preparation is a very important part of the data science process
in fact this is where you will spend most of your time on any data science effort
it can be a tedious process but it is a crucial step
always remember garbage in garbage out
if you do not spend the time and
effort to create good data for the analysis you will not get good results
no matter how sophisticated the analysis technique you are using is
step 3 : analyzing data
now that you have your data nicely prepared
the next step is to analyze the data
data analysis involves building a model from your data
which is called input data
the input data is used by the analysis technique to build a model
what your model generates is the output data
there are different types of problems and
so there are different types of analysis techniques
the main categories of analysis techniques are classification regression
clustering association analysis and graph analysis
we will describe each one
in classification the goal is to predict the category of the input data
an example of this is predicting the weather as being sunny
rainy windy or cloudy in this case
another example is to classify a tumor as either benign or malignant
in this case the classification is referred to as binary classification
since there are only two categories
but you can have many categories as well
as the weather prediction problem shown here having four categories
another example is to identify handwritten digits as
being in one of the ten categories from zero to nine
when your model has to predict a numeric value instead of a category
then the task becomes a regression problem
an example of regression is to predict the price of a stock
the stock price is a numeric value not a category
so this is a regression task instead of a classification task
other examples of regression are estimating the weekly sales of a new
product and predicting the score on a test
in clustering the goal is to organize similar items into groups
an example is grouping a company customer base into distinct segments for
more effective targeted marketing like seniors adults and
teenagers as we see here
another such example is identifying areas of similar topography
like mountains deserts plains for land use application
yet another example is determining different groups of weather patterns
like rainy cold or snowy
the goal in association analysis is to come up with a set
of rules to capture associations within items or events
the rules are used to determine when items or events occur together
a common application of association analysis is known as market
basket analysis which is used to understand customer purchasing behavior
for example association analysis can reveal that banking customers
who have certificate of deposit accounts surety cds also
tend to be interested in other investment vehicles such as money market accounts
this information can be used for cross - selling
if you advertise money market accounts to your customers with cds
they are likely to open such an account
according to data mining folklore a supermarket chain used association
analysis to discover a connection between two seemingly unrelated products
they discovered that many customers who go to the supermarket late on sunday night
to buy diapers also tend to buy beer who are likely to be fathers
this information was then used to place beer and
diapers close together and they saw a jump in sales of both items
this is the famous diaper beer connection
when your data can be transformed into a graph representation with nodes and
links then you want to use graph analytics to analyze your data
this kind of data comes about when you have a lot of entities and
connections between those entities like social networks
some examples where graph analytics can be useful are exploring the spread of
a disease or epidemic by analyzing hospitals and doctors records
identification of security threats by monitoring social media
email and text data
and optimization of mobile communications network traffic
and optimization of mobile telecommunications network traffic
to ensure call quality and reduce dropped calls
modeling starts with selecting one of the techniques we listed
as the appropriate analysis technique depending on the type of problem you have
then you construct the model using the data you have prepared
to validate the model you apply it to new data samples
this is to evaluate how well the model
does on data that was used to construct it
the common practice is to divide the prepared data into a set of data for
constructing the model and reserving some of the data for
evaluating the model after it has been constructed
you can also use new data prepared the same way as with the data that was used to
construct model
evaluating the model depends on the type of analysis techniques you used
let briefly look at how to evaluate each technique
for classification and regression you will have the correct output for
each sample in your input data
comparing the correct output and
the output predicted by the model provides a way to evaluate the model
for clustering the groups resulting from clustering
should be examined to see if they make sense for your application
for example do the customer segments reflect your customer base
are they helpful for use in your targeted marketing campaigns
for association analysis and
graph analysis some investigation will be needed to see if the results are correct
for example network traffic delays
need to be investigated to see what your model predicts is actually happening
and whether the sources of the delays are where they are predicted
to be in the real system
after you have evaluated your model to get a sense of its performance on your data
you will be able to determine the next steps
some questions to consider are should the analysis be
performed with more data in order to get a better model performance
would using different data types help
for example in your clustering results
is it difficult to distinguish customers from distinct regions
would adding zip code to your input data help
to generate finer grained customer segments
do the analysis results suggest a more detailed look at
some aspect of the problem
for example predicting sunny weather gives very good results
but rainy weather predictions are just so - so
this means that you should take a closer look at your examples for rainy weather
perhaps you just need more samples of rainy weather or
perhaps there are some anomalies in those samples
or maybe there are some missing data that needs to be included in order
to completely capture rainy weather
the ideal situation would be that your model platforms very well with respect to
the success criteria that were determined
when you defined the problem at the beginning of the project
in that case you are ready to move on to communicating and
acting on the results that you obtained from your analysis
as a summary data analysis involves selecting the appropriate technique for
your problem building the model then evaluating the results
as there are different types of problems
there are also different types of analysis techniques
step four reporting insights
the fourth step in our data science process is reporting the insights gained
from our analysis
this is a very important step to communicate your insights and
make a case for what actions should follow
it can change shape based on your audience and should not be taken lightly
so how do you get started
the first thing to do is to look at your analysis results and
decide what to present or report as the biggest value or biggest set of values
in deciding what to present you should ask yourself these questions
what is the punchline
in other words what are the main results
what added value do these results provide or
how can the model add to the application
how do the results compare to the success criteria determined at
the beginning of the project
answers to these questions are the items you need to include in your report or
presentation
so make them the main topics and gather facts to back them up
keep in mind that not all of your results may be rosy
your analysis may show results that are counter to what you were hoping to find
or results that are inconclusive or puzzling
you need to show these results as well
domain experts may find some of these results to be puzzling and
inconclusive findings may lead to additional analysis
remember the point of reporting your findings
is to determine what the next step should be
all findings must be presented so that informed decisions can be made
visualization is an important tool in presenting your results
the techniques that we discuss and explore in data can be used here as well
what were they
scatter plots line graphs heat maps and other types of graphs
are effective ways to present your results visually
this time you are not plotting the input data but
you are plotting the output data with similar tools
you should also have tables with details from your analysis as backups
if someone wants to take a deeper dive into the results
there are many visualization tools that are available
some of the most popular open source ones are listed here
r is a software package for general data analysis
it has powerful visualization capabilities as well
python is a general purpose programming language
that also has a number of packages to support data analysis and graphics
d3 is a javascript library for
producing interactive web based visualizations and data driven documents
leaflet is a lightweight mobile friendly javascript library
to create interactive maps
tableau public allows you to create visualizations
in your public profile and share them or put them on a site or blog
google charts provides cross - browser compatibility
and closed platform portability to iphones and android
timeline is a javascript library that allows you to create timelines
in summary you want to report your findings by presenting your results and
value add with graphs using visualization tools
step 5 act turning insights into action
now that you have evaluated the results from your analysis and
generated reports on the potential value of the results the next step is to
determine what action or actions should be taken based on the insights gained
remember why we started bringing together the data and
analyzing it in the first place
to find actionable insights within all these data sets
to answer questions or for improving business processes
for example
is there something in your process that should change to remove bottle necks
is there data that should be added to your application to make it more accurate
should you segment your population into more well defined groups for
more effective targeted marketing
this is the first step in turning insights into action
now that you have determined what action to take
the next step is figuring out how to implement the action
what is necessary to add this action into your process or application
how should it be automated
the stakeholders need to be identified and become involved in this change
just as with any process improvement changes we need to monitor and
measure the impact of the action on the process or application
assessing the impact leads to an evaluation
evaluating results from the implemented action will determine your next steps
is there additional analysis that need to be performed in order to yield
even better results
what data should be revisited
are there additional opportunities that should be explored
for example let not forget what big data enables us to do
real - time actions based on high velocity streaming information
we need to define what part of our business needs real - time action to be
able to influence the operations or the interaction with the customer
once we define these real time actions we need to make sure that
there are automated systems or processes to perform such actions and
provide failure recovery in case of problems
as a summary big data and
data science are only useful if the insights can be turned into action
and if the actions are carefully defined and evaluated
steps in the data science process
we have already seen a simple linear form of data science process
including five distinct activities that depend on each other
let summarize each activity further before we go into the details of each
acquire includes anything that makes us retrieve data including; finding
accessing acquiring and moving data
it includes identification of and authenticated access to all related data
and transportation of data from sources to distributed files systems
it includes way to subset and match the data to regions or times of interest
as we sometimes refer to it as geo - spacial query
the next activity is prepare data we divide the pre - data activity
into two steps based on the nature of the activity
namely explore data and pre - process data
the first step in data preparation involves literally looking
at the data to understand its nature what it means its quality and format
it often takes a preliminary analysis of data or
samples of data to understand it
this is why this step is called explore
once we know more about the data through exploratory analysis
the next step is pre - processing of data for analysis
pre - processing includes cleaning data sub - setting or
filtering data creating data which programs can read and
understand such as modeling raw data into a more defined data model
or packaging it using a specific data format
if there are multiple data sets involved
this step also includes integration of multiple data sources or streams
the prepared data then would be passed onto the analysis step
which involves selection of analytical techniques to use
building a model of the data and analyzing results
this step can take a couple of iterations on its own or
might require data scientists to go back to steps one and
two to get more data or package data in a different way
step four for communicating results includes evaluation of analytical results
presenting them in a visual way creating reports that include
an assessment of results with respect to success criteria
activities in this step can often be referred to with terms like interpret
summarize visualize or post process
the last step brings us back to the very first reason we do data science
the purpose
reporting insights from analysis and determining actions from insights based
on the purpose you initially defined is what we refer to as the act step
we have now seen all the steps in a typical data science process
please note that this is an iterative process and findings from one step
may require the previous step to be repeated with new information
the sixth v value
in this module
we described the five ways which are considered to be dimensions of big data
each way presented a challenging dimension of big data namely
size complexity speed quality and connectedness
although we can list some other rays base on the context we prefer to list these
five s fundamental dimensions that this big data specialization helps you work on
however at the heart of the big data challenge
is turning all of the other dimensions into truly useful business value
the idea behind processing all this big data in the first place
is to bring value to the problem at hand
in week two we will explore how to take the first steps into
starting to generate value out of big data
now that we saw all the ways let focus on an example of a big data challenge
let imagine now that you are part of a company called eglence inc
one of the products of eglence inc is a highly popular mobile game
called catch the pink flamingo
it a multi - user game where the users have to catch special types
of pink flamingos that randomly pop up on the world map on their
screens based on the mission that gets updated randomly
the game is played by millions of people online throughout the world
one of the goals of the game is to form a network of players to collectively
cover the world map with pink flamingo sightings and compete other groups
users can pick their groups based on player stats
the game website sends free cool stuff to registered users
registration requires users to enter demographic information such gender
year of birth city highest education and things like that
however most of the users enter inaccurate information about themselves
just like most of us do
to help improve the game the game collects realtime usage activity
data from each player and feeds them to it data servers
the players of this game are enthusiastically active on social media
and have strong associations with the game
a popular twitter hashtag for this game is catchthepinkflamingo
which gets more than 200 000 mentions worldwide per day
there are strong communities of users who meet via social media and
get together to play the game
now imagine yourself as the big data solutions architect for fun games inc
there are definitely examples of all three types of data sources in this example
the mobile app generates data for the analysis of user activity
twitter conversations of players form a rich source of unstructured data from
people
and the customer and
game records are examples of data that this organization collects
this is a challenging big data example
where all characteristics of big data are represented
there are high volumes of player game and
twitter data which also speaks to the variety of data
the data streams from the mobile app website and
social media in real - time which can be defined as high velocity data
the quality of demographic data users enter is not clear and
there are networks of players which are related to the balance of big data
cloud computing : an important big data enabler
in our first lecture in this course we mentioned the cloud as one of
the two influences of the launch of the big data era
we called it on - demand computing and
we said that it enables us to compute any time any anywhere
simply whenever we demand it
in this video
we will see how we deploy the cloud to our benefit in our big data applications
the main idea behind cloud computing
is to transform computing infrastructure into a commodity
so application developers can focus on solving application - specific challenges
instead of trying to build infrastructure to run on
so how does this happen
we can simply define a cloud computing service
as a rental service for computing
you rent what you want and return upon usage
think about this you would not buy or
even build a truck every time you have to move a piece of furniture
you would simply rent
why build a computing cluster when you can rent
especially if you are not using it all the time
similarly you can rent a car or a bike when you are on vacation
so you can bike anytime anywhere
let dig into this question
what factors do you consider when you are developing a solution for your yourself or
your client
should you build a hardware and software resources yourself
or should you rent these resources from the cloud
let look at in - house hardware and software resource building first
if you choose to develop in - house capabilities you have to hire people and
buy hardware that suits your requirements
these includes but not limited to buying networking hardware
storage disks upgrading hardware when it becomes obsolete and so on
not to forget the real estate cost of keeping the hardware
how do you estimate the size of your hardware needs
do you make a five year estimate or ten year
in today fast changing world
it is becoming harder to estimate future demands
getting the software that fits your needs is equally challenging
most software installations require a lot of tweaking and
manual intervention that require a lot of skills
you will need your engineers to do this
compatibility issues bring problems that are hard to foresee
most software is updated on a daily basis
you must ensure you are updated
this insures you avoid security risks and get the best
over all building your own data center or computing power house can be expensive
and it can be time consuming maintaining it is a task by itself
this requires high initial capital investments and
efficient operation of several departments in your business
which you might not have if you are a startup company
most people forget to include the cost of disposing old hardware
now lets see what the cloud can do for us
cloud benefits are similar to what you would get from a rental car company
you pay for what you use which means a low capital investment
you do not need to go to the dealership do a negotiation get a bank loan
get insurance
that means quick implementation of your projects
just like you do not need to buy a car if you only need a car for
a limited use deploying your application on a server that is geographically
closer to your client can give you fast service and happy customers
for startup and small business it can be challenging to do so
cloud lets you do this with a click
you can be sitting at a coffeeshop or your home and starting your internet business
without a huge capital investment thanks to the cloud
and you do not need to have a five or ten year resource estimation plan
adapt to your requirements faster if your business is growing faster than you
thought
cloud lets you forget about the resource management problems and
lets you focus on your business products or domain expertise with minimal cost
just as you can rent a truck or a convertible at a rental car company
you can build your own custom machine on cloud
with a custom machine we mean a commodity cluster
made out of the right type of computing nodes for your application
you pick not only a cpu or a gpu but
pick from a whole menu of compute memory and storage choices
it a buffet on the cloud
design machines to suit your application requirements data size and analytics
get what you want and pay for what you use
compare this with buying and
maintaining all combinations of hardware that you possibly would use
that is so costly and not possible at all times
thanks to all these advantages there are many cloud server providers today
and the numbers are growing
here we list some of the players in the cloud computing market
take a moment to look at them
you will probably recognize some big names and
some others you have not even heard of before
as a summary cloud does the heavy lifting so your team can extract
value from data with getting bogged down in the infrastructure details
cloud provides convenient and
viable solutions for scaling your prototype to a full fledged application
you can leverage the experts to handle security
robustness and let them handle the technical issues
your team can work on utilizing your strengths
to solve your domain specific problem
cloud service models : exploration of choices
there are many levels of services that you can get from cloud providers
any cloud computing discussion will involve terms like application
as a service platform as a service and infrastructure as a service
all of these refer to business models around using the cloud
with different levels of engagement and servicing similar to rental agreements
iaas infrastructure as a service can be defined as a bare minimum rental service
this is like renting a truck from a company that you can assume has hardware
and you do the packing of your furniture and drive to your new house
you as the user of the service install and maintain an operating system
and other applications in the infrastructure as a service model
the amazon ec2 cloud is a good example for this model
paas platform as a service
is the model where a user is provided with an entire computing platform
this could include the operating system and programming languages that you need
it could extend to include the database of your choice or even a web server
you can develop and
run your own application software on top of these layers
the google app engine and microsoft azure are two examples of this model
saas the software as a service model is the model
in which the cloud service provider takes the responsibilities for the hardware and
software environment such as the operating system and the application software
this means you can work on using the application to solve your problem
dropbox is a very popular software as a service platform
ultimately the decision of which service you want to explore is a function of
several variables
it depends on the skill level of your team to handle computing environment
development and maintenance
it also depends on how you might need to use the service
you need to pick the right service model that
best fits you in terms of long term goals
finally when you are deploying a cloud service you also have to understand
all the security risks since your data resides on third party service
security is a very important aspect in today world of growing
digitization of information
you must make your client data safety a top priority
and hence this should be an important criteria in your decision
all the security risks must be understood and
evaluated as your data resides on third party servers
we are seeing other forms of services being added
to the family of cloud services
the logic of infrastructure platform and
software as a service is getting extended further
xaas is an umbrella term that signifies
even finer - grain control over computing resources that you want to rent
for example storage as a service communication as a service
marketing as a service and so on
as a summary infrastructure as a service platform as a service and application
as a service are three main class service models that are being used with success
picking one will depend on the number of variables which are company goals
these three models have inspired many similar models
to emerge around cloud computing
in this lecture we will be learning about the basic file manipulation commands for
the hadoop file system or hdfs
we will first start by downloading a text file of words
we will use this text file to copy to and from the local file system in hdfs and
later on we will use it to run word count on
after we download the text file we will open a terminal shell and
copy the text file from the local file system to hdfs
next we will copy the file within hdfs and
also see how to copy file from hdfs to the local file system
finally we will see how to delete a file in hdfs
let start
we are going to download text file to copy into hdfs
it does not matter what the contents of the text file is so we will download
the complete works of shakespeare since it contains interesting text
first click on the icon here to launch a web browser
now we will search google for the complete works of shakespeare
i am going to be using this first link here
and we will provide this link in the reading section
so this is the complete works of shakespeare and
we will save it to a text file in the local file system by clicking on the icon here
the open menu and selecting save page
so we will call it words txt
and the save in folder it going to save it into the downloads directory
once that completes we will open a terminal window by clicking on the icon here
so if we go into the downloads ddrectory by typing a cd downloads and
running ls we can see that words txt was successfully downloaded
moving on let copy words txt from the local file system to the hdfs file system
the command to do this is hadoop fs - copyfromlocal words txt
when i run this it will copy it from the local directory and
local file system to hdfs
we can see that the file was copied by running hadoop fs - ls
you can see that the file was successfully copied
next we can copy this file to another file within hdfs
we can do this by running hadoop fs - cp words txt words2 txt
the first words txt is the file that already exists in hdfs
the second words 2 txt
is the new file that we are going to create when we run this command
let run it and again we are can run
hadoopfs - ls to see the files in hdfs
we can see the original file words txt and the copy that was made words2 txt
let copy words2 txt from hdfs to the local filesystem
we can do this by running hadoop fs - copytolocal words2 txt
after i run this command i can call ls to see the contents of the local file system
so now we have the new file words2 txt which we have just copied from hdfs
the last step in this lecture is to delete a file in hdfs
we can delete words2 txt by running hadoop fs
but is rn words2 txt
as you can see it printed that it deleted the file
we can also run hadoop fs - ls to verify that the file is deleted
you can see that there only the original words txt and words2 txt was deleted
getting started
why do we worry about foundations
starting next week you will start diving into the details of the hadoop
framework for big data
before you start taking a little bit of time to understand some core
concepts will help you to digest the information on hadoop better and faster
imagine yourself attending a chemistry lab
before you start hearing about the tubes and mixtures you really need
to understand the chemistry or theory of the practical concepts in the lab
similarly learning these concepts now will help
you with your understanding of the practical concepts in the hadoop lectures
in addition we want to prepare you to understand the tools beyond hadoop
any big data system that you find will be built on these core concepts
so these foundations will help you beyond this course
now let get started
getting started
why hadoop
we have all heard that hadoop and
related projects in this ecosystem are great for big data
this module will answer the four ws and an h about why this statement is true
before we dive further into the details of hadoop
let take a moment to analyze the characteristics of the hadoop ecosystem
what is in the ecosystem
why is it beneficial
where is it used
who uses it
and how do these tools work
the hadoop ecosystem frameworks and applications that we will describe in this
module have several overarching themes and goals
first they provide scalability to store large volumes of data
on commodity hardware
as the number of systems increases so does the chance for crashes and
hardware failures
a second goal supported by most frameworks in the hadoop ecosystem
is the ability to gracefully recover from these problems
in addition as we have mentioned before big data comes in
a variety of flavors such as text files graph of social networks
streaming sensor data and raster images
a third goal for the hadoop ecosystem then
is the ability to handle these different data types for any given type of data
you can find several projects in the ecosystem that support it
a fourth goal of the hadoop ecosystem
is the ability to facilitate a shared environment
since even modest - sized clusters can have many cores
it is important to allow multiple jobs to execute simultaneously
why buy servers only to let them sit idle
another goal of the hadoop ecosystem is providing value for your enterprise
the ecosystem includes a wide range of open source projects
backed by a large active community
these projects are free to use and easy to find support for
in the following lectures in this module
we will take a more detailed look at the hadoop ecosystem
first we will explore the kinds of projects available and
the types of capabilities they provide
next we will take a deeper look at the three main parts of hadoop
the hadoop distributed file system or hdfs
yarn the scheduler and resource manager
and mapreduce a programming model for processing big data
we will then discuss cloud computing and the types of service models it provides
we will also describe situations in which hadoop is not the best solution
this module then concludes with two readings involving hands - on
experience with hdfs and mapreduce
so let get started
mapreduce simple programming for big results
mapreduce is a programming model for the hadoop ecosystem
it relies on yarn to schedule and
execute parallel processing over the distributed file blocks in hdfs
there are several tools that use the mapreduce model to provide a higher level
interface to other programming models
hive has a sql - like interface that adds capabilities that help with
relational data modeling
and pig is a high level data flow language
that adds capabilities that help with process map modeling
traditional parallel programming requires expertise on a number of computing and
systems concepts
for example synchronization mechanisms like locks semaphores
and monitors are essential
and incorrectly using them can either crash your program or
severely impact performance
this high learning curve makes it difficult
it is also error prone since your code can run on hundreds or
thousands of nodes each having many cores
and any problem related to these parallel processes
needs to be handled by your parallel program
the mapreduce programming model greatly simplifies running code in parallel
since you do not have to deal with any of these issues
instead you only need to create and map and reduce tasks and you do not
have to worry about multiple threads synchronization or concurrency issues
so what is a map and reduce
map and reduce are two concepts based on functional programming
where the output the function is based solely on the input
just like in a mathematical function f x = y y depends on x
you provide a function or operation for a map and reduce
and the runtime executes it over the data
for map the operation is applied on each data element
and in reduce the operation summarizes elements in some manner
an example using map and reduce will make this concepts more clear
hello word is a traditional first program you code
when you start to learning programming languages
the first program to learn or hello word of map reduce is often wordcount
wordcount reads one or more text files and
counts the number of occurrences of each word in these files
the output will be a text file with a list of words and
their occurrence frequencies in the input data
let examine each step of wordcount
for simplification we are assuming we have one big file as an input
before wordcount runs the input file is stored in hdfs
as you know now
hdfs partitions the blocks across multiple nodes in the cluster
in this case four partitions labeled a b c and d
the first step in mapreduce is to run a map operation on each node
as the input partitions are read from htfs map is called for
each line in the input
let look at the first lines of the input partitions a and
b and start counting the words
the first line in the partition on node a
says my apple is red and my rose is blue
similarly the first line on partition b says you are the apple of my eye
let now see what happens in the first map node for partition a
map creates a key value for
each word on the line containing the word as the key and 1 as the value
in this example the word apple is read from the line in partition a
map produces a key value of apple 1
similarly the word my is seen on the first line of a twice
so the key values of my 1 are created
note that map goes to each node containing a data block for
the file instead of the data moving to map
this is moving computation to data
let now see what the same map operation generates for partition b
since each word only happens to occur once
a list of all the words with one key - value pairing each gets generated
please take a moment to observe the outputs of map and
each key - value pair associated to a word
next all the key - values that were output from map are sorted based on their key
and the key values with the same word are moved or shuffled to the same node
to simplify this figure each node only has a single word in orange boxes
but in general a node will have many different words
just like our example from the two lines in a and b partitions
here we see that you and apple are assigned to the first node
the word is to the second node
and the words rose and red to the third
although for simplicity we drew four map nodes and three shuffle nodes
the number of nodes can be extended as much as the application demands
next the reduce operation executes on these nodes to
add values for key - value pairs with the same keys
for example apple 1 and
another apple 1 becomes apple 2
the result of reduce is a single key pair for
each word that was read in the input file
the key is the word and the value is the number of occurrences
if we look back at our wordcount example
we see that there were three distinct steps
namely the map step the shuffle and sort step and the reduce step
although the wordcount example is pretty simple
it represents a large number of applications to which these three steps
can be applied in order to achieve data parallel scalability
for example now that you have seen the wordcount application
consider changing the wordcount algorithm to index all
the urls by words after a web crawl
this means instead of pointing to a number the keys would refer to urls
after the map with this new function which by the way is called a user
defined function the output of shuffle and sort would look like this
now when we reduce the urls all the urls that mention apple would look like this
this is in fact one of the ways a search engine like google works
so now if somebody came to the interface built for this application
to search for the word apple and entered apple
it would be easy to get all the urls as the word itself
no wonder the first mapreduce paper was produced by google
we will give you a link to the original google paper on mapreduce from
2004 at the end of this lecture
it is pretty technical but
it gives you a simple overview without the current system implementations
we just saw how mapreduce can be used in search engines
in addition to counting the words and documents
although it possible to add many more applications let stop here for
a general discussion on how the points of
data parallelism can be used in search in this three step pattern
there is definitely parallelization during the map step
this parallelization is over the input
as each partition gets processed one line at a time
to achieve this type of data parallelism we must decide on
the data granularity of each parallel competition
in this case it will be a line
we also see parallel grouping of data in the shuffle and sort phase
this time the parallelization is over the intermediate products
that is the individual key - value pairs
and after the grouping of the intermediate products
the reduce step gets parallelized to construct one output file
you have probably noticed that the data gets reduced
to a smaller set at each step
this overview gave us an idea of what kinds of tasks that mapreduce is good for
while mapreduce excels at independent batch tasks similar to our applications
there are certain kinds of tasks that you would not want to use mapreduce for
for example if your data is frequently changing
mapreduce is slow since it reads the entire input data set each time
the mapreduce model requires that maps and
reduces execute independently of each other
this greatly simplifies your job as a designer
since you do not have to deal with synchronization issues
however it means that computations that do have dependencies
cannot be expressed with mapreduce
finally mapreduce does not return any results
until the entire process is finished
it must read the entire input data set
this makes it unsuitable for interactive applications where the results must be
presented to the user very quickly expecting a return from the user
as a summary mapreduce hides complexities of parallel programming and
greatly simplifies building parallel applications
many types of tasks suitable for
mapreduce include search engine page ranking and topic mapping
please see the reading after this lecture on making pasta sauce
with mapreduce for another fun application using the mapreduce programming model
programming models for big data
we have seen that scalable computing over the internet to achieve
data - parallel scalability for big data applications is now a possibility
thanks to commodity clusters
cost - effective commodity clusters together with advances in distributed
file systems to move computation to data
provide a potential to conduct scalable big data analytics
the next thing we will talk about is how to take
advantage of these infrastructure advances
what are the right programming models
a programming model is an abstraction or existing machinery or infrastructure
it is a set of abstract runtime libraries and
programming languages that form a model of computation
this abstraction level can be low - level as in machine language in computers
or very high as in high - level programming languages for example java
so we can say if the enabling infrastructure for
big data analysis is distributed file systems as we mentioned
then the programming model for big data should enable the programmability
of the operations within distributed file systems
what we mean by this being able to write computer programs that work
efficiently on top of distributed file systems using big data and
making it easy to cope with all the potential issues
based on everything we discussed so
far let describe the requirements for big data programming models
first of all such a programming model for big data should support
common big data operations like splitting large volumes of data
this means for partitioning and placement of data in and
out of computer memory along with a model to synchronize the datasets later on
the access to data should be achieved in a fast way
it should allow fast distribution to nodes within a rack and these are potentially
the data nodes we moved the computation to
this means scheduling of many parallel tasks at once
it should also enable reliability of the computing and
full tolerance from failures
this means it should enable programmable replications and
recovery of files when needed
it should be easily scalable to the distributed notes where the data gets
produced
it should also enable adding new resources to take advantage of distributive
computers and scale to more or faster data without losing performance
this is called scaling out if needed
since there are a variety of different types of data
such as documents graphs tables key values etc
a programming model should enable operations over a particular set
of these types
not every type of data may be supported by a particular model but
the models should be optimized for at least one type
is it getting a little complicated
it does not have to have to be
in fact we apply similar models in our daily lives for everyday tasks
let look at the scenario where you might unknowingly apply this model
imagine a peaceful saturday afternoon
you receive a phone call from a friend and she says
she they will be at your house in an hour for dinner
it seems like you completely forgot that you had invited your friends for dinner
so you say you are looking forward to it and head to the kitchen
as a quick solution you decide to cook pasta with some tomato sauce
you need to take advantage of parallelization so
that the dinner is ready by the time your guest arrive that within an hour
you call your spouse and your teenage kids to action in the kitchen
now you need to give them directions to start dicing the ingredients for you
but in the heat of the moment you end up mixing the onions tomatoes and peppers
instead of sorting them first
you give everyone a randomly mixed batch of different types of vegetables
they are required to use their computer powers to chop the vegetables
they need to ensure not mix different types of veggies
when everyone is done chopping you want to group the veggies by their types
you ask each helper to collect items of the same type put them in a large
bowl and label this large bowl with the sum of individual bowl weights
like tomatoes in one bowl peppers in another and the onions in the third bowl
in the end
you have nice large bowls with the total weight of each vegetable labeled on it
your helpers are soon done with their work while you are focused on coordinating their
actions and other dinner tasks in the kitchen you can start cooking your pasta
what you have just seen is an excellent example of big data modeling in action
only it is really the data processed by human processors
this scenario can be modeled by a common programming model for big data
namely mapreduce
mapreduce is a big data programming model that supports all
the requirements of big data modeling we mentioned
it can model processing large data
split complications into different parallel tasks and
make efficient use of large commodity clusters and distributed file systems
in addition it abstracts out the details of parallelzation
full tolerance data distribution monitoring and load balancing
as a programming model
it has been implemented in a few different big data frameworks
next week we will see more details on mapreduce and
how its hadoop implementation works
to summarize programming models for
big data are abstractions over distributed file systems
the desired programming models for big data should handle large volumes and
varieties of data
support full tolerance and provide scale out functionality
mapreduce is one of these models
implemented in a variety of frameworks including hadoop
we will summarize the inner workings of the hadoop implementation next week
in this lecture we will use hadoop to run wordcount
first we will open a terminal shell and
explore the hadoop - provided mapreduce programs
next we will verify the input file exists in hdfs
we will then run wordcount and explore the wordcount output directory
after that we will copy the wordcount results
from hdfs to the local file system and view them
let begin
first we will open a terminal shell by
clicking on the icon at top of the window here
next we will look at the map produced programs that come with hadoop
we can do this by running hadoop jars user jars hadoop examples jar
this command says we are going to use the jar command to run a program
in hadoop from a jar file
and the jar file that we are running from is in usr jars hadoop - examples jar
many programs written in java are distributed via jar files
if we run this command we will see a list of different programs that come with hadoop
so for example wordcount
count the words in a text file
wordmean count the average length of words
and other programs such as sorting and calculating the length of pi
in the previous lecture we downloaded the works of shakespeare and
saved it into hdfs
let make sure that file is still there by running hadoop fs - ls
we can see that the file is still there and it called words txt
we can run wordcount by running hadoop jar
usr jars hadoop - examples jar wordcount
this command says that we are going to run a jar
and this is the name of the jar containing the program
and the program we are going to run is wordcount
when we run it we see that it prints the command line usage for
how to run wordcount
this says that wordcount takes one or more input files and an output name
now both the input and the output are located in hdfs
so we have the input file that we just listed words txt in hdfs
we can run wordcount
so we will run hadoop jar usr jars hadoop - examples jar
wordcount words txt out
this is saying we are going to run the wordcount program using words txt
as the input and put the output in a directory called out
so we will run it
as wordcount is running your prints progress to the screen
it will print the percentage of map and reduce completed
and when both of these reach 100 then the job is done
now that the job is complete let look at the results
we can run hadoop fs - ls to see the output
this shows that out was created and this is where our results are stored
notice that it a directory with a d here
so hadoop word count created the directory to contain the output
let look inside that directory by running hadoop fs - ls out
blank audio we can see that there are two files in this directory
the first is success this means that the wordcount job completed successfully
the other file part - r - 00000 is a text file
containing the output from the wordcount command
now let copy this text file to the local file system from hdfs and then view it
we could copy it by running hadoop fs - copytolocal
out part - r - 00000 local
and we will say local txt is the name
you can view the results of this
we are running more local txt
this will view the contents of the file
we can hit spacebar to scroll down
we see the results of wordcount in this file
each line is a particular word and the second column is the count
of how many words of this particular word was found in the input file
you can hit q to quit
scalable computing over the internet
most computing is done on a single compute node
if the computation needs more than a node or parallel processing
like many scientific computing problems we use parallel computers
simply put a parallel computer is a very large number of
single computing nodes with specialized capabilities connected to other network
for example the gordon supercomputer here at the san diego supercomputer center
has 1 024 compute nodes with 16 cores each equalling 16 384 compute cores in total
this type of specialized computer is pretty costly
compared to its most recent cousin the commodity cluster
the term commodity cluster is often heard in big data conversations
have you ever wondered what it exactly means
commodity clusters are affordable parallel computers
with an average number of computing nodes
they are not as powerful as traditional parallel computers and
are often built out of less specialized nodes
in fact the nodes in the commodity cluster
are more generic in their computing capabilities
the service - oriented computing community over the internet have pushed for
computing to be done on commodity clusters as distributed computations
and in turn reducing the cost of computing over the internet
in commodity clusters the computing nodes are clustered in racks
connected to each other via a fast network
there might be many of such racks in extensible amounts
computing in one or more of these clusters across
a local area network or the internet is called distributed computing
such architectures enable what we call data - parallelism
in data - parallelism many jobs that share nothing can work on
different data sets or parts of a data set
this type of parallelism sometimes gets called as job level parallelism
but in this specialization we will refer to it as data - parallelism
in the context of big - data computing
large volumes and varieties of big data can be analyzed using this mode
of parallelism achieving scalability performance and cost reduction
as you can imagine there are many points of failure inside systems
a node or an entire rack can fail at any given time
the connectivity of a rack to the network can stop or
the connections between individual nodes can break
it is not practical to restart everything every time if failure happens
the ability to recover from such failures is called fault - tolerance
for fault - tolerance of such systems two neat solutions emerged
namely redundant data storage and
restart of failed individual parallel jobs
we will explain these two solutions next
as a summary the commodity clusters are a cost effective way
of achieving data parallel scalability for big data applications
these type of systems have a higher potential for partial failures
it is this type of distributed computing that pushed for
a change towards cost effective reliable and
fault - tolerant systems for management and analysis of big data
the hadoop distributed file system a storage system for big data
as a storage layer the hadoop distributed file system or the way we call it hdfs
serves as the foundation for most tools in the hadoop ecosystem
it provides two capabilities that are essential for managing big data
scalability to large data sets
and reliability to cope with hardware failures
hdfs allows you to store and access large datasets
according to hortonworks a leading vendor of hadoop services
hdfs has shown production scalability up to 200 petabytes and
a single cluster of 4 500 servers
with close to a billion files and blocks
if you run out of space you can simply add more nodes to increase the space
hdfs achieves scalability by partitioning or
splitting large files across multiple computers
this allows parallel access to very large files since the computations run in
parallel on each node where the data is stored
typical file size is gigabytes to terabytes
the default chunk size the size of each piece of a file is 64 megabytes
but you can configure this to any size
by spreading the file across many nodes
the chances are increased that a node storing one of the blocks will fail
what happens next
do we lose the information stored in block c
hdfs is designed for full tolerance in such case
hdfs replicates or
makes a copy of file blocks on different nodes to prevent data loss
in this example the node that crashed stored block c
but block c was replicated on two other nodes in the cluster
by default hdfs maintains three copies of every block
this is the default replication factor
but you can change it globally for every file or
on a per file basis
hdfs is also designed to handle a variety of data types aligned with
big data variety
to read a file in hdfs you must specify the input file format
similarly to write the file you must provide the output file format
hdfs provides a set of formats for common data types
but this is extensible and you can provide custom formats for your data types
for example text files can be read
line by line or a word at a time
geospatial data can be read as vectors or rasters
data formats specific to geospatial data or
other domain specific data formats
like fasta or fastq formats for sequence data genomics
hdfs is comprised of two components
namenode and datanode
these operate using a master slave relationship
where the namenode issues comments to datanodes across the cluster
the namenode is responsible for metadata
and datanodes provide block storage
there is usually one namenode per cluster
a datanode however runs on each node in the cluster
in some sense the namenode is the administrator or
the coordinator of the hdfs cluster
when the file is created the namenode records the name
location in the directory hierarchy and other metadata
the namenode also decides which data nodes to store the contents of the file and
remembers this mapping
the datanode runs on each node in the cluster
and is responsible for storing the file blocks
the data node listens to commands from the name node for block creation
deletion and replication
replication provides two key capabilities
fault tolerance and data locality
as discussed earlier when a machine in the cluster has a hardware failure there
are two other copies of each block that are stored on that node
so no data is lost
replication also means that the same block will be stored on different nodes on
the system which are in different geographical locations
a location may mean a specific rack or a data center in a different town
the location is important since we want to move computation to data and
not the other way around
we will talk about what moving computation to data means later in this module
as i mentioned earlier the default replication factor is three but
you can change this
a high replication factor means more protection against hardware failures
and better chances for data locality
but it also means increased storage space is used
as a summary hdfs provides
scalable big data storage by partitioning files over multiple nodes
this helps to scale big data analytics to large data volumes
the application protects against hardware failures and
provides data locality when we move analytical complications to data
the hadoop ecosystem : so much free stuff !
how did the big data open - source movement begin
in 2004 google published a paper about their
in - house processing framework they called mapreduce
the next year yahoo released an open - source
implementation based on this framework called hadoop
in the following years other frameworks and
tools were released to the community as open - source projects
these frameworks provided new capabilities missing in hadoop
such as sql like querying or high level scripting
today there are over 100 open - source projects for
big data and this number continues to grow
many rely on hadoop but some are independent
with so many frameworks and tools available how do we learn what they do
we can organize them with a layer diagram to understand their capabilities
sometimes we also used the term stack instead of a layer diagram
in a layer diagram a component uses the functionality or
capabilities of the components in the layer below it
usually components at the same layer do not communicate
and a component never assumes a specific tool or component is above it
in this example component a is in the bottom layer
which components b and c use
component d uses b but not c
and d does not directly use a
let look at one set of tools in the hadoop ecosystem as a layer diagram
this layer diagram is organized vertically based on the interface
low level interfaces so storage and scheduling on the bottom
and high level languages and interactivity at the top
the hadoop distributed file system or hdfs is the foundation for
many big data frameworks since it provides scaleable and reliable storage
as the size of your data increases you can add commodity hardware
to hdfs to increase storage capacity so
it enables scaling out of your resources
hadoop yarn provides flexible scheduling and
resource management over the hdfs storage
yarn is used at yahoo to schedule jobs across 40 000 servers
mapreduce is a programming model that simplifies parallel computing
instead of dealing with the complexities of synchronization and scheduling you
only need to give mapreduce two functions map and reduce as you heard before
this programming model is so
powerful that google previously used it for indexing websites
mapreduce only assume a limited model to express data
hive and pig are two additional programming models on
top of mapreduce to augment data modeling of mapreduce
with relational algebra and data flow modeling respectively
hive was created at facebook to issue sql - like
queries using mapreduce on their data in hdfs
pig was created at yahoo to model data flow based programs using mapreduce
thanks to yarn stability to manage resources
not just for mapreduce but other programming models as well
giraph was built for processing large - scale graphs efficiently
for example facebook uses giraph to analyze the social graphs of its users
similarly storm spark and flink were built for
real time and in memory processing of big data on
top of the yarn resource scheduler and hdfs
in - memory processing is a powerful way of running big data applications even faster
achieving 100x better performance for some tasks
sometimes your data or processing tasks are not easily or
efficiently represented using the file and directory model of storage
examples of this include collections of key - values or large sparse tables
nosql projects such as cassandra mongodb and hbase handle these cases
cassandra was created at facebook but facebook also used hbase for
its messaging platform
finally running all of these tools requires a centralized management system
for synchronization configuration and to ensure high availability
zookeeper performs these duties
it was created by yahoo to wrangle services named after animals
a major benefit of the hadoop ecosystem
is that all these tools are open - source projects
you can download and use them for free
each project has a community of users and developers that
answer questions fix bugs and implement new features
you can mix and match to get only the tools you need to achieve your goals
alternatively there are several pre - built stacks of these tools
offered by companies such as cloudera mapr and hortonworks
these companies provide the core software stacks for free and
offer commercial support for production environments
as a summary the hadoop ecosystem
consists of a growing number of open - source tools
providing opportunities to pick the right tool for
the right tasks for better performance and lower costs
we will reveal some of these tools in further detail and
provide an analysis of when to use which in the next set of lectures
generating value from hadoop and
pre - built hadoop images that come as off the shelf products
assembling your own software stack from scratch can be messy and
a lot of work for beginners
the task of setting up the whole stack could consume a lot of project time and
man power reducing time to deployment
getting pre - built images is similar to buying pre - assembled furniture
you can obtain a ready to go software stack which contains a pre - installed
operating system required libraries and application software
it saves you from the trouble of putting the different
parts together in the right orientation
you can start using the furniture right away
packaging of these pre - built software images is enabled
by virtual machines using virtualization software
without going into too much detail one of the benefits of virtualization
software is that it lets you run a ready made software stack within minutes
your software stack comes as a large file
virtualization software provides a platform where your stack can run
many companies provide images for their version of the hadoop platform
including a number of tools of their choice
hortonworks is one of the companies that provides a pre - built software stack for
both mac and windows platforms
cloudera is another company that provides pre - installed and
assembled software stack images
cloudera image is what we will be working with in this course
many other companies provide similar images
additionally lots of online tutorials for beginners are on vendors websites for
self - training of users working with these images and
the open source tools they include
once you choose the vendor you can check out their website for
tutorials on how to get started quickly
there are plenty of resources online for that
you can deploy pre - built images over the cloud
this would further accelerate your application deployment process
it is always best to evaluate which approach is most cost effective for
your business model and organization
companies such as cloudera hortonworks and others
provide step - by - step guides on how to set up pre - built images on the cloud
as a summary using pre - built software packages have a number of benefits and
can significantly accelerate your big data projects
even small teams can quickly prototype deploy and validate their project ideas
the developed analytical solutions can be scaled to larger volumes and
increase velocities of data in a matter of hours
these companies also provide enterprise level solutions for large
full - fledged applications
an added benefit is that there are plenty of companies which provide
ready - made solutions
that means lots of choices for you to pick the one most suited to your project
what is a distributed file system
most of us have file cabinets in our offices or
homes that help us store our printed documents
everyone has their own method of organizing files
including the way we bin similar documents into one file or
the way we sort them in alphabetical or date order
when computers first came out the information and
programs were stored in punch cards
these punch cards were stored in file cabinets
just like the physical file cabinets today
this is where the name file system comes from
the need to store information in files comes from a larger need
to store information in the long - term
this way the information lives after the computer program or
what we call process that produced it terminates
if we do not have files our access to such information would not be possible
once a program using or producing it
even during the process we might need to store large amounts of information
that we cannot store within the program components or computer memory
in addition once the data is in a file
multiple processes can access the same information if needed
for all these reasons we store information in files on a hard disk
there are many of these files and
they get managed by your operating system like windows or linux
how the operating system manages files is called a file system
how this information is stored on disk drives has high impact
on the efficiency and speed of access to data especially in the big data case
while the files have exact addresses for their locations in the drive referring
to the data units of sequence of these blocks that called the flat structure
or hierarchy construction of index records that called the database
they also have human readable symbolic names generally followed by an extension
extensions tell what kind of file it is in general
programs and users can access files with their names
the contents of a file can be numeric alphabetic alphanumeric
or binary executables
most computer users work on personal laptops or
desktop computers with a single hard drive
in this model the user is limited to the capacity of their hard drive
the capacity of different devices vary
for example while your phone or
tablet might have a storage capacity in the order of gigabytes your
laptop computer might have a terabyte of storage but what if you have more data
some of you probably had issues in the past with
running out of space on your hard drive
a way to solve this is to have an external hard drive and
store your files there or you can buy a bigger disk
both options are a bit of a hassle to copy the data to a new disk are not they
they might not even be an option sometimes
now imagine you having two computers and
storing some of your data in one and the rest of your data in another
how you organize and partition your data between these computers is up to you
you might want to store your work data in one computer and
your personal data in another
distributing data on multiple computers might be an option but
it raises new issues
in this situation you need to know where to find the files you need
depending on what you re doing
you can find it manageable if it s just your data
but now imagine having thousands of computers
to store your data with big volumes and variety
would not it be good to have a system that can handle the data access and
do this for you
this is a case that can be handled by a distributive file system
now let assume that there are racks of these computers
often even distributed across the local or
wide area network because such file systems distributed file systems
data sets or parts of a data set
can be replicated across the nodes of a distributed file system
since data is already on these nodes then analysis of parts of the data
is needed in a data parallel fashion computation can be moved to these nodes
additionally distributed file systems replicate the data
between the racks and also computers distributed across geographical regions
data replication makes the system more fault tolerant
that means if some nodes or a rack goes down
there are other parts of the system the same data can be found and analyzed
data replication also helps with scaling the access to this data by many users
often if the data is popular many reader processes will want access to it
in a highly parallelized replication
each reader can get their own node to access to and analyze data
this increases overall system performance
note that a problem with having such a distributive replication is
that it is hard to make changes to data over time
however in most big data systems the data is written once and
the updates to data is maintained as additional data sets over time
as a summary a file system is responsible from the organization of
the long term information storage in a computer
when many storage computers are connected through the network
we call it a distributed file system
distributed file systems provide data scalability fault tolerance and
high concurrency through partitioning and replication of data on many nodes
when to reconsider hadoop
the hadoop ecosystem is growing at a fast pace
this means a lot of stuff that was difficult or
not supportive is becoming possible
in this lecture
we will look at some aspects that clearly make a good match for hadoop
we will also look at several aspects that might motivate you
to evaluate hadoop at a deeper level
and does hadoop really make sense for your specific problem
first let look at the key features that make a problem hadoop friendly
if you see a large scale growth in amount of data you will tackle
probably it makes sense to use hadoop
when you want quick access to your old data which would otherwise go on tape
drives for archival storage hadoop might provide a good alternative
other hadoop friendly features include
scenarios when you want to use multiple applications over the same data store
high volume or high variety are also great indicators for
hadoop as a platform choice
small data set processing should raise your eyebrows
do you really need hadoop for that
dig deeper and find out exactly why you want to use hadoop before going ahead
hadoop is good for data parallelism
as you know data parallelism is the simultaneous execution of the same
function on multiple nodes across the elements of a dataset
on the other hand task parallelism as you see in this graph
is the simultaneous execution of many different functions
on multiple nodes across the same or different data sets
if your problem has task - level parallelism you must do further
analysis as to which tools you plan to deploy from the hadoop ecosystem
what are the precise benefits that these tools provide
proceed with caution
not all algorithms are scalable in hadoop or
reducible to one of the programming models supported by yarn
hence if you are looking to deploy highly coupled data processing algorithms
proceed with caution
do a thorough analysis before using hadoop
are you thinking of
throwing away your existing database solutions and replacing them with hadoop
think again
hadoop may be a good platform where your diverse data sets can land and
get processed into a form digestible with your database
hadoop may not be the best data store solution for your business case
evaluate and proceed with caution
hdfs stores data in blocks of 64 megabytes or larger
so you may have to read an entire file just to pick one data entry
that makes it a bit harder to perform random data access
the hadoop ecosystem is growing at a faster pace than ever
this slide shows some of the moving targets in the hadoop ecosystem and
the additional needs which must be addressed by new tools
to the hadoop ecosystem
mainly advanced analytical queries
latency sensitive tasks and cyber security of sensitive data
here we give pointers to tools you might want to look into further
to understand the challenges these need tools address
as a summary although hadoop is good with scalability of many algorithms it is just
one model and does not solve all issues in managing and processing big data
although it would be possible to find counterexamples we can generally say
that the hadoop framework is not the best for working with small data sets
advanced algorithms that require a specific hardware type
task level parallelism infrastructure replacement or random data access
yarn the resource manager for hadoop
yarn is a resource manage layer that sits just above the storage layer hdfs
yarn interacts with applications and schedules resources for their use
yarn enables running multiple applications over hdfc increases
resource efficiency and let you go beyond the map reduce or
even beyond the data parallel programming model
when hadoop was first created this was not the case
in fact the original hadoop stack had no resource manager
these two stacked diagrams show some of it evolution over the last ten years
one of the biggest limitations of hadoop one point zero
was it inability to support non - mapreduce applications
it had several terrible resource utilization
this meant that for advanced applications such as graph analysis that
required different ways of modelling and
looking at data you would need to move your data to another platform
that a lot of work if your data is big
adding yarn in between hdfs and the applications enabled
new systems to be built focusing on different types of big data applications
such as giraph for graph data analysis storm for
streaming data analysis and spark for in - memory analysis
yarn does so by providing a standard framework
that supports customized application development in the hadoop ecosystem
yarn lets you extract maximum benefits from your data sets
by letting you use the tools you think are best for your big data
let take a peek into the architecture of yarn without getting too technical
in this picture notice the resource manager in the center and
the node managers on each of the three nodes on the right
the resource manager controls all the resources and decides who gets what
node manager operates at machine level and is in charge of a single machine
together the resource manager and
the node manager form the data computation framework
each application gets an application master
it negotiates resource from the resource manager and
it talks to node manager to get its tasks completed
notice the ovals labeled container the container
is an abstract notions that signifies a resource that is
a collection of cpu memory disk network and
other resources within the compute note to simplify and
be less precise you can think of a container and the machine
we looked at the essential gears of the yarn
engine to give you an idea of the key components of yarn
now when you hear terms like resource manager node manager and
container you will have an understanding of what tasks they are responsible for
here is a real life example to show the strength hadoop 2 0 over 1 0
yahoo was able to run almost
twice as many jobs per day with yarn than with hadoop 1 0
they also experienced a substantial increase in cpu utilization
yahoo !
even claimed that upgrading to yarn was equal into
adding 1000 machines to their 2500 machine cluster
that big
yarn success is evident from an explosive growth of
different application that the hadoop ecosystem now has
new to yarn
you can use the tool of your choice over your big data without any hassle
compare this with hadoop 1 0 which was limited to mapreduce alone
let review a summary of the key take - aways about yarn
yarn gives you many ways for applications to extract value from data
it lets you run many distributed applications over the same hadoop cluster
in addition yarn reduces the need to move data around and
supports higher resource utilization resulting in lower costs
it a scalable platform that has enabled growth of several applications
over the hdfs enriching the hadoop ecosystem
at this point you hopefully have a good general idea of what big data means and
why big data is important
so now we need to focus on what to do
when we have an application that uses big data
in this video we focus on the problem of managing big data
so at the end of the video
you should be able to describe what data management means in general and then
specifically recognize the issues that are involved in the management of big data
first let see what data management means in general
instead of giving you definitions of data management
let think of some questions that must be asked and
answered well if you are to manage a reasonable amount of data
now we can not possibly cover all questions one should ask for
a data - centric application but here are some important ones which range from how
we get the data to how we work with it to how we secure it from malicious users
we will visit these issues one at a time
ingestion means the process of getting the data
into the data system that we are building or using
now you might think why is it worth talking about
we will just read the data from somewhere like a file
and then using some command place it into the data system
or we will have have some kind of a web form or
other visual interface and just fill it in so that the data goes into the system
both of these ways of data ingestion are valid
in fact they are valid for
some big data systems like your airline reservation system
however when you think of a large scale system
you wold like to have more automation in the data ingestion processes
and data ingestion then becomes a part of the big data management infrastructure
so here are some questions you might want to ask when you automate data ingestion
now take a minute to read the questions
we will look at two examples to explore them in greater detail
the first example is that of a hospital information system that we discussed in
course one in the context of precision medicine
we said that hospitals collect terabytes of medical record
from different departments and be considered big data systems
the second example is a cloud based data store where many people upload their
messages chats pictures videos music and so fourth
the cloud storage also supports active communication between the members and
store their communication in real time
so let think of a hypothetical hospital information information and
the answer to depressions that we are putting there
now do not take the numbers to be very accurate
they are just examples
but it illustrates some important points
one note that there are two kinds of likeness associated with data
some data like medical images are large data objects by themselves
secondly the records themselves are quite small but
the size of the total collection of records is very high
two while there is a lot of patient data the number of data sources that is
the different departmental systems contributing to the total information
system does not change very much over time
three the rate of data ingestion is not enormous and is often proportional
to the number of patient activities that takes place at the hospital
four the system contains medical records so
data can never be discarded even when there are errors in the data
the errors in this specific case are flagged but the data is retained
now this is the kind of rule called an error handling policy
which might be different for different application problems
an air handling policy is part of a larger scheme of policies called
ingestion policies
another kind of ingestion policy involves decisions regarding what the system should
do if the data rate suddenly increases or becomes suspiciously low
in this example we have deliberately decided not to include it in the design
now compare the previous case with the case of the online store of
personal information
again this is just an imaginary example
so do not think of all the parameters to be exact
now in this case one the store will have a fast growing membership
each member will use multiple devices to capture and ingest their data
two over all members together the site will be updated at a really fast rate
making this a large volume data store with a fast ingest rate
three in this system our primary challenge is to keep up with the data
rate and hence erroneous data will be discarded after just one edit to reinvest
four now there is an actual policy for handling data overflow
which essentially says keep the excess data in a site store
and ingest them when the data rate becomes slower
but if the site store starts getting full
start dropping some incoming data at a rate of 0 1 at a time
now we should see why data ingestion together with it
policies should be an integral part of a big data system
especially when it involves storing fast data
a very significant aspect of data management is to document define
implement and test the set of operations that are required for
a specific application
as we will see later in the specialization some operations are independent of
the type of data and some others would require us to know the nature of the data
because the operations make use of a particular data model
that is the way that it is structured
in general there are two broad divisions of operations
those that work on a singular object and
those that work on collections of data objects
in the first case an operation that crops an image
that means extracts a sub area from an area of pixels
is a single object operation because we consider the image as a single object
one can think of many subclasses of the second category
where the operations are on data collections
we briefly referred to three very common operations that can be done
regardless of the nature of the data
the first is to take a collection and filter out a subset of that collection
the most obvious case is selecting a subset from a set
in this example we select circles whose number is greater than three
a second case is merging two collections together to form a larger collection
in the example shown
two three structure data items are merged by fusing the node with a common property
that is two
in the last case we compute a function on a collection and
return the value of the function
so in this example the function is a simple count
in the real world this kind of aggregate function can be very complicated
we will come back to this issue when we talk more about map readings but
in this course we will talk about many different data operations
every operator must be efficient
that means every operator must perform its task as fast as possible
by taking up as little memory or our disk as possible
obviously the time to perform an operation
will depend on the size of the input and the size of the output
so if there is an opportunity to use concurrency where the operator can split
its data and have different threads operate on the pieces at the same time
it should definitely do so
we present a simple example of an operator we saw on the previous slide
so this operator called selection
refers to choosing a subset of a set based on some conditions
here we are choosing a subset of circles whose numbers are even
to make it more efficient we can take the input data and
partition it randomly into two groups
now for each group
we can concurrently run the subset algorithm and get the partial results
for this operation the partial results can be directly sent to the output
without any additional processing step
okay we in essence store the data efficiently
but is it any good
are there ways of knowing if the data is potentially error free and useful for
the intended purpose
this is the issue of data quality
there are many reasons why any data application
especially larger applications need to be mindful of data quality
here are three reasons of course there are more that we do not mention
the first reason emphasizes that the ultimate use of big data
is its ability to give us actionable insight
poor quality data leads to poor analysis and hence to poor decisions
the second related data in regulated industries in areas like clinical
trials for pharmaceutical companies or financial data like from banks
errors in data in these industries can regulate regulations leading to
legal complications
the third factor is different than the first two
it says if your big data should be used by other people or
a third party software it very important for
the data to give good quality to gain trust as a leader provider
a class of big data applications is scientific where large
integrated collections of data are created by human experts to
understand scientific questions
ensuring accuracy of data will lead to correct human engagement and
interaction with the data system
gartner the well known technology research and
advising company created a 2015 industry report on big data qualities
in this report they identify the approaches to meeting
the data quality requirements in the industry
this methods include the adherence to standards where applicable
it also refers to the need to create the rules in the data system
that can be use to check if the data passes a set of correct this qualities
like is even employed above 18
it also includes methods to clean the data if it found to have errors or
inconsistencies
further the data quality management should include a well define work flow on how
low quality data could be corrected to bring it back to a high level of quality
there are many ways of looking at scalability
and we will consider them as we go forward in the course
one way is to consider scaling up and scaling out
simply put it is a decision between making a machine
that makes a server more powerful versus adding more machines
the first choice will involve adding more memory
replacing processes with process of more course and
adding more processes within a system with a very fast internet connection speed
the second choice will involve adding more machines to a relatively slower network
now there are no absolutes here
in many cases we will choose the former to get more performance for
large leader systems
the general trend in the big data world
however is to target the scale out option
most big data management systems today
are designed to operate over a cluster up machines and
have the ability to adjust as more machines are added and when machines fail
cluster management and management of data operations over a cluster
is an important component in today big data management systems
now we will briefly touch upon the complex issue of data security
it is obvious that having more sensitive data implies the need for more security
if the data is within the walls of an organization
we will still need a security plan
however if a big data system is deployed in the cloud
over multiple machines security of data becomes an even bigger challenge
so now we need to ensure the security for not only the machines
but also the network which will be heavily used during data transfer
across different phases of data operations
for example if the data store and the data analysis are performed over
different sets of servers that every analysis operation gets to
an additional overhead of encrypting the data as the data gets to the network and
decrypting when it gets to the processing server
this effectively increases operational cost
as of today while there are many security products the methods for
ensuring security and achieving data processing efficiency at the same time
remains a research issue in big data management
now the goal of a storage infrastructure obviously is to store data
there are two storage related issues we consider here
the first is the issue of capacity
how much storage should we allocate
that means what should be the size of the memory how large and
how many disk units should we have and so forth
there is also the issue of scalability
should the storage devices be attached directly to the computers
to make the direct io fast but less scalable
or should the storage be attached to the network
that connect the computers in the cluster
this will make disk access a bit slower but
allows one to add more storage to the system easily
now these questions do not have a simple answer
if you are interested you may look up a website given on your reading list
a different class of questions deals with the speed of the iu operation
this question is often addressed with this kind of diagram here called a memory
hierarchy or storage hierarchy or sometimes memory storage hierarchy
the top of the pyramid structure shows a part of memory called cache memory
that lives inside the cpu and is very fast
there are different levels of cache called l1 l2 l3
where l3 is the slowest but still faster than what we call memory
shown here in orange near the middle
the figure shows their speed in terms of response times
notice the memory streamed here is 65 nanoseconds per access
in contrast
the speed of the traditional hard disk is of the order of 10 milliseconds
this gap has prompted the design of many data structures and
algorithms that use a hard disk but tries to minimize the cost of
the io operations between the fast memory and the slower disk
but more recently a newer kind of storage
very similar to the flash drives or
usbs that we regularly use have made an entry as a new storage medium
these devices are called ssds or solid state devices
they are much faster than spinning hard disks
an even newer addition is the method called nvme
nvm stands for non - volatile memory
that makes data transfer between ssds and memory much faster
what all this means in a big data system is that now we have the choice of
architecting a storage infrastructure by choosing how much of each type of
storage we need to have
in my own research with large amounts of data i have found that using ssds
speed up all look up operations in data by at least a factor of ten over hard drives
of course the flip side of this is the cost factor
the components become increasingly more expensive as we go from the lower layers
of the pyramid to the upper layers
so ultimately it becomes an issue of cost - benefit tradeoff
sound let us consider a real life application to
demonstrate the utility and the challenges of big data
many industries naturally deal with large amounts of data
for our discussion we consider an energy company that provides gas and
electricity to its consumers in an urban area
in this news report you can see that commonwealth edison or con ed
the gas and electric provider of new york
decided to place smart meters all through its jurisdictions
that comes to 4 7 million smart meters
now smart meters are smart because aside from measuring energy consumption
they have a two way communication capability between the meter and
the central system at the gas and electric company
in other words they generate real time data from the meters to be stored and
processed at the central facility
how much data
according to this report
the number of data received at the center is 1 5 billion per day
so the system will not only consume this data but process it and
produce output at 15 - minute intervals and sometimes 5 minute intervals
let do the math
that comes to ingesting and processing
about 10 5 million data points per 15 minutes
so what kind of computation must take place within these 15 minutes
well one obvious computation is billing where one needs to compute who especially
in the commercial sector who actually owns the meter and should be billed
this requires combining the meter data
with the data in the customer database maintained by the company
but let just consider computation related to analytics
we can list at least four different kinds of computations
the first is computing the consumption pattern per user not per meter
per user where the output is a histogram of hourly usage
so the x axis of the histogram is hourly intervals and
the y - axis is a number of units consumed
this leads to the computed both daily and over larger time periods
to determine the hourly requirements for this consumer
the second computation relates to estimating the effects of
outdoor temperature on the electricity consumption of each consumer
for those you who are statistically inclined
this often involves fitting a piece - wise linear progression model to the data
the third task is to extract the daily consumption trends that occur
regardless of the outdoor temperature
this is again a statistical computation and may require something like
a periodic alter regression algorithm for time series theta
the algorithm is not that important there
what is more important is the ability to make make good prediction has a direct
economic impact because the company needs to buy energy from others
for example an under - prediction implies they will end up paying more for
buying energy at the last moment to meet the consumer requirements
the fourth task is to find groups of similar consumers based on their usage
pattern so that the company can determine how many distinct groups of customers
there are and design targeted energy saving campaigns for each group
this requires finding similarities over large number of time series data
which is a complex computation
regardless of the number and complexity of computation required
the company constrained by the fact that it has only 15 minutes to process the data
before the next and computation has to be performed
that issue is not just the bigness of the data but
the strip and strings of the arrival to output time
the analytics has value only if it can be completed within the life - cycle deadline
so if we were to design a big data system for such a company you would need to
understand how much are the computation can be executed in parallel and
how many machines with what kind of capability are required to handle the data
rate and the number and complexity of the analytical computations needed
hi my name is chad berkley
i am the cto of flightstats and i am here today to talk to you a little bit about
our platform and how we acquire and process data
but first of all i would like to start by just kind of introducing the company and
telling you a little bit about what we are all about
so flightstats is a data company and
we basically are the leading provider of global real - time flight status data
we pull in data from over 500 sources and we aggregate that data back together and
we sell it out to our customers which our other businesses as well as consumers
so just to give you a little bit of information about the scope and
scale of what we do
like i said we have over 500 sources of data
and on a daily basis we process about 15 million flight events
those that includes landings arrivals departures
any time the status of the flight changes we got some sort of message on that
we process about 260 million aircraft positions per day so we have an extensive
network that monitors graph positions for realtime flight tracking applications
and we also handle about one million pnrs or passenger name records
which are the actual data type of an itenerary any time you
book travel a pnr is created for you for your travel
and it includes all of the segments like air travel ferries
hotels taxis anyhting that can be scheduled on your trip
and we basically take in all that data and
we aggregate it together and we sell it back out
and how most people kind of know us for flightstats com that our
consumer site for business where we handle about 2 million daily requests
and we handle about 1 million mobile app requests
that our b to b side we cert out a lot of data by apis and real time data feeds
people make about 15 million api requests to us everyday
and we also send out about one and half million flight and trip notifications
so if you get a push notification to your phone
telling you that your flight is delayed or on time
that possibly has come from us
so a little bit about how the data flows through our company
we bring in all these different types of data and
our sources and it flows through our data acquisition team
we have a team whose primary purpose is to pull in all sorts of raw data
a very heterogeneous datasets
and process that into a normalized form
so if you kind of follow the blue arrow in this diagram you can see that it goes
through this raw data channel through the data hub
which the data hub is a central component of our system that i will talk
a little bit more about in a second
so the blue data the blue line is raw data coming in from the source
it goes through our data acquisition system
it turns into that purple line which is a normalized form
it then goes back through our data hub again and into our processing engine
our processing engine is really where most of the business logic happens
the first thing we have to do is we have to match any piece of
flight information against a flight that we know about and
primarily the way we know about flights is through schedules
so we import schedules on a daily basis from one of our partner
schedule providers
that data once it matched is then processed and
the processing basically looks at each message and tries to determine if
we think that that message needs to be passed on to consumers
so you know it looks at things like have we seen that message before
or is it a duplicate
is it from a data source that we trust
are there other things going on that we need to know about that
may impact whether that message is true or not
and once we decide that a message should be passed through
if you follow the green line
it goes into our process data channel on our hub and
it then pushed out to a couple different places
so first of all
it goes into our production database which is where all of our real time data lives
that database serves data to our websites
to our mobile apps and a variety of other places
it also goes into our data warehouse which
is where our analytics products use it
i will talk a bit more about that in a minute
and then the stream of data actually goes up to so many of our customers
we do not need a database on our side
they would rather build a database on their side so
we actually just stream all of the processed data directly to them
they then host it within their own systems
so a little bit more about the hub the hub is central to how we move data around
it a technology that we developed in - house
and it an object storage based scalable highly available
multi - channel data queuing and eventing system
the object storage part is we use amazon s3 to store this data
so it an object storage system
it scalable we can scale it horizontally or
vertically depending on but the what type of data is flowing through it
it highly available meaning
that we have multiple instances of it in different data centers
so if one that goes down we can easily pull another one up or
it we are going to cross multiple instances
and then it multi channel
so it got a rest interface and any surface can create
a new channel within the system and start posting data to it
that data is then queued based on the time that it comes in and
other services can be listening for events on those channels
so as soon as a new piece of data comes into one of those channels
any service that listening on that channel gets an event notification
they that service can then act upon that piece of data
and do whatever processing it may need to do
this project is open source and anybody can download it and use it
so a little bit about some of the data that we collect and aggregate
and flifo is kind of the industry term for flight information
and primarily we look at kind of the five different parts of flight
so we pull in information on gate departure and then that becomes a runway
departure basically when the wheels go up that is a runway departure
we do in - flight positional tracking so when your flight is moving along
about once every ten seconds we get notified of its latitude and longitude
and its heading and its speed and
its vertical center descent rate and several other variables
then once it lands
as soon as the wheels touch the ground we are notified of a runway arrival and
when the door is opened at the gate we have gate arrival information
all five of these data fields come in three different forms
so we have a scheduled scheduled departure and arrival
we have estimated departure and arrival which can come from a variety of sources
either airlines airports positional data et cetera
and then we have actuals so if we have an airport or
an airline that sending us data about exactly when the wheels touch down or
exactly when that door opens on that aircraft we push that data as well
we also generate some data at flight stops
so special incidents if an aircraft has an issue it in the news
we do flag our content with a message from our support staff
we do some prediction
right now we are just starting to get into that market or we are actually trying to
predict 24 hours out whether a flight will be delayed disrupted or on time
we do some synthetic positions so over oceans primarily
we do not get tracking data on aircraft over the oceans
there is currently no satellite - based tracking system for aircraft
so we basically take the last known position a heading a speed
and if we have a flight plan we will use a flight plan to synthesize the positions
when we are not getting actual positions over large bodies of water
we also generate notifications so the push alerts
the preflight emails delay notifications those types of things
we create those based on what we see in the data that coming in to us
we store all of our historical data in a data warehouse
so right now we have six years of historical flight data
and that powers our analytics products
so we allow airlines to do competitive analysis and route analysis
routes are very important to airlines
that how they compete with each other and
that primarily how they are judged by the faa and
other governmental organizations on whether they are on - time or not
we also do airport operations analysis things like taxi in and taxi out times
very important for lots of airports runway utilization
hourly passenger flows through airports that type of information
and we do on - time performance metrics so
airlines can look at how they are doing
how many flights did they complete
how many flights were on time within 14 minutes
and they can compare themselves to their competitors
so we host all of this in a hybrid cloud architecture
hybrid cloud basically means that we have our own private datacenter resources and
we also host resources in the amazon web services cloud
most of our core data processing and service layer is in our private data
center and we are getting ready to spin up a second private data center as well
right now our main data center is in portland oregon and we are going to spin
another one up on the east coast of the united states probably in q2 or q3
for our api we try to keep those close to our customers so
api end points and web end points live in amazon
and they are automatically routed to whichever end point is closest to you
you will automatically be routed to them
all of our private infrastructure is virtualized with vmware
we pretty much have a fully virtualized environment
and we are an agile shop so we have six small fast teams
those are product centric teams we allow them to be as customer interactive
as they need to be and we try to make our teams semi autonomous
so teams get to choose their own tools they get to choose their
own development methodologies they choose a variety of things
and we physically allow them
to do what they need to do to get their job done as quickly as possible
we try to automate everything
you do something once manually and then the next time you write a script or
program to do it
and we also measure everything
right now we are taking in about 2 5 billion metrics per month off
of our systems
and we use those metrics to monitor our application performance
to monitor revenue to monitor pretty much everything we do in the company
we really try to enable total system awareness
everything from the hardware layer up to the website is monitored
and we use industry best practices and tools and of course we try to recruit and
hire the best talent possible a little bit about our software stock
we are primarily a java shop
our core processing services are all written in java
we do use node js in our microservice edge layer
and node js is actually starting to move more down into the processing service
layer as well
we use many different types of data bases
our primary realtime database is post press
and we use mongo for the backend of our api services
on the website we are all html5 and we are moving to react and redux and
we are making use of elasticsearch for quick searching and indexing on our data
and of course we have ios and android mobile applications
so you can find out more about flightstats on our website
if you need data for your applications
please go to the developer center at developer flightstats com
you can sign up for a free test account and
be able to pull data directly off of our apis
if you are interested in the hub like i said that open source
please check out the git hub page and if you have any additional questions
feel free to contact myself john berkeley and
i would be happy to answer any of your questions via email
thanks for listening today and hope you have a great day
bye
different data sources in the game industry include using your finger
what type of device is coming from
the amount of headsets
it pretty much infinite
as far as the number of ways we can bring data in from the game
and it could be joystick or mouse keyboards there lots of ways
as well as what happens inside the game itself as far cars or
the driving tires flying machines anything
the volume of data it really depends on the type of game and
how often they want to send the data in
how many types of events they have tagged and how many users are playing the game
so if you have a user you have 5 million users that are playing your game and
you are tapping and you are tracking each tap of the screen
of where they went or each click of the mouse as they were using it
you are going to get a lot of volume of data
and so you need to be prepared to bring in a lot
of different data very very quickly
as far as the variety of data it depends
you have round pizzas and you have round tires
i mean they are completely different
they are both round but there different ways that you are going to want to know how
many pepperoni are on one pizza and how many lug nuts go on a tire
so the variety is really unlimited as well
it really just depends on each game
so you have to be prepared to bring in all kinds of data
touch data wheel data track speeds anything
and if you put taxonomy together that you can define as an example of verb
object location value and any number of other sources then you can basically
track anything you want as long as they all fall into the same kind of buckets
and the buckets can be different sizes based on the type of events
they do not all need to be 4 some can be 2 some can be 20
it does not really matter
the modeling challenge has really come down to who designs the structure at which
you store your data and how you want to retrieve that data
those kind of of storage and retrieval models are very very important
because what it really comes down to is speed
you can record a lot of data and it can take you five years to query it
it does not really do you any good
so you need to make sure you plan for reporting speed because that ultimately
what within the organisation needs is the ability to report on it very quickly
the management challenges really come down to trying to figure out what data to
store
a lot of times we go into various companies and you have got producers sitting
across the hall from designers and they do not even know each other
they do not realize what they want and the programmer says
i am going to put these events in and the product manager who wants to figure out
how many times somebody crashed says well i need these events in
so unless they are communicating you are going to get the wrong type of data
so the management challenge is trying to make sure everybody communicates
they decide on the taxonomy and the structure and
then we can go forward with tagging and getting in the entire game working
we process stayed in two main ways
one is streaming data
one is batched or scheduled data
streaming data has scripts that run instantly the minute the data arrives
and so as the data come in it gets processed and
then stored in a reporting format
so they can easily generate reports up to the second very very quickly
batch processing data really depends on the type of data where it coming from
most of the time when we download data from itunes or youtube or
something like that it comes in a csv or a very similar format
there not really a lot of processing we need to do
it more of ingesting that data
there are processes we need to run with some type of batch data but
most of the batch data we receive comes in as a csv or
other similar already processed formats
so typically while you can do processing in both modes most processing typically
happens with the streaming real - time data than it does with offline batch data
we actually did not use any technology in the a big data space
we created our own from scratch
what we did was we decided what kind of model we wanted
how we were going to store data
how we were going to retrieve data
and ultimately how we were going to reduce the data
because the more and more and more data you have the slower it is to actually do
a query because you have to look through all the different pieces of data
a lot of databases solve this problem for you but they were really doing it in more
generic way were we needed something very specific
so we started from scratch building our own data storage and retrieval and
reporting from the ground up
when it came to scalability it was really about designing the parts of
the system that could be independently scaled
so if data coming in in real - time we send that into what we call a gateway
and the gateway could be three gateways let say
but if the data starts getting over loaded
i just have to add another gateway
and a gateway is just this little light layer that just receives data
passes it on and goes back to it job does not do anything else
so it can receive a lot of data very quickly but
also i can just add another one
and it just automatically logs in and adds itself to a list and
now the data is being distributed amongst four gateways instead
query engine is the same way
when you are doing queries to try to get data out of the system so
you can build reports
if i need more query engines because people are doing more reporting
we can add more query engines
so the idea behind scalability is trying to break the services up into
the type of services that they most make sense
so that if you need to
you can add just the service without rebuilding the entire platform
my advice for people designing systems for big data is to first
try to understand what you want to accomplish
what is the goal
i mean we are going to ingest everything and we are going to report on everything
it not really something that you can achieve without some special thought
if you are going to focus on your area going to be say gardening
then look at what kind of things you are going to do in the gardening area and
try to focus on what that type of data is going to be
this is not going to restrict you to only being a gardener but
it is going to give you focus on how to design your system so
that they are actually going to work for you
you are going to continually evolve your systems add more things to them and
grow them
i would not suggest starting with an unlimited variety of options and
hoping you are going to solve all the problems
start with the goal of what your current solution is and expand from there
data can be fun but it can also be overwhelming
so try to keep the data in mind without keeping the world in mind and
i think you will be just fine
in this video we will provide a quick summary of the main points from our
first course on introduction to big data
if you have just completed our first course and
do not need a refresher you may now skip to the next lecture
after this video you will be able to recall
what started the big data era and the three main big data sources
summarize the volume variety velocity and
veracity issues related to each source
explain the five step data science process to gain value from big data
remember the main elements of the hadoop stack
we began our first course with an explanation of how a lead torrent of
big data combined with cloud computing capabilities to process data anytime and
anywhere has been at the core of the launch of the big data era
this big torrent of big data is often boil down to a few varieties of data
generated by machines people and
organizations with machine generated data
we refer to the data generated from real time sensors and industrial machinery or
vehicles
web logs that track user behavior online
environmental sensors
personal health trackers among many other sense data sources
with human generated data we really refer to the vast amount of social media data
status updates tweets photos and videos
with organization generated data we refer to more traditional types of data
including transaction information data bases and
structure data often stored in data warehouses
note that big data can be structured semi - structured and unstructured
which is a topic we will talk about more and in depth later in this course
whatever your big data application is and the types of big data you are using
the real value will come from integrating different types of data sources and
analyzing them at scale
overall by modeling managing and
integrating diverse streams to improve our business and
add value to our big data even before we start analyzing it
as a part of modeling and
managing big data is focusing on the dimensions of scale availability and
considering the challenges associated with this dimensions to pick the right tools
volume variety and velocity are the main dimensions which
we characterized big data and describe its challenges
we have huge amounts of data in different formats and
varying quality which must be processed quickly
veracity refers to the biases noise and abnormality in data
or the unmeasurable certainty is in the truthfulness and trustworthiness of data
and valence refers to the connectedness of big data
such as in the form of graph networks
each v presents a challenging dimension of big data mainly of size
complexity speed quality and consecutiveness
although we can list some other v based on the context
we prefer to list these five as fundamental dimensions which
this big data specialization helps you work on
moreover we must be sure to never forget the sixth v : value
at the heart of the big data challenge is turning
all of the other dimensions into truly useful business value
how will big data benefit you and your organization
the idea behind processing all this big data in the first place
is to bring value to the problem at hand
we need to take steps into big data engineering and
scalable data science to generate value out of big data
we have all heard it
data signs turns big data into insides or even actions
but what does that really mean
data signs can be taught of as the basis for empirical research
like data is used to induce information on the observations
these observations are mainly data
in our case big data related to a business or scientific use case
inside is a term we use to refer to the data products of data science
it is extracted from a diverse amount of data
through a combination of exploratory data analysis and modeling
the questions are sometimes less specific and it can require looking
carefully at the data for patterns in it to come up with a specific question
another important point to recognize is that data science is not static
one time analysis
it involves a process where models where you generate give us insights
are constantly improve to a further and prequel evidence and iterations
there are many ways to look at this process
one way of looking at it as two distinct activities
mainly big data engineering and big data analytics
or computational big data science as i like to call it
since more than simple analytics are being performed
a more detailed way of looking at the process reveals five listing steps or
activities of the data science process
namely acquire prepare analyze report and act
we can simply say that data science happens at the boundary of all the steps
ideally this process should support experimental work
which is constantly iterated and leads to more scientific exploration
as well as producing actionable results during these explorations
using dynamic scalability on big data and cloud platforms
this five step process can be used in alternative ways in real life big data
applications if we add the dependencies of different tools to each other
the influence of big data pushes for
alternative scalability approaches at each step of the process
acquire includes anything that helps us retrieve data
including finding accessing acquiring and moving data
it includes identification of and authenticated access to all related data
as well as transportation of data from sources to destinations
it includes ways to subset and match the data to regions or
times of interest which we sometimes refer to as geospatial querying
we divide the prepare data step into two sub - steps
based on the nature of the activity
the first step in data preparation involves exploring the data
to understand its nature what it means its quality and format
it often takes a preliminary analysis of data or
samples of data to understand it
this is why this primary step is called prepare
once we know more about the data through exploratory analysis
the next step is pre - processing of data for analysis
it includes cleaning data subsetting or filtering data and
creating data which programs can read and understand by modelling raw data
into a more defined data model or packaging it using a specific data format
we will learn more about data models and data formats later in this course
if there are multiple data sets involved
this step also includes integration of different data sources or
streams which is a topic we will explore in our course three
the prepared data then would be passed on to the analysis step
which involves selection of analytical techniques to use
building a model of the data and analyzing results
this step can take a couple of iterations on its own or
might require a data scientist to go back to steps 1 and
2 to get more data or package data in a different way
so exploration never ends
step 4 for communicating results includes evaluation of analytical results
presenting them in a visual way creating reports that include
an assessment of results with respect to success criteria
activities in this step can often be referred to with terms like interpret
summarize visualize and post - process
the last step brings us back to the very first reason we do data science
for a purpose
reporting insights from analysis and determining actions from insights based
on the purpose you initially defined is what we refer to as the act step
we have now seen all of the steps in a typical data science process
please note that this is an iterative process and findings from
one step may require previous steps to be repeated but need information
leading for further exploration and application of these steps
scalability of this process to big data analysis requires the use of
big data platforms like hadoop
the hadoop ecosystem frameworks and applications
provide such functionality through several overarching themes and goals
first they provide scalability to store large volumes of data
on commodity hardware
as the number of systems increase so
does the chance for crashes and hardware failures
they handle fault tolerance to gracefully recover from these problems
in addition they are designed to handle big data capacity and compressing text
files graphs of social networks streaming sensor data and raster images
we can add more data types to this variety
for any given data type
you can find several projects in the ecosystem that support it
finally they facilitate a shared environment
allow multiple jobs to execute simultaneously
additionally the hadoop ecosystem includes a wide range of open source
projects backed by a large and active community
these projects are free to use and easy to find support for
today there are over 100 big data open source projects
and this continues to grow many rely on hadoop but some are independent
here is one way of looking at a subset of tools in the hadoop ecosystem
this layer diagram is organized vertically based on the interface
lower level interfaces to storage and scheduling on the bottom and
high level languages and interactivity at the top
the hadoop distributed file system or hdfs is the foundation for
many big data frameworks since it provides scalable and reliable storage
as the size of your data increases you can add commodity
hardware to hdfs to increase storage capacity
so it enables what we call scaling out of your resources
hadoop yarn provide flexible scheduling and
resource management over the htfs storage
yarn is use at yahoo to schedule jobs across 40 000 servers
mapreduce is a programming model that simplifies parallel computing
instead of dealing with the complexities of synchronization and scheduling you only
need to give mapreduce two functions map and reduce
this programming model is so
powerful that google previously used it for indexing websites
mapreduce only assumes a limited model to express data
hive and pig are two additional programming models
on top of mapreduce to augment data modeling of mapreduce
with relational algebra and data flow modeling respectively
hive was created at facebook to issue sql - like queries using
mapreduce on their data in hdfs
pig was created at yahoo to model dataflow based programs using mapreduce
thanks to yarns ability to manage resources not just for
mapreduce but other programming models
giraph was built for processing large scale graphs efficiently
for example facebook uses giraph to analyze the social graphs of its users
similarly storm spark and flink were built for
real time and in - memory processing of big data
on top of the yarn resource scheduler and hdfs
in - memory processing is a powerful way of running big data applications
even faster achieving 100x better performance for some tasks
sometimes your data processing or tasks are not easily or
efficiently represented using the file and directory model of storage
examples of this include collections of key values or large sparse tables
nosql projects such as cassandra mongodb and
hbase handle all these cases
cassandra was created at facebook and facebook also use hbase for
its messaging platform
finally running all this tools requires a centralized management system for
synchronization configuration and to ensure high availability
zookeeper created by yahoo to wrangle services named after animals
performs these duties
just looking at the small number of hadoop stack components
we can already see that most of them are dedicated to data modeling
management and efficient processing of the data
in the rest of this course we will give you fundamental knowledge and
some practical skills on how to start modeling and managing your data and
picking the right tools for this activity from a plethora of big data tools
welcome to course two of the big data specialization
i am amarnath gupta
and i am ilkay altintas
we are really excited to work with you in this course
to develop your understanding and skills in big data modeling and management
you might have just finished our first course and see the potential and
challenges of big data
if you have not it not required but for
those with less background in the area you might find it valuable
let explain what we mean by big data modeling and management
suppose you have an application where the data is big in a sense and
it has a large volume or has high speed or comes with a lot of variations
even before you think of how to handle the bigness
you need to have a sense of what the data looks like
the goal of data modeling is to formally explore the nature of data so
that you can figure out what kind of storage you need and
what kind of processing you can do on it
the goal of data management is to figure out
what kind of infrastructure support you would need for the data
for example does your environment need to keep multiple replicas of the data
do you need to do statistical computation with the data
once these operational requirements you will
be able to choose the right system that will let you perform these operations
we will also introduce management of big data as it is
streaming from data sources and talk about storage architectures for big data
for example how can high velocity data get ingested
managed stored in order to enable real time analytical capabilities
or what is the difference between data at rest and data in motion
and how can a data system enable both
once you have understood the basic concepts of data modeling
data management and streaming data we will introduce you
to the characteristics of large volume data and how to think about that
thus we will transition from classical database management systems
that is dbmss to big data management systems or bdmss
we will present brief overviews of several big data management systems
available in the marketplace today
we are so excited to show you examples of archived and streaming big data sets
our goal is to provide you with simple hands on exercises that require
no programming but show you what big data looks like and why various
big data management systems are suitable for specific kinds of big data
in the end you will be able to design a simple
big data information system using this knowledge
we wish you a fun time learning and
hope to hear from you in the discussion forums and learner stories
happy learning and think big data
this is the second course in the 2016 version of our big data specialization
after listening to learners like you we have changed some of the content and
ordering in the specialization
this course takes you on the first step of any big data project
its modeling and management
we hope that this background on what big data looks like and
how it is modeled and managed in a large scale system will make you feel
more prepared to take steps towards retrieving and processing big data and
perform big data analytics which are topics coming up in the next courses
the third component of a data model is constraints
a constraint is a logical statement
that means one can compute and test whether the statement is true or false
constraints are part of the data model because they can specify something about
the semantics that is the meaning of the data
for example the constraint that a week has seven and
only seven days is something that a data system would not know unless this
knowledge is passed on to it in the form of a constraint
another constraint shown here
tells the system that the number of titles for a movie is restricted to one
different data models
as we will see in the next module will have different kinds of constraints
there may be many different kinds of constraints
a value constraint is a logical statement about data values
on a previous slide we have said that the age that is
the value of data elements representing the age of an entity can not be negative
we also saw an example of uniqueness constraint when we said
every movie can have only one title
in the words of logic
there should exist no data object that a movie and has more than one title
it easy to see that enforcing these constraints requires us
to count the number of titles and then verify that it one
now one can generalize this to count the number of values associated with
each object and check whether it lies between an upper and lower bound
this is often called a cardinality constraint of data property
in a medical example here the constraint has a lower limit of 0 and
an upper limit of 3
a different kind of value constraint can be enforced by restricting the type of
the data allowed in a field
if we do not have such a constraint we can put any type of data in the field
for example you can have - 99 as the value of the last name of a person
of course that would be wrong
to ensure that this does not happen we can enforce the type of the last name
to be a non - numeric alphabetic string
this example shows a logical expression for this constraint
a type constraint is a special kind of domain constraint
the domain of a data property or
attribute is the possible set of values that are allowed for that attribute
for example the possible values for
the day part of the date field can be between 1 and 31
while a month may have the value between 1 and 12
or alternately a value from the set january february ect till december
now one can devise a more complex constraint where the value of the date
for april june and september and november are restricted between 1 and 30
and if you think about it all three constraints that we have
described in the last slide are value constraints
so they only state how to restrict the values of some data property
in sharp contrast structural properties restrict the structure of the data
we will choose a more complex example for this
suppose we are a matrix as shown in the example and
we have restricted to be a square matrix
so the number of columns is exactly equal to the number of rows
we have not put any restriction on the number of rows or columns
but just that they have to be the same
now this constrains the structure of the matrix and
implies that the number of entries in the structure will be a squared number
if we convert this matrix to a three column table as shown and impose
the same squareness constraint it will translate to a more complex condition
that the number of data rows will be the square of
the number of unique values in column one of the table
we will encounter some more structural constraints in the next module
the second component of a data model is a set of operations that can be performed
on the data
and in this module
we will discuss the operations without considering the bigness aspect
in course three
we will come back to the issue of performing these operations when the data is large
now operations specified the methods to manipulate the data
since different data models are typically associated with different structures
the operations on them will be different
but some types of operations are usually performed across all data models
we will describe a few of them here
one common operation extract a part of a collection based on the condition
in the example here we have a set of records and
we are looking for a sub set that satisfies the condition that
the fifth field has a value greater than 100 000
the only one record satisfies this requirement
note that we called this operation subsetting rather loosely
depending on the context it also called selection or filtering
the next common operation is retrieving a part of a structure that is specified
in this case we specify that we are interested
in just the first two fields of a collection off records
but this produces a new collection of records which has only these fields
this operation like before has many names
the most dominant name is projection
in the next module we will see several versions of this operation for
different data models
the next two operations are about combining two collections
into a larger one
the term combine may be interpreted in various ways
the most straightforward of them is said union
the assumption behind the union operation
is that the two collections involved have the same structure
in other words if one collection has four fields and another has 14 fields or
if one has four fields on people and the dates of birth and the other has four
things about countries and their capitols they cannot be combined through union
in the example here their two collections have three and
two records respectively with one record that common between them
the green one
the result collection has four record
because duplicates are disallowed because it a set operation
there is indeed another version of union where duplicates are allowed and
will produce five records instead of four
the second kind of combining called a join can be done when
the two collections have different data content but have some common elements
in the example shown
the first field is the common element between the two collections on the left
in this kind of data combination there are two stages
first for each data item think of a record of collection one
one finds a set of matching data items in collection two
thus the first records of the two collections match
based on the first field
in the second phase of the operation
all fields of the matching record pairs are put together
in the first record of the result collection shown on the right
one gets the first four fields on the first collection and
the remaining two fields from the second collection
now in this one example we found one pair of matching records from the collections
in general one would find more than one matching record pairs
as you can see this operation is more complex and
can be very expensive when the size of the true collections are large
in the big data world we often hear the term structured data that is data having
a structure which is quite different from the so - called unstructured data
but what is a structure
let consider file 1
it a typical csv file that has three lines with different content
but the file content is uniform in the sense that each line
call it a record has exactly three fields
which we sometimes call data properties or attributes
further the first two of these fields are strings and the third one is a date
we can add more records that lines with the same pattern of data
to the file in the same fashion
the content will grow but the pattern of data organization will remain identical
this repeatable pattern of data organization makes the file structured
now let look at file 2 which is four records of five fields each
except that the third record seems to be missing the last entry
is this file structured
we argue that it is because the missing value makes the third record incomplete
but it does not break the structure or the pattern of the data organization
let looks at these two files side by side
clearly file 2 has more fields and hence is sort of wider than the first file
would you say that they have the same structure
well on the face of it they do not
but if you think more broadly
you would notice that they are both collection of k fields
the size of the collection respectively three and four differs
and k is 3 in the first case and 5 in the second
but we can think of 3 and 5 as parameters
in that case we will say that these files have been generated by a similar
organizational structure and hence they have the same data model
now in contrast consider this file
just looking at it it impossible to figure out how the data is organized and
how to identify subparts of the data
we would call this data unstructured
often compressed data like jpeg images mp3 audio files
mpeg3 video files encrypted data are usually unstructured
in module two we will elaborate on data models that are not fully structured or
are structured differently
this is the first of two hands - on exercises involving
sensor data from a weather station
in this one we will look at static data in a text file
the next one we will look at live data streaming from the weather station
in real time
in this exercise we will begin by opening a terminal window and
changing into the directory containing the station measurements
we will look at these measurements in a text file and then look at the key for
these measurements so we can understand what the values mean
finally we will plot the measurements
let begin
first we will open a terminal window by clicking on the terminal icon on the top
of the toolbar
next we will cd into the directory
containing the sensor data
we will run cd downloads big - data - two sensor
we can write ls to see the contents of this directory
the data from the weather station is in a text file called wx - data txt
we can run more wx - data txt to see the contents of this file
each line of this file is a separate set of measurements
there are two columns in this file the first column is a time stamp and
it separated by a second column by a tab
the second column itself has separate columns and these are separated by commas
the time stamp is the number of seconds since 1970
you will notice that it increases for each time stamp
you will notice that it increases for each measurement
but sometimes measurements come in at the same time
for example this one at 006
the measurements we see that the prefix is 0r1 for
most of them but some have 0r2
if we look at the other measurements
we see that all the 0r1 measurements start with dn dm dx and so on
whereas r2 begins with ta ua and pa
if we scroll down in the text file by hitting the space bar
we will see there are other measurements besides r1 and r2
for example there r5 that has th vh vs and so on
and there r0 which has all the measurements
so dn dm dx ta ua pa
and the remaining ones
next we will open another internal window and look at the key to this
measurements click on the tool bar to open the terminal window
cd into downloads big data two sensor
and the key to these measurements is in a file called wxt520format txt
we can run more wxt520format txt to see this file
this file says where each of the prefix is mean for
example sn is the wind speed minimum
sm is the wind speed average
and ta is the air temperature
so if we go back to our sensor file we see here ta equals 13 9c
that means the air temperature at this
time was 13 9 degrees celsius
we can also create a plot of the data in this text file
by running plot - data py wx - data txt ta
this says to plot the data in the wx - data file and the measure that we
want to apply is ta which according to our key is the air temperature
when we run it it displays a plot of the air temperature found in the text file
in this hands - on exercise
we will be looking at an image file which uses an array data model
first we will open a terminal window and display an image file on the screen
next we will examine the structure of the image and finally
extract pixel values from various locations in the image
let begin
first we will open a terminal window by clicking on the terminal icon at the top
of the toolbar
next we will cdn2 the directory containing the image
cdn2downloads bigdata2 image
we can run ls to see the image in different scripts
the file australia jpg is an image that we want to view
we can use eog to view it
run eog australia jpg eog is a common image viewer on linux
australia jpg is a satellite image of the australian continent
now let look at the structure of this image file
if we go back to our terminal window we can run the image
viewer in the background by hitting ctrl + z and then bg
we can view the dimensions or structure of the array data model of this
image by running dimensions py australia jpg
this says that the image has 5250 columns and 4320 rows
so it is a two - dimensional image
additionally each cell or
pixel within this image is composed of three 8 - bit pixels
these pixels are composed of three elements red green and blue
we can extract or view the individual pixel elements
at a specific location in the image by using the pixel py script
we can run pixel py australia jpg 0 0 to see the value at one location
the 0 0 location is the corner of the image
if we go back to the image the corners are all the ocean so they are dark blue
if we look at the value that was extracted we see that blue has a high
value of 50 whereas red and green are low with 11 and 10
if we view it at another corner by looking at 5000 0
we will see the same value
if we go back to the image the middle of the image which is the land
is orange or yellow
it definitely not blue so let take a look at a pixel value there
okay run pixel py australia jpg 2000 2000
this says that the red has a value of 118 green is 89 and the blue is 57
so the red and green are higher than blue so it not ocean
this is the second hands on exercises for csv data
in the first we saw how to import a csv file into a spreadsheet and
make a simple plot
in this one we will learn how to filter data and
perform some aggregate operations
we will begin by opening a terminal window and starting a spreadsheet
next we will load the csv data into the spreadsheet and
perform a filter over several columns
finally we will calculate an average and sum from the data
let begin
first we open a terminal window by clicking on the terminal icon in
the top toolbar
we can start the spreadsheet by writing oocalc
next let load our csv data into the spreadsheet
we click on file open census csv
and click ok on this dialog to load the data
column f in the spreadsheet is the state and
column h is the census population for 2010
let create a filter that just shows the data for
california for counties larger than one million people
we can create this filter by first selecting both the state name column and
the census 2000 population column
next we go to data filter standard filter
here we change the field name to be the state name
the condition we leave at equals and the value we use california
this filters all the rows unless the state is california
we then want to filter for
all the counties whose population is greater than one million people
to do that in this second line here we change the operator to and
the field name should be census 2010 population and
the condition should be greater than
then set the value to be one million
and click ok
we can see that all the data from the spreadsheet has disappeared except where
the state name is california and
the population is greater than one million people
we can reset or remove this filter to see all the data again
by going to data filter
reset filter
you can perform aggregate operations on the data in a spreadsheet
next let perform some aggregate operations over the data
we can compute the average and the sum of the data
to do this let run these calculations in a separate sheet
create a new sheet by clicking on the green plus button
to compute the average we select a cell and enter = average and
then we select the data that we want to compute the average from
if we go back to sheet one
we can select some of the data from the h column
so let just choose several counties in alabama
when we hit enter it takes us back to sheet one and
we can see that the average is computing
similarly we can compute the sum by entering = sum open parentheses
going back to sheet one and selecting the columns we want to sum
when we are done hit enter and the sum is computed
in this hands on exercise we will be looking at json data
first we will open a terminal window and
then look at the contents of a json file containing tweets from twitter
next we will examine the schema of this json file
finally we will extract different fields from the json data
let begin
first we will open a terminal window
by clicking on the terminal icon at the top of the toolbar
next we will see cd into the directory containing the json data
by running cddownload big data 2 json
we can run ls to see the json file
the json file is called twitter json
we can run more twitter json to view the contents of this file
the json data contains semi - structured data which is nested several levels
there are many tweets in this file and it hard to read using the more command
you can use space to scroll down and when we are done hit q
we can run the jsonschema pi command to view the schema of this data
we run jsonschema pitwitter json
and we will add a pipe more at the end
this shows the nested fields within this data
at the top level there are fields like contributors text and id and so
on but there are also fields nested within these top level fields for
example entities also contains called symbols media hashtags and
so on if we scroll down by hitting space
we will see that there several levels of nesting
for example user also has follow request sent id and so on
we can run the print json script to view the contents of a particular tweet and
a particular field within that tweet
let run print json py
it asks for the file name so
we will enter twitter json
and we will look at tweet 99
so let look at the top level field called text
so here we see the text for note the 99th tweet in this file
we could also look at a nested field within the file by running print json
again the file name is twitter json
we will look at tweet 99 again
and we will look at the field entities hashtags
the hashtags that are embedded or nested within the entities field
this is the first of two hands on exercises involving csv data
in this exercise we will import a csv file into a spreadsheet and
make a simple plot
we will begin by opening a terminal window and looking at a csv file in the terminal
next we will start the spreadsheet application and
import the csv data into the spreadsheet
we can then look at the rows and columns of the csv file and make a simple plot
let begin first open a terminal shell by
clicking on the black terminal icon at the top of the toolbar
next let cd into the directory containing the csv data
we will run cd space download big - data - 2 csv
we can run ls to
see the csv files
the file census csv contains census data for the united states
we can run the command more census csv to see the contents of this file
the first line of this file is the header with the columns separated by commas
you can go down in the file by hitting space
hit q to quit more
next let start a spreadsheet application
we run oocalc to start this
we can import the census data csv file into
the spreadsheet by going to file open
clicking on downloads
big data 2 csv census csv
in this dialog click ok
you can see into this spreadsheet
import of the csv data to a bunch of rows and columns
each column that was separated by a comma in the csv file
is a column in the spreadsheet
we can see that our csv file was successfully imported into
the spreadsheet
if we scroll down to the bottom of the spreadsheet
we can see how many rows there were in the csv file
there are 3194 rows in the csv file
if this file instead had millions or 10 millions of rows
then we would have to use a big data system such as hadoop or hdfs
let scroll back to the top
next let make a simple plot of some of the data in the csv file
let plot the population estimates for several years for the state of alabama
the state of alabama is given in the second row and
the population estimates are given in these columns
let select j through o so you get the population
estimate for 2010 through 2015
we can create a plot of these values by clicking on the chart button
and clicking finish
in the second hands on for csv data we will perform some filtering and
some aggregate operations over the data
welcome
in this module we will talk about data models
if you completed the introductory course of this specialization
you might recall our video on data variety
one way to characterize data variety
is to identify the different models of data that are used in any application
so what is a data model
and why do we care about data models in the context of big data
in this lesson we will introduce you to three components of a data model and
what they tell us about the data
so after this lesson you will be able to distinguish between structured and
unstructured data
describe four basic data operations namely selection projection union and join
and enumerate different types of data constraints like type value and
structural constraints
you will also be able to explain why constraints are useful to specify
the semantics of data
now regardless of whether the data is big or small one needs to know or determine
the characteristics of data before one can manipulate or analyze them meaningfully
let use a simple example suppose you have data is
a file of records with fields called first name last name and date of birth of
the employees in the company that this file consists of records with fields
and not for instance plain text gives us more insight
into the organization of the data in the file and hence is part of the data model
this aspect is called structure
similarly the consideration that we can perform
data arithmetic with the date of birth field and
not with the first name field is also part of our understanding of data model
these are called operations
finally we may know that in this company no one age
that is today date minus the date of birth cannot be less than 18
so it gives us a way to detect records with blatantly erroneous dates of birth
in the following three videos
we will look at these three aspects of data models more carefully
we mentioned before that a data model is characterized by the structure of
the data that it admits the operations on that structure and
a way to specify constraints
in this lesson
we will present a more detailed description of a number of common data models
we will start with relational data
it is one of the simplest and most frequently used data models today and
forms the basis of many other traditional database management systems
like mysql oracle teradata and so forth
so after this video you will be able to
describe the structural components of a relational data model
demonstrate which components become a data model schema
explain the purpose of primary and foreign keys
and describe join and other operations
the primary data structure for
a relational model is a table like the one shown here for a toy application
but we need to be careful about relational tables which are also called relations
this table actually represents a set of tuples
this is a relational tuple represented as a row in the table
we were informally calling this a record before
but a relational tuple implies that unless otherwise stated the elements of it
like 203 or 204 mary and so forth are atomic
that is they represent one unit of information and
cannot be decomposed further
we will return to this issue in the next few slides
thus this is a relation of six tuples
remember the definition of sets
it a collection of distinct elements of the same type
that means i cannot add this tuple to the solution
because if i do it will be introducing a duplicate
now in practice many systems will allow duplicate tuples in a relation but
mechanisms are provided to prevent duplicate entries if the user so chooses
so i cannot add it
here is another tuple i cannot add
it has all the right pieces of information but
it all in the wrong order
so it is a tuple dissimilar with the other six tuples in the relation
okay so how does the system know that this tuple is different
this brings our attention to the very first row that is the header of this table
painted in black
this row is part of the scheme of the table
lets look at it
it tells us the name of the table in this case employee
this also tells us the names of the six columns called attributes of the relation
and for each column
it tells us the allowed data type that is the type constraint for each column
given this schema
it should now be clear why the last red row does not belong to this table
the schema in a relational table can also specify constraints
shown in yellow in the third line of the schema row
it says that the minimum salary of a person has to be greater than 25000
further it states that every employee must have a first and last name
they cannot be left null that means without a value
why does not department or title column have this constraint
one answer can be that a newly hired employee may not be assigned
a department or a title yet but can still be an entry in the table
however the department column has another constraint
it restricts the possible values that is the domain of the attribute
to only four possibilities
hr it research and business
finally the first says that id is a primary key
this means it is unique for each employee
and for every employee knowing the primary key for
the employee will also uniquely know the other five attributes of that employee
you should now see that a table with a primary key
logically implies that the table cannot have a duplicate record because if we do
it will violate the uniqueness constraint associated with the primary key
let us introduce a new table containing the salary history of employees
the employees are identified with the column empid but
these are not new values that this table happens to have
they are the same ids that are present in the id column of the employee table
presented earlier
this is reflected in the statement made on the right
the term references means the values in this column can exist
only if the same values if you are in employees the table being referenced
also called the parent table
so in the terminology of the relational model the empid column of empsalaries
table is called a foreign key that refers to the primary key of the employees table
note that empid is not a primary key in this empsalaries table
because it is multiple to post with the same empid
reflecting the salary of the employee at different times
you will remember join is a common operation that we discussed before
so here is an example of a relational join performed
on the first three columns of employee and empsalaries table
where employees id and empsalaries empid columns are matched for equality
the output table shows all the columns involved
the common column is represented once
this form of join is called a natural join
it is important to understand that join is one of the most expensive
that means time consuming and space consuming operations
as data becomes larger and tables contain hundreds of millions of tuples the join
operation can easily become a bottleneck in a larger analytic application
so for analytical big data application that needs joins it very important to
choose a suitable data management platform that makes this operation efficient
we will return to this issue in module four
we end this video on a practical note
in many scientific and
business applications people start with csv files
manipulate them with the spreadsheet then migrate their relational system only
as an afterthought where the data becomes too large to handle the spreadsheet
while the spreadsheet offers many useful features
it does not conform and enforce many principles of relational data models
consequently a large amount of time may be spent in cleaning up and
correcting data errors after the migration actually happens
let me show a few examples from a spreadsheet that has 125 000 rows and
over 100 columns
the spreadsheet here lists terrorism attacks gathered from news media
so each row represents one attack
this is a valuable piece of data for people who study terrorism
but we are going to look at it from a relational data modelling viewpoint
first notice the column marked in green
it lists two weapons used in the attack separated by a semicolon
why is this really common
it makes this column non - atomic
it means that this column actually has two different values
in a relational design this information will be moved to another table
just like the multiple salaries of employees were placed in a separate table
next notice the column outlined in red
it describes the amount of property damaged by a possible terrorist attack
in this column the intended legitimate values are unknown
minor major and catastrophic
however the value in the highlighted part of the spreadsheet is minor and
then within bracket likely less than 1 million
which means a query like find all attacks for
which the property damage is equal to minor cannot be answered directly
instead we need to perform a substring search for
minor in the beginning of the description
which is doable but it a more expensive operation
this shows the columns of the spreadsheet
so this is part of the schema of the data
if you observe carefully you will see a recurring pattern
the designer of the data table determined that there can be at most three types of
attacks within a single encounter and represented with three separate columns
now in proper relational modeling one would say that there is a one to many
relationship between the attack and the number of attack types
in such a case it would be more prudent
to place these attack type columns in a separate table and
connect with the parent using a primary key foreign key relationship
here another block with a similar pattern
this time this is about the types and subtypes of weapons used
now can you determine how you might be able to reorganize this block
we will leave this as an exercise
it can be said without a doubt and the internet and
the worldwide web changed everything in our lives
the worldwide web is indeed the largest information source there is today
but what is the data model behind the web
we will say that it is the semi - structure data model
so after going through this video you will be able to distinguish between
the structured data model that we talked about the last time and
semi - structured data model
further you will recognize that the most
times the semi - structured data refers to tree structured data
and you can explain why tree navigation operations are important for
formats like xml and json
let a take a very simple web page
now this page does not have a lot of content or stylization
it does not even have links to other pages but
let look at the corresponding html code
this code is used by the browser so that it can render the html and
notice a few things in this data
the entire data comes within the html and slash html blocks
and we similarly have a body begin and end a header begin and
end a list begin and end and a paragraph begin and end
everywhere here a block is nested within a larger block
the second item to notice is that unlike a relational structure
there are multiple list items and multiple paragraphs
and any single document would have a different number of them
this means while the date object has some structure it is more flexible
so this is the hallmark office semi structure date model
now xml or
the extensible markup language is another well known standard to represent data
you can think of xml as a generalization of html where the elements that
the beginning and end markers within the angular brackets can be any string
and not like the ones allowed by standard html
let see an example from a biological case
as you can see there are two elements called sample attribute
they do structurally different because they
have different numbers of sub elements called the value
another interesting issue about xml data processing
is that you can actually credit for the structure elements
for example it is perfectly fine to ask what is the name of the element
which contains a sub - element whose textual content is cell type
as you can see you will get two results sample attribute
an experimental factor because sample attribute has a sub - element called
category and experimental factor has a subelement called link and
each of these subelements have the value celltape
now we cannot perform an operation like this in a relational data model
for example we cannot say which relation has a column with a value john
the same idea can also be seen in json or the java script object notation which
is a very popular format used for many different data like twitter and facebook
consider the example here all of the format looks different
we have a similar nested structure varies that is lists
containing other lists which will contain topples which consists of p value ps
so the key value pairs at atomic property names and their values
but one way to generalize about all these different forms of semi structured data
is to model them as trees
let go back to xml
the left side shows an xml document and
the right side shows the corresponding tree
since the top object of the root element is document
it is also the root of the tree
now under document we have a report element with author and
date under it and also a paper element with title author and source under it
the actual values like is the textual content of an element
since a text data item cannot have any further components
these text values are always the leaves of the tree
now modeling a document as a tree has significant advantages
a tree is a well - known data structure
that allows what is called a navigational access to data
imagine you are standing on the note paper
now you can perform a getparent operation and navigate the document
or you can perform a getchildren operation to get to the title author and source
you can even perform a getsiblings operation and get to the report
you can also ask a textual query like which strings have the substring data and
seek their root - to - node path to get to the path from document to the text nodes
you can possibly see how queries can be evaluated on the tree
now let us take the query
who is the author of xml query data model
in one evaluation scheme we can navigate up from the text note to title
to paper and then navigate down to author and then to don robie
well how do we know that we have to get up to paper before reversing the direction
well paper is the least that the lowest in the tree
common ancestor of the author note and the xm query data model note
we will come back to semi structure data in a later module
in this hands - on activity we will be looking at graph data in gephi
first we will import data into gephi and then examine the properties of the graph
next we will perform some statistical operations on the graph data
and then run some different layout algorithms
let begin
we are not running gephi in the cloudera virtual machine on the coursera website
there will be a reading with instructions on how to download install and
run gephi on your native hardware instead of in the virtual machine
once you have gephi started let import the data into gephi
we will go to file import spreadsheet and in the csv dialog
we will click the button with dot dot dot
we will choose diseasegraph csv and click open
make sure that as table says edges table click next
and make sure create missing nodes is checked
we will click finish to import the csv file as a graph
gephi now shows the graph in the center pane
the little black circles are the nodes of the graph and
the lines between them are the edges
in the top right we can see that there are 777 nodes and 998 edges
next let perform some statistical operations on this graph
in the statistics pane we can see average degree
let compute the average degree of the graph by clicking on run
this says that the average degree is 2 569
let close this let compute the connected
components we will click on run
we will leave this as a directed since the graph is directed
click ok it says that there
are 5 weakly connected components and 761 strongly connected components
let close this
next let run some different layout algorithms over the graph
the bottom left we will go to choose layout
we will choose force atlas and click run
click stop to stop the layout
we can see that gephi has grouped strongly connected components together
in different clusters
we can also see that they are parts of the graph that are not connected
let run a different layout algorithm
the combo box choose fruchterman reingold click run
after it runs for a few seconds click stop then click the magnifying glass
center on graph to see the whole graph
in this layout all the nodes appear to be equally spaced
but we can also see the nodes with many edges
in this hands on activity we will be working with lucene
a search engine that uses a vector space model to index data
first we will open a terminal window and
change into the directory containing the data and scripts
next we will index some text documents and query terms in lucene
after that we will query using weighted terms or
boosting to see how this changes the rankings
finally we will show the term frequency - inverse document frequency or
tf - idf in terms
let begin
first let open a terminal window by clicking on the terminal icon at the top
of the tool bar
next let cd into the directory containing the scripts and data
we will run cd
downloads big - data - 2 vector
we will run ls to see the scripts
the data directory contains three text files
each of these text files contains news data about elections
let index these files by running runlucenequery sh data
next let query lucene for some terms in these text documents and see the rankings
let query for the term voters
you can see the rankings and scores that news1 csv ranked first
news2 csv was the second ranking and the third was news3 csv
let query for delegates
for this term we see that news2 csv
was first and news1 was second and
news3 did not contain the term at all
now let query for both terms voters and delegates
in this result we see that news2 was ranked first
news1 was ranked second and
news3 was ranked third
now lets use query term waiting or
boosting to increase the relevance of voters
i can do this by ensuring voters carat 5 delegates
the carat 5 notation is a syntax for
lucene for boosting
when we run this we see that now news1 is ranked first
news2 is ranked second and news3 is ranked third
notice this is different from the original query with voters and delegates
where news2 is ranked first and news1 was ranked second
now let look at the term frequency inverse document frequency or tf - idf
we will enter q to quit this and
we will run lucene tf - idf sh data
let look at the tf - idf for voters
you can see that it ranked number 1 for news1
second news 2 and news 3 is last
lets try delegates
here we see that news 2 had a higher score than news 1
and news 3 is not listed because news 3 does not contain this term
hit q to quit
so the next category of data we discuss has the form of graphs or networks
the most obvious example being social networks
now speaking of social networks
tim libzek created a social network from the lord of the rings trilogy
this graph represents the characters allegiances
that is who is faithful to whom in the books
so the nodes are characters and other entities like cities and
the edges connecting pairs of nodes represent allegiances
so after this video you will be able to identify graph data in practical problems
and describe path neighborhood and connectivity operations in graphs
but this specialization includes a separate course in graph analytics
that provides a much more detailed treatment on the subject
now what distinguishes a graph from other data models
is that it bears two kinds of information
one properties and attributes of entities and relationships and
two the connectivity structure that constitutes the network itself
one way to look at this data is shown in the figure
borrowed from the apache spark system
in this representation
the graph on the left is represented by two tables on the right
the vertex or node table gives ids to nodes and lists their properties
the edge table has two parts
the colored part represents the properties of the edge
whereas the white part contains just the direction of the arrows in the network
thus since there is a directed edge going from node 3 to node 7
there is a tupple 3 7 in that part of the edge table
now this form of the graph model is called the property graph model
which we will see many times in this course and in the specialization
now representing connectivity information gives graph data a new kind of
computing ability that different from other data models we have seen so far
even without looking at the properties of the nodes and edges one can get very
interesting information just by analyzing or querying this connectivity structure
consider a social network with three types of nodes user city and
restaurant and three types of edges friend likes and lives in
the leftmost node ag represents me
and i am interested in finding a good italian restaurant in new york
that my friends or their friends who also live in new york like
i shall possibly choose it3 because it has the highest number of
like edges coming into it from people who have a lives in edge to new york
and at the same time
can be reached by following the friend edges going out from me
now this shows a very important class of operations and ground data namely
traversal that involves edge following based on some sort of conditions
a number of path operations required some sort of optimization
the simplest among these is the well known shortest path query which is applied to
node networks to find the best route from a source location to a target location
the second class of optimization operations is required to find
an optimal path that must include some user specified nodes for
the operation has to determine the order in which the nodes once we visited
the classical application is a trip planner
where the user specifies the cities she wishes to visit and
the operation will optimize the criterion like the total distance covered
the third category is a case where the system must find the best possible
path in the network given two or
more optimization criteria which cannot be satisfied simultaneously
for example if i want to travel from my house to the airport
using the shortest distance but also minimizing the amount of highway travel
the algorithm must find a best compromise
this is called a pareto - optimality problem on graphs
the neighborhood of a node n in a graph is a set of edges directly connected to it
a k neighborhood of n is a collection of edges between nodes that are
at most k steps away from n
so going back to our mini social network graph bob jill
and sarah are the first neighbors of ag while max tim and
pam belong to the second neighborhood and not the first neighborhood of ag
finally jen is a third level neighbor
an important class of analysis to perform with neighborhoods is community finding
a community and a social network can be a very close group of friends
so the graph shown in this figure has four communities
one can see in the figure that each community has a higher density of edges
within the community and a lower density across two different communities
finding densely connected parts of a graph
helps identify neighborhoods that can be recognized as communities
a more complex class of operations include finding the best possible clusters
which is another name for communities in a graph so
that any other grouping of nodes into communities will be less effective
now as graphs become bigger and denser these methods become harder to compute
thus neighborhood - based optimization operation present
significant scalability challenges
if we inspect the neighborhood of every node in a graph sometimes
we will find neighborhoods that are different from all others
these neighborhoods are called anomalous
consider the following four graphs and on the central red node
the first graph is odd because it almost perfectly star shaped
that is the nodes that the red node is connected to are almost unconnected
amongst themselves
that really odd because it does not happen in reality much
so it an anomalous node
the second figure shows a neighborhood to which
a significantly large number of neighbors has connected amongst themselves
this makes the graph very cliquish where a clique refers to a neighborhood
where each node is connected to all other neighborhood nodes in the neighborhood
the third figure shows a neighborhood
where some edges have an unusually heavy weight compared to the others
the fourth figure shows a special case of the third
where one edge is predominantly high rate compared to all the other edges
connectedness is a fundamental property of a graph
in a connected graph
each node is reachable from every other node through some path
if a graph is not connected but there are subgraphs of it which are connected
then these subgraphs are called connected components of the original graph
in the figure on the right there are four connected components
a search gradient like finding optimal paths
should be performed only within each component and not across them
for large graphs there are several new parallelized techniques for
the detection of connected components
we will discuss a map reduce based technique for
connected components in a later course
we have discussed quite a few data models but
there are many other data models that have been developed for
various purposes and we really cannot cover all of them in a single course
we will end these lectures on data models with an example that may give you
an insight into a class of objects that define in many different applications
so after this video you will be able to describe how arrays can serve
as a data model explain why images can be modeled as vector arrays
specify a set of operations on scalar and vector arrays
now we have all seen the arrays
in the simplest case an array is a matrix like this
let call this array a
the top row in yellow gives the column numbers and
the left column also in yellow gives the row numbers
when we need to refer to a value of the array as a 3 2
we mean the value of the cell in row 3 and column 2
this is called indexed structure where 3 and
2 are the row and column indices that are necessary to get the value of a data item
the area has two dimensions
so hence there are two indexes
if these were a three dimensional array we would have three indexes
now earlier
we have seen that we can represent the two dimensional array as a three column table
one column for the row index one column for the column index and
the last column for the value
thus a k dimensional array can be represented as a relation with k
plus one columns
the number of tuples in this representation will be the product of
the size of the first dimension times the size of the second dimension and so forth
then in this case the size is five in each dimension
so there are 25 c column tuples in a relation representing the array
a more useful situation occurs when the cells of an array have
a vectors as values
as you can see in the 2d vector array here each cell has a three vector
that is a vector with three elements
therefore if we want to receive a cell value and
treat it like before we will get back the whole vector
now this type of data should look familiar to you
because images often have a red green and blue channels per pixel
in other words
images of vector valued arrays where each array cell has a three color vector
we can also think of the array model in the context of satellite images
where there are many more channels depending on the range of wavelengths
each channel catches
let us consider the operations on arrays of vectors
because it is a combination of two models one can create different combinations of
array operations vector operations and composite operations
here are some
the dimension of the array here the first operation is two
if we pick up any dimension say one
the size of it is also two because they are two elements
zero and one in each dimension
as we saw before the value of the cell 1 1 is a vector 16 301 74
while the value of a11 component 2 is 74
the length of the vector is a square root of the sum of the elements of the vector
so length of a11 would come to 310 375
the distance function can be so
simple like the euclidean distance function between two vectors or
the cosine of an angle between them as we saw in the previous lecture
but it can also be something more complex based on the needs of the application
obviously one can also perform operations like selection over indices so
we can ask which cells had the zero value greater than 25
giving as the result zero one and one zero
you will experience some of these operations in your hands on session
next we will look at a data model that has been successfully used to
retrieve data from large collections of text and images
let stay with text for now
text is often thought of as unstructured data
primarily because it does not really have attributes and relationships
instead it is a sequence of strings punctuated by line and parent of breaks
so one is to think of a different way to find and analyze text data
in this video we will describe that finding text from a huge collection of
text data is a little different from the data modules we have seen so far
to find text we not only need the text data itself but
we need a different structure that is computed from the text data
to create the structure
we will introduce the notion of the document vector model which we call a vector model
further you will see that finding a document
is not really an exact search problem
here we will give a query document and
ask the system to find all documents that are similar to it
after this video you will be able to describe
how the similarity is computed and how it is used to search documents
finally you will see that search engines use some form of vector models and
similarity search to locate text data
and you will see that the same principle can be use for finding similar images
let us describe the concept of a document to an example
so lets consider three types of document shown here
now we will create a matrix
the rows of the matrix stand for
the documents and columns represent the words in the documents
we put the number of occurrences of returning the document in
the appropriate cell of the matrix
in this case the count of each term in each document happens to be one
this is called the term frequency matrix
so now that we have created the term frequency matrix
which we call tf for short
we will create a new vector called the inverse document frequency for each term
we will explain why we need this vector on the next slide
first let see how it computed
the number of documents n here is 3
the term new occurs twice in the collection
so the inverse document frequency or idf of the term new
is log to the base 2 n divided by term count
that is log to the base 2 3 divided by 2 which is 0 584
we will show the ideal score for all six terms here
now some of you may wonder why we use log to the base 2 instead of let
say log to the base 10
there is no deep scientific reason for it
it more of a convention in many areas of computer science
when many important numbers are powers of two
in reality log to the base two of x is the same
number as log to the base ten of x times log to the base two of ten
the second number that is log to the base two of ten is a constant
so the relative score of idf does not change regardless of the base we use
now let understand this number one more time
the document frequency of a term is the count of that term in the whole
collection divided by the number of documents
here we take the inverse of the document frequency so
that n the number of documents is in the numerator
now before we continue let understand the intuition behind the idf vector
now suppose you have 100 random newspaper articles and
let say 10 of them cover elections
which means all the others cover all other subjects
now in this article let say we will find the term election 50 times in total
how often do you think you will find the term is as in the verb is
you can imagine that it will occur in all hundred of them and
that too multiple times
we can safely assume that the number of occurrences of is
will be 300 at the very least
thus the document frequency of is is six times the document frequency of election
but that does not sound right does it
is is such a common word that it prevalence has a negative impact
on its informativeness
so now if you want to compute the idf of is and
election the idf of is will be far lower
so idf acts like a penalty factor for
terms which are too widely used to be considered informative
now that we have understood that idf is a penalty factor
we will multiply the tf numbers through the idf numbers giving us this
this is a column - wise multiplication of the tf numbers with the idf
numbers giving us what we call the tf - idf matrix
therefore for each document we have a vector represented here as a row
so that row represents the relative importance of each term in the vocabulary
vocabulary means the collection of all words that appear in this collection
if the vocabulary has 3 million entries then this vector can get quite long
also if the number of document grows let just say to 1 billion
then it becomes a big data problem
now the last column after each document of vector here
is the length of the document vector
which is really the square root of the sum of squares of the individual term scores
as shown in the formula
to perform a search in the vector space
we write a query just like we type terms in google
here the number of terms is three
out of which the term new appears two times
in fact this is the maximum frequency out of all terms in the query
so we take the document vector of the query and multiply each term
by the number of occurrences divided by two which is the maximum term frequency
now in this case it gives us two non - zero terms
0 584 and
0 292 for new and york
then we compute the length of the query vector just like we did for
the document vectors on the previous slide
next we will compute the similarity between the query vector and each document
with the idea that we will measure how far the query vector is from each document
now there are many similar functions defined and used for different things
a popular similarity measure is the cosine function
which measures the cosine function of the angle between these two vectors
the mathematical formula for computing the function is given here
the intuition is that if the vectors are identical
then the angle between them is zero
and therefore the cosine function evaluates to one
as the angle increases
the value of the cosine function decreases to make them more dissimilar
the way to compute the function is to multiply the corresponding elements of
the two vectors
that is the first element of one with the first
element of the second one and so forth
and then sum of these products
here the only contributing terms are from new and
york because these are the only two non - zero terms in the query vector
this sum is then divided by the product of the document length and
the query length that we have computed earlier
look at the result of the distance function and you will notice that
the document 1 is much more similar to the query than the other two
so while similarity scoring and document ranking process working effectively
the method is a little cotton dry
more often than not users would like a little more control
over the ranking of terms
one way of accomplishing this is to put different weights on each query term
and in this example the query term york has a default weight of one
times has a weight of two
and post has a weight of five as specified by the user
so relatively speaking
york has a weight of 1 divided by 1 + 5 + 2 is equal to 0 125
times has a weight of 0 25 and post has a weight of 0 625
now the scoring method we showed before will change a bit
the query of vector and its length were exactly as computed before
however now each term in the query vector is further multiplied by these
relative weights
in our case the term york now has a much higher rate
so as expected this will change the ranking of the documents and
new york post will have the highest rank
now similarity search is often used for images using a vector space model
one can compute futures from images
and one common feature is a scatter histogram
consider the image here
one can create the histogram of the red green and
blue channels where histogram is the count of pixels having a certain density value
this picture is mostly bright so the count of dark pixels is relatively small
now one can think of histograms like a vector
very often the pixel values will be bend before creating a vector
the table shown is a feature vector where the numbers for each row have been
normalized with the size of the image to make the row sum equal to one
similar vectors can be computed of the image texture shapes of objects and
any other properties
thus making a vector space model significant for unstructured data
in our experience as educators we have observed that
learners often make the assumption that the format of the data
is the same as the logical model of the data in the way that you operate on it
the goal of this very short lecture is to ensure
that we can clearly distinguish between the two
so after watching this video you will be able to explain the difference between
format which is a serialized representation of the data as opposed to
data model which we have discussed at length in the previous months
perhaps the simplest example of a data format is a csv file so here is
a snippet of a csv file from the global terrorism database we discussed earlier
we know that csv or common separative values means
that the term between two commas is the value of an attribute
but what is this value
the common notion is that it a content of a single relation
where each line is a record that a tuple and
the iod value in the csv corresponds to the iod attribute as shown here
now that might very well be true but let look at a different example
let say this snippet here is my csv file
there is no difference between the previous file and this one
however here is how i like to see the data
as you can see this is a graph
and the data model is the same although the format is still csv
this is the second hands on exercise for sensor data
in the first we looked at static data in a text file
in this one we will be looking at real - time streaming measurements
first we will open a terminal window and
cd into the directory containing the data and the scripts
next we will connect to the weather station and
look at the real - time data as it streams in
after that we will look at the key to remind ourselves what the fields mean
and finally we will plot the data streaming from the weather station
let begin
first open a terminal window by clicking on the terminal icon
top of the toolbar
noise let run cd downloads big - data - 2 sensor
you can run ls to see the name of the scripts
let run stream - data py to see the real - time data
this shows us the real - time measurements coming from the weather station
by looking at the time stamps
we can see that each measurement arrives about one second after the previous one
additionally we can see that r1 comes fairly often
whereas other measurements such as r2 are not as often
we can open another terminal and
look at the key to remind ourselves what these measurements mean
the key is in wxt - 520 - format txt
we could run more wxt - 520 - format txt to view it
if we go back to our live data we can see that the 19th
measurement here says ta was 22 5 degrees celsius
and look up here see that ta is the air temperature
the next measure we can see that dn was equal to 255d
according to our key dn is the wind direction minimum and
the units are degrees
we can also plot specific measurements streaming live from the weather station
let plot the wind speed average
if we look at our key we see that the wind speed average is sm
so we can plot this by running stream - plot - data py sm
this plots the data as the weather station sends it to us
if we look at the x - axis
we can see that one measurement comes in about every second
we can plot other measurements by choosing different fields from the key
for example we can plot the air pressure by running stream - plot - data py pa
since pa is the air pressure
first thing we notice is that there only one measurement so far in the graph
this means that the air pressure measurements are not coming as
fast as the wind measurements
in fact we only got one
in this hands - on activity
we will be looking at real time data streaming from twitter
first we will open a terminal window and
cd into the directory containing python scripts to access this data
next we will look at the contents of tweets streaming from twitter
containing specific words
finally we will plot the frequency of these streaming tweets
let begin
first click on the terminal icon at the top of the toolbar
let cd into the directory containing the python scripts to access the real time
data from twitter
we will run cd downloads big - data - 2 json
we can run ls to see the files in this directory
the file auth should be created containing your twitter authentication information
you could see the separate reading for how to setup the twitter app and
how to create this file
next let run the script live tweets to view tweets in real time containing
a specific word
let run livetweets py president
this will show the real time tweets containing the word president
inaudible runs in the first column you can see the time stamp of the tweet
in the second column you can see the text
when you are done hit ctrl + c
let run livetweet again using a different keyword that appear more
frequently
let use the word time we will run livetweet time
when we are done hit ctrl + c
we can plot the frequency of these tweets by running the script plot tweets
let run plot tweet president to see the frequency for the word president
as this runs we could see the frequency changes over time
i can see that the maximum was one
and a few times there were just one tweet in that second
when you are done looking at the graph
click in the terminal window and hit enter
now let plot the frequency for the word time
run plottweets py time
this plot shows that the word time appears a lot more frequently than president
we can see spikes in the frequency of 40 and a maximum of around 65
when you are done looking at the graph
click on the terminal window and press enter to quit
with big data streaming from different sources in varying formats models and
speeds it is no surprise that we need to be able to ingest this data
into a fast and scalable storage system
that is flexible enough to serve many current and future analytical processes
this is when traditional data warehouses with strict data models and data
formats do not fit the big data challenges for streaming and batch applications
the concept of a data lake was created in response of these data big storage and
processing challenges
after this video you will be able to describe
how data lakes enable batch processing of streaming data
explain the difference between schema on write and schema on read
organize data streams and data lakes and
data warehouses on a spectrum of big data management and storage
what is a data lake
simply speaking a data lake is a part of a big data infrastructure
that many streams can flow into and
get stored for processing in their original form
we can think of it as a massive storage depository with huge
processing power and ability to handle a very large number of concurrence
data management and analytical tasks
in 2010 the pentaho corporation cto james dixon
defined a data link as follows
if you think of a datamart as a store of bottled water cleansed and
packaged and structured for easy consumption
the data lake is a large body of water in a more natural state
the contents of the data lake stream in from a source to fill the lake
and various users of the lake can come to examine it dive in or take samples
a data lake works as follows
the data gets loaded from its source
stored in its native format until it is needed
at which time the applications can freely read the data and add structure to it
this is what we call schema on read
in a traditional data warehouse the data is loaded into the warehouse
after transforming it into a well defined and structured format
this is what we call schema on write
any application using the data needs to know this format in order to retrieve and
use the data
in this approach
data is not loaded into the warehouse unless there is a use for it
however schema on read approach of data lakes ensures
all data is stored for a potentially unknown use at a later time
so how is a data lake from a data warehouse
a traditional data warehouse stores data in a hierarchical file
system with a well - defined structure
however a data lake stores data as flat files with a unique identifier
this often gets referred to as object storage in big data systems
in data lakes each data is stored as a binary large object or
blob and is assigned a unique identifier
in addition each data object is tagged with a number of metadata tags
the data can be searched using these metadata tags
to retrieve it when there is a need to access it
from a users perspective
metadata is stored is not a problem as long as it is accessible when needed
in hadoop data architectures data is loaded into hdfs and processed
using the appropriate data management and analytical systems on commodity clusters
the selection of the tools is based on the nature of the problem being solved and
the data format being accessed
we will talk more about the processing of data streams and
data lakes in the next course in this specialization
to summarize a data lake is a storage architecture for
big data collection and processing
it enables collection of all data suitable for
analysis today and potentially in the future
regardless of the data source structure and
format it supports storage of data and transforms it only when it is needed
a data lake ideally supports all parts of the user base to benefit from
this architecture including business storage analytics and computing experts
finally and perhaps most importantly
data lakes are infrastructure components within a big data architecture
that can evolve over time based on application - specific needs
what is a data stream
after this video
you will be able to summarize the key characteristics of a data stream
identify the requirements of streaming data systems and
recognize the data streams you use in your life
when we talked about how big data is generated and
the characteristics of the big data using sound waves
one of the challenges we mentioned was the velocity of data coming in varying rates
for some applications this presents the need to process data
as it is generated or in other words as it streams
we call these types of applications streaming data processing applications
this terminology refers to a constant stream of data flowing from a source
for example data from a sensory machine or data from social media
an example application would be making data - driven marketing decisions in
real time
through the use of data from real - time sales trends
social media analysis and sales distributions
another example for streaming data processing is monitoring of industrial or
farming machinery in real time
for monitoring and detection of potential system failures
in fact any sensor network or
internet of things environment controlled by another entity
or set of entities falls under this category
for example as you have seen in an earlier video
flightstats is an application
that processes about 60 million weekly flight events
that come into their data acquisition system
and turns it into real - time intelligence for airlines and
millions of travelers around the world daily
so how then do we define a data stream
a stream is defined as a possibly unbounded sequence of
data items or records
that may or may not be related to or correlated with each other
each data is generally timestamped and
in some cases geo - tagged
as you have seen in our examples the data can stream from many sources
including instruments and many internet of things application areas
computer programs websites or social media posts
streaming data sometimes get referred to as event data as
each data item is treated as an individual event in a synchronized sequence
streams pose very difficult challenges for
conventional data management architectures
which are built primarily on the concept of persistence static data collections
due to the fact that most often we have only one chance to look at and
process streaming data before more gets piled on
streaming data management systems cannot be separated from real - time processing
of data
managing and
processing data in motion is a typical capability of streaming data systems
however the sheer size variety and
velocity of big data adds further challenges to these systems
such systems are designed to manage relatively simple computations
such as one record at a time or
a set of objects in a short time window of the most recent data
the computations are done in near - real - time
sometimes in memory and as independent computations
the processing components often subscribe to a system
or a stream source non - interactively
this means they sent nothing back to the source nor
did they establish interaction with the source
the concept of dynamic steering involves dynamically changing the next steps or
direction of an application through a continuous
computational process using streaming
dynamic steering is often a part of streaming data management and processing
a self - driving car is a perfect example of a dynamic steering application
but all streaming data applications fall into this category
such as the online gaming example we discussed earlier in this course
amazon kinesis an other open - source apache
projects like storm flink spark streaming and
samza are examples of big data streaming systems
many other companies also provide streaming systems for
big data that are frequently updated in response
to the rapidly changing nature of these technologies
as a summary dynamic near - real - time streaming data management
processing and steering is an important part of today big data applications
next we will look at some of the challenges for
streaming data management and processing
now that we have seen what streaming data means
let s look at what makes streaming data different and what some management and
processing challenges for streaming data are
after this video you will be able to compare and
contrast data in motion and data at rest
differentiate between streaming and batch data processing
and list management and processing challenges for streaming data
we often hear the terms data addressed and
data in motion when talking about big data management
data - at - rest refers to mostly static data collected from one or
more data sources and the analysis happens after the data is collected
the term data - in - motion refers to a mode
although similar data collection methods apply
the data gets analyzed at the same time it is being generated
just like the sensor data processing in a plane or a self - driving car
analysis of data addressed is called batch or static processing and
the analysis of streaming data is called stream processing
the run time and memory usage of most algorithms that process static data
is usually dependent on the data size and
this size can easily be calculated from files or databases
a key property of streaming data processing is the size of the data
is unbounded and this changes the types of algorithms that can be used
algorithms that require iterating or looping over the whole data set are not
possible since with stream data you never get to the end
the modeling and management of streaming data should enable computations on
one data element or a small window of group of recent data elements
these computations can update metrics monitor and
plot statistics on the streaming data
or apply analysis techniques to the streaming data
to learn about the dynamics of the system as a time series
since computations need to be completed in real time
the analysis tasks processing streaming data should be quicker or
not much longer than the streaming rate of the data
which we define by it velocity
in most streaming systems the management and
processing system subscribe to the data source but does not
send anything back to the stream source in terms of feedback or interactions
these requirements for streaming data processing are quite different than batch
processing where the analytical steps have access to often all data and
can take more time to complete a complex analytical task with less pressure
on the completion time of individual data management and processing tasks
most organizations today use a hybrid architecture
sometimes get referred to as the lambda architecture for
processing streaming and back jobs at the same time
in these systems streaming wheel over the real - time data is managed and
kept until those data elements are pushed
to a batch system and become available to access and process as batch data
in such systems a stream storage layer is used to enable fast
trees of streams and ensure data ordering and consistency
and a processing layer for
data is used to retrieve data from the storage layer to analyze it and
most probably little bit to a batch data stream and notify the streaming
storage that the data set does no longer need to be in streaming storage
the big data challenges we discussed were scalability data replication
and durability and fault tolerance arise in this type of data very significantly
among many there are two main challenges that needs to be overcome
to avoid data loss and enable real time analytical tasks
one challenge in streaming data process is that the size and
frequency of the mean data can significantly change over time
these changes can be unpredictable and may be driven by human behavior
for example streaming data found on social networks such as facebook and
twitter can increase in volume during holidays
sports matches or major news events
these changes can be periodic and occur for example in the evenings or weekends
for example people may post messages on facebook more in the evening
instead of during the day working hours
streaming data changes may also be unpredictable and sporadic
there can be an increase in data size and
frequency during during major events sporting matches and things like that
other changes include dropping or missing data or even no data
when there are network problems or device generating the data has hardware problems
as an example of streaming data fluctuation
consider the number of tweets per second
on average there are 6 000 tweets sent every second
however in august 2013 the world record was
set when over 144 000 tweets were sent in a second
that a factor of 24 increase
at the end of this lesson we will ask you to focus on twitter streams for
trending topics and any other topic
you will notice how the rates of tweets streaming
changes between different times and different topics
to summarize streaming data must be handled differently than static data
unlike static data where you can determine the size streaming data is
continually generated and you can not process it all at once
streaming data can unpredictably change in both size and frequency
this can be due to human behavior
finally algorithms for
processing streaming data must be relatively fast and simple
since you do not know when the next data arrives
in a previous lecture
we said that new interesting solutions are emerging in the big data product space
while these solutions do not have the full fledged power of a dbms
they offer novel feature combinations that suit some application space just right
one of these products is aerospike
which calls itself a distributed nosql database and
key value store and goes on to say that it is architected for
the performance needs of today web scale applications
the diagram here is from an aerospike whitepaper
it shows how aerospike relates to the ecosystem for which it is designed
the top layer shows several applications for real time consumer facing systems
such as travel recommendation systems pricing engines used for
stock market applications real time decision systems that
analyze data to figure out whether an investment should be done and so forth
now all of these systems have the common need
that large amounts of data should be accessible to them at any point of time
the aerospike system can interoperate with hadoop - based systems so
spark or a legacy database or even a real time data source
it can exchange large volumes of data with any such source and
serve fast lookups and queries to the applications above
now that translates to a very high availability robust and
strong consistency needs
the figure here presents a high level architecture diagram of aerospike
the first item to notice here is what they call a fast bat
which essentially refers to the left side of the architecture
the client system processes transactions
that is data that are primarily managed in a primary index that is a key value store
this index stays in memory for operational purposes
however the server also interacts with the storage layer for persistence
the storage layer uses three kinds of storage systems
in memory with a dynamic ram or dram a regular spinning disk
and flash ssd which is solid state device for fast loading of data when needed
in fact the aerospike system
has optimized its performance with characteristics of an ssd in mind
for those of who are not sure what an ssd is you can think of
an ssd as a kind of storage device whose random read performance is much
faster than speeding hard disk and the write performance is just a little slower
one vendor recently advertised its ssd has sequence share read speeds of up to
2 500 mbps and the sequential write speeds as fast as 1 500 mbps
now why is this important in a big data discussion
when we speak of scalability grade efficiency fast transactions and so
forth we often do not mention that part of the performance
guarantee is governed by the combination of hardware and software
so the ability to offer more efficient persistent storage with fast io
implies that while a significant amount of information can be stored on disk
it can be done without compromising the overall system performance for
an environment that needs fast data loading
the second point of uniqueness is a secondary index there
aerospike built secondary index fields that are non - primary keys
a non - primary key is a key attribute that makes a tuple unique
but it has not been chosen as a primary key
in aerospike secondary indices are stored in main memory
they are built on every node in a cluster and co - located with the primary index
each secondary index entry contains references to records
which are local to the node
as a key value store aerospike uses standard database like
scalar types like integer string and so forth as well as lists like reddis
the map type is similar to the hashtag of reddis and contains attribute value pairs
since it is focused on real time web application it supports geospatial data
like places with latitude and longitude values or regency polygons
this allows them to perform kv store operations for example like is
the location of this in la jolla which is a point - in - polygon query
or a distance query like find hotels within three miles of my location
kv queries are constructed programmatically
now interestingly aerospike also provides a more declarative language called aql
aql looks very similar to sql
the standard query language for relational databases
a query like select name and
age from user star profiles projects out the name and age values
from the profile record set that belongs to the ding space called users
the language also allows advocate functions like sum and
average and other user defined functions
which the system may evaluate through a map produced time operation
we mentioned earlier that while most medium assists today offer base
guarantees aerospike despite being a distributor information system
actually offers acid guarantees
this is accomplished using a number of techniques
we will consider a few of them to give you a flavor of the mechanisms that current
systems use to balance between large scale data management and
transaction management in a cluster where nodes can join or leave
you may recall that consistency means two different things
one is to ensure that all constraints like domain constraints are satisfied
the second meaning is applied to distributor systems and
ensures all copies of a data item in a cluster are in sync
for operations and single keys with replication and
secondary indices aerospike provides immediate consistency
using synchronous writes to replicas within the cluster
synchronous write means the write process will be considered
successful only if the replica is all subdated
no other write is allowed on the record while the object of replica is pending
so what happens if there is an increase in the number of write operations due to
an increase in ingestion rate
in aerospike it is possible to relax this immediate consistency condition
by bypassing some of the consistency checks
but if this is done eventual consistency will still be enforced
durability is achieved by storing data in the flash ssd on every node and
performing direct reads from the flash
now durability is also maintained through the process of replication because we have
multiple copies of data
so even if one node fails the latest copy of the last data is available from one or
more replica nodes in the same cluster
as well as in nodes residing in remote clusters
but does that just contradict the cap theorem
the cap theorem holds when the network is partitioned
that means when nodes in different parts of the network
have different data content
aerospike reduces and tries to completely eliminate the situation by making
sure that the master knows exactly where all the other nodes are
and the replication is happening properly even when
the new nodes are joining the network
in the previous modules we talked about data variety and streaming data
in this module we will focus on a central issue in large scale data processing and
management and that is when should we use hadoop or yarn style system
and when should we use a database system that can perform parallel operations
and then we will explore how the state of the art big data management systems
address these issues of volume and variety
we start with the problem of high volume data and
two contrasting approaches for handling them
so after this video you will be able to
explain the various advantages of using a dbms over a file system
specify the differences between parallel and distributed dbms
and briefly describe a mapreduce - style dbms and
its relationship with the current dbmss
in the early days when database systems were not around or
just came in databases were designed as a set of application programs
they were written to handle data that resided in files in a file system
however soon this approach led to problems
first there are multiple file formats
and often there was a duplication of information in different files
or the files simply had inconsistent information that was very hard to
determine especially when the data was large and the file content was complex
secondly there was not a uniform way to access data
each data access task like finding employees in a department sorted by their
salary versus finding employees in all departments
sorted by their start date needed to be written as a separate program
so people ended up writing different programs for
data access as well as data update
a third problem was rooted to the enforcement of constraints
often called integrity constraints
for example to say something like every employee has exactly one job title
one had arrived that condition as part of an application program called
so if you want to change the constraint you need to look for
the programs where such a rule is hard coded
the fourth problem has to do with system failures
supposed joe an employee becomes the leader of a group and moves in to
the office of the old leader ben who has now become the director of the division
so we update joe details and move on to update ben new office for
the system crashes
so the files are incompletely updated and
there is no way to go back and start all over
the term atomicity means that all of the changes that we need to do for
these promotions must happen altogether as a single unit
they should either fully go through or not go through at all
this atomicity is very difficult to handle when the data reside in one or more files
so a prime reason for the transition to a dbms is to alleviate these and
other difficulties
if we look at the current dbms especially relational dbms
we will notice a number of advantages
dbmss offer query languages which are declarative
declarative means that we state what we want to retrieve
without telling the dbms how exactly to retrieve it
in a relational dbms we can say find the average set of salary of
employees in the r d division for every job title and sort from high to low
we do not have to tell the system how to group these records by job title or
how to extract just the salary field
a typical user of a dbms who issues queries does not worry about how
the relations are structured or whether they are located in the same machine
or spread across five machines
the goal of data independence is to isolate the users from the record
layout so long as the logical definition of the data
which means the tables and their attributes are clearly specified
now most importantly relational dbmss have developed a very mature and
continually improving methodology of how to answer a query efficiently
even when there are a large number of cables and
the number of records exceeds hundreds of millions
from a 2009 account eb uses the tera data system with
72 machines to manage approximately 2 4 terabytes of relational data
these systems have built powerful data structures algorithms and
sound principles to determine how a specific array should be onset
efficiently despite the size of the data and the complexity of the tables
now with any system bad things can happen
systems fail in the middle of an operation
malicious processes try to get unauthorized access to data
one large can often underappreciated aspect of a dbms is
the implementation of transaction safety and failure recovery
now recall our discussion of atomicity
in databases a single logical operation on the data is called a transaction
for example a transfer of funds from one bank account to another
even involving multiple changes like debiting one account and
crediting another is a single transaction
now atomicity is one of the four properties that a transaction should
provide
the four properties collectively called acid are atomicity
consistency isolation and durability
consistency means any data written to the database must be
valid according to all defined rules including constrains
the durability property ensures that once a transaction has been committed
it will remain so even in the event of power loss crashes or errors
the isolation property comes in the context of concurrency
which refers to multiple people updating a database simultaneously
to understand concurrency think of an airline or a railway reservation system
where hundreds and thousands of people are buying cancelling and
changing their reservations and tickets all at the same time
the dbms must be sure that a ticket should no be sold twice
or if one person is in the middle of buying the last ticket
another person does not see that ticket as available
these are guaranteed by the isolation property that says
not withstanding the number of people accessing the system at the same time
the transactions must happen as if they are done serially that is one after another
providing these capabilities is an important part of the m in dbms
so next we consider how traditional databases handle large data volumes
the classical way in which dbmss have handled the issue of large
volumes is by created parallel and distributed databases
in a parallel database for example parallel oracle
parallel db2 or post sql xe
the tables are spread across multiple machines and operations like selection
and join use parallel algorithms to be more efficient
these systems also allow a user to create a replication
that is multiple copies of tables
thus introducing data redundancy so
that failure on replica can be compensated for by using another
further it replicates in sync with each other and
a query can result into any of the replicates
this increases the number of simultaneous that is conquer into queries
that can be handled by the system
in contrast a distributed dbms which we will not discuss in detail in this course
is a network of independently running dbmss that communicate with each other
in this case one component knows some part of the schema of it is neighboring
dbms and can pass a query or part of a query to the neighbor when needed
so the important takeaway issue here is
are all of these facilities offered by a dbms important for
the big data application that you are planning to build
and the answer in many cases can be negative
however if these issues are important then the database management
systems may offer a viable option for a big data application
now let take a little more time to address an issue that often discussed in
the big data word
the question is if dbmss are so powerful
why do we see the emergence of mapreduce - style systems
unfortunately the answer to this question is not straightforward
for a long while now dbmss have effectively used parallelism specifically
parallel databases in addition to replication would also create partitions
so that different parts of a logical table can physically reside on different
machines then different parts of a query can access the partitions in parallel and
speed up creative performance
now these algorithms not only improve the operating efficiency but
simultaneously optimize algorithms to take into account the communication cost
that is the time needed to exchange data between machines
however classical parallel dbmss did not take into account machine failure
and in contrast mapreduce was originally developed not for storage and
retrieval but for distributive processing of large amounts of data
specifically its goal was to support complex custom computations that could
be performed efficiently on many machines
so in a mapreduce or mr setting
the number of machines could go up to thousands
now since mr implementations were done over hadoop file systems
issues like node failure were automatically accounted for
so mr effectively used in complex applications like data mining or
data clustering and these algorithms are often very complex and
typically require problem specific techniques
very often these algorithms have multiple stages
that is the output from one processing stage is the input to the next
it is difficult to develop these multistage algorithms in a standard
relational system
but since these were genetic operations many of them were designed to work
with unstructured data like text and nonstandard custom data formats
now it now amply clear that this mixture of data management requirements
and data processing analysis requirements have created an interesting tension in
the data management world
just look at a few of these tension points
now dbmss perform storage and retrieval operations very efficiently
but first the data must be loaded into the dbms
so how much time does loading take
in one study scientists use two cvs files
one had 92 attributes with about 165 million tuples for
a total size of 85 gigabytes
and the other had 227 attributes with 5 million tuples for
a total size of 5 gigabytes
the time to load and index this data in mysql and postgresql took 15 hours each
in a commercial database running on three machines it took two hours
now there are applications like the quantities in the case we discussed
earlier where this kind of loading time is simply not acceptable
because the analysis on the data must be performed
within a given time limit after it arrival
a second problem faced by some application is that for
them the dbmss offer too much functionality
for example think of an application that only looks at the price of an item
if you provide it with a product name or product code
the number of products it serves is let say 250 million
this lookup operation happens only on a single table and
does not mean anything more complex like a join
further consider that while there are several hundred thousand customers
who access this data none of them really update the tables
so do we need a full function dbms for this read - only application
or can we get a simpler solution which can use a cluster of machines but
does not provide all the wonderful guarantees that a dbms provides
at the other end of the spectrum there is an emerging class of optimization
that meets all the nice transactional guarantees that a dbms provides
and at the same time meets the support for efficient analytical operations
these are often required for systems like real - time decision support
that will accept real - time data like customer purchases on a newly released
product will perform some statistical analysis so
that it can determine buying trends
and then decide whether in real - time
a discount can be offered to this customer now
it turns out that the combination of traditional requirements and
new requirements is leading to new capabilities and
products in the big data management technology
on the one hand dbms technologies are creating new techniques that make
use of mapreduce - style data processing
many of them are being developed to run on hdfs and
take advantage of his data replication capabilities
more strikingly dbmss are beginning to have a side door for
a user to perform and mr - style operation on hdfs files and
exchange data between the hadoop subsystem and the dbms
thus giving the user the flexibility to use both forms of data processing
it has now been recognized that a simple map and
reduce operations are not sufficient for many data operations leading to
a significant expansion in the number of operations in the mr ecosystems
for example spark has several kinds of join and
data grouping operations in addition to map and reduce
sound dbmss are making use of large
distributed memory management operations to accept streaming data
these systems are designed with the idea that the analysis they need to perform on
the data are known before
and as new data records arrive they keep a record of the data
in the memory long enough to finish the computation needed on that record
and finally computer scientists and
data scientists are working towards new solutions
where large scale distributed algorithms are beginning to emerge to solve different
kinds of analytics problems like finding dense regions of a graph
these algorithms use a mr - style computing and
are becoming a part of a new generation of dbms products
that invoke these algorithms from inside the database system
in the next video we will take a look at some of the modern day data management
systems that have some of these capabilities
as we mentioned in the last lesson there is no single irricuteous solution for
big data problems
so in this lesson
our goal will be to explore some existing solutions in a little more depth
so after this lesson you will be able to
explain the at least five desirable characteristics of
a big data management system explain the differences between acid and
base and
list examples of bdmss and describe some of their similarities and differences
so we start from high level suppose there were an ideal big data management system
what capabilities or features should such a system have
professor michael carey of the university of california irvine
has described a number of characteristics
we will go through them and use them as an idealistic yardstick
against which we compare existing solutions
first the ideal bdms would allow for a semi - structured data model
now that does not mean it will only support a specific format like xml
the operative word here is flexible
the flexibility can take many forms
one of which is the degree to which schemas should be supported by the system
in a perfect world it should support
a completely traditional application which requires the development of a schema
at the same time it should also support applications which require no schema
because the data can vary in terms of its attributes and relationships
a different axis of flexibility is in the data types it supports
for example it should support operations on text and documents
it should also permit social media and other data that have a time component and
need temporal operations like before after during and so on
similarly it should allow spacial data and
allow operations like find all data within a five mile radius of a landmark
as we saw in a previous lesson
a big advantage of a dbms is that is provides a query language
there is a notion that query languages present a steep learning curve for
data science people with no background in computer science
however to effectively manage large volumes of data
it often more convenient to use a query language and
let the query processor automatically determine optimal ways to receive data
now this query language may or may not look like sql
which is the standard query language used by the modern relational systems but
it should at least be equally powerful
now this is not an unreasonable feature given that most dbms vendors offer their
own extension of sql of course it not enough to just have a good query language
today big data systems must have a parallel query engine
which will run on multiple machines
the machines can be connected to a shared nothing architecture or
shared memory architecture or a shared cluster
the shared nothing means two machines do not share a disk or memory
but this is a critical requirement for
any bdms regardless of how complete the supported query languages is for
efficiency sake continuing with our list the next
capability of a bdms is often not emphasized as much as it should be
some applications working on top of a bdms will issue queries
which will only have a few conditions and a few small objects to return
but some applications especially those generated by other software tools or
machine learning algorithms can have many many conditions and
can return many large objects
in my own work we have seen how internet bots can blast an information system
with really large queries that can potentially choke the system
but that should not happen in a bdms
now we discussed streaming data in a previous lesson
in many cases a bdms will have both streaming data
which adds to the volume as well as to the large data that
need to be combined with the streaming data to solve a problem
an example would be to combine streaming data from weather stations
with historical data to make better predictions for wild fire
we have discussed the definition significance and
importance of scalability before
however what a bdms needs to guarantee
that it is designed to operate over a cluster possibly a cluster of hundred or
thousand of machines and that it knows how to handle a failure
further the system should be able to handling new machines joining or
existing machines leaving the cluster
finally our bdms must have data management capabilities
it should be easy to install restart and configure provide high availability and
make operational management as simple as possible even when
a bdms is declined across data centers that are possibly geographically apart
in a prior module we discussed the acid properties of transactions and
said that bdmss guarantee them
for big data systems there is too much data and
too many updates from too many users
so the effort to maintain acid properties
may lead to a significant slowdown of the system
now this lead to the idea that while the acid properties are still desirable
it might be more practical to relax the acid conditions and replace them
with what is called the base properties beginning with basic availability
this states that the system
does guarantee the availability of data in the following sense
if you make a request there will be a response to that request
but the response could still be failure to obtain data or
the data is not inconsistent state or changing state
well this is not unusual because it much like waiting for
a check to clear a bank account
second there is a soft state
which means the state of the system is very likely to change over time
so even during times without input
there may be changes going on through the system due to eventual consistency
thus the state of the system is always soft
and finally there eventual consistency
this means that the system will eventually become consistent
once it stops receiving input
when it stops receiving input
the data will propagate to everywhere that it should sooner or later go to but
in reality the system will continue to receive input
and it not checking the consistency of every transaction at every moment
because there still lots of transactions to process
so if you make a new facebook post your friend in zambia who is supposed
to see your update but is served by a very different data center in a different
geographic region will certainly see it but may not see right away
now for those of you who have a bit of computer science background
we just want to mention in passing that there is actually some theoretical results
behind this relaxation
the result comes from what is called the cap theorem
also named bauer theorem after the computer scientist eric bauer
he states that it is impossible for a distributed computer system
to simultaneously provide all three of the following guarantees
consistency
it means all nodes see the same data at any time
availability which is a guarantee that every request receives a response
about whether it succeeded or failed
and partition tolerance
which means the system continues to operate
despite arbitrary partitioning due to network failures
now most of the big data systems available today will adhere
to these base properties although several modern systems
do offer the stricter acid properties or at least several of them
now given the idealistic background of what is desirable and
achievable in a big data system today marketplace for
big data related products looks somewhat like this
now this is matt turk depiction of big data products from a couple of years back
you would notice that the products are grouped into categories like no sql
massively parallel databases analytic systems real time systems and so forth
in this lesson we will do a quick tour through a few of these products
from different areas of this landscape
in each case our goal will to be assess what aspects of our ideal bdms they cover
and whether they have obvious limitations
now we will not cover all features of every system but will highlight
those aspects of the system that are relevant to our discussion on bdms
the first up in our rapid tour of modern systems is redis
redis calls itself an in - memory data structure store
in simple terms redis is not a full blown dbms in the sense we discussed earlier
it can persist data on disks and does so to save its state but
it intended use is to optimally use memory and memory based methods
to make a number of common data structures very fast for lots of users
here is a list of data structures that redis supports
a good way to think about them is to think of a data lookup problem
now in the simplest case a lookup needs a key value pair
where the key is a string and the value is also a string
so for a lookup we provide the key and get back the value
simple right
let see
i am sure you have seen captures like this
these are small images used by websites to ensure that the user is a human and
not a robot
the images presented to the user who is supposed to write the text he or
she sees in the image into a text box
upon success the user is let in
to implement this one obviously needs a key value stored
where the key is the idea of the image
and the value is the desired text
now what if we wanted to use the image itself as the key
instead of an id number that you generate separately
the content of the image
which let say is a jpg file can be thought of as a binary string
but can it serve as a key then
according to the redis specification it can
the redis string can be binary and
can have a size of up to 512 megabytes although its internal limit is higher
so small images like this can indeed be used as binary string keys
in some application scenarios keys may have an internal structure
for example product codes may have product family
manufacturing batch and the actual product id strung together into one id
the example shown here is a typical twitter style key to store the response
to comment one two three four
how long do we want to keep the comment around
this is a standard big data issue when it comes to streaming data
whose data values have limited utility beyond the certain period
one typically would not look for
this response possibly three months after the conversation
one would certainly not like to keep such a value in memory for a long time
because the memory is being used as a cache for rapid access to current data
in fact redis has the ability to delete an expired key and
can be made to call a function to generate a new key
an interesting side benefits to structured keys
that it can encode a hierarchy to the structure
in the example
we show keys that represent increasingly finer subgroups of users
with this structure
a lookup on user commercial entertainment will also retrieve values
from user commercial entertainment movie industry
a slightly more complex case occurs when the value is not atomic
but a collection object like a list which by definition is an ordered set
an example of such a list can come from twitter
that uses redis list to store timelines
now borrowed from a twitter presentation about their timeline architecture
our timeline service can take a specific id and
it quickly identifies all tweets of this user that are in the cache
these tweets are then populated by the content of the tweet
then returned as a result
this list can be long but the insertion and delete operations on the list
can be performed in constant time which is in milliseconds
if a tweet is retweeted the ids of those tweets are also added
to the list of the first tweet as you can see for the three cases in the figure
when the lists are long space saving becomes an important issue
so redis employs a method called ziplists which essentially
compacts the size of the list in memory without changing the content
often producing significant reduction in memory used
of course while ziplists are very efficient for
retrieval they are a little more complex for insertion and deletion operations
since redis is an open source system
twitter made a few innovations on the redis data structures
one of these innovations is that they created lists of ziplists
this gave them the flexibility of having constant timing insertions and
deletions and at the same time used the compressed representation to save space
in 2012 the timeline service has about
40 terabytes of main memory serving 30 million user queries per second
running on over 6 000 machines in one data center
for those interested i would like to point you to two wonderful twitter presentation
explaining twitter use of redis among other design issue for
a realtime data system like twitter
we also introduce links in the supplemental readings for this lesson
now the value to be looked up by the keys can actually be more complicated and
can be records containing attribute value pairs themselves
redis values can be hashes
which are essentially named containers of unique fields and their values
in the example the key std : 101
is associated with five attributed value pairs
the hashed attributes are stored very efficiently
and even when the list of attributed value pairs in a hash is really long
retrieval is efficient
horizontal scalability or
scale out capabilities refers to the ability of a system
to achieve scalability when the number of machines it operates on is increased
redis allows data partitioning through range partitioning and hash partitioning
rate partitioning takes a numeric key and breaks up the range of keys into bins
in this case by bins of 10 000 each of bin is assigned a machine
and ultimately a partitioning is where computing a hashing function on a key
suppose we have 10 machines
we pick the key and use the hash function to get back a number
we represent the number modular 10 and the result in this case
2 is the machine to which the record will be allocated
replication is accomplished in redis through master - slave mode
the slaves have a copy of the master node
and can serve read queries
clients write to the master node
and master node replicates to the slaves
clients read from the slaves to scale up the read performance
the replication processes are synchronous
that is that slaves do not get replicated data it locks them with each other
however the replication process does ensure
that they are consistent with each other
the next system we will explore is vertica
which is the relational dbms designed to operate on top of htfs
it belongs to a family of dbms architectures called column stores
other products in the same family are ucdv
carrot cell xvelocity from microsoft and so forth
the primary difference between a row store and
a column store is shown in the diagram here
logically this table has five columns
emp number department number
hire date employee last name and employee first name
in a row oriented design the database internally organizes the record
two four by two
in a column store the data is organized column wise
so the nth number column is stored separately from the department id
column and so forth
now suppose a query needs to find the id and
department id of all employees who were hired after first of january 2001
the system only needs to look up
the hire date column to figure out which records qualify
and then pick up the values of the id
and the department of id columns for the qualifying records
the other columns are not touched
so if a table has 30 to 50 columns very often only a few of them are needed for
any single query
so for tables with 500 million rows and 40 columns a typical query is very fast
and uses much less memory because a full record is not used most of the time
my own experience is that with an application that needed a database
with 150 billion tuples in a table
accounting operation took a little under three minutes to complete
a second advantage of the column store comes from the nature of the data
in a column store data in every column is sorted
the figure on the right shows three sorted columns of a table
with three visible columns
the bottom of the first column shown here
has many accurate sixteen transactions on the same day
the second column has customer ids which can be numerically close to each other
they are all within seventy values of the first customer
so in the first case we can just say that the value is one one
2007 and the next 16 records have this value
that means we do not have to store the next 16 values thus saving space
now this form of shortened representation is called compression
and this specific variety is called run - length encoding or rle
another form of encoding can be seen in the second column
here the customer ids a long integer but for
the records shown there are nearby numbers
so if we pick a value in the column and just put the difference between
this value and other values the difference will be small
it means we will need fewer bites to represent them
this one of compression is called frame - of - reference encoding
the lesson to remember here is that compressed data presentation
can significantly reduce the total size of a database and if bdms
should use all such tricks to improve space efficiency
while the space efficiency and performance of vertica is impressive for
large data one has to be careful about how to design a system with it
like google web table and
apache cassandra vertica allows the declaration of column - groups
these are columns like first name and
last name which are very often accessed together
in vertica a column group is like a mini table
which is treated like a little row storied in the system
but because these groups represent activists that are frequently co accessed
the grouping actually improves performance
so an application developer is better off when the nature and
the frequency of user queries are known to some degree
and this knowledge is applies to designing the column groups
an important side effect of column structure organization of vertical
is that the writing of data into vertica is a little slower
when rows are added to a table vertica initially places
them in a row - wise data structure and
then converts them into a column - wise data structure which is then compressed
this lowness can be perceptible for large uploads or updates
vertica belongs to a new breed of database systems that call themselves
analytical databases
this means two slightly different things
first vertica offers many more statistical functions than in
classical dbms
for example one can perform operations over a window
to see an example consider a table of stock ticks having a time attribute
a stock name and a value of the stock called bid here
this shows that data values in the table now we would like to compute
a moving average of the bit every 40 seconds
we show the query in a frame below
now we are not going into the details of the query just consider the blue part
it says the average which is the avg function in yellow
it must be computed on the last column which is bit
but this computation
must be over the range that is computed on the timestamp call
so the range is defined by a 40 second row before that current row so
here the computation of the average advances for the stock abc
and for each computation the system only considers the rows whose
timestamp is within 40 seconds before the current row
the table on the right shows the result of the query
the average value 10 12
is the same as the actual value because there are no other rows within 40 seconds
the next two result rows average over the preceding rows
was times r within 40 seconds of the current row
when we get to the blue row
that we notice that it occurs 1 minute 16 seconds after the previous row
so we cannot consider the previous sort in the computation
instead the result is just the value of the bid in the current row
the takeaway from this example is that analytical computations like
this are happening inside the database and not in an external application
this brings us to the second feature of vertica as an analytical database
r is a well known free statistics package that used by statisticians
data minors predictive analytics experts
today r can not only read data from files
but it can go to an sql database and grab data to perform statistical analysis
over time r has evolved and
given rights to distributed r which is a high performance platform for r
as expected in this distributed setting
the system operates in a master slave mode
the master node coordinates computations by sending commands to the workers
the worker nodes maintain data partitions and
apply the computation functions to the data
just getting the data parallelly
the essential data structure is a distributed array
that is an array that is partitioned as shown here
now in this diagram the partitions are equal but
in practice they may be all different sizes
on which one can compute a function for each of these mini - arrays
the bottom diagram shows a simple work flow of constructing and
deploying a predictive model
the role of vertica here
is that it a data supplier to the worker nodes of r and a model consumer
the data to be analyzed is the output of the vertica query
which is transferred in memory through a protocol called vertica fast transfer
through distributed r as a darray
when the model is created in r
it should come back as a code that goes through vertica as a function
this function can be called from inside vertica
as if it was a user defined function
now in sophisticated applications the features of the data needed for
predicted modeling will also be computed inside the dbms possibly
using the new analytical operations of vertica that we have just shown
now this will make future computation much faster and
improve the efficiency of the entire analytics process
going forward we believe that most dbms will want to play in the analytics field
will support similar functions
most of you have heard of mongodb as a dominant store for
json style semi - structured data
mongodb is very popular and
there are a number of excellent tutorials on it on the web
in this module we would like to discuss a relatively new big data management
system for semistructured data that currently being incubated by apache
it called asterixdb
originally asterixdb was conceived by the university of california irvine
since it is a full fledged dbms
it provides acid guarantees to understand the basic design of asterixdb
let consider this incomplete json snippet taken from an actual tweet
we have seen the structure of json before
here we point out that entities and user the two parts
in blue are nested that means embedded within the structure of the tweet
if we represent a part of the schema of this abbreviated structure in asterixdb
it will look like this
here a dataverse is like a name space for data
data is declared in terms of data types
the top type which looks like a standard data with stable declaration
represents the user portion of the json object that we highlighted before
the type below represents the message
now instead of nesting it like json
the user attribute highlighted in blue is declared to have the type
twitterusertype thus it captures the hierarchical structure of json
we should also notice that the first type is declared as open
it means that the actual data can have more attributes than specified here
in contrast the tweetmessage type is declared as closed
meaning that the data instance must have the same attributes as in the schema
asterixdb can handle spatial data as given by the point data types shown in green
the question mark at the end of the point type says that this attribute is optional
that means all instances need not have it
finally the create dataset actually asks the system to create a dataset
called tweetmessages whose type is the just declared quick message type
astrerixdb which runs on hdfs provides several options for credit support
first it has its own query language called the asterix query language
which resembles the xml credit language query
the details of this query language are not important right now
we are illustrating the structure of a query just to show what it looks like
this particular query asks for
all user objects from the dataset twitterusers in descending order of their
follower count and in alphabetical order of the user preferred language
what is more interesting and distinctive is that asterixdb has a creative
processing engine that can process queries in multiple languages
for its supported language they have developed a way to
transfer the query into a set of low level operations like select and
join which their query exchange can support
further they have determined how a record described in one of these
languages can be transformed into an asterix
in this manner the support hive queries
which is expressed in like this
xquery hadoop map reduce as wall as a new language
called sql + + which extends sql for json
like a typical db bdms
asterixdb is designed to operate on a cluster of machines
the basic idea not surprisingly is to use partition data parallellism
each data set is divided into instances of various types
which can be decomposed to different machines by either range partitioning or
hash partitioning like we discussed earlier
a runtime distributed execution engine called hyracks is used for
partitioned parallel execution of query plans
for example let assume we have two relations customers and orders
as you can see here
our query is find the number of orders for
every market segment that the customers belong to
now this query need a join operation between the two relations
using the o custkey as a foreign key of customer into orders
it also needs a grouping operation which for
each market segment will pull together all the orders which will then be counted
you do not have to understand the details of this diagram at this point
we just want to point out that the different parts of the query
that are being marked the customer filed here has two partitions
that reside on two nodes nc one and nc two respectively
the orders file also has two partitions
but each partition is dually replicated
one can be accessed either of nodes nc3 or nc2 and the other on nc1 and nc5
hyracks will also break up the query into a number of jobs and
then fill it out which tasks can be performed in parallel and
which ones must be executed stage by stage
this whole thing will be managed by the cluster controller
the cluster controller is also responsible for replanning and
reexecuting of a job if there is a failure
asteriskdb also has the provision
to accept real time data from external data sources at multiple rates
one way is from files in a directory path
consider the example of tweets
as you have seen with the hands - on demo
usually people acquire tweets by accessing data through an api that twitter provides
very typically a certain volume of tweets lets say for
every 5 minutes is accumulated into a json file in a specific directory
the next 5 minutes in another json file and so forth
the way to get this data into asterisks db
is to first create an empty data set called tweets here
the next task is to create a feed
that is an externally resource
one has to specify that it coming from the local file system called local fs here
and the location of the directory the format and
the data type it going to copy it
next the feed is connected to the data set and
the system starts reading unread files from the directory
another way for asteriskdb to access external data is directly from an api
such as the twitter api
to do this one would create a dataset as before
but this time the data feed is not on the local file system
instead it uses the push twitter method which invokes the twitter
client with the four authentication parameters required by the api
once the feed is defined it is connected to the data set as before
now we move to another apache product for
large scale text data searching called solr
systems like solr and
its underlying text indexing engine are typically designed for search problems
so they would typically be part of a search engine
but before we talk about solr or
large scale text we need to first appreciate some fundamental challenges
when it comes to storing indexing and matching text data
the basic challenge comes from the numerous ways in which
a text string may vary making it hard to define what a good match is
let us show some of these challenges
remember in each case we are asking whether the strings shown on
either side of the double tilde sign should match
the first issue is about spelling variations and capitalization
the second issue relates structured strings
where different parts of a string represent different kind of information
we have seen this before for file paths urls and like in this case product ids
the problem is that the searcher may not always know the structure or
my job on misposition the internal punctuations
the next problem is very common with proper nouns which are represented in
various ways including dropping a part of the string picking up only the initials
but consider the last variation should bh obama really match the full name
the next example is about frequently used synonyms
if the document has one of the synonyms while the query uses another
should they match
example 5 illustrates a very common problem
people use abbreviations all the time
if we look at text and social media and
instant messaging we see a much wider variety of abbreviations
how well should they met with the real correct version of the term
now problem six is a special case of problem five
many long nouns are shortened
because we take the first initial letter of each significant word
we say significant because we drop words like of as shown here
this is called initialism
just so you know when an initialism can be said like a real word
it called an acronym
thus ibm is an initialization but nato is an acronym
now problem seven and problem eight show two
different situation where we first must decide what to do with the period sign
in the first case we should not find a match because students and
american are in two different sentences punctuated by a period sign
but in the second case we should find a match because the period
does not designate a sentence boundary
lucene the engine on which solr is built is effectively not a database
but a modern inverted index
what is an inverted index
let first define a vocabulary as a collection of terms
where a term may be a single word or it can be multiple words
it can a single term or it can be a collection of synonyms
but how would a search engine know what a term is
we will revisit this question in a couple of slides
for now let just say that if we have a corpus of documents we can
extract most of the terms and construct a vocabulary for that collection
we can then define occurrence as a list
containing all the information necessary for each term in the vocabulary
it would include information like which documents have the term
the positions in the document where the term occurs
we can then go on to compute the count of the term in the document and the corpus
referring back to a previous module in this course we can also compute
the term frequency and inverse document frequency for the collection
an inverted index is essentially an index which for
every term stores at least the id of the document where the term occurs
practically other computed numbers or
properties associated with the terms will also be included in the index
solr is an open source enterprise search platform
the heart of solr is its search functionality built for full text search
however solr provides much more than tech search
it can take any structured document even csv files
which can be broken up into fields and can index each field separately
full text indexes where text columns are supplemented by indexes for
other types of data including numeric data dates geographic coordinates and
fields where domains are limited to an emergent set of values
solr provides other facilities like faceted search and
highlighting of terms that match a query
now if you are not familiar with the term faceted search
let look at the screenshot from amazon com
i performed a search on the string dell laptop
consider the highlighted part of the image
each laptop record carries a lot of attributes like the display size
the processor speed the amount of memory and so forth
these attributes can be put into builds like processor type has intel i5 i7 etc
faceted search essentially extracts the individual values of these fields and
displays them back to the user usually with a count of the number of records
we see this in the upper part of the marked portion
which says there are 5619 laptops per 411 tablets
these are called facets
if a user clicks on a facet documents with only those values
that just the tablets will be presented back to the user
now let get back to the question of what a term is and
how a solr system should know it
solr allows the system designer to specify how to parse a document
by instructing how to tokenize a document and how to filter it
tokenization is the process of breaking down the characters read
for example one can break the stream at white spaces and
get all the words as tokens
then it can filter out the punctuation like the period the apostrophe and so
on just to get the pure words
the code snippet on the right essentially achieves this
it uses a standard tokenizer that gets the words with immediate punctuation
the first filter removes the punctuations
the second filter turns everything into lowercase
and the third filter uses a synonym file to ensure that
all the synonyms get the same token after ignoring the case
the last filter removes common english words like a and the
while a similar process would need to happen when we get the query string
it will also need to go through a tokenization and token filtering process
in the query analyzer example there are six filters within the tokenizer
we use a pattern tokenizer which will remove the white spaces and
periods and semi - colon
the common grams filter creates tokens out of pairs of terms and
in doing so makes sure that words in the stopword file are used
so if we have the string
the cat the term the should not be ignored in this filter
now the filters here are executed in order
after the common grams filter is already done
the next filter removes all the stopwords in the file
the fifth filter makes sure that if the queries coming from a web form
all the html characters are stripped off
finally the remaining words are stemmed so that runs and
running in the query would match the word run in the document
we will end this section with a discussion on solr queries that is searches
we present a csv file with nine records and seven attributes
we issue queries against the system by posing a web query
in these examples we show some of the queries one can post to the system
this will be covered in more detail during the hands - on session
just notice that the q equal to is a query and the fl is what you want to back
listens on activity who will be performing queries assessing the postgres database
first will open a terminal window and start the postgres shell
next we will look at table and column definitions in database
who s in query the content of the buy - clicks table
and see how to do this query but filter specific rows and columns from the table
next we will perform average and
some aggregation operations on a specific column
and finally
we will see how to combine two tables by joining them on a single column
let begin
first click on the terminal icon at the top of the toolbar
to open a terminal window
next let start the postgres shell by running psql
the postgres shell allows us to enter queries and run commands for
the postgres database
we can see what tables are in the database by running d
this says that there are three tables in the database
adclicks buyclicks and gameclicks
we could use d table name to see the definition of one of these tables
let look at the definition of buyclicks
we enter d buyclicks
this shows that there seven columns in the database
these are the column names and here the data type for each of the columns
now let look at the contents of the buyclicks table
we can query the contents by running the command select from buyclicks;
the select says that we want to do a query
the star means we want to retrieve all the columns and
from buyclicks says which table to perform the query from
and finally all commands in postgres shell need to end with a semicolon
when we run this command we see the contents of the buyclicks table
column header is at the top and the contents are below
again hit space to scroll through the contents and hit q when we are done
now let view the contents of only two of the columns
let query only the price and the user id from the buyclicks table
to do this we run select price userid from buyclicks
this command says we want to query only the price and
userid columns from the buyclicks table
when we run this we only get those two columns
we can also perform queries that just select certain rows and
meet a certain criteria
for example
let make a query that only shows the rows containing the price over 10
you can do this by running select price
userid from buyclicks where price 10
this query says we only want to see the price and userid columns from
the buyclicks table where the value in the price column has a value greater than 10
we run this we see that we always have price values greater than 10
the sql language has a number of aggregation operations built into it
for example we can take the average price by running
select avg price from buyclicks
this command will show the average price from all the data in the buyclicks table
another aggregate operation is sum
we can see the total price by running
select sum price from buyclicks
we can also combine two tables by joining on a common column
if you recall we have three tables in our database adclicks
buyclicks and gameclicks
we look at the description the definition of adclicks buy running d adclicks
you can see that it also has a column called userid
let combine buyclicks and adclicks based on this common column
you can do this by running select adid
buyid adclicks userid from adclicks join
buyclicks on adclicks userid = buyclicks userid
this query says we want to just see the adid buyid and
userid columns and we want to combine the adclicks table
the buyclicks table and we will be combining them on
the userid column and it common in both those tables
when we run it you see just the three columns
next we will consider queries where two tables are used
let consider the query
find the beers liked by drinkers who frequent the great american bar
for this query we need the relation frequents and likes
now look at the scheme of these relations in the light blue box
they have a common attribute called drinker
so if we use the attribute drinker
we need to tell the system which one we are referring to
now look at the sql query the from clause in the query has these two relations
to handle a common attribute name issue
we need to give nicknames aliases to these relations
therefore in the from clause we say likes has the alias l and
frequents has the alias f
since we want to find beers like before we use a select distinct clause for beer
as we saw before using select distinct avoids duplicates in the result
the where clause has two kinds of conditions
the first kind is a single table condition
in this case bar = the great american bar on the frequents relation
the second kind is a joined condition which says that the drinker attribute in
the frequency relation is the same as the drinker attribute of the likes relation
we encode this in sql in the last line of the query using aliases
why did we not say l beer in the select clause or f bar in the first condition
we could have the query would have been equally right
but we are using a shortcut because we know that these attributes are unique
already in the query
now let look at the query again
this time from the viewpoint of evaluating the query
there are many ways to evaluate the query but
the way it most likely to be evaluated is this
the query will first look at the tables that have single table conditions
so it would perform a select operation
on the frequents table to match the records of the condition
that the great american bar equal to the great american bar
why is this strategy good
it because the selection operative reduces the number of triples to consider
thus if there are thousand triples in the relation frequents
maybe 60 of them matches the desired bar
so in the next step we have to deal with a fewer number of records than thousand
all right the next step will be a join with a likes relation
a join requires two relations in a join condition
the join condition comes from the query
the first relation shown with an underscore symbol here
is a result of the previous operation
another way of saying this is that the result of
the selection is piped into the join operation
that means we do not create
an intermediate table from the result of the selection
the results are directly supplied to the next operator which in this case is join
now the result of the join operator is an intermediate structure with columns beer
from likes relation and
the drinker from the frequents relation that we have processed
this intermediate set of triples is piped to the project operation that
picks up the beer column
now we need to process the distinct clause for
deduplicate elimination which then goes to the output
we have already seen how the select project queries on single tables
are evaluated when the tables are partitioned across several machines
we will now see how we process join queries in the same setting
for our case consider that the likes and
frequents tables are on two different machines
in the first part of the query
the selection happens on the machine with the frequents table
the output of the query is a smaller table with the same scheme as frequents
that is with drinkers and bars
now we define an operation called semijoin
in which we need to move data from one machine to another
the goal of the semijoin operation is to reduce the cost of data movement
that is to move data from the machine which has
the frequents data to the machine with the likes data
the cost is reduced if we ship less data
the way to it is to first find which data the join operation actually needs
clearly it needs only the drinkers column and not the bars column
so the drinkers column is projected out then
just this column is transmitted to the second machine
finally the join is performed by looking at the values in the likes column
that only matches the values in the shipped data
that means only the data from likes that matches the drinkers that are chosen
these are then the join results which would go to the output of the operation
now here you can see the semijoin operation graphically
the red table on the left is the output of the selection operations on the left
the white table on the right is the table to be joined to
since we need only the drinkers column
it is projected to create a one - column relation
notice that the red table has two entries for pete who frequented two bars
but the output of the project is condensed in the yellow table
to just show the drinkers where pete appears only once
for those of you with a background in computer science
this can be done using a hash map like data structure
this one - column table is now shipped to site2 which has the likes relation
now at site2 the shipped relation is used to find matches from
the drinkers column and it finds only one match called sally
so the corresponding result triples in this case
only one triple is produced at the end of this operation
now the original table and the matching table are shipped
to the last of the operation to finish the join operation
and more efficient version of this is shown in the next slide
in this version the first two steps this and that are the same
then the result of the reduce is also shipped to site1 to find
the matches from the red relation
another reduce operation is performed on site1 now
to get the matching records on the red relation
finally these two reduced relations are shipped to
the site where the final join happens
and all of this may seem like a lot of detail
let me repeat something i have said before
if we have a system like db2 or spark sql that implements multi - site joins it
will perform this kind of operation under the hood you do not have to know them
however if we were to implement a similar operation and all that you have
is hadoop you may end up implementing this kind of algorithm yourself
the queries in real life are little more complex than what we have seen before
so let consider a more complex query
let s find bars where the price of miller is the same as or
less than what the great american bar called tgab here charges for bud
you may say but we do not really know what tgab charges for bud
that correct so we can break up the query into two parts
first we will find this unknown price and then we will use that price
to find the bars that would sell miller for the same price or better price
now this is a classic situation where the result from the first part of
the query should be fed as a parameter to the second query
now this situation is called a subquery
we write this in sql as shown in the slide here
what makes this query different is that the part where price is less than equal
to instead of specifying a constant like 8
we actually place another query which computes the price of a bud at tgab
the shaded part is called the inner query or the subquery
in this case both the outer query and
the inner query use the same relation which is sells
now in terms of evaluation the inner query is evaluated first
and the outer query uses its output
now while it may not be obvious at this time
notice that the inner query is independent of the outer query
in other words
even if we did not have the outer query we can still evaluate the inner query
we say in this case that the subquery is uncorrelated
let look at another example of a subquery
in this example we want to find the name and
manufacturer of each beer that fred did not like
so how do we know what fred did not like
we do however know that the set of beers that fred likes because they
are listed in the likes relation
so we need to subtract this set from the total set of beers that the company has
recorded
this subtraction of sets can be performed in several ways
one of them is to use the not in construct
so the query class job is to take every name from the beers table and
output it only if it does not appear in the set produced by the inner query
similar to the previous query the subquery here is also uncorrelated
now this is a more sophisticated query
the intention is to find beers that are more expensive
than the average price of beer
but since beers have different prices in different bars
we have to find the average for every bar
therefore the idea is to find the average price of beer for
every bar and then compare the price of each beer with respect to this average
now look at the query and the table
let assume we are processing the first table
the beer is bud and the price is 5
now we need to know if 5 is greater than the average price of beer sold at hgat
to do this we need to compute the inner query okay
so now let look at the fourth row
the price of guinness needs to be compared to that average again for hgat
in fact for every table processed by the outer query
one needs to compute the inner query for that bar
this makes the inner subquery correlated with the outer query
now a smart query processor will store the average once it computed and
then reuse the stored value instead of computing over and over again
what is an aggregate query
let use a simple example of finding the average price of bud
this is like a simple select project query with the additional aspect
that it takes a list of price values of bud from different bars and
then computes an average
in the example shown the average of the five prices is 4 2
in other words the average function
the avg function takes a list of values and produces a single value
now there are many functions that have this behavior
the sum function takes a list of values and
adds them up to produce a single value
the count function takes a list of list of values and
counts the number of items in that list and so on
these are called aggregate functions
now if we wanted to count only the price values that are different that is 3
4 and 5 just once we can write the select clause a little differently
we would say that the average is over distinct values
of price which in this case will result in 4
you should recognize that most analytical operations need to use statistical
functions which are aggregates
so another important analytical requirement
is computing the statistical aggregate by groups
for example we often compute the average salaries of employees per department
now back to our example here we want to find the average price paid for
bud per drinker where we know that a drinker visits many bars
so the grouping variable here is drinker
so we have three attributes at play price which we need to aggregate
drinker which we need to group by and bar which is a join attribute
the fourth attribute namely beer is used for selection and
does not participate in grouping
so after the selection we will get an intermediate relation
containing drinker bar and price
with this the group by operation will create one result row for
each drinker and place the average price over all such rows
now how does group by and
aggregate computation work when the data is partitioned
let take the same query
we are looking for the average price of bud grouped by drinker
but this time the result of the selection are in two different machines
imagine that this time they are range partitioned by row numbers
which we have not shown to maintain clarity
now with the group by operation the data will get repartitioned by the grouping
attribute that drinker
and then the aggregate function is computed locally
to accomplish this repartitioning task each machine groups its own data locally
determines which portions of data should be transmitted to a different machine
and accordingly ships it to that machine
now there are several variants of this general scheme
which are even more efficient
now if this reminds you of the map operation you saw in your previous course
you are exactly right
this fundamental process of grouping partitioning and redistribution of data
is inherent in data - parallel computing and implemented inside database systems
welcome back
in this video we will provide you a quick summary of the main points from
our last course on big data modeling and management
if you had just completed our second course and do not need a refresher
you may now skip to the next lecture
after this video you will be able to recall why big data modeling and
management is essential in preparing to gain insights from your data
summarize different kids of data models
describe streaming data and the different challenges it presents and explain the differences
between a database management system and a big data management system
in the second course we described a data model as a specification
that precisely characterizes the structure of the data
the operations on the data and the constraints that may apply on data
for example a data model may state that
a data is structured like a two - dimensional array or a matrix
for this structure one may have a data access operation
which given an index of the array we use the cell of the array to refer to
a data model may also specify constraints on the data
for example while a total data set may have many arrays
the name of each array must be unique and
the values of a specific array must always be greater than zero
database management systems handle low level data management operations
help organization of the data using a data model and
provide an open programmable access to data
we covered a number of data models
we showed four models that were discussed in more details
the relational data to date is the most used data model
here data is structured like tables which are formally called relations
the relational data model has been implemented in traditional database
systems
but they are being refreshly implemented in modern data systems over hadoop and
spark and are getting deployed on cloud platforms
the second category of data gaining popularity is semi - structured data
which includes documents like html pages xml data and
json data that are used by many internet applications
this data can have one element nested or
embedded within another data element and hence can often be modeled as a tree
the third category of data models is called graph data
a graph is a network where nodes represent entities and
edges represent relationships between pairs of such entities
for example in a social network nodes may represent users and
edges may represent their friendship
the operations performed on graph data includes traversing the network so
that one can find friend of a friend of a friend if needed
in contrast to the previous three models that there is a structure to the data
the text data is much more unstructured because an entire data item
like a new article can be just a text string
however text is the primary form of data
in information retrieval systems or search engines like google
we also discussed streaming data or data with velocity as a special
class of data that continually come to the system at some data rate
examples can be found in data coming from road sensors that measure traffic
patterns or stock price data from the stock exchange that may come
in volumes from stock exchanges all over the world
streaming data is special because a stream is technically an infinite data source
and therefore we keep filling up memory and
storage and will eventually go beyond the capacity of any system
streaming data therefore needs a different kind of management system
for this reason streaming data is processed in memory
in chunks which are also called windows
often only the necessary part of the data stream or
the results of queries against the data stream is stored
a typical type of query against streaming data are alerts or notifications
the system notices an event like multiple stock price changing within a short time
streaming data is also used for prediction
for instance based on wind direction and temperature data streams
one can predict how a wildfire is going to spread
in the last course we also covered a number of data systems that we called
big data management systems
these systems use different data models and
have different capabilities but are characterized by some common features
they are also designed from the start for parallel and distributed processing
most of them implement data partition parallelism which if you can recall
refers to the process of segmenting the data into multiple machines so
data retrieval and manipulations can be performed in parallel on these machines
many of these systems allow a large number of users who constantly update and
query the system
some of the systems do not maintain transaction consistency with every update
that means
not all the machines may have all the updates guaranteed at every moment
however most of them provide a guarantee of eventual consistency
which means all the machines will get all updates sooner or later
therefore providing better accuracy and time
the third common characteristic of big data management systems is
that they are often built on top of a hadoop - like platform that provides
automatic replication and a map - reduce style processing ability
some of the data operations performed within these systems make use of these
lower level capabilities
after this refresher on data modeling and
management let start big data integration and processing
so hi
in the previous course we saw examples of different data models and
talked about a few current data management systems
in this module we will focus on data retrieval
data retrieval refers to the way in which data desired
by a user is specified and retrieved from a data store
note that in this course we are using the term data retrieval in two ways
assume that your data is stored in a data store that follows a specific data model
like for example the relational data model
by data retrieval we will refer to one
the way you specify how to get the desired data out of the system
this is called the query specification method and two
the internal processing that occurs within the data management system to compute or
evaluate that specified retrieval request
while query specification can apply to small data stores or large data stores
we will keep an eye on the nature of query evaluation when the data is big
further we will consider how the query specification changes
when we deal with faster streaming data
a query language is a language in which a retrieval request is specified
a query language is often called declarative which means it lets you
specify what you want to retrieve without having to tell the system how to retrieve
for example you can say
find all data from relation employee where the salary is more than 50000
now you do not have to write a program which will tell the system to open a file
skip the first 250 bytes then in a loop pick the next 1024 bytes
probe into the 600th byte and read an integer and so forth
instead of writing such a complicated procedure
you just specify the data items that you need and the system does the rest
for example sql structured query language
is the most used query language for relational data
now in contrast to a query language a database programming
language like oracle pl sql or postgres pgsql are high - level
procedural programming languages that embed query operations
we will look at some query languages in detail and
show examples of database programming languages
the first query language we will look at is sql
which is the ubiquitous query language when the data is structured
but has been extended in many ways to accommodate other types of data
for this course we will stick to the structured aspect of the language
now you should know that sql is used for classical database management systems
like oracle as well as modern hadoop style distributed systems such as spark
now we will work with an illustrative example
first we need to define the schema of the database
now think of a business called the beer drinkers club that owns many bars
and each bar sells beer
our schema for this business has six relations of tables
the first table lists these bars the names addresses and
the license number of the bar
notice that the attribute name is underlined because it is the primary key
of the bars relation
recall that the primary key refers to a set of attributes
in this case just the name that makes a record unique
note that the relation bars with the attribute name
within parenthesis is the same as the table shown on the right
we will use both representations as we go forward
the second table called beers this is the names and manufacturers of beer
now not every bar sells the same brands of beer and even when they do
they may have different prices for
the same product because of differences in the establishment costs
so the sells table records which bar sells which beer at what price
now our business is special
it also keeps information about the regular member customers
so the drinkers relation has the name address and phone of these customers
well not only that it knows which member visits
which bars and which beer each member likes
clearly the beer drinkers club knows its customers
the most basic structure of an sql query is a select - from - where clause
in this example we are looking for beer names that are made by heineken
so we need to specify our output attribute
in this case the name of the beer
the logical table which will be used to answer the query in this case beers
and the condition that all the desired data items should satisfy
namely the value of the attribute called manf is heineken
now there are few things to notice here
first the literal heineken is put within quotes
because it a single string literal
remember that in this case
the string is supposed to match exactly including the case
secondly if you go back to the data operations discussed in course two
you will recognize that this form of query can also be represented
as a selection operation on the relation beers with a condition on the manf
attribute followed by a projection operation
that outputs the name attribute from the result of the selection operation
so the selection operation finds all tuples of beer for which the manufacturer
is heineken and from those tuples it projects only the name column
the result of the query is a table with one single attribute called name
we illustrate some more features of sql using two example queries
the first looks for expensive beer and its price
let say we consider a beer to be expensive if it costs more than 15
per bottle
from the schema
we know that the price information is available in the table called sells
so the from clause should use sells
the where clause is intuitive and
specifies the price of the beer to be greater than 15
now notice that the sells relation also has a column called bar
now if two different bars sell the same beer at the same price
we will get both entries in the result
but that not what we want
now regardless of the multiplicity of bars that have the same price for
the same beer we want the result just once
so this is achieved through the select distinct statement
which ensures that the result relation will have no duplicate
the second example shows the case where more than one condition
must be specified by the result
in this query the business must be in san diego and
at the same time it must be a temporary license holder
which means the license number should start with 32
as we see here these conditions are put together by the and operator
thus the query will pick the third record in the table
because the first record satisfy the first condition and not the second condition
in a few slides we will come back to the evaluation of this type of queries
in the context of big data
now remember one can also place a limit on the number of results to return
if our database is large and we need only five results for
example for a sample to display we can say limit 5
now the exact syntax of this limit clause may vary between dbms vendors
now if the table of beers was large and had millions of entries
the table would possibly need to be split over many machines
another way of saying that is that the table will be partitioned
across a number of machines
since a query simply performs a selection and
projection here it can be evaluated in parallel
remember that name is the primary key of the table
one standard way of partitioning the data
is called a range partitioning by the primary key
this simply means that the rows of the table are put in groups
depending on the alphabetical order of the name value
so beers with names starting with e and b here are placed in machine 1
those starting with c and d are in machine 2
and if there are too many rows for entries where the name starts with h
maybe h is split into machines 5 and 6
this is shown in the sketch here
next we will show how queries are performed over partition tables
but before we do that you should know that all database management companies
like ibm chair data microsoft and others have a solution like this for
large volumes of data where data partitioning is used
newer systems like spark and sql are naturally distributed and
therefore offer data partitioning
so we show the same partition tables as we saw before
now we will ask two queries
the first query asks for all tuples as records from the beers table
where the name of the beer starts with am
and the second query is exactly what we asked before
the first query in the sql looks like this
we said select from beers to mean all attributes from table beers
the where clause shows the syntax for a partial match query
in this query there are two new syntax elements
the first is a predicate called like
when we use like we are telling the query engine
that we only have partial information about the string we want to match
this partly specified string is called a string pattern
that means there is this part of the string we know and
a part that we do not know
in this case we know that our design string starts with am so we would write am
and then we put to refer to the part of the string that we do not know
putting them together we get am
if we wanted to find say am somewhere in the middle of the string
we would write the pattern as am
the second query is not new
we saw it in the last slide
however as we will see next evaluating the second query will be a little more
tricky in a partition database than that we usually see for big data
let talk about the first query in this data partition setting
the question to ask is do we need to touch all partitions to answer the query
of course not we know that the name is a primary key for the table of beers
we also know that the system did arrange partitioning on the name attribute
this means that the evaluation process should only access machine 1
because no other machine will have records for names starting with a
now this is exactly what we as humans
do when we look up an entry in a multivolume encyclopedia
we look for the starting words then figure out which specific volume would
have that entry then pick up just that volume
thus so long as the system knows the partitioning strategy
it can make its job much more efficient
when a system processes thousands of queries per second
this kind of efficiency actually matters
now raised partitioning is only one of many partitioning
schemes used in a database system okay
let try to answer the second query in the same partition setting
now the query condition is on the second attribute manf
now in one sense it a simpler query
there is no light pattern here and
we know exactly the string that we are looking for namely the string heineken
however this time we really cannot get away
by using the partitioning information because the partitioning activity is
different from the attribute on which the query condition is applied
so this query will need to go to all partitions
technically speaking the query needs to be broadcast
from the primary machine to all machines as shown here
next this broadcast query will be independently and
in parallel execute the query on the local machine
then these results need to be brought back into the primary machine
and then they need to be unioned together
and only then the results can be formed and returned to the client
now this might seem like a lot of extra work
however remember the shaded part of the query is executed in parallel
which is the essence of dealing with large data
now at this point you might be thinking wait a minute what if i had 100 machines
and the desired data is only in 20 of them
should we needlessly go through all 100 machines find nothing in 80 of them and
return 0 results from those machines
then why do the extra work
can it not be avoided
well to do this it would need one more piece in the solution
it called an index structure
very simply
an index can be thought of as a reverse table where given the value in a column
you would get back the records where the value appears as shown in the figure here
using an index speeds up query processing significantly
with indexes we can solve this problem in many different ways
the top table shows the case where each machine has its own index for
the manf column
this is called a local index because the index is in every machine
that holds the data for that table on that machine
in this case looking up heineken in the index
we would know which records would have the data
since the index is local the main query will indeed go to all machines but
the lookup will be really instant and the empty results would return very quickly
in the second case we adopted a different solution
here there is an index on the main machine all on a separate index server
now when we place a data record in a machine
this index keeps an account of the machine that contains the record with that value
look at the second table to the right
given the value of heineken we know that it is only in three machines
and therefore we can avoid going to the other machines
clearly we can always use both indexing schemes
this will use more space but queries will be faster
now this gives you some of the choices you may need to make with big data
whether you use a parallel dbms or a distributed data solution
welcome to big data integration and processing
welcome to course three of the big data specialization
i am amarnath gupta
and i am ilkay altintas
we are really excited to work with you in this course
to develop your understanding and skills in big data integration and processing
by now you might have just finished our first two courses and
learned the basics of big data modelling and management
if you have not it not required
but for those that less background in the data modelling and
data management areas you might find it valuable
we understand that you may not have any background on data management
we are going to introduce query languages we will first look at sql in some detail
and then move to query languages for mongodb which is a semi structured
data management system and aerospike which is a key value store
we will also introduce concepts related to processing of big data as
big data pipelines
we talk about data structures and transformations related to batch and
stream processing as steps in a pipeline
providing us a way to talk about big data processing
without getting into the details of the underlying technologies
once we have reviewed the concepts and related systems we will switch gears
to hands on exercises with spark one of the most popular big data engines
we will show you examples of patch and stream processing using spark
as you know for many data science applications
one has to use many different databases and analyze the integrated data
in fact data integration is one leading cause leading to the bigness of data
we will give you a rapid exposure to information integration systems
through use cases and point out the big data aspects one should pay attention to
we are also excited to show you examples of data processing using splunk
our goal here is to provide you with simple hands on exercises
that require no programming but
show you how one can use interfaces like splunk to manage and process big data
we wish you a fun time learning and
hope to hear from you in the discussions forums and learner stories as usual
well happy learning and think big data
in this video we will talk about the challenges of ingesting and
processing big data and remind ourselves why need any paradigm and
programming models for big data
after this video you will be able to summarize the requirements of programming
models for big data and why you should care about them
you will also be able to explain how the challenges of big
data related to its variety volume and velocity affects its processing
before we start let imagine an online gaming newscase
just like the one we have for catch the pink flamingo
you just introduced the game and users started signing up
you start with a traditional relational database
keeping track of user sessions and other events
your game server receives an event notification every time
a user opens his session and makes a point in the game
initially everything is great your game is working and
the database is able to handle the event streams coming into the server
however suddenly your game becomes highly popular a good problem to have
the database management system in your game server wo not be able to
handle the load anymore
you start getting errors that the events cannot be inserted into the database
at the speed they are coming in
you decide that you will have a buffer or a queue to process the advancing chunks
maybe also at the same time processing them to be organized in windows of time or
game sessions
however in time as the demand goes up you will need more processing nodes and
even more database servers that can handle the load
this is a typical scenario that most web sites face when confronted
with big data issues related to volume and velocity of information
as this scenario demonstrates
solving the problem in one step might be possible initially
but the more reactive fixes the game developers add the system
becomes less robust and more complicated to evolve
while the developers initially started with an application and
the database to manage
now they have to manage a number of issues related to this
infrastructure management just to keep up with the load on the system
similarly the database servers can be effected and corrupted
the replication and fault tolerance of them need to be handled separately
let start by going through these issues
let say one of the processing nodes went down
the system needs to manage and restart the processing and
there will be potentially some data loss in the meantime
the system would need to check every processing node
before it can discard data
each note and each database has to be replicated separately
batch computations that need data from multiple data servers need to access and
maintain use of the data separately which might end up being quite slow and costly
big data processing techniques we will address in this course
will help you to reduce the management of the mentioned complexities
including failing servers and breaking compute nodes
while helping with the scalability of the management and processing infrastructure
we will talk about using big data systems like spark to achieve data parallel
processing scalability for data applications on commodity clusters
we will use to spark runtime libraries and programming models to
demonstrate how big data systems can be used for application management
to summarize what our imaginary game application needs from big data system
first of all there needs to be a way to use common big data operations
to manage and split large volumes of events data streaming in
this means the partitioning and placement of data in and
out of computer memory along with a model to synchronize the datasets later on
the access to data should be achieved in a fast way
the game developers need to be able to deploy
many event processing jobs to distributed processing nodes at once
and these are potentially the data nodes we move the computations to
it should also enable reliability of the computing and
enable fault tolerance from failures
this means enabling programmable replications and
recovery of event data when needed
it should be easily
scalable to a distributed set of nodes where the data gets produced
it should also enable scaling out
scaling out is simply adding new resources like distributed computers to
process more or faster data at scale without losing performance
there are many data types in an online game
although we talked about time click events and
scores it would be easy to imagine there are graphs of players
text - based chats and images that need to be processed
our big data system should enable processing of such
a mixed variety of data and potentially optimize handling of
each type separately as well as together when needed
in addition our system should have been able both streaming and
batch processing enabling all the processing to be debuggable and
extensible with minimal effort
that means being able to handle operations at small chunks of data
streams with minimal delay that is what we call low latency
while at the same time handle processing of potentially all available data
in batch form and all through the same system architecture
latency is a word that we use and hear a lot in big data processing
here we refer to how fast the data is being processed or simply
the difference between production or event time and processing time of a data entry
in other words latency is quantification
of the delay in the processing of the streaming data in the system
while some big data systems are good at it
hadoop for instance is not a great choice for operations that require low latency
let finish by remembering the real reasons for
all these requirements of big data processing
making a different from processing in a traditional data architecture
big data has varying volume and velocity requiring the dynamic and
scalable batch and stream processing
big data has a variety requiring management of data in many
different data systems and integration of it all at scale
next we will describe aggregation functions
we have seen the first query before
select count simply translates to a count function
now we could also say db drinkers find count
but using count directly is more straightforward
now let ask to count the number of unique addresses for drinkers
so we do not care what the address is
we just care if it exists
this is accomplished through the exists : true expression
thus if an address exists for a drinker it will be counted
another area where we need to count is when we have an array valued attribute
like places
if we just want the number of elements in the raw list
we will write db country findplaces length and we will get six
however if we want distinct values we will use distinct instead of find and then
use the length for counting the number of distinct elements in this case 4
now mongodb uses an internal machinery called the aggregation framework
which is modeled on the concept of data processing pipelines
that means documents enter a multi - stage pipeline which transforms
the documents at each stage until it becomes an aggregated result
now we have seeing a similar mechanism for relational data
the aggregation pipelines starts by using the aggregate primitive
the most basic pipeline stages provides filters that operate like queries and
the document transformations that modify the form of the output document
the primary filter operation is match which is followed by a query condition
in this case status is a
and expectedly the match operation produces a smaller number of documents
to be processed at the next stage
this is usually followed by the group operation
now this operation needs to know which attributes should be grouped together
in the example here cust id is the grouping attribute so
it is passed as a parameter to the group function
now notice the syntax
id : cust id says that the grouped data will have an id attribute
and its value will be picked from the cust id
attribute from the previous stage of computation
thus the before the cust id is telling the system that
cust id is a known variable in the system and not a constant
the group operation also needs a reducer
which is a function that operates on an activity to produce an aggregate result
in this case the reduce function is sum
which operates on the amount attribute from the previous stage
like cust id we use amount to indicate that it a variable
as we saw in the relational case
data can be partitioned into chunks on the same machine or on different machines
these chunks are called chards
the aggregation pipeline of mongodb can operate on a charded collection
the grouping operation in mongodb can accept multiple attributes like
the four shown here
also shown is a post grouping directive to sort on the basis of two attributes
the first is a computed count variable in ascending order
so the one designates the ascending order
the next sorting attribute is secondary
that means if two groups have the same value for count
then they will be further sorted based on the category value
but this time the order is descending because of the - 1 directive
in course two we have seen solar a text search engine from apache
mongodb has a built in text search engine which can be invoked through the same
aggregation framework we saw before
imagine that mongodb documents in this case are really text documents placed in
a collection called articles
in this case the match directive of the aggregate function must be told
it going to perform a text function on the article corpus
the actual text function is search
we set search terms like hillary democrat such that having
either term in a document will satisfy the search requirement
as is the case of any text engine
the results of any search returns a list of documents each with a score
the next task is to tell mongdb to sort the results based on textscore
what is the meta here
meta stands for metadata that is additional information
remember that the aggregation operations are executed in a pipeline
any step in the pipeline can produce some extra data or
metadata for each processed document
in this example the metadata produced by the search function
is a computed attribute called textscore
so this directive tells the system to pick up this specific metadata attribute and
use it to populate the score attribute which would be used for sorting
finally the project class does exactly what is expected
it tells the system to output only the title of each document and
suppress its id
the last item in our discussion of mongodb is join
we have seen that join is a vital operation for data management operations
interestingly mongodb introduced this equivalent of join only in version 3 2
so the joining in mongodb also happens in the aggregation framework
there are a few ways of expressing joins in mongodb
we show one here that explicitly performs a join to a function called look up
we use an example form the mongodb documentation
now here are two document collections order and inventory
notice that the item key in orders has values abc jkl etc
and the sku key in the inventory has comparable values abc def etc
so these two are joinable by value
the way to specify this join one can use this query
the db orders aggregate declaration states that orders is
sort of the home or local collection
now in the aggregate the function lookup needs to know what to look up for
each document in orders
the from attribute specifies the name of the collection as inventory
the next two parameters are the local and
foreign matching keys which are item and sku respectively
the last item as : is a construction part of
the join operation which says how to structure the match items into the result
now before we show you the results let see what should match
the abc item in order should match the abc in sku
similarly the jkl item should match the jkl in sku
okay but there is one more twist
here is the actual result
the first two records show exactly what we expect
there is a new field called inventory - docs in the batching record
the third record however shows something interesting
inventory has two records shown here what do they match
now they match the empty document in orders because
orders has a document whose item field is null
so it matches documents and inventory where the sku item is also null
explicitly as in document 5 or implicitly as in document 6
this concludes our discussion of queries in the context of mongodb
in this hands on activity we will be using pandas to read csv files and
perform various queries on them
pandas is a data analysis library for python
first we will create a new jupyter python notebook
next we will use pandas to read a csv file into a dataframe
we will then view the contents of the dataframe and see how to filter rows and
columns of it
next we will perform average and sum operations on the dataframe
and finally show how to merge two dataframes by joining on a single column
let begin
we will start by creating a new ipython notebook
clicking on new and selecting python 3 under notebooks
first we will import the pandas library by writing import pandas
remember that in ipython notebooks to run a command
we hold down the shift key and hit enter
next let read buyclicks csv into a pandas dataframe
we will put it in a variable called buyclicksdf
we will read it using pandas read csv
and we will read the buy - clicks csv file
we can see the contents of the file by just running the variable by itself
and notice that the file has many rows and then ipython truncates this
the dot dot dot
we can see only the top five rows by calling head 5
next let look at only two
columns in the buyclicks data
let look at price and user id
we can do these by first entering buyclicks dataframe in the same text for
specifying only certain columns to show is open bracket open bracket and
then the name of the columns you want to view
so want your price and user id and again
we only want to see the first five rows so we will do head 5
now let query the buyclicks data for only the prices less than 3
first we will enter buyclicksdf one square bracket
to filter our particular column we enter buyclicksdf and then column name
now we specify the limit of the query by entering <3
this shows first five rows where the price is less than three
we can also perform aggregate operations on panda dataframes
we can sum all the price data by entering buyclicksdf price sum
another aggregate operation we can perform is looking at the average
let look at the average for price
the function is called mean
so once your buyclicksdf price mean
can also join two dataframes on a single column
first let read in another csv into a different dataframe
we will read in adclicks csv
so we will says adclicksdf = pandas read csv
we will say ad - clicks csv
to verify that we read this data successfully let look at the contents
now let combine the buyclicks dataframe and
the adclicks data frame on the user id call
we will put the result in the new dataframe called mergedf
so we will say mergedf = adclicksdf merge
then we need to say which dataframe we are merging with
buyclicksdf and the column that we are merging on
so we will say on = userid
finally we can look at the contents with this merged dataframe
so now from mongodb we will go to aerospike which is a key value store
key value stores typically offer an api
that is the way to access data using a programming language like python or java
we will take a very brief look at aerospike which offers both
a programmatic access and a limited amount of query access to data
the data model of aerospike is illustrated here
data are organized in lean spaces which can be in memory or on flash disks
name spaces are top level data containers
the way you collect data in name spaces relates to how data is stored and managed
so name space contains records indexes and policies
now policies dictate name space behavior like how data is stored
whether it on ram or disk or
how how many replicas exist for a record and when records expire
a name space can contain sets you can think of them as tables
so here there are two sets people and places
and a set of records which are not in any set
within a record data is stored in one or many bins
bins consist of a name and a value
the example written here is in java and
you do not have to know java to follow the main point here
here we are creating indexes on key value data that handled by aerospike
this data set comes from twitter
each field of a tweet is extracted and put into aerospike as a key value pair
so we declare the namespace to be
example and the record set to be tweet
the name of the index to be testindex and the name of the bin as user name
since this index is stored on disk an sql - like command
like show index shows the content of the index as you can see here
this routine shows
how data can be inserted into aerospike programmatically
again the goal is to point out a few salient aspects of data insertion
regardless of the syntax of the language
now since this is a key value store one first needs to define the key
this line here says that the key in the namespace call example and set call
tweet is the value of the function getid which returns the id of a tweet
when the data is populated we are essentially creating bins
here user name is the attribute and
the screen name obtained from the tweet is the value
the actual insertion happens here in the client
the client put statement where we need to mention the key and
the bins we have just created
now why are we inserting two bins at a time
two bins with two ids and user name
this is an idiosyncrasy of the aerospike client
after data is inserted one can create other data using aql
which is very much like sql
this screenshot shows a part of the output of a simple select star query
now in your hands - on exercise you will be able to play with the aerospike data
this is just a screenshot showing the basic query syntax of aql
that is aerospike query language and a few examples
the last two lines show a couple of interesting features of the language
the operation between 0 and 99 is a nicer way of stating a range query
which gives a lower and upper limits on a variable
the last line shows the operation cost
which transforms one type of data to another type
here it transforms coordinates that is latitude and longitude data
to a json format called geojson which is designed to represent geographic data
in a json structure
we will finish our coverage of queries with a quick reference to an advanced
topic which is beyond the scope of this course
now you have seen in prior courses that streaming data is complex to process
because a stream is infinite in nature
now does this have any impact on query languages and evaluation
the answer is that it absolutely does
we will mention one such impact here
this shows a pictorial depiction of streaming data
the data is segmented into five pieces shown in the white boxes in the upper row
these can be gathered for example every few seconds or every 200 data objects
the query defines a window to select
key of these data objects as a unit of processing
here case three
so three units of data are picked up in a window unit
to get the next window it is moved by two units
this is called a slide of the window
since the window size is three and the slide is two
one unit of information overlaps between the two consecutive windows
the lower line in this diagram shows the initialized item let ignore it
followed by two window sets of data records for processing
thus the query language therefore will have to specify a query
that an sql query over a window which is also specified in the query
now in a traffic data stream example the sql statement might look like this
where the window size is 30 second and
the slide is the same size as window giving output every 30 seconds
so streaming data results in changes in both the query language and
the way queries are processed
in this hands - on activity we will be querying documents in mongodb
first we will start a mongodb server and then run the mongodb shell
we will see how to show the databases and collections in the mongodb server
we will look at an example document in the database and
see how to find distinct values for a field
next we will search for specific field values and
see how to filter fields returned in a query
finally we will search using regular expressions and operators
let begin first we will start the mongodb server
open the terminal window by clicking on the terminal icon the top of the toolbar
we will cd into downloads big - data - 3 - mongodb
we will start the mongodb server by running
mongodb bin mongod - - dbpath db
the arguments dbpath db
specified that the database on mongodb is in the directory named db
run this to start the server
next we will start the mongodb shell so that we can perform queries
we will open another terminal window
again cd into downloads big - data - 3 - mongodb
we will start the shell by running mongodb bin mongo
we can see what databases are available in the mongodb server by running the command
show dbs
we have created the sample database with json data from twitter
we can use the use command to change to this database
we will run use sample
we can see the collections in this database by running show collections
there only one collection called users
so all of the queries will be using the users collection
let count how many documents there are in the users collection by writing
db users count
we can look at one of these documents by writing db users findone
this document contains jason from a twitter tweet
you can see the field names here with their values
there are also nested fields under the user field
and each of these fields also has values
you can find the distinct values for
particular field by using the distinct command
let find the distinct values for the username field
we will write db users distinct user name
next let find all the documents in this collection where the field username
matches the specific value
the value we will search for is actionsportsjax
we will run the command db users find
and the field name is username and
the value we are searching for is actionsportsjax
results of this query is compressed all in one line
if we append the pretty to the previous query
we can see the formatted output
so we will run the same command with append pretty
we can filter the fields returned from the queries
let perform the same query again but only show the tweet id field
we can do this by adding a second argument to the find command
so we will run the same command again
but add a second argument saying tweet id : 1
the underscore id field is a primary key used in all documents in mongodb
you can turn this off by adding another field to our filter
we will run the same command again but turn of id
next we use the regular expression search to find strings containing the document
for example if we want to find all the tweets containing the text fifa
we can run db users find tweet text fifa
there are no results in this query because this query is searching for
tweet text equals fifa
that is the entire contents and the value of tweet text must be fifa
instead if we want to look for
fifa anywhere in the tweet text we can do a regular expression search
to do this replace the double quotes with slashes
so we will run the same command again
but replacing double quotes with slashes
we can count how many documents are returned by this query by running the same
command again but appending count
we can also search for documents in mongodb where the field values are greater
than or less than a certain value
for example lets find tweet mention count greater than six
we will run db users find and the field name is tweet mentioned count
and we want to look for the value where this field is greater than six
so i will enter a gt : 6
in a prior course we looked at json as an example of semi - structured data
and we demonstrated that json data can be thought of as a tree
in this course we will focus on querying json data
before we start lets review the details of the json structure and
get an initial sense of how to query this form of data
let consider a simple json collection and
look at the structures substructures actually it composed of
the atomic element in the structure is a key value pair for example
name is the key and sue is the value in this case an atomic string value
to query a key value pair
we should be able perform one basic operation given the key return the value
now the value can also be an array an array is a list
so the query operations on it can either be on its position in the list or
on the value
thus we should be able to ask for the second element of the array called badges
or we should be able to seek objects of which the key called badges
has a value of blue
notice here that the document collection here is itself an array
within square brackets and it just two elements in it
the top level array does not have a key by default it called db
these key value peers are structured as tuples
often with a name in the snippet shown
favorites has a tuple of two key value pairs
now tuples can be thought of as relational records as the operations
would include projection of an attribute and selection over a set of tables
on the other hand the area called points
has two tuples these two tuples named
as you will see we will address these tuples by their positions
finally this one has nesting
that means a mini structure can be embedded within another structure
so we need operations that will let us navigate
from one structure to any of it embedded structures
now just like a basic sql query states which parts of which records from one or
more people should be reported a mongodb query states
which parts of which documents from a document collection should be returned
the primary query is expressed as a find function which contains two arguments and
an optional qualifier there are four things to notice in this function
the first is the term collection
this tells the system which document collection to use and
therefore is roughly similar to the from clause when restricted to one table
so if the name of the collection is beers the first part would say db beers find
the second item is a query filter which lists all conditions that
the retrieved documents should satisfy so it like a where clause
now if we want to return everything then this filter is left blank
otherwise we will fill it in a couple of ways shown in the next few slides
the third term is a projection class which is essentially a list of variables
that we want to see in the output
the fourth and last item sits after the find function ends and
is separated by a dot it called a cursor modifier
the word cursor relates back to sql where cursor is defined
as a block of results that is returned to the user in one chunk
this becomes important when the set of results is too large to be returned all
together and the user may need to specify how much or
what portion of results they actually want
so we will start out with a few queries
where we show how the same query can be expressed in sql and
in mongodb the first query wants everything from beers
the sql query is structured on the table beers and
the select asks to return all rows
in mongodb the same query is more succincted
since the name of the collection is already specified in
calling the find function the body of the find function is empty
that means there are no query conditions and no projection clauses in it
the second query
needs to return the variables beer and price for all records
so the find function here needs an empty query condition denoted by the open and
closed brace symbols but the projection clauses are specifically identified
there is a 1 if an attribute is output and a 0 if it is not
as a shortcut only variables with 1 are required
okay so when do you use 0
a common situation is the following
every mongodb document has an identifier named id
by default every query will return the id of the document
if you do not want it to return this designated attribute
you should explicitly say id : 0
next we will add query conditions
that is the equivalent of the where clause in sql
our query number three has the query condition where name is equal to a value
in mongodb that equal to translate to a variable colon value form
notice the symbol used for a string is quotes
query four is more interesting for two reasons
first we see a way in which the distinct operation is specified
notice here that the primary query function is not find any more but
a new function called distinct
as we will see later again in our slides
mongodb uses a few special query functions for some of the operations
so you need to know which function should be used in what context
when you write mogodb queries
secondly in this query we have a non - equality condition
namely the price is greater than 15
this example shows mongodb style of using operators in a query
it always variable :
followed by mongodb name for the operator and then the comparison value
so where would you find mongodb operators
here are some of the operators supported in mongodb
these operators and others are listed in the url shown at the bottom
the operators shown here are color coded
the top blue set are the comparison operators
we see the gt greater than operation that we used in the last slide
the green colored operations are array operations which we will see shortly
and the yellow operators at the bottom are logical operations that
combine two conditions in different ways like the and operation we saw in sql
now the last operator nor is interesting
because it is used to specify queries when neither of two conditions must hold
for example find all beer whose name is neither bad nor
is the price less than 6 per bottle
now i would strongly encourage you to play with these operators in
your hands on session
now i am sure you remember the like query in sql
mongodb uses regular expressions to specify partial string matches
now some of you may not know what a regular expression is
let first use some examples
the first example is the same query we saw before when we are asking for
beer manufacturers whose name has a sub string a - m in it
so a - m can appear anywhere within the name
to do this
the query condition first states that it is going to use a regex operation
and then we have to give the partial string as am
then it gives the directive that this match
should be case insensitive by placing an i after the partial string
and if we just wanted to do names we would stop right after the find function
but here we also want to do a count which is a post operation
after the find so we use count at the end of the find function
now what if we have the same query but we want the partial string a - m
to appear at the beginning of the name and
you would like the a to really be a capital letter
in this case we use the caret sign to indicate
that the partial string is at the beginning of the name
naturally we also drop the i at the end because the match is no longer case
insensitive a more complex
partial string pattern will be a case where our name starts with capital a - m
then has a number of characters in the middle and ends with corp
so for the first part the string pattern is ^ am
for the second part that is any character in the middle we use dot
to represent any character and star to represent zero or more occurrences
for the third part we say corp but
put a dollar at the end to say that it must appear at the end of the string
the regular expression pattern is a sub - language in itself and
is supported by most programming languages today
we will refer you to the following url to learn more about it
also note an example that instead of saying find count
we can directly use the count function natively defined in mongodb
one important feature of json is that everything contain arrays as a type of
collection objects this enables us to query arrays in multiple ways
one of them is to consider an array as a list and
perform intersection operations the first query shows this
the data item is shown on the right
it has the area value attribute called tags with three entries
the first query asks if two specific strings belong to the array
in other words it wants to get the document whose tagged attribute
intersects with the query supplied array
in this case there is an intersection and the document is returned
in the second case it is asking for
a documents who tags attribute has no intersection
now notice the nin operator so there is no intersection with this list
so in this document there exists and intersection so nothing will be returned
a different kind of array query uses the positions of the list elements and
wants to extract a portion of the array
this is illustrated in the third query which asks for
the second and third items of the array
to encode this in mongodb we use the slice operator
which needs two parameters the number of variable limits to skip
and the number of variable limits to extract after skipping
in this case we need to extract items two and three so the skip value is one and
the number of items is two thus returning summer and japanese
now we could get the same result if we pose the query using the last statement
in this case the minus says that the system should count from the end and
the true says that it should extract two elements
now if we omitted the minus sign it will come from the beginning and
fetch the first two elements
finally we can also ask for a document who second element in tags is summer
in this case we use an array index tags 1 to denote the second element
compound statements are queries with multiple query conditions that
are combined using logical operations
the query shown here has one condition which is the and are in terms of mongodb
the and of three different clauses
the last clause is the most straight forward
it states that the desired item should not be coors
the first clause is an or that is a or between two sub - conditions
a the prices either 3 99 or b it is 4 99
the second clause is also an or of two sub conditions
a the rating is good and b the quantity is less than 20
this query shows that the and and
the or operators need a list that is an array of arguments
to draw a quick comparison
here the example of the same query imposed with sql
now an important feature of semi - structured data is that
it allows nesting
we showed three documents here where there is an area named points
which in turn has two tuples with the elements points and bonus
let assume that these three documents are part of a collection so
they form three items in an area called users
our goal is to show how we can write queries to extract data
from these documents with nesting
the first query wants to find documents for
which the value of points should be less than or equal to 80
now which ones
now points 0
refers to the first tuple under the outer points and
points 0 points refers to the first element of that tuple
clearly only the second documents satisfies this query
now what happens if we have the same query but we drop the zero
now we are looking for points points without specifying the array index
this means that the points element in
any of the tuples should have a value of 80 or less
so now the first and the second document will satisfy the query
we can put multiple conditions as seen in the third query
it looks for a document where the points element of a tuple should be utmost 81
and the bonus should be exactly 20 and clearly the second document qualifies
but does the third document qualify
in this case the first tuple satisfies points greater than 81 and
the second tuple satisfies bonus equal to 20
the answer is no because the comma is treated as an implicit and
condition within the same double as shown in the yellow braces
now remember that we said in course two that all semi - structured
data can be viewed as a tree
now what if i pick a node of a tree and ask for all the descendents of that node
that would require the system to recursively get chidenodes
over increasing depth from the given node
unfortunately at this time mongodb does not support recursive search
a different kind of scaling problem arises when we try to answer queries over a large
number of data sources but before we do that let see how a query is answered in
the virtual data integration setting
we are going to use a toy scenario in a medical setting
simple as we have four data sources
each with one table for the sake of simplicity
notice that two sources s1 and s3 have the same schema
now this is entirely possible because sources may be independent of each other
further there is no guarantee that they would have the same exact content
maybe these two sources represent clinics at different locations
so next we look at the target schema
for simplicity let consider that it not an algorithmically creative
probabilistic mediator schema but just a manually designed schema with five tables
but while we assume that the target schema is fixed
we want the possibility that we can add more sources
that means more clinics as the system grows
now i am beginning to add the schema mapping
now there are several techniques of specifying schema mappings
one of them is called local - as - view
this means we write the relations in each source as a view over the target schema
but this way of writing the query as we can see here may seem odd to you
it called syntax but you do not need to know it
just as an example the first few things the treats relation in s1 maps to
so you see that arrow that means maps to
so it maps to the query select doctor
chronic disease from treats patient has chronic disease
where treatspatient patient is equal to has chronic disease dot patient
we see the query here in the yellow box
the only thing we should notice here is that the select class on the query
has two attributes doctor and
chronic disease which are exactly the same attributes of the treats relation in s1
now let ask a query that gives the target schema
which doctors are responsible for discharging patients
which translates to the sql query shown here
now the problem is how to translate this query to a query that can
be sent to the sources
now ideally this should be simplest query with no extra operations as shown here
s3 treats means treats relation in sources 3
now you can see the ideal answer
to find such an optimal query reformulation it turns out that this
process is very complex and becomes worse as a number of sources increases
thus query reformulation
becomes a significant scalability problem in a big data integration scenario
let look at the second use case
public health is a significant component of our healthcare system
public health systems monitor detect and take action when epidemics strike
not so long ago we have witnessed public health concerns due to anthrax virus
the swine flu and the bird flu
but these epidemics caused a group called wadds to develop a system for
disease surveillance
this system would connect all local hospitals in the washington dc area and
is designed to exchange disease information
for example if a hospital lab has identified a new strain of a virus
other hospitals and the centers for disease control cdc
in the network should be able to know about it
it should be clear that this needs a data integration solution where the data
sources would be the labs the data would be the lab tests medical records and
even genetic profiles of the virus and the subjects who might be infected
the table here shows the different components with this architecture
we will just digest the necessary parts for our requirement
just know that rim which stands for reference information model is global
schema that this industry has developed and expects to use as a standard
why we want to exchange and combine new information from different hospitals
every hospital is independent and
can implement their own information system any way they see fit
therefore even when there are standards like hl - 7 that
specify what kind of data a held cache system should have an exchange
there are considerable variations in the implementation of the standard itself
for example the two wide boxes show a difference in representation
of the same kind of data this should remind you of the data variety problem
let say we have a patient with id 19590520 whose lab
reports containing her plasma protein measurements are required for
analyzing her health condition
the problem is that the patient went to three different clinics and
four different labs which all implement the standards differently
on top of it
each clinic uses its own electronic medical record system
which we have a very large amount of data
so the data integration system job is to transform the data from the source schema
to the schema of the receiving system in this case the rim system
this is sometimes called the data exchange problem
informally a data exchange problem can be defined like this
suppose we have a given database whose relations are known
let us say we also know the target database schema and
the constraints the schema will satisfy
further we know the desired schema mappings between the source and
this target schema
what we do not know is how to populate the tuples in the target database
from the tuples in the socialization in such a way that both schema mappings and
target constraints are simultaneously satisfied
in many domains like healthcare a significant amount of effort has been
spend by the industry in standardizing schemas and values
for example loinc is a standard for medical lab observations
here item like systolic blood pressure or
gene mutation are encoded in this specific way as given by this standard
so if we want to write that the systolic diastolic pressure of
a individual is 132 by 90 we will not write out the string systolic blood pressure
but use the code for it
the ability to use standard code is not unique to healthcare data
the 50 states of the us all have two letter abbreviations
generalizing therefore whenever we have data such as the domain is finite and have
a standard set of code available we give a new opportunity of handling big deal
mainly reducing the data size through compression
the compression refers to a way of
creating an encoded representation of data
so that this encoder form is smaller than the original representation
a common encoding method is called dictionary encoding
consider a database with 10 million record of patient visits a lab
each record indicates a test and its results
now we show it this way like in a columnar structure
to make the point that the data is kept in a column stored relational database
rather than a row store relational database
now consider the column for test code
where the type of test is codified according to the standard
we replace a string representation of the standard by a number
the mapping between the original test code and
the encoded number are also stored separately
now suppose there are a total of 500 tests
so this separate table called the dictionary here has 500 rows
which is clearly much smaller than ten million right
now 500 distinct values can be represented by encoding them in 9 bits
because 2 to the power of 9 is 512
other encoding techniques would be applied to attributes like date and patient id
that full large data we cannot reduce the number of total actual rules
so we have to store all ten million rules
but we can reduce the amount of space required by storing data in a column
oriented data store and by using compression indeed modern
systems use credit processing algorithms to operate directly on compress data
data compression is an important technology for big data
and just like is a set of qualified terms for lab tests clinical data
also uses snomed which stands for systematized nomenclature of medicine
snomed is a little more than just a vocabulary
it does have a vocabulary of course
the vocabulary is the collection of medical terms in human and
medicine to provide codes terms synonyms and definitions that cover anatomy
diseases findings procedures micro organisms substances etcetera
but it also has relationships
as you can see a renal cyst is related to kidney because
kidney the finding site of a renal cyst
if we query against an ontology it would look like a graph grid
in this box
we are asking to find all patient findings with a benign tumor morphology
in terms of querying we are looking for edges of a graph where one noticed
the concept that we need to find which is connected to a node called benign neoplasm
that is benign tumor through an edge called associated morphology
that applying this query against the data here produces all benign tumors
of specific organs as you can see by the orange rounded group
but now that we have these terms
we can use these terms to search outpatient records with these terms would
have been used so what is the essence of this used case
this is can shows that an in division system in a public health domain and
in many other domains must be able to handle variety
in this case there a global schema called rim shown here all queries and
analyses performed by a data analysts should be against this global schema
however the actual data which is generated by different medical facilities
would need to be transformed into data in this schema
this would require not only format conversions but
it would need to respect all constraints imposed by the source and by the target
for example a source may not distinguish between an emergency surgical procedure
and a regular surgical procedure
but the target may want to put them in different tables
we also saw that the integration system for
this used case would need to use quantified data but this gives
us the opportunity to use data compression to gauge story and query efficiency
in terms of variety we saw how relational data like patient records xml
data like hl7 events and graph data like ontologies are co - used
to support this the integration system must be able to do both model
transformation and query transformation
query transformation is the process of taking a query on the target schema
converting it to a query against a different data model
for example part of an sql query against the rim may need to go to snowmad and
hence when you to be converted to a graph query in the snowmad system
model transformation is a process of taking data
represented in one model in one source system and
converting it to an equivalent data in another model the target system
hello my name is victor lou
i am the solutions engineer of global philanthropy of daameer org
helping researchers academia
and non - profits find the insights that matter using data
today i am here to give you a production environment
personalized music recommendation project
that was done for ponomusic and so what is pono music
pono music is revolutionizing music listening by bringing back native
high - resolution audio
it the way that artists intended and recorded their music
neil young the iconic artist and musician is also the founder and ceo
pono music is the only complete high - resolution music ecosystem
that includes the pono player the pono music store the pono music community
they have been super generous in allowing us to
take a look behind the scenes as how we built out the recommendations
so david meer supports their mission by providing a music recommendation
engine that is both scalable and flexible as pono grows their user base
let begin by visiting pono music website as you can see
they have a few shelves that focus on
various recommendations that are not tailored to each individual user
if you login then an additional shelf would appear
that would deliver the recommendations that are created in data gear
so how does datamirror accomplish this
in a nutshell datamirror is a end to end antalis platform which contains ingestion
preparation analysis visualization and operationalization all the same platform
and having all the capabilities in one platform is superior to
traditional technology stack
integration between disparate technologies brings a lot of unnecessary challenges
we take advantage of open source big data technologies
specifically we run natively and hadoop and spark for our back end
and we leverage d3js on the front end for visualizations
our excel - like interface makes it easy for
folks who do not know how to code to also get in with the data modeling
it is very much self - service
in the case of pono music data mirror deployment
we have deployed a hadoop on amazon on web services
but we can also be deployed off premise if
needed it does not have to be in the clouds
in fact we could work with many many different distributions of hadoop
we can access dean rear through any modern web browser
as you can see here we are using google chrome but it works on any browser right
so lets go ahead and take a look at the a; let log into data grip
so we are going to go ahead and log in here
so what you are seeing here is the browser tab and we can see various artifacts
which include connections such as connections to the pull nose
salesforce com instance or a connection to aws s3 instance
because datamirror comes with so
many prebuilt connectors which include connections to salesforce com and s3
we can easily grant access to those systems in order to pull or
push data in and out of the dev
for example let take a quick look at the salesforce com configuration here
as you can see we have already configured salesforce as the connector type
when we hit next here
we will we that you can authorize a data manager to retrieve data
we are not going to do it because this is a production environment so
i do not want to disrupt the pools
but if we were to click it it will give us a salesfloor com blogging stream
and so as soon as we login the datameer would have access via the o - off token
and so this is valid for a period of time
i am going to go ahead and
hit the cancel button as this is a production environment
and so now we are ready to look at an import job artifact
so this is the sales force import job and
as you can see we go in here and we configure it
we can see that it connected to the pono music smdc connection
i am going to go ahead and hit next here with salesforce com
we just have to simply define the soql
which is basically a querying language that based on sql
to locate data contained within the salesforce com objects
you can see the select statement here you can also see the familiar
from statement and you can also see the where statement as well
so in order to protect the privacy of the users
datameer has the capability to obfuscate sort of columns that are sensitive
and so in other words we can scramble sensitive fields such as email or
physical addresses
and at this point in time i am going to go ahead and cancel out and i am going to
show the next part of this demo in an obfuscated workbook environment
the artifacts contained in the obfuscated folders are duplicates of the import job
of the workbook from their production counterparts as you can see here
so as you can see in the import job settings we have configured
the same connections here but for the obfuscated columns here
now we are obfuscating the owner email as well as the street address
now we hit next here
and so you can see various fields are being pulled here from salesforce right
and in particular i want to highlight the
the owner email that field so as you can see these are the obfuscated fields
similarly the actual street address that also masked as well
i am going to go ahead and hit cancel
i will go back to rather we are going to go check out the workbook environment
which is where we do the preparation and analysis
to the obfuscated workbook environment
as you can see we are starting with a raw source of data here
this was the data that was contained in the data sheet
take note that there a variety of icons that indicate different types of sheets
so you could see here this is the raw data type
this is a regular worksheet
you have a union sheet and you have a joint sheet and
we will go into a little bit more detail as we get to them
so as you can see the interface is very much like excel
looking at the second sheet pairs and it using a function called group by
so the group by function is a type of aggregation function in datameer speak
as you can see you can build the functions by pointing and clicking
but you can also enter the formula to create nested functions or
apply arithmetic operations just as a cell
we take all the unique combinations of albums purchased for
each of the unique email using a group pair function
then we pull out each of the elements of the pairings using a list element
function so let see here
if you were to build a function from scratch you can see this
so then you create a group by function and then direct it at a column
you basically pass it to argument
to find out the occurrence of each pairing of albums
we are going to go ahead and look at this lr sheet
and so these are we are using group by functions as well here so
we are grouping by the first item one and then item two
and then we are doing a group count
which is counting the frequency of occurrences of those cells
similarly we are going to do a similar thing but
with the item two first now and then item one and then doing a group count
and the reason is we do not care about the order
and so we repeat this on the next sheet reversing the order of the albums to make
sure that we capture all the combinations since the order does not matter to us
and then we use our unit sheet function to append the second frequency
counting sheet to the first frequency counting sheet as you can see here
it drag and drop of course and so we have connected them together
you can do multi - sheets but in this case we only have two right
so it okay
we ignore the co - occurrent set sheet as it is currently not used in the final output
we were kind of experimenting with other recommendation models
we are rebuilding those workbooks
so one of the really cool features for we can execute the workbook but
deselect the storage of intermediary sheets
this means that we only need relevant functions are executed
at a to the data lineage of columns that are contained in the selector sheet
moving on we have to create a separate sheet from the raw data
that counts the number of times an album occurs across all of the purchases
so you can see here which students will buy an album and then we do a count
we bring the code occurrences and the frequency together using the join
feature as you can see it is a drag and drop interface
you got the obfuscated workbook each of the worksheets here and
within each worksheets you got various columns
you can bring those you can drag and drop them into here to do the joins
you can do different types of joins you got the inner outer etc
you can also do multi column joins
you can do multi sheet joins
you can also select which columns you want to keep during the join
go ahead and cancel out here
datameer does not allow us to add additional functions to a joint sheet so
we duplicate it by right clicking and then hitting the duplicate button
and then we create the next sheet which contains a link to columns so
it will be linked to the rating sheet
this is see the link columns back to the joint sheets and then
we simply add a calculation where it the number of times
the co - occurrence occurs divided by the number of times that the first album
in the column appears throughout the data set
the idea is to give a high recommendation for albums that appear frequently
together while simultaneously penalizing albums that are too common
and so at this point i would like to write a few more joins
that bring together the album id the email
recommended album id based on the album id and email so take a look here
so as you can see here and then
before we finish we also do an anti joint by performing
the outer left joint with the almighty in the email
and then filtering so this is by the way this is a double column joint
and then we do a filter so then we filter out all the for
the obfuscated owner fields that are empty
we apply a filter to it
so finally we use a few group i functions to do some deep duplication
so we use group by functions again
and then so we make sure that the album functions are unique for each user and
then we use a group max function
in order to preserve the highest rating for each of the unique
recommendations the final desired output is on the recommenders sheet
it leverages the group top end function so you can see here group top numbers
so we only want to look at the to 20 recommendations for each user
and in addition we also create a email row number field
which is a key that needed for salesforce com and
it is generated by a simple concatenation function here
something that note that sound is big on data governance data lineage
as you can see we can keep track of how all the raw data flows through
from the raw data set all the way to the end product
so each workbook functions can be also exported in json format to keep
track of revision history
we are not ready to operationalize things and so how do we do it
get our workbook configurations
go ahead and exit out of the workbook
let go back to the production environment
as you can see
the workbook recalculation retriggers when the import job is completed
we also only retain the latest results so
we select purge historical results as you can see here
as i mentioned earlier a data mirror makes it easy to operationalize a workbook
because we only select the final output sheets
and so you see everything unchecked except for the recommended sheet
and datameer basically will automatically determine what is a critical path
of the intermediary sheets to produce the desired output sheet
once the recommendation workbook is calculated
then this triggers the export job run
i am going to go ahead and move to the export job artifact
exit out of this
go ahead and save or not save
we will see the export job let go ahead and configure that
hit next share
csv outputs so
this triggers the export job to run
which is how we basically push the results of the recommendations to s3
we elected to use s3 because we are already hosting at services and
s3 is an affordable storage solution
we cannot push directly to salesforce com at the present because
it a only connection
therefore we need to push data to the storage area
which can be scheduled for using apex
a general challenge for is the role limitation on each pool
fortunately datamirror comes with the option to push
files that are broken into one megabyte chunks
so as you can see here in advanced settings 1 megabyte and
then we set a type of consecutive numbering scheme
and so it dynamic naming conventions using time stamps and numbering for
each of the chunks
so that sums up the current co - curds d deployment
as you have seen we have easily integrated data from salesforce com
created a recommendation model and set up a push to s3 automatically for
easy consumption back to salesforce com
finally we operationalized this by triggering each of the steps sequentially
all in sitting on top of the powerful hadoop platform
what is next
well pono music is working on implementing google analytics tracking for
each user at the apple pages
so let go back to the apple music store here
just for an example let take a look at the train led zeppelin two album
as you can see all of those album ids that we were looking at earlier
these are actually embedded in the url
this means that in the near future we can actually adapt recommendations based
on the buying behavior to recommendations based on both buying and browser behavior
we can look at recommendations based on genre perhaps we can try to look at most
recent purchases or browsing behavior in the last three to six to nine months
or we could use album metadata such as album release date to give additional
recommendations
also it is quite simple to just duplicate the recommendations workbook in
inaudible to try any number of these options
and so that means we can do a lot of ab testing
as we track how users react to each of the modified recommendation algorithms
the possibilities are literally endless
so anyhow thanks again for checking out how data mirror
builds a simple code current recommendation engine for music
please feel free to direction questions or
comments to me at victor liu datamirror com
thanks again
amarnath just finished overviewing querying and integrational big data
although fundamental understanding of these concepts are important
some of these tasks can be accomplished
using graphical user interface based tools or software products
in this short module we introduce you to two of those tools
splunk and datameer
we have selected a few videos from the site of our sponsors splunk
to give you an overview of using such tools for different applications
you will also have a short hands - on activity on splunk
in addition we provide you a comprehensive video on
using datamere in the digital music industry
keep in mind splunk and datamere are just two of the many
tools in this category but they represent a huge industry
open xc is an open source hardware - software platform
we wanted to see what correlations we could actually create within this model dashboards
it plugs into your car and it gives you all the data that you can possibly want
what we are interested in is looking at how you
can make the car much more modular and customizable
getting a lot of this data and afford cars
out and letting developers do whatever they want with it
you could kind of like update technology as technology progresses
so what we are really trying to do is like catch up with
the consumer electronics design cycle not the automotive design cycle types
the clock has not started yet
one of the tests that we did was a gas car versus an electric car
so we are trying to see which is faster
which is expecting the most energy
which is the most cost efficient
and we wanted to
measure does not electric car driver drive different than a gas car driver
so actually by using the open xc data
and by splunking that creating links in
dashboards will give it to match ups and correlations
it all comes down to how much are they mashing the gas
we have been internally calling that dashboard the lead foot dashboard
who the most efficient driver
there one of our drivers actually going low and
slow and actually using into the brakes not really gnashing on the gas
and driving more like a normal person would
when you drive an electric car it a lot quicker off the line than a gas powered car
so we find people kind of smashing
on the gas pedal but sort of easing up on the electric pedal
so i have got some data for you here
we see what is this i am doing
it says you are doing
there we go
battery car is high there you go
hurry up
there we go we do not even need because open xc we just cut it
these are basically all of
the sensor readings that are being broadcast from that firefly box
it plugged into the diagnostics port of the car
it about how much power can we kind of give
away in order to incentivize a community of makers
we want to be able to actually harness that and create
an environment where they can much more quickly
experiment with our ideas
enrich the platform in general
make our vehicles in that sense more valuable
in this hands on activity we will be performing queries in splunk
first we will open a browser and login to splunk
next we will import a csv file and search its contents
we will see how to filter fields for specific values and
also perform statistical calculations on the data
let begin
first open a web browser and navigate to the splunk web page
we will enter localhost : 8000
next we will log in to splunk using admin and the default password
next we will import a csv file into splunk
we will click on add data
upload we will click on select file
and we will choose the census csv file that we downloaded
click next
on the left it should say source type csv
if it does not click on the button and
go down to structured and select csv
in this table we see a preview of the data
you should see the column names of the csv file at the top
click on next
review
and submit
now that the file has been imported successfully click on start searching
in the search box it fills in the default query
source = cencus csv the host name and sourcetype = csv
we could change these fields to search other files or
other data types if we imported those into splunk
now let search census csv for particular values in the fields
let search for all the data where the state is california
we will enter stname = california
you will see the results down here
you could search for other states by using or
for example we can add or stname = alaska
this will search for state names equal to california or alaska
we can add conditions to our query as well
let search for state equals california whose population was over one million
we will do this by saying stname = california
census2010pop 1000000
can limit the results to one or more columns
you do this by adding pipe table ctyname to the end of our query
in spunk queries the pipe command is used to send the outputs from the first part of
the query into the next
you can also show more than one column from the output
if we add a comma census2010pop to the end of this
we will see both the city name and the population
you can also see a visualization of this data by clicking on the visualization tab
at the bottom on the x - axis we see the county names and
the y values are the population numbers
now let perform some statistics on this data
we will begin by counting the number of records where the state is california
you can do this by saying stname = california pipe stats count
now switch back to the statistics tab see the result here
now let see the total population for california
you can replace count with sum cenus2010pop
you can also calculate the average population
we will replace sum with mean
hello my name is mitch fleichmann senior instructor here at splunk
today we are going to install splunk on linux
i am using one of the splunk education linux servers
let examine the environment
first of all notice i am logged in as the user splunker
as a best practice do not install splunk as the root user
i am currently in the opt directory where i have already downloaded
the tarball from splunk com download for this platform
as a final check let check the system to make sure we have the correct operating
system and kernel
this is indeed a linux machine let get confirmation that it is also 64 bit
so we are good to go
the next step is to unzip and untar the installer and
that we can do with the gunzip and tar commands
when everything untucks you will notice a new sub directory created named splunk
and we can navigate to the splunk bin directory to start up splunk
couple of ways to start splunk with no switches
on the first startup you will be prompted to read and agree to the software license
or as a shortcut you can start up splunk and accept the license
and notice a couple of port numbers being grabbed port 8000 for
splunk web and port 8089 for splunk management
the splunk daemon has started
splunk is generating its own keys
and we can see the splunk web interface the url
as a best practice
you may also want to consider automating splunk to start when the machine boots
that you can do as the root user
by issuing the splunk enable command
enable boot - start as the - user splunker
the same user that we just consult splunk with
so lets log in to splunk web and see how the system looks
and for that we will go back to the browser
go to the appropriate url
and we can see upon first login
you are prompted to login with the credentials admin password changeme
since this is the first login
you also coach to change your password to something more secure
and it highly recommended to follow this best practice as well
and also on first connection
you will also see a splash screen showing you what is new in version 6
in this case powerful analytics
some changes to the ui to make it more intuitive
simplified component management for cluster management
folder management and so on
also a richer developer experience
close down this window and you can explore the navigation options
and notice in the left side
you see a panel showing you the apps to navigate to and manage
and on the right side you see some panel showing you data in the system and
various links for help
let go to the search and reporting app by clicking here
and you can see the search far up top
some tips on how to search and then data to search
since this is a fresh install there is no data to search so
the next step is to index data and begin searching
good luck
sound hello this is chris busheers
part of the splunk education team
in this video i will show you how install splunk onto a window server
first we need to get the software from the splunk com download page
we will need to select that the platform is 32 or 64 - bit
if you are not sure if your system is 32 or
64 - bit you can check your system properties
as you can see this server is 64 - bit so we can install that version
if we saw a system type of 32 - bit we would download the 32 - bit version
we run the installer by double clicking on it
there is button to view the license agreement and a check box to accept it
at this point we can either install splunk with the defaults or
customize our installation
let click on the customize options to see what settings can be selected
the first option is to change the installation location of splunk
we are fine with this location so we click next
now we must choose what account type to install splunk as local system or
domain account
a local system account will allow splunk to access all data on or
forwarded to this machine
a domain account will allow you to collect logs and
metrics from remote machines as well as local and forwarded data
you are required to provide a domain account with the proper domain rights
to use this type
local system works well for us so we click next
we can select to have a shortcut to splunk added and click install to continue
music
once installed we can select to have splunk launch and click finish
this splunk web interface opens in our default browser
we enter the default user name of admin and a password of change made
a dialog box appears asking us to change our password
it is always best practice to do this
once logged in we are taken to the splunk launcher homepage
and that all it takes to get splunk installed on windows
now dig in and start exploring
sound
our third and
final case is applicable to most companies that create customer - focused products
they want to understand how their customers are responding to the products
how the product marketing efforts are performing
what kind of problems customers are encountering and what new features or
feature improvements the customers are seeking and so forth
but how does the company get this information
what kind of data sources would carry this information
the figure show some of these sources
they are in focused user surveys emails sent by the customers in blogs and
product review forums specialized groups on social media and user forums
in short they are on the internet or in material received through the internet
now how many sources are there
two
the number would vary
a new sites a new postings and
new discussion threads would come up all the time
in all of these the goal is to identify information that
truly relates to the companies product its features and its utility
to cast this as a type of big data problem
we look at a task that computer scientists called data fusion
consider a set of data sources s as we mentioned on the last slide and
a set of data items d
a data item represents a particular aspect of a real world entity
which in our case is a product of the company
for each data item a source can but not necessarily will provide a value
for example
the usability of an ergonomically split keyboard can have a value good
the value can be atomic like good or a set or a list or
sometimes embedded in the string
for example the cursor sometimes freezes when using the touchpad
is a string which has a value about the touchpad
the goal of data fusion is to find the values of data items from a source
in many cases the system would find a unique true value of an item
for example the launch data of a product in europe should be the same true value
regardless of the data source one looks at
in other cases we could find a value distribution of an item
for example the usability of our keyboard may have a value distribution
that with data fusion we should be able to collect the values of real world
items from a subset of data sources
it is a subset because not all data sources
will have relevant information about the data item
there are some other versions of what a data fusion is but for
our purposes we will stick with this general description
now one obvious problem with the internet is that there are too many data
sources at any time these lead to many difficulties
first it is to be understood that with too many data sources
there will be many values for the same item
often these will differ and sometimes they will conflict
a standard technique in this case is to use a voting mechanism
however even a voting mechanism can be complex
due to problems with the data source
one of the problems is to estimate the trustworthiness of the source
for each data source
we need to evaluate whether it reporting some basic or known facts correctly
if a source mentions details about a rainbow colored iphone
which does not exist it trustworthiness reduces
because of the falsity of the provided value of this data item
accordingly a higher vote count can be assigned to a more trustworthy source
and then this can be used in voting
the second aspect is copy detection
detecting weather once was has copied information from another can be very
important for detail fusion task in customer analytics
if a source has copied information
it such that discounted vote count can be assigned to a copy value and
voting that means the copy in source will have less weight
now this is especially relevant when we compute value distributions because if we
treat copies as genuine information we will statistically bias the distribution
now here is active research on how to detect copies how to determine bias and
then arrive at a statistically sound estimation of value distribution
but to our knowledge these methods are yet to be applied to existing software for
big data integration
it should be very clear by now but
there are two kinds of big data situations when it comes to information
the first two uses cases that we saw requires an integration system
to consider all sources because the application demand so
in contrast problems where data comes from too many redundant potentially
unreliable sources like the internet the best results can be obtained if we have
a way of evaluating the worthiness of sources before information integration
but this problem is called source selection
the picture on the right shows the result of a cost benefit analysis for
data fusion
the x - axis indicates the number of sources used and
the y - axis measures the proportion of true results that were returned
we can clearly see that the plot peaks around six - to - eight sources and
that the efficiency falls as more sources are added
in a cost benefit analysis the cost must include both the human and
the computational costs
while the benefit is a function of the accuracy of the fusion result
the technique for solving this problem comes from economics
assuming that cost and benefits are measure in the same unit for
example dollars
they proposed to continue selecting sources
until the marginal benefit is less than the marginal cost
now recent techniques were performing this computation at quite scalable
in one setting selecting the most beneficial sources
from a total of one million sources took less than one hour
this completes our coverage of the big data integration problems
hello and welcome
my name is rene and i will be sharing with you how to create a report using pivot
to access the pivot interface click pivot on the navigation menu
the first step is to select a prebuilt data model
now the data model allows you to create compelling reports and
dashboards without having to know how to write complex search queries
as a side note data models are typically created by a knowledge manager that
understands their organization index data
grasps the search language and are familiar with lookups
transactions field extractions and calculated fields
for our example we are going to use buttercup games online sales
now this data model includes the online sales activities
it made up of nine objects
each object represents a specific set of events in a hierarchical structure
the http request would include the largest number of events in this data model
the next object successful request
would be a subset of the http request events and so on
let say that we want to create a report for purchases over the last seven days
we would select the most appropriate object
in this case we are going to select successful purchase
after you have selected the object you will notice that a new
pivot view will display
if you notice the count of successful purchase is the total
number of events for this specific object
now it is based off of all time
before you begin you should have an idea of what type of report you want to create
so let say that we want to create a bar chart
we are going to select that from the left navigation pane
so the third icon will allow me to click and select bar chart
so at this point we are ready to start building our report
the first selection is time range
let set that to the last seven days
the next one is filter now we do not need to define filter because we have already
selected an object of successful purchase and that what we are reporting against
now for my x axis i am going to select product name
you will notice that i can set the label
i can set the sort order
i can even set how many maximum bars that i want
the next thing to define is the y axis
at this time it set to count of successful purchase
but i want the total sales by product
so i am going to select price and
then you will notice that my value is already set to sum
so i am going to keep it as sum
my report is starting to look really good
but after reviewing it i might decide that i want to see values segmented by host
so let do that in order to set the segmentation
of a specific product name i could go and set the color to the field that i want
so i am going to select host
now you will see that my total sales are segmented by host
so we really like this report
let go ahead and save it
so we are going to click on save as
select report and give it a title
let call it product sales by host
we are going to click save and then we are going to view our report
it was that easy to create a report through pivot
now let just say that we want to go and work with another pivot
this time we are going to just go and
create a statistic table to view some of that data
let go ahead and click pivot again
we will select the same data model
buttercup games online sales and let keep to the object that
we are familiar with right now successful purchases
as i mentioned i want to just simply create a statistic table
i want to show you how we would go about doing that
so the first step is to think about what are some of the row data that you want
let just assume that we want to view the product names within their categories
so let go ahead under split rows we are going to select category first
notice that i can set a label if i want
let go ahead and set it capitalized category
i am going to add that to my table
you will see that it becomes the first column
now i want to add another column
let go ahead and click the plus right next to categories
again we are still working with the split rows
i am going to select product name again if you want to set a label you can do that
now this is the label of our column
add to table
and i want you to notice that now we are viewing each product
within their category
now at this point if you look at the statistic that is being defined
it the count of successful purchases
that is defined as column values
now if i want to add to this i can append and have another column
let go ahead and click the plus next to the count of successful purchase
this time i want to add the price
and you will notice that i have different values available
i could do a sum a count an average max min
let keep it as a sum and let add a label of total sales
and let add to table
so this is just to show you how quick it is to go and
build a table with the statistics that you would need
now at this point if ever you decide i only want to view the data for
the last seven days
just note that you could go back up to your filter and
your first filter is based off of all time
so we could set that to the last seven days
so of course that the data in our table will change
now the last thing i want to show you here is if ever you did want to see
the count and the total sales per host as we have defined in our previous example
that is where you could go to the split columns and
define how you wish to split that information
so let go ahead and select host again
and i am just going to click on add to table
now i could see that the information has been split by host
i have www1 count of successful purchases as well as total sales
and then i have the split of www2 i have the count and the total sales and etc
so this concludes our short video hope you enjoy it
thank you
welcome
in this short module we will talk about information integration which refers
to the problem of using many different information sources to accomplish a task
in this module we will look at the problems and solutions through a few use cases
so after this video you will be able to explain the data integration problem
define integrated views and schema mapping describe the impact of increasing
the number of data sources appreciate the need to use data compression
and describe record linking data exchange and data fusion tasks
our first use case starts with an example given at an ibm website for
their information integration products
it represents a very common scenario in today business world
due to the changing market dynamics companies
are always selling off a part of their company or acquiring another company
as these mergers and acquisitions happen databases which were developed and
stored separately in different companies would now need to be brought together
now take a minute to read this case
this is the case of an expanding financial services group that growing its customer
base in different countries
and all they want is a single view of their entire customer base
in other words it does not matter which previous company originally had
the customers suncorp - metway want to consolidate all customer
information as if they were in one single database
and in reality of course they may not want to buy a huge machine and
migrate every subsidiary company data into it
what they are looking to create is possibly a software solution which would make all
customer - related data to appear as though they were together as a single database
this software solution is called an information integration system
this will help them ensure that they have a uniform set of marketing campaigns for
all their customers
let try to see hypothetically of course what might be involved in creating
this combined data and what kind of use the integrated data might result in
so we first create a hypothetical scenario
although suncorp have a large number of data sources
we will take a much simpler situation and
have only two data sources from two different financial service companies
the first data source
which is an insurance company that manages it data with a relation of dbms
this database has nine tables where the primary object of information is a policy
the company offers many different types of policies
sold to individual people by their agents
now as it true for all insurance companies policyholders pay their monthly
dues and sometimes people make claims against their insurance policies
when they do the details of the claims are maintained in the database
these claims can belong to different categories and when the claims have
paid to the claimants the transaction is recorded in the transactions table
as we have done several times now
the primary keys of the table are the underlined attributes here
the second company in our example is a bank
which also uses a relational database
in this bank both individuals and businesses called corporations here
can have accounts
now accounts can be of different types
for example a money market account is different from a savings account
a bank also maintains its transactions in a table which can be really large
but the dispute in a bank record case happens when the bank is
charged a customer or the customer has declined responsibility of the charge
this can happen for example if a customer internet account was hacked or
a debit card got stolen
the bank keeps a record of these anomalies and
fraudulent events in a disputes table all right
let see what happens after the data from these two subsidiary companies
are integrated
after the merger the company wants to do a promotional goodwill activity
they would like to offer a small discount to their
insurance policyholders if they are also customers of the newly acquired bank
how do you identify these customers
let see
in other words we need to use the table shown on the left to create the table
shown on the right called discount candidates
one is to create a yellow tables from the insurance company database and
the blue table from the bank database and then join them to construct the table
with a common customer id and both the policykey and bank account number
now this relation which is derived that is computed by querying two different
data sources and combining their results is called an integrated view
it is integrated because the data is retrieved from different data sources
and it called a view because in database terminology
it is a relation computed from other relations
to populate the integrated view discount candidates
we need to go through a step called schema mapping
the term mapping means to establish correspondence between
the attributes of the view which is also called a target relation and
that of the source relations
for example we can map the full address from individuals to the address attribute
in discountcandidates but this would only be true for
customers whose names and addresses match in the two databases
as you can see policyholders uses the full name of a customer whereas
individuals has it broken down into first name middle initial and last name
on the other hand full address is a single field in individuals but
represented in full attributes in the policyholders relation
the mappings of account number and policykey are more straightforward
well what about customer id which does not correspond to anything in the four
input relations
we will come back to this later on
okay now we will define an integrated relation
how do we query
for example
how do you find the bank account number of a person whose policykey is known
you might think what is the problem here
we have a table
just say select account number from discount candidates where policykey
is equal to 4 - 937528734 and we are done
well yes you can write this query but how the query be evaluated
that depends on what is called the query
architecture of the data integration system
the figure on the left shows the elements of this architecture
we will discover it in more detail but on this slide
we will just describe the three axes of this cube
the vertical z axis specifies whether we have one data source or
multiple data sources
our interest is in the case where there are multiple data sources
the x axis asks whether the integrated data is actually stored physically
in some place or whether it is computed on the fly each time a query is asked
if it is all precomputed and stored we say that the data is materialized
and if it is computed on the fly we say it virtual
the y axis asks whether there is a single schema or
global schema defined all over the data integrated for
an application or whether the data stay in different computers and
it is accessed in a peer - to - peer manner at runtime
thus the seemingly simple select project query will be evaluated
depending on which part of the cube our architecture implements
but for now let return to our example use case
an obvious goal of an information integration system
is to be complete and accurate
complete means no eligible record from the source should be absent in
the target relation
accurate means all the entries in the integrated relation should be correct
now we said on the previous slide that a matching
customer is a person who was in both databases and
has the same name and address in the two databases
now let look at some example records
specifically consider the records marked by the three arrows
the two bank accounts and the policy record do not match for name or
for address
so our previous method would discard them
but look at the records closely
do you think they might all belong to the same customer
maybe this lady has a maiden name and
a married name and has moved from one address to another
maybe she changed her social security number somewhere along the way
so this is called a record linkage problem
that means we would like to ensure that the set of data records that belong to
a single entity are recognized perhaps by clustering
the values of different attributes or by using a set of matching rules so
that we know how to deal with it during the integration process
for example we need to determine
which of the addresses should be used in the integrated relation
which of the two bank accounts
if the answer is both accounts 102 and 103 we will need to change
the schema of the target relation to a list instead of an atomic number
to avoid creating multiple tuples for the same entity
as we saw the schema of adding process is a task of figuring out
how elements of the schema from two sources would relate to each other and
determining how they would map the target schema
you also saw that this is not really a simple process that we are trying to
produce one integrated relation using a couple of relations from each source
in a big data situation there are dozens of data sources or
more because the company growing and each source may have a few hundred tables
so it becomes very hard to actually solve
this correspondence - making problem completely and accurately just because
the number of combinations one has to go through is really really high
one practical way to tackle this problem is not to do a full - scale detail
integration in the beginning but adopt what is called a pay - as - you - go model
the pay - as - you - go data management principle is simple
the system should provide some basic integration services at the outset and
then evolve the schema mappings between the different sources on an as needed
basis
so given a query the system should generate a best effort or approximate
answers from the data sources for a perfect schema mappings do not exist
when it discovers a large number of sophisticated queries or
data mining tasks over certain sources it will guide the users to make
additional efforts to integrate these sources more precisely
okay so how does the first approximate schema mapping performed
one approach to do this is called probabilistic schema mapping
we will describe it in more detail next
in the previous step
we just decided to create the disk count candidates rrelation in an ad hoc way
and in a big data situation
we need to carefully determine what the integrated schema
also called mediated schemas should be and we should evaluate them properly
since our toy company is trying to create a single customer view
it natural to create an integrated table called customers
but how can we design this table
here are some options
we can create the customer table to include individuals and corporations and
then use a flag called customer type to distinguish between them
now in the mediated schema then the individuals first name
middle initial last name policyholder name and
corporation name would all map to customer name similarly
the individual full address the corporation registered address
and the policyholder address plus city plus state
plus zip would all map to customer address
now we can enumerate all such choices of which attributes to group together and
map for each single attribute in the target schema
but no matter how you will do it it will never be a perfect fit because
not all these combinations would go well together
for example should that date of birth be included in this table
would it make sense for corporations
in probabilistic mediated schema design we answer this question by
associating probability values with each of these options
to compute these values we need to quantify the relationships between
attributes by figuring out which attributes should be grouped or
clustered together
now two pieces of information available in the source schemas
can serve as evidence for attribute clustering
one the parallel similarity of source attributes and two
statistical properties of service attributes
the first piece of information indicates when two attributes are likely to be
similar and is used for creating multiple mediated schemas
one can apply a collection of attribute matching modules
to compute pairwise similarity
for example individual names and
policyholder names are possibly quite similar
are individual names versus corporation names similar
now the similarity between two source attributes ein and ez
measure how closely the two attributes represent the same real world concept
the second piece of information indicates
when two attributes are likely to be different and is used for
assigning probabilities to each of the mediated schemas
for example date of birth and
corporation name possibly will never co - occur together
but for large schemas with large data volumes
one can estimate these measures by taking samples from the actual database
to come up with reasonable similarity co - occurrence scores
to illustrate attribute regrouping we take a significant re - simplified example
here we want to create customer transactions as a mediated relation
based upon the bank transactions and insurance transactions
each attribute is given an abbreviation for simplicity
below you can see three possible mediated schemas
in the first one the transaction begin and end times
from bank transactions are grouped into the same cluster as transaction date time
from the insurance transactions because all of them are the same type
similarly transaction party that means who is giving or receiving money
and transaction description are grouped together with transaction details
the second schema keeps all of them separate
and the third candidate schema groups some of them and not others
now that we have multiple mediated schemas which one should we choose
now i am presenting here a qualitative account of the method
the primary goal is to look for what we can call consistency
a source schema is consistent with a mediated schema if
two different attributes of the source schema do not occur in one cluster
and in the example med3 that means related schema three
is more consistent with bank transactions because unlike med1
it keeps tbt tet in two different clusters
once this is done we can count the number of consistent sources for each candidate
mediated schema and then use this count to come up with a probability estimate
this estimate can then be used to choose the k best schemas
should one ever choose more than one just best schema
well that a hard question to answer in general
it is done when the top capability estimates are very close to each other
sound the splunk platform for operational intelligence is
a revolutionary suite of products that is unlocking unprecedented value for
thousands of customers around the world
why splunk
it all starts with machine data
machine data is the big data generated by
all the technologies that power our businesses
from the applications servers websites and network devices in the data center and
the cloud to the mobile device in the palm of your hand
thermostats train sensors electric cars and the internet of things
machine data is everywhere
it fast - growing and complex
it also incredibly valuable why
because it contains a definitive record of all activity and behavior
splunk software collects and indexes this data at massive scale
from wherever it generated regardless of format or source
users can quickly and easily monitor search analyze and
report on their data all in real time
machine data is different
it cannot be processed and analyzed using traditional methods
splunk software does not rely on brittle schemas and inflexible databases
splunk is easy to deploy easy to use and
easy to scale whether on premises or in a public private or hybrid cloud
splunk is also available as a cloud service
and for big data environments that used hadoop for cheap app storage
we have hunk splunk analytics for hadoop
music
our customers from around the world illustrate why so
many organizations use splunk
intuit has standardized on splunk delivering operational visibility for
their leading online products including quickbooks quicken and turbotax
intuit considers splunk one of their cornerstone technologies
that is helping them innovate and deliver better service to their customers
cisco one of the world largest technology providers
empowers their global security team with splunk enterprise
to gain a centralized view into end user and system activities
splunk has dramatically helped improve their incident detection and
response rate
splunk was key to domino pizza success during the super bowl
by monitoring database uptime and order response
armed with new levels of customer understanding
domino was able to strengthen their online business in addition to saving
hundreds of thousands of dollars replacing legacy technologies with splunk
we are thrilled to hear domino call splunk their secret sauce
another great splunk story includes cars and the internet of things
working together with the ford motor company and ford openxc platform
splunk delivered connected car dashboards to examine driving behavior and
vehicle performance
uk - based tesco is one of the world largest retailers
with nearly 1 million customers and a half billion online orders per week
customer satisfaction is a critical metric
tesco deployed splunk to gain a unified view across their websites transactions
and business gaining valuable digital intelligence about their customers
splunk was founded to pursue a disruptive vision to make machine data accessible
usable and valuable to everyone
find out more about splunk and
operational intelligence by downloading the executive summary
or better yet
experience the value firsthand by downloading splunk software for free
chances are someone in your organization already has
sound
aggregations in big data pipelines
after this video you will be able to compare and
select the aggregation operation that you require to solve your problem
explain how you can use aggregations to compact your dataset and reduce volume
that is in many cases
and design complex operations in your pipeline using a series of aggregations
aggregation is any operation on a data set that performs a specific transformation
taking all the related data elements into consideration
let say we have a bunch of stars which are of different colors
different colors denote diversity or variety in the data
to keep things simple we will use letter f to denote a transformation
in the following slides
we will see examples of how f can take the shape of different transformations
if we apply a transformation that does something using the information of
all the stars here we are performing an aggregation
loosely speaking we can say that applying a transformation f
that takes all the elements of data as input is called aggregation
one of the simplest aggregations is summation over all the data elements
in this case let say every star counted as 1
summing over all the stars gives 14
which is the summation of 3 stars for yellow
5 stars for green and 6 stars for color pink
another aggregation that you could perform is summation of individual star colors
that is grouping the sums by color
so if each star is a 1 adding each group will result in 3 for
yellow stars 5 for green stars and 6 for pink stars
in this case
the aggregation function f will output 3 tuples of star colors and counts
in a sales scenario each color could denote a different product type
and the number 1 could be replaced by revenue generated by a product
in each city the product is sold
in fact we will keep coming back to this analogy
you can also perform average over items of similar kind
such as sums grouped by color
continuing the example earlier
you can calculate average revenue per product type using this aggregation
other simple yet useful aggregational operations to help you extract meaning
from large data sets are maximum minimum and standard deviation
remember you can always perform aggregation as a series of operations
such as maximum of the sums per product
that is summation followed by maximum
if you first sum sales for each city that is for
each product then you can take the maximum of it
by applying maximum function to the result of the summation function
in this case you get the product which has maximum sales in the country
aggregation over boolean data sets that can have true - false or
one - zero values could be a complex mixture of and or and not logical operations
a lot of problems become easy to manipulate using sets
because sets do not allow duplicate values
depending on your application this could be very useful
for example to count the number of products from a sales table
you can simply take all the sales tables and create sets
of these products in those tables and take a union of these sets
to summarize by choosing the right aggregation you can generate compact and
meaningful insights that enable faster and effective decision making in business
you will find that in most cases
aggregation results in smaller output data sets
hence aggregation is an important tool set to keep in pocket when dealing with
large data sets and big data pipelines
big data processing pipelines : a dataflow approach
most big data applications are composed of a set of operations
executed one after another as a pipeline
data flows through these operations
going through various transformations along the way
we also call this dataflow graphs
so to understand big data processing we should start by
understanding what dataflow means
after this video you will be able to summarize what dataflow means and
it role in data science
explain split - do - merge as a big data pipeline with examples
and define the term data parallel
let consider the hello world mapreduce example for
wordcount which reads one or more text files and
counts the number of occurrences of each word in these text files
you are by now very familiar with this example but as a reminder
the output will be a text file with a list of words and
their occurrence frequencies in the input data
in this application the files were first split into hdfs
cluster nodes as partitions of the same file or multiple files
then a map operation in this case
a user defined function to count words was executed on each of these nodes
and all the key values that were output from map were sorted based on the key
and the key values with the same word were moved or shuffled to the same node
finally the reduce operation was executed on these nodes
to add the values for key - value pairs with the same keys
if you look back at this example we see that there were four distinct steps
namely the data split step the map step the shuffle and
sort step and the reduce step
although the word count example is pretty simple it
represents a large number of applications that these three
steps can be applied to achieve data parallel scalability
we refer in general to this pattern as split - do - merge
in these applications data flows through a number of steps going through
transformations with various scalability needs leading to a final product
the data first gets partitioned
the split data goes through a set of user - defined functions to do something
ranging from statistical operations to data joins to machine learning functions
depending on the application data processing needs
these do something operations can differ and can be chained together
in the end results can be combined using a merging algorithm or
a higher - order function like reduce
we call the stitched - together version of these sets of steps for
big data processing big data pipelines
the term pipe comes from a unix separation that
the output of one running program gets piped into the next program as an input
as you might imagine one can string multiple programs together
to make longer pipelines with various scalability needs at each step
however for big data processing
the parallelism of each step in the pipeline is mainly data parallelism
we can simply define data parallelism as running the same functions
simultaneously for the elements or partitions of a dataset on multiple cores
for example in our word count example data
parallelism occurs in every step of the pipeline
there definitely parallelization during map over the input
as each partition gets processed as a line at a time
to achieve this type of data parallelism
we must decide on the data granularity of each parallel computation
in this case it is a line
we also see a parallel grouping of data in the shuffle and sort phase
this time the parallelization is over the intermediate products
that is the individual key - value pairs
and after the grouping of the intermediate products
the reduce step gets parallelized to construct one output file
you have probably noticed that the data gets reduced to a smaller set
at each step
although the example we have given is for
batch processing similar techniques apply to stream processing
let discuss this for
our simplified advanced stream data from an online game example
in this case your event gets ingested
through a real time big data ingestion engine like kafka or flume
then they get passed into a streaming data platform for
processing like samza storm or spark streaming
this is a valid choice for processing data one event at a time or chunking
the data into windows or microbatches of time or other features
any pipeline processing of data can be applied to the streaming data here
as we wrote in a batch - processing big data engine
the process stream data can then be served through a real - time view or
a batch - processing view
real - time view is often subject to change as potentially delayed new data comes in
the storage of the data can be accomplished using h - base cassandra
hdfs or many other persistent storage systems
to summarize big data pipelines get created to process data
through an aggregated set of steps that can be represented with the split -
do - merge pattern with data parallel scalability
this pattern can be applied to many batch and
streaming data processing applications
next we will go through some processing steps in a big data pipeline in
more detail first conceptually then practically in spark
now that we went through an overview of the spark ecosystem and
the components of the spark stack it is time for us to start learning more about
its architecture and run our first spark program in the cloud vm
after this video you will be able to describe how spark
does in - memory processing using the resilient distributed dataset abstraction
explain the inner workings of the spark architecture and
summarize how spark manages and executes code on clusters
i mentioned a few times that spark is efficient because it
uses an abstraction called rdds for in memory processing
what this means might not be clear to some of you yet
let remember the alternative
in hadoop mapreduce each step also pipeline
reads from disk to memory performs the computations and
writes back its output from the memory to the disk
however writing data to disk is a costly operation and
this cost becomes even more with large volumes of data
here is an interesting fact
memory operations can be up to 100 000 times
faster than disk operations in some cases
spark instead takes advantage of this and allows for
immediate results of transformations in different stages of the pipeline and
memory like map and reduce here
here we see that the outputs of map operations
are shared with reduce operations without being written to the disk
the containers where the data gets stored in memory
are called resilient distributed datasets or rdds for short
rdds are how spark distributes data and computations across
the nodes of a commodity cluster preferably with large memory
thanks to this abstraction
spark has proven to be 100 times faster for some applications
let define all the words in this interesting name
beginning with the last one datasets
datasets that rdd distributes comes from a batch data storage like hdfs
no sql databases text files or streaming data ingestion systems like cafco
it can even conveniently read and distribute the data from your local disc
like text files into spark or even a hierarchy of folders
when spark reads data from these sources it generates rdds for them
the spark operations can transform rdds into other rdds like any other data
here it important to mention that rdds are immutable
this means that you cannot change them partially
however you can create new rdds by a series of one or many transformations
next let look at what distributed means in the rdd context
as i mentioned before rdds distribute partitioned data collections and
computations on clusters even across a number of machines
for example running on the amazon cloud
the complexity of this operation is hidden by this very simple interface
computations are a diverse set of transformations of rdds like map
filter and join
and also actions on the rdds like counting and saving them persistently on disk
the partitioning of data can be changed dynamically to optimize spark
performance
the last element is resilient and it very important because in a large
scale computing environment it is pretty common to have node failures
it very important to be able to recover from these
situations without losing any work already done
for full tolerance in such situations spark tracks the history of each
partition keeping a lineage over rdds over time
so every point in your calculations spark knows which are the partitions
needed to recreate the partition in case it gets lost
and if that happens
then spark automatically figures out where it can start the recompute from and
optimizes the amount of processing needed to recover from the failure
before we create our first spark program using rdds in pi spark in the cloud
layer vm let review spark architecture
from a bird eye view spark has two main components
a driver program and worker nodes
the driver program is where your application starts
it distributes rdds on your computational cluster and
makes sure the transformations and actions on these rdds are performed
driver programs create a connection to a spark cluster or
your local spark through a spark context object
the default spark context in the spark shell is
an object called sc for spark context
for example in the upcoming reading for creating word counts in spark
we will use sc as the context to
generate rdds for a text file using the line of code shown here
the driver program manages a potentially large number of nodes called worker nodes
on a local computer we can assume that there only one worker node and
it is where the spark operations execute
a worker node in spark keeps a running java virtual machine
called jvm commonly called the executor
depending on the illustration
executor can execute task related to mapping stages or
reducing stages or other spark specific pipelines
this java virtual machine is the core that all the computation is executed
and this is the interface also to the rest of the big data storage systems and tools
for example if we ever had the hadoop file system htfs as the storage system
then on each worker node some of the data will be stored locally
as you know the most important point of this computing framework is to bring
the computation to data
so spark will send some computational jobs to be executed
on the data that are already available on the machine thanks to hdfs
data will be read from hdfs and
get processed in memory the results will be stored as one rdd
the actual computation is running straight in the executor
that is the jvm that runs your scala or java codes
instead if you are using pyspark then there will be several python
processes generally one for task but
you can configure it depending on your application
in a real big data scenario we have many worker nodes running tasks internally
it is important to have a system that can automatically manage provisioning and
restarting of these nodes
the cluster manager in spark has this capability
spark currently supports mainly three interfaces for cluster management
namely spark standalone cluster manager the apache mesos and hadoop yarn
standalone means that there a special spark process that takes care of
restarting nodes that are failing or
starting nodes at the beginning of the computation
yarn and mesos are two external research measures that can be used also for
these purposes
choosing a cluster manager to fit your application and
infrastructure can be quite confusing
here we give you a good article as a starting point on
how to pick the right cluster manager for your organization
to summarize the spark architecture includes a driver program
the driver program communicates with the cluster manager for
monitoring and provisioning of resources and
communicates directly with worker nodes to submit and execute tasks
rdds get created and passed within transformations running in the executable
finally let see how this setup works on the cloudera vm
in the cloudera vm we are using spark in standalone mode and
everything is running locally
so it a single machine and on the same machine we have our driver program
the executor jvm and our single pyspark process
with that we are ready to start with our first reading to install spark and
then running our word count program using the spark environment
after a brief overview of some of the processing systems
in the big data landscape it is time for us to dive deeper into spark
spark was initiated at uc berkeley in 2009 and
was transferred to apache software foundation in 2013
since then spark has become a top level project with many users and
contributors worldwide
after this video you will be able to list the main motivations for
the development of spark draw the spark stack as a layer diagram
and explain the functionality of the components in the spark stack
as we have discussed in our earlier discussions while hadoop is great for
batch processing using the mapreduce programming module
it has shortcomings in a number of ways
first of all since it is limited to map and reduce based transformations
one has to restrict their big data pipeline to map and reduce steps
but the number of applications can be implemented using map and
reduce it not always possible and
it is often not the most efficient way to express a big data pipeline
for example you might want to do a join operation between different data sets or
you might want to filter or sample your data
or you might have a more complicated data pipeline with
several steps including joins and group byes
it might have a map and reduce face but maybe another map face after that
these types of operations are hard or impossible to express using mapreduce and
cannot be accommodated by the mapreduce framework in hadoop
another important bottleneck in hadoop mapreduce that is critical for
performance is that mapreduce relies heavily on reading data from disc
this is especially a problem for iterative algorithms that require taking several
passes through the data using a number of transformations
since each transformation will need to read its inputs from the disk
this will end up in a performance bottleneck due to io
most machine learning pipelines are in this category
making hadoop mapreduce not ideal for machine learning
and as i mentioned in the system overview the only programming language
that mapreduce provides a native interface for is java
although it possible to run python code to implementation for it is more complex
and not very efficient especially when you are running not with text data but
with floating point numbers
the programming language issue also affects how interactive
the environment is
most data scientist prefer to use scripting
languages due to their interactive shell capabilities
not having such an interface in hadoop really makes it difficult to use and
adapt my many in the field
in addition in the big data era having support for
streaming data processing is a key for
being able to run similar analysis on both real time and historical data
spark came out of the need to extend the mapreduce framework
to overcome this shortcomings and
provide an expressive cluster computing environment that can provide interactive
querying efficient iterative analytics and streaming data processing
so how does apache spark provide solutions for these problems
spark provides a very rich and expressive programming module that
gives you more than 20 highly efficient distributed operations or transformations
pipe - lining any of these steps in spark simply takes a few lines of code
another important feature of spark is the ability to run these computations
in memory
it ability to cache and process data in memory
makes it significantly faster for iterative applications
this is proven to provide a factor of ten or even 100 speed - up
in the performance of some algorithms especially using large data sets
additionally spark provides support for batch and streaming workloads at once
last but not least spark provides simple apis for python
scala java and sql programming through an interactive shell to
accomplish analytical tasks through both external and its built - in libraries
the spark layer diagram also called stack
consists of components that build on top of the spark computational engine
this engine distributes and monitors tasks across the nodes of a commodity cluster
the components built on top of this engine are designed to interact and
communicate through this common engine
any improvements to the underlying engine becomes
an improvement in the other components thanks to such close interaction
this also enables building applications that span across these different
components like querying data using spark sql and applying machine learning
algorithms the query results using sparks machine learning library and mllib
the spark core is where the core capability is
of the spark framework are implemented
this includes support for
distributed scheduling memory management and full tolerance
interaction with different schedulers like yarn and mesos and
various nosql storage systems like hbase also happen through spark core
a very important part of spark core is the apis for
defining resilient distributed data sets or rdds for short
rdds are the main programming abstraction in spark
which carry data across many computing nodes in parallel and transform it
spark sql is the component of spark that provides querying structured and
unstructured data through a common query language
it can connect to many data sources and provide apis to convert
query results to rdds in python scala and java programs
spark streaming is where data manipulations take place in spark
although not a native real - time interface to datastreams spark streaming enables
creating small aggregates of data coming from streaming data ingestion systems
these aggregate datasets are called micro - batches and
they can be converted into rdbs in spark streaming for processing
mllib is sparks native library for
machine learning algorithms as well as model evaluation
all of the functionality is potentially ported to any programming language sparks
supports and is designed to scale out using spark
graphx is the graph analytics library of spark and
enables the vertex edge data model of graphs to be converted into rdds as
well as providing scalable implementations of graph processing algorithms
to summarize through these layers spark provides diverse
scalable interactive management and analyses of big data
the interactive shell enables data scientists to conduct exploratory
analysis and create big data pipelines while also enabling the big
data system integration engineers to scale these analytical pipelines
across commodity computing clusters and cloud environments
there are many big data processing systems but
how do we make sense of them in order to take full advantage of these systems
in this video we will review some of them and
a way to categorize big data processing systems as we go through our review
after this video you will be able to recall the hadoop ecosystem
draw a layer diagram with three layers for data storage data processing and
workflow management
summarize an evaluation criteria for big data processing systems and
explain the properties of hadoop spark flink
beam and storm as major big data processing systems
in our introduction to big data course
we talked about a version of the layer diagram for the tools
in the hadoop ecosystem organized vertically based on the interface
lower level interface is the storage and scheduling on the bottom and
higher level languages and interactivity at the top
most of the tools in the hadoop ecosystem are initially built to complement
the capabilities of hadoop for distributed filesystem management using hdfs
data processing using the mapreduce engine and resource scheduling and
negotiation using the yarn engine
over time a number of new projects were built
either to add to these complimentary tools or to handle
additional types of big data management and processing not available in hadoop
arguably the most important change to hadoop over time
was the separation of yarn from the mapreduce programming model
to solely handle resource management concerns
this allowed for hadoop to be extensible to different programming models
and enabled the development of a number of processing engines for
batch and stream processing
another way to look at the vast number of tools that have been added to the hadoop
ecosystem is from the point of view of
their functionality in the big data processing pipeline
simply put these associate to three distinct layers for data management and
storage data processing and resource coordination and workflow management
in our second course we talked about the bottom layer
in this diagram in detail namely the data management and storage
while this layer includs hadoop hdfs there are a number of other systems that
rely on hdfs as a file system or implement their own no sql storage options
as big data can have a variety of structure semi structured and
unstructured formats and gets analyzed through a variety of tools
many tools were introduced to fit this variety of needs
we call these big data management systems
we reviewed redis and aerospike as key value stores
where each data item is identified with a unique key
we got some practical experience with lucene and
gephi as vector and graph data stores respectively
we also talked about vertica as a column store database
where information is stored in columns rather than rows
cassandra and hbase are also in this category
finally we introduce solr and asterisk db for managing unstructured and
semi - structured text and mongodb as a document store
the processing layer is where these different varieties of data gets
retrieved integrated and analyzed which is the primary focus of this class
in the integration and processing layer
we roughly refer to the tools that are built on top of the hdfs and yarn
although some of them work with other storage and file systems
yarn is a significant enabler of many of these tools making a number of batch and
stream processing engines like storm spark flink and being possible
we will revisit these processing engines and explain why we have so
many later in this lecture
this layer also includes tools like hive or spark sql for
bringing a query interface on top of the storage layer
pig for scripting simple big data pipelines using the mapreduce framework
and a number of specialized analytical libraries for machine learning and
graph analytics like giraph as graphx of spark are examples of such libraries for
graph processing
and mahout on top of the hadoop stack and mllib of spark are two options for
machine learning
although we have a basic overview of graph processing and machine learning for
big data analytics later in this course we wo not go into the details here
instead we will have a dedicated course on each of them
later in this specialization
the third and top layer in our diagram is the coordination and management layer
this is where integration scheduling coordination and
monitoring of applications across many tools in the bottom two layers take place
this layer is also where the results of the big data analysis gets communicated to
other programs websites visualization tools and business intelligence tools
workflow management systems help to develop automated solutions that can
manage and coordinate the process of combining data management and analytical
tests in a big data pipeline as a configurable structured set of steps
the workflow driven thinking also matches this basic process of data
science that we overviewed before
oozie is an example of a workflow scheduler that can interact with
many of the tools in the integration and processing layer
zookeeper is the resource coordination and monitoring tool and
manages and coordinates all these tools and middleware named after animals
although virtual management is my personal research area and
i talk more about it in other venues
in this specialization we focus mainly on big data integration and processing
and we will not have a specific lecture on this layer in this course
we give you a reading on big data workflows after this video as
further information and a starting point for the subject
in data integration and processing pipelines
data goes through a number of operations which can apply
a specific function to it can work the data from one format to another
join data with other data sets or filter some values out of a data set
we generally refer to these as transformations some of which can also
be specially named aggregations as you have seen in amarnath earlier lectures
in this video we will reveal some common transformation operations that we see
in these pipelines some of which we refer to as data parallel patterns
after this video you will be able to list common data
transformations within big data pipelines and design
a conceptual data processing pipeline using the basic data transformations
simply speaking transformations are higher order functions or
tools to convert your data from one form to another just like
we would use tools at the wood shop to transform logs into furniture
when we look at big data pipelines used today
map is probably the most common transformation we find
the map operation is one of the basic building blocks of the big data pipeline
when you want to apply a process to each member of a collection
such as adding 10 bonus to each
person salary on a given month a map operation comes in very handy
it takes your process and understand that it is required to perform
the same operation or process to each member of the set
the figure on the left here shows the application
of a map function to data depicted in grey color
here colors red blue and yellow are keys to identify each data set
as you see each data set is executed separately even for the same colored key
the reduce operation helps you then to collectively apply the same
process to objects of similar nature
for example when you want to add your monthly spending in different categories
like grocery fuel and dining out the reduce operation is very useful
in our figure here on the top left
we see that data sets in grey with the same color
are keys grouped together using a reduced function
reds together blues together and yellows together
it would be a good idea to check out the spark word count hands - on to see
how map and reduce can be used effectively for getting things done
map and reduce are types of transformations that work on a single
list of key and data pairings just like we see on the left of our figure
now let consider a scenario where we have two data sets identified
by the same keys just like the two sets and colors in our diagram
many operations have such needs where we have to look at all the pairings of
all key value pairs just like crossing two matrices
for a practical example imagine you have two teams
a sales team with two people and an operations team with four people
in an event you would want each person to meet every other person
in this case a cross product or
a cartesian product becomes a good choice for organizing the event and
sharing each pairs meeting location and travel time to them
in a cross or cartesian product operation each data partition gets
paired with all other data partitions regardless of its key
this sometimes gets referred to as all pairs
now add to the cross product by just grouping together the data
partitions with the same key just like the red data
and the yellow data partitions here
this is a typical match or join operation
as we see in the figure here match is very similar to the cross product
except that it is more selective in forming pairs
every pair must have something in common
this something in common is usually referred to as a key
for example each person in your operations team and
sales team is assigned to a different product
you only want those people to meet who are working on the same product
in this case your key is product
and you can perform and match operation and
send emails to those people who share a common product
the number of emails is likely to be less than when you performed a cartesian or
a cross product therefore reducing the cost of the operation
in a match operation only the keys with data in both sets get joined
and become a part of the final output of the transformation
now let consider listing the data sets with all the keys
even if they do not exist in both sets
consider a scenario where you want to do brainstorming sessions
of people from operations and sales and
get people who work on the same products in the same rooms
a co - group operation will do this for you
you give it a product name as they key to work with and
the two tables the sales team and operations team
the co - group will create groups which contain team members
working on common products even if a product does not exist in one of the sets
the last operation we will see is the filter operation
filter works much like a test
where only elements that pass a test are shown in the output
consider as a set that contains teams and a number of members in their teams
if your game requires people to pair up
you may want to select teams which have an even number of members
in this case you can create a test that only passes the teams which have
an even number of team members shown as divided by 2 with 0 in the remainder
the real effectiveness of the basic transformation we saw here
is in pipelining them in a way that helps you to solve your specific
problem just as you would perform a series of tasks on a real block
of wood to make a fine piece of woodwork that you can use to steer your
ship which in this case is your business or research
now that we revealed all three layers
we are ready to come back to the integration and processing layer
just a simple google search for big data processing pipelines
will bring a vast number of pipelines with large number of technologies
that support scalable data cleaning preparation and analysis
how do we make sense of it all to make sure we use the right tools for
our application
we will continue our lecture to review a set of evaluation criteria for
these systems and some of the big data processing systems based on this criteria
depending on the resources we have access to and characteristics of our application
we apply several considerations to evaluate and
pick a software stack for big data
of these first one we consider is the execution model
and the expressivity of it to support for various transformations of batch or
streaming data or sometimes interactive computing
semantics of streaming including exactly once or
at least one processing for each event or being able to keep the state of the data
is an important concern for this execution model
latency is another important criteria depending on the application
having a low latency system is very important for
applications like online gaming and hazards management
whereas most applications are less time critical
like search engine indexing and would be fine with a batch processing ability
scalability for both small and large datasets and different
analytical methods and algorithms is also an important evaluation criteria
as well as support for different programming language
of the libraries used by the analytical tools that we have access to
finally while all big data tools provide fault tolerance
the mechanics of how the fault tolerance is handled is an important issue to consider
let review five of the big data processing
engines supported by the apache foundation using this evaluation criteria
the mapreduce implementation of hadoop provides a batch execution
model where the data from hdfs gets loaded into mappers before processing
there is no in - memory processing support
meaning the mappers write the data on files before the reducers can read it
resulting in a high - latency and less scalable execution
this also hinders the performance of iterative and
interactive applications that require many steps of transformations using mapreduce
although the only native programming interface for
mapreduce is in java other programming languages like python provide modules or
libraries for hadoop mapreduce programming however with less efficiency
data replication is the primary method of fault tolerance
which in turn affects the scalability and execution speed further
spark was built to support iterative and
interactive big data processing pipelines efficiently using an in - memory
structure called resilient distributed datasets or shortly rdds
in addition to map and reduce operations it provides support for
a range of transformation operations like join and filter
any pipeline of transformations can be applied to these rdd in - memory
making spark performance very high for iterative processing
the rdd extraction is also designed to handle fault tolerance with
less impact on performance
in addition to hdfs
spark can read data from many storage platforms and it provides support for
streaming data applications using a technique called micro - batching
its latency can be on the order of seconds depending on the batch size
which is relatively slower compared to native streaming platforms
spark has support for a number of programming languages including scala and
python as the most popular ones as well as built - in libraries for
graph processing and machine learning
although flink has very similar transformations and
in - memory data extractions with spark it provides direct support for
streaming data making it a lower - latency framework
it provides connection interfaces to streaming data ingestion engines like
kafka and flume
flink supports application programming interfaces in java and
scala just like spark
starting with it original version called stratosphere
flink had it own execution engine called nephele and had an ability
to run both on hadoop and also separately in its own execution environment
in addition to map and reduce flink provides abstractions for
other data parallel database patterns like join and group by
one of the biggest advantage of using flink comes from it optimizer
to pick and apply the best pattern and execution strategy
there has been experiments comparing fault tolerance features of flink
to those of sparks which conclude that sparks slightly better for spark
the beam system from google is a relatively new system for
batch and stream processing with a data flow programming model
it initially used google own cloud data flow as an execution environment but
spark and flink backends for it have been implemented recently
it a low - latency environment with high reviews on fault tolerance
it currently provides application programming interfaces in java and
scala and a python sdk is in the works
sdk means software development kit
beam provides a very strong streaming and windowing framework for streaming data
and it is highly scalable and reliable allowing it to make trade - off
decisions between accuracy speed and cost of processing
storm has been designed for
stream processing in real time with very low - latency
it defined input stream interface abstractions called spouts and
computation abstractions called bolts
spouts and bolts can be pipelined together using a data flow approach
that data gets queued until the computation acknowledges
the receipt of it
a master node tracks running jobs and
ensures all data is processed by the computations on workers
nathan mars the lead developer for storm built the lambda architecture
using storm for stream processing and hadoop mapreduce for batch processing
the lambda architecture originally used storm for
speed layer and hadoop and hbase for batch and
serving layers as seen in this diagram
however it was later used as a more general framework that can combine
the results of stream and batch processing executed in multiple big data systems
this diagram shows a generalized lambda architecture containing some of the tools
we discussed earlier including using spark for both batch and speed layers
in this course we picked spark as a big data integration and
processing environment since it supports most of our evaluation criteria
and this hybrid data processing architecture using built - in data querying
streaming and analytical libraries
we will continue our discussion with spark and hands - on exercises in spark
analytical operations in big data pipelines
after this video
you will be able to list common analytical operations within big data pipelines and
describe sample applications for these analytical operations
in this lesson we will be looking at analytical operations
these are operations used in analytics which is the process of
transforming data into insights for making more informed decisions
the purpose of analytical operations is to analyze the data to discover meaningful
trends and patterns in order to gain insights into the problem being studied
the knowledge gained from these insights
ultimately lead to more informed decisions driven by data
here are some common analytical operations that we will discuss in this lecture
classification clustering
path analysis and connectivity analysis
let start with classification
in classification the goal is to predict a categorical target from the input data
a categorical target is one with discreet values or
categories instead of continuous values
for example this diagram shows
a classification task to determine the risk associated with a loan application
the input consists of the loan amount
applicant information such as income age debts and a down payment
from this input data the task is to determine whether
the loan application is low risk or high risk
there are many classification techniques or algorithms that can be used for
this problem
we will discuss a specific one namely decision tree in the next slide
the decision tree algorithm is one technique for classification
with this technique
decisions to perform the classification task are modeled as a tree structure
for the loan risk assessment problem a simple decision tree is shown here
where the loan application is classified as being either low risk or
high risk based on the loan amount
the applicant income and the applicant age
the decision tree algorithm is implemented in many machine learning tools
this diagram shows how to specify decision tree from input data knime
a graphical user - interface - based machine learning platform
some examples of classification are the prediction of whether cells from
a tumor are benign or malignant categorization of
handwritten digits as being zero one two etc up to nine
and determining whether a credit card transaction is legitimate or fraudulent
and classification of a loan application as being low - risk medium - risk or
high - risk as you have seen
another common analytical operation is cluster analysis
in cluster analysis or clustering
the goal is to organize similar items in to groups of association
this diagram shows an example of cluster analysis in which customers are clustered
into groups according to their preferences of movie genre
so customers who like sci - fi movies are grouped together
those who like drama movies are grouped together
and customers who like horror movies are grouped together
with this grouping new movies as well as other products
such as books can be offered to the right type of costumers in order to
generate interest and increase revenue
a simple and commonly used algorithm for cluster analysis is k - means
with k - means samples are divided into k clusters
this clustering is done in order to minimize the variance or
similarity between samples within the same cluster
using some similarity measures such as distance
in this example k is equal to three and
k - means divides the original data shown on the left into three clusters
shown as blue green and red on the chart on the right
the k - means clustering algorithm is implemented on many machine - learning
platforms
the code here shows how to read in and
parse input data and perform k - means clustering on the data
other examples of cluster analysis are grouping a company s customer base
into distinct segments for more effective targeted marketing finding articles or
webpages with similar topics for retrieving relevant information
identification of areas in the city with rates of particular types of crimes for
effective management of law enforcement resources and
determining different groups of weather patterns such as rainy cold or snowy
classification and cluster analysis are considered machine learning and
analytical operations
there are also analytical operations from graph analytics
which is the field of analytics where the underlying data is structured as or
can be modeled as the set of graphs
one analytical operation using graphs as path analysis
which analyzes sequences of nodes and edges in a graph
a common application of path analysis
is to find routes from one location to another location
for example you might want to find the shortest path from your home to your work
this path may be different depending on conditions such as the day of the week
time of day traffic congestion weather and etc
this code shows some operations for path analysis on neo4j
which is a graph database system using a query language called cypher
the first operation finds the shortest path between specific nodes in a graph
the second operation finds all the shortest paths in a graph
connectivity analysis of graphs has to do with finding and
tracking groups to determine interactions between entities
entities in highly interacting groups are more connected
to each other than to entities of other groups in a graph
these groups are called communities and
are interesting to analyze as they give insights into the degree and
patterns of the interaction between entities and also between communities
some applications of connectivity analysis are to extract conversation threads
for example by looking at tweets and retweets
to find interacting groups for example to determine which users are interacting
with each other users to find influencers for example to understand
who are the main users leading to the conversation about a particular topic
or who do people pay attention to
this information can be used to identify the fewest number of
people with the greatest influence
for example for political campaigns or marketing on social media
this code shows some operations for
connectivity analysis on neo4j using the query language cypher again
the first operation finds the degree of all the nodes in a graph
and the second creates a histogram of degrees for all nodes in a graph
to determine how connected a node in a graph is we need to look at its degree
the degree of a node is the number of edges connected to the node
a degree histogram shows the distribution of node degrees in the graph and
is useful in comparing graphs and identifying types of users for
example those who follow versus those who are followed in social networks
to summarize and add to these techniques the decision tree algorithm for
classification and k - means algorithm for cluster analysis that we covered in this
lecture are techniques from machine learning
machine learning is a field of analytics focused on the study and construction of
computer systems that can learn from data without being explicitly programmed
our course on machine learning in this specialization will cover these
algorithms in more detail along with other algorithms used for
classification and cluster analysis
as well as algorithms for other machine learning tasks
such as regression association analysis and tools for
implementing and executing machine learning algorithms
as a summary of the graph analytics the path analytics technique for finding
the shortest path and the connectivity analysis technique for analyzing communities
that we discussed earlier are techniques used in graph analytics
as explained earlier graph analytics is the field of analytics
where the underlying data is structured or can be modeled as a set of graphs
our graph analytics course in the specialization will cover these and other
graph techniques and we will also cover tools and platforms for graph analytics
in summary analytic operations are used to discover meaningful
patterns in the data in order to provide insights into the problem being studied
we looked at some of the examples of analytical operations for classification
cluster analysis path analysis and connectivity analysis in this lecture
in this hands - on activity
we will be performing word count on the complete works of shakespeare
first we will copy the shakespeare text into the hadoop file system
next we will create a new jupyter notebook and
read the shakespeare text into a spark rdd
we will then perform wordcount using map and reduce
and write the results to hdfs and view the contents
let begin
in the intro to big data course we copy the shakespeare text into hdfs
let see if it still there
if not we can copy it now
click on the terminal icon at the top of the toolbar
now we can run hadoop fs - ls to see what is in our hadoop filesystem directory
there are no files in htfs so let copy it
if you already have words txt in your htfs directory you can skip this next step
cd into downloads
big - data - 3 spark - wordcount
we can do ls to see the file
let copy this file to htfs
we run hadoop fs copy from local words txt
we can write hadoop fs - ls again to verify that the file is there
now let do work count in spark
we will do this in an ipython notebook using jupyter server
look on the web browser icon the top of the toolbar
and go to the jupyter server url which is local host port 8889
next let create a new ipython notebook
the first step is to read the words txt files in htfs into a spark rdd
we will call the rdd lines
we can read it using the spark context sc in calling the text file method
the argument is the url of the word set txt file and hdfs
let run this we can
view the contents of this rdd by calling lines take 5
the argument 5 says how many lines to show of the rdd
next we will transform this rdd of lines into an rdd of words
we will say words = lines flatmap
lambda line :
line split double quote space double quote
this creates a new rdd called words by running flatmap over the line rdd
the argument is this lambda expression
a lambda in python is a simple way to declare a one line expression
in this case there one argument called line and
we called it split method on this line and we split on spaces
we can run this and look at the contents of words
we can see that each element now is an individual word
next we will create tuples of these words
we will put them in a new rdd called tuples
enter tuples
= words map : lambda
word; word 1
this creates the tuples by transforming words
this uses map and another lambda function
in this case the lambda takes one argument and returns a tuple
where the first value of the tuple is the word
the second value is the number 1
not that in this case we use map whereas before we used flat map
in this case we want a tuple for every word in the words
so we have a one to one mapping between inputs and outputs
previously while we were splitting lines into word each line had multiple words
in general
you want to use map when you have a one to one mapping between inputs and outputs
in flatmap you have a one to many or none mapping between inputs and
outputs let run this and look at tuples
we can see that each word now has a tuple initialized with the count of 1
we can now count all the words by combining or reducing these tuples
we will put this in a new rdd called counts
so we will say counts equals tuples reduce by key
lambda a b :
a + b
in this case the lambda function takes two arguments a and be and
will return the result of adding a and b
to view the result
you can see now that the counts for each words have been created
we can write this result back to hdfs
let say counts coalesce 1 saveastextfile
and then the url
the coalesce means we only want a single output file
let go back to our shell and view the results
we will run hadoop fs - ls to see the directory
and run it again to look inside the wordcount directory
and once more to look inside wordcount outputdir
as you recall the output from hadoop jobs is part - 0000
this is also true for spark jobs
let copy this file to the local file system
we will run hadoop fs copytolocal
wordcount outputdir part - 00000
you can view the results with more
in this hands on activity
we will be using spark streaming to read weather data
first we open the spark streaming jupyter notebook
next we will look at sensor format and measurement types
we will then create a spark dstream of weather data read the measurements and
create a sliding window of the data
we will define a function to display the maximum and minimum values in the window
we start to stream processing to give their results
before we begin this activity we need to change the virtual box settings for
our carder virtual machine
start streaming needs more than one thread of execution
so we need to change the settings to add more than one virtual processor
first shut down your cloudera virtual machine and go to the virtual box manager
select the cloudera virtual box and click on settings
next click on system click on processor
and change the number of cpu to be two or more
when you are done click okay and start the machine as usual
let begin
first click on the browser icon at the top of the tool bar
navigate to the jupyter notebook server monitoring local host calling 8889
we will then go in to downloads
big data 3
spark - streaming
let then open spark - streaming notebook
this first line shows the example data we get from the weather station
each line has a time stamp and a set of measurements
each of these abbreviations is a particular type of measurement
followed by the actual value
the next cell shows the key for these measurements
for this hands - on we are interested in the average wind direction
which is abbreviated as dm
this next cell defines a function that parses each line of text and
pulls out the average wind speed
we define it here so we do not have to type it in later
let run this cell
next let create a streaming spark context
first we will need to import the module
we will enter from pyspark streaming import streamingcontext
we can create a new streaming context
we will put in in a variable called ssc
we will enter ssc = streamingcontext sc 1
the sc is a streamingcontext
the 1 specifies the batch interval 1 second in this case
let run this
next we will create a dstream
we will import the streaming weather data over a tcp connection
we will put this in a dstream called lines
let say lines = ssc sockettextstream
we will enter the host name in port of the weather station
rtd hpwren ucsd edu for 12028
let run this
next we will create a new d - stream called vals that would hold the measurements
we will say vals = lines flatmap parse
this calls the parse function we defined above for
each of the lines coming from the weather station
the resulting d - stream will have just the average wind direction values
we will run this
next we will create a window that will aggregate the d - stream values
we will say window = vals window 10 5
the first argument specifies that the length of the window should be 10 seconds
the second argument specifies that the window should move every 5 seconds
let run this
next we will define a function that prints the minimum and
maximum values that we see
we will start by entering the definition
def stats this will take an rdd as an argument
next let print the entire contents of the rdd
print parenthesis rdd collect
this will print the entire content of the rdd
in a real big data application
this will be impractical due to the size of the data
however for this hands on the rdd is small and so
we can use this to see the contents of the rdd
next we will print the min and max
before we do that however
we should check to make sure that the size of the rdd is greater than zero
we will check that rdd count is greater than 0
finally we will print the minid max
we will enter print max = min =
outside of the quote we will do
format rdd max rdd min
let run this next
let call this function stats
so all the rdds in our sliding window
i will enter window foreachrdd stats
run this
we are now ready to start our streaming processing
we can do this by entering ssc start
we will run this to start the streaming
when we want to stop this streaming we will run ssc stop
please scroll up and look at the beginning of the output
we will see that it printing the full window and the min and max values
notice that in the beginning the window is not yet filled
in this case there only three entries
we count to see that the window is moving by five measurements
for example the last five measurements in the second window
are the first five measurements in the third window
in this hands on activity we will be using sparksql to
query data from an sql database
first we will open the sparksql jupyter notebook
we will connect spark to a postgres table
and then view the spark dataframe schema and count the rows
we will view the contents of the data frame
see how to filter rows and columns
and finally perform aggregate operation on a column
let begin
first click on the browser icon the top of the toolbar
sound next
navigate to the jupyter notebook server
it localhost : 8889
go to downloads
big data 3 spark sql
to open the sparksql notebook
the first three cells have already been entered for you
first we import the sqlcontext run this
next we create an sqlcontext from the sparkcontext run this
and next we will create a spark dataframe from a postgres table
we used the read attribute format
the jdbc argument means that we are using a java database connection
the next line sets the url option
it says we are using postgres database running on the local host
the database name is cloudera and the username is cloudera
the second option db table
says we want our data frame to be the game clicks table
and finally we call load
let execute this
you can see the schema of the data frame by calling df printschema
this shows the name of each column along with the data type
we can count the rows in this df frame by calling df count
we can look at the first five rows by calling df show 5
this shows all the columns in the data frame
we can select specific columns by using the select method
let select just the user id and team level columns
i will enter df select userid teamlevel
parenthesis
and finally we only want to see the top five rows
so we will do show 5
we can also select rows that have a specific value
let look for the rows where the team level is greater than one
we will enter df filter
we will specify that we want team level greater than one by entering df
square bracket team level greater than one
and again we only want the user id and team level columns
and finally only the first five rows
we can use the group by method to aggregate a particular column
for example the ishit column has a value of zero or one
and we can use group by to count how many times each of these values occurs
or a df groupby ishit and we will call count to count the values
we can also perform aggregate statistical operations on the data in a data frame
let compute the mean and sum values for ishit
first we need to import the statistical functions we will
run from pyspark sql functions import star
next we will run df select mean ishit sum ishit
we can also join two data frames on a particular column
let join the existing data frame of the game clicks table with the adclicks table
first we need to create data frame for the adclicks table
let go back up
copy the content of this cell
paste it
we put the adclicks table the data frame called df2
and we will change the db table option to the adclicks
run it
let print the schema of df2
you can see that it also has a column called user id
so let join the game clicks data frame with the add
clicks data frame on this column
we put the result in a new data frame called merged
we will say merge = df join df2 userid
we will run it
let look at the schema
we will call merge printschema
we can see that this merged data frame has the column for both game clicks and
adclicks
finally we will look at the top five rows in this merged data frame
we will run merge show
we have now seen some simple transformations and
how spark can create rdds from each other using transformations
we learned that transformations are evaluated after an action is performed
so we can simply define actions as rdd operations that trigger the evaluation of
the transformation pipeline and return the final result to the driver program or
save the results to a persistent storage
we can also call them the last step in a spark pipeline
let now look at a few action operations
after this video you will be able to explain the steps of a spark pipeline
ending with a collect action and list four common action operations in spark
a very common action in spark is collect
in this example we can imagine that initially we are reading from hdfs
the rdd partitions that go through the transformation steps in our big data
pipeline are defined as flatmap and groupbykey
when the final step is done the collect action is called and
spark sends all the tasks for execution to the worker notes
collect will send all the resulting rdds from the workers and
copy them to the java virtual machine on the driver program
and then this will be piped also to our python shell
while collect copies all the data another action take
copies the first n results of the driver
if the results are too large to fit in the driver memory
then there an opportunity to write them directly to hdfs instead
among many other actions reduce is probably the most famous one
reduce takes two elements and returns a result like sum
but in this case we do not have a key we just have a large area of some values
and we are running this function over and
over again to reduce everything to one single value
for example to the global sum of everything
another very useful action is saveastext
to save the results to local disk or hdfs and
this is very useful if the output of the power computation is pretty large
hello i hope you enjoyed your first programming experience with spark
although the words count example is simple
it is useful in starting to understand how to work with rdds
after this video you will be able to use two methods to create rdds in spark
explain what immutable means interpret a spark program as a pipeline
of transformations and actions and list the steps to create a spark program
so let remember where we are
we have a driver program that defines the spark context
this is the entry point to your application
the driver converts all the data to rdds and
everything from this point on gets managed using the rdds
rdds can be constructed from files or any other storage
they can also be constructed from data structures for collections and
programs like lists
all the transformations and actions on these rdds take place either locally
or on the worker nodes managed by a cluster manager
each transformation results in a new updated version of the rdd
the rdds at the end get converted and
saved in a persistent storage like hdfs or your local drive
as we mentioned before rdds get created in the driver program
the developer of the driver program
who in this case is you is responsible for creating them
you can just read in a file through your spark context or
as we have in this example you can provide an existing collection
like a list to be turned into a distributed collection
you can also create an integer rdd using parallelize
and provide a number of partitions for
distribution as we do create the numbers rdd in this line
here the range function in python
will give us a list of numbers starting from 0 to 9
the parallelize function will create three partitions
of the rdd to be distributed based on the parameter that was provided to it
spark will decide how to assign partitions to our executors and worker nodes
the distributed rdds can in the end be gathered into a single partition on
the driver using the collect transformation
now let think of a scenario were we start processing the created rdds
there are two types of operations that help with processing in spark
namely transformations and actions
all partitions written in rdd go through the same transformation in
the worker node executors when a transformation is applied to an rdd
spark uses lazy evaluation for transformations
that means they will not be immediately executed but
instead wait for an action to be performed
the transformations get computed when an action is executed
for this reason a lot of times you will see run
time errors showing up at the action stage and not at the transformation stages
it is very similar to haskell or erlang
if any of you are familiar with these languages
let put some names on these transformations
we can have a pipeline by converting a text file into an rdd with two partitions
filter some values out of it and maybe apply a map function to it
in the end the run the collect action on the mapped rdds
to evaluate the results of the pipeline and convert the outputs into results
here filter and map are transformations and collect is the action
although the rdds are in memory and they are not persistent
we can use the cash function to make them persistent cash
for example in order to reuse the rdd created from a database query that could
otherwise be costly to re - execute we can instead cache these rdds
we need to use caution when using the cache option
as it can consume too much memory and generate a bottleneck itself
as a part of the word count example we mapped the words rdd to generate tuples
we then applied reducebykey to tuples to generate counts
in the end we convert the number of partitions to one so
that output is one file when written to this later
otherwise output will be spread over multiple files on disk
finally saveastextfile is an action that kickstarts the computation and
writes to disk
to summarize in a typical spark program
we create rdds from external storage or local collections like lists
then we apply transformations to these rdds
like filter map and reducebykey
these transformations get lazily evaluated until an action is performed
actions are performed both for local and parallel computation to generate results
next we will talk more about transformation and actions in spark
in the last video we talked about the programming model for
spark where rdd get generated from external datasets and gets partitioned
we said rdds are immutable meaning they cannot be changed in place even partially
they need a transformation operation applied to them and
get converted into a new rdd
this is essential for keeping track of all the processing that has been
applied to our dataset providing the ability to keep a linear chain of rdds
in addition as a part of a big data pipeline we start with an rdd
and through several transformation steps many other rdds as
intermediate products get executed until we get to our final result
we also mention that an important feature of spark
is that all these transformation are lazy
this means they do not execute immediately when applied to an rdd
so when we apply a transformation nothing happens right away
we are basically preparing our big data pipeline to be executed later
when we are done defining all the transformations and perform an action
spark will take care of finding the best way to execute this computation and
then start all the necessary tasks in our worker nodes
in this video we will explain some common transformation in spark
after this video you will be able to explain the difference between
a narrow transformation and wide transformation
describe map flatmap filter and coalesce as narrow
transformations and list two wide transformations
let take at look at probably the simplest transformation which is a map
by now you are well versed in home networks
it applies the function to each partition or element of an rdd
this is a one to one transformation
it is also in the category of element - wise transformations since it transforms
every element of an rdd separately
the code example in the blue box here applies a function
called lower to all the elements in a text rdd
the lower function
turns all the characters in a line to lower case letters
so the input is one line of text with any kind of
capitalization and the outfit is going to be the same line all lower case
in this example we have two worker nodes drawn as orange boxes
the black boxes are partitions of our dataset
we work by partition and not by element
as you would remember this it is the difference between spark and mapreduce
the partition is just a chunk of our data with some number of elements in it and
the map function gets applied to all elements in that partition in each
worker node locally
each node applies the map function to the data or
rdd partition they received independently
let look at a few more in element - wise transformation category
flatmap is very similar to map
however instead of returning an individual element for each map
it returns an rdd with an aggregate of all the results for all the elements
in the example in the blue box
the split words fuction takes a line as an input
which is one element and it output is each word as a single element
so it splits a line to words
the same thing gets done for each line
when the output for all the lines is flattened
we get a simple one - dimensional list of words
so we will get all the words in all the lines in just one list
depending on the line length the output partitions might be of different sizes
detected here by the height of each black box being different
in spark terms map and flatmap are narrow transformations
narrow transformation refers to the processing where the processing
logic depends only on data that is already residing in the partition and
data shuffling is not necessary
another very important transformation is filter
often we are interested just in a subset of our data or
we want to get rid of bad data
filter transformation takes the function take executes on each element
of a rdd partition and
returns only the elements that the transformation element returns true
the example code in the blue box here applies a filter
function that filters out words that start with the letter a
the function starts with a takes the input word
then transforms it to lowercase and then checks if the word starts with a
so the output of this operation will be a list with only words that start with a
this is another narrow transformation
so it only gets executed locally
without the need to shuffle any rdd partitions across the word kernels
the output of filter depends on the input and the filter functions
in some cases
even if you started with even rdd partitions within the worker nodes
the rdd size can significantly vary across the workers after a filter operation
then this happens is a pretty good idea to join some of those partitions
to increase performance and even out processing across clusters
this transformation is called coalesce
coalesce simply helps with balancing the data partition numbers and sizes
when you have significantly reduced your initial data after some filters and
other transformations
having a large number of partitions might not be very useful anymore
in this case
you can use coalesce to reduce the number of partitions to a more manageable number
until now we talked about narrow transformations that happen in a worker
node locally without having to transfer data through the network
now let start talking about wide transformations
let remember our word count example
as a part of the word count example we map the words rdd could generate tuples
the output of map is a key value pair list where the key is the word and
the value is always one
we then apply it reducebykey to tuples to generate counts
which simply sums the values for each key or word
let imagine for a second that we use groupbykey instead of reducebykey
we will come back to reducebykey in just a little bit
remember mapped outputs tuples
which is a list of key value pairs in the forms of word one
at each worker node we will have tuples that have the same word as key
in this example apple as the key and 1 as the count and 2 worker nodes
trying to group together all the counts of a word across worker nodes
requires shuffling of data between these nodes
just like we do for the word apple here
groupbykey is the transformation that helps us combine values with
the same key into a list without applying a special user define function to it
as you see on the right the result of a groupbykey transformation on all
the map outputs by the word apple is the key ends up in a list with all ones
if you instead apply the function to list like summing up all the values
then we could have had the word count results
in this case 2
if we instead applied a function to the list like summing up all the values
then we would have had the word count results
if we need to apply such functions to a group of values related to a key like
this we use the reducebykey operation
reducebykey helps us to combine the value using a reduce function
which in the word count case is a simple summation
in groupbykey and reducebykey transformations
we observe the behavior that require shuffling of the data across work nodes
we call such transformations wide transformations
in wide transformation operations processing depends on data
residing in multiple partitions distributed across worker nodes and this
requires data shuffling over the network to bring related datasets together
as a summary we have listed a small number of transformations in spark with
some examples and distinguished between them as narrow and wide transformations
although this is a good start i advise you to go through the list
provided at the link shown here after you complete this beginner course
read about the rest of the transformations in spark before you start programming in
spark and have fun with transformations
lastly we will introduce you to spark graphx
after this video you will be able to describe graphx is
explain how vertices and edges are stored in graphx and
describe how pregel works at a high level
graphx is apache spark application programming interface for
graphs and graph - parallel computation
graphx uses a property graph model
this means both nodes
and edges in a graph can have attributes and values
in graphx the node properties are stored in a vertex table and
edge properties are stored in an edge table
the connectivity information that is which edge connects which nodes
is stored separately from the node and edge properties
graphx is built on special rdds for vertices and edges
vertexrdd represents a set of vertices
all of which have an attribute called a
the edgerdd here extends this basic edge storing by
the edges in columnar format on each partition for performance
note that vertexid are defined to be unique by design
the edge class is an object with a source vertex and
destination vertex and an edge attribute
in addition to the vortex and edge views of the property graph
graphx also has triplet view
the triplet view logically joins vortex and edge properties
graphx has an operator that can execute operations
from the pregel library for graph analytics
this pregel operator executes in a series of super steps
which defines a messaging protocol for vertices
we will revisit graph analytics and
using graphx in more detail in course five of the specialization
in summary spark can be used for graph parallel computations
graphx uses special rdds for storing vertex and edge information
and the pregel operator works in a series of super steps
now we will introduce you to spark mllib
after this video you will be able to describe what mllib is
list the main categories of techniques available in mllib
and explain code segments containing mllib algorithms
mllib is a scalable machine learning library that runs on top of spark core
it provides distributed implementations of commonly used machine learning
algorithms and utilities
as with spark core mllib has apis for scala java python and r
mllib offers many algorithms and
techniques commonly used in a machine learning process
the main categories are machine learning
statistics and some common utility tools for common techniques
as the name suggests
many machine learning algorithms are available in mllib
these are algorithms to build models for classification regression and
clustering
there are also techniques for evaluating the resulting models
for example you can compute the values for
a receiver of creating characteristic that we call an roc curve
a common statistical technique for
plotting the performance of a binary classifier
statistical functions are also provided in mllib
examples are summary statistics means standard deviation etc
correlations and methods to sample a dataset
mllib also has techniques commonly used in the machine learning process
such as dimensionality reduction and
feature transformation methods for preprocessing the data
in short spark mllib offers
many techniques often used in a machine learning pipeline
let take a look at an example to compute summary statistics using mllib
note that we will use the spark pipe of api similar to the ones used for
our other examples in this course
here is the code segment to compute summary statistics for
a data set consisting of columns of numbers
lines of code are in white and the comments are in orange
the first line imports statistics functions from the stat module
the second line creates an rdd of vectors with the data
you can think of each vector as a column in a data matrix
the next line denoted with three invokes
the column stats function to compute summary statistics for each column
the last three lines show by four print out the mean
variance and number of non - zero entries for each column
as you can see from this example computing the summary statistics for
a data set is very straightforward using a mllib
here is another example
although we will go through the ratio learning details in our next course
here we give you a hint of how to use two ratio learning techniques
one for classification and one for clustering
this code segment shows the six steps to build a decisiontree for classification
the first line imports the decisiontree module
the second line imports mlutils module
the next line fails the decisiontree to classify the data for two classes
then the model is printed out and finally the model is saved in a file
here is another mllib example this time for clustering
this code segment shows the 5 - step code to build a k - means clustering
the first line imports the k - means module the second line
imports an array module from numpy
the next two lines read in the data and parses it using space as the limiter
then the k - means model
is built by dividing the parseddata into three clusters
finally the cluster centers are printed out for each
in summary mllib is spark machine learning library
it provides algorithms and
techniques that are implemented using distributors processing
the main categories of algorithms and
techniques available in machine learning library are machine learning
statistics and utility functions for the machine learning process
over the next couple of videos
we will introduce you to the basic components of the spark stack
in this lecture we start with spark sql
after this video you will be able to process structured data using spark sql
module and explain the numerous benefits of spark sql
spark sql is the component of spark that enables querying structured and
unstructured data through a common query language
it can connect to many data sources and provides apis to convert
the query results to rdds in python scala and java programs
spark sql gives a mechanism for
sql users to deploy sql queries on spark
spark sql enables business intelligence tools to connect to
spark using standard connection protocols like jdbc and odbc
spark sql also provides apis to convert the query data into dataframes
to hold distributed data
dataframes are organized as named columns and basically look like tables
the first step to run any sql spark is to create a sqlcontext
once you have an sqlcontext you want to leverage it
to create a dataframe so you can deploy complex operations on the data set
dataframes can be created from existing rdds
hive tables or many other data sources
a file can be read and converted into a dataframe using a single command
the show function here will display the dataframe in your spark show
rdds can be converted to dataframes but require a little more work
first you will have to convert each line into a row
once your data is in a dataframe you can perform all sorts of
transformation operations on it as shown here including show
printschema select filter and groupby
to summarize spark sql lets you run relational queries on spark
it also lets you connect to a variety of databases and
deploy business intelligence tools over spark
we will go through some of this functionality in one of the readings and
in the upcoming hands - on session
next we will talk about spark streaming
after this video you will be able to summarize how spark reads streaming data
list several sources of streaming data supported by spark and
describe spark sliding windows
spark streaming provides scalable processing for
real - time data and runs on top of spark core
continuous data streams are converted or
grouped into discrete rdds which can then be processed in parallel
spark streaming provides apis for scala
java and python like other spark products
spark streaming can read data from many different
types of resources including kafka and flume
kafka is a high throughput published subscribed messaging system
and flume collects and aggregates log data
spark streaming can also read from batch
input data sources such as hdfs
s3 and many other non sql databases
additionally spark streaming can read directly from twitter raw tcp sockets
and many other data sources that are real - time data providers
so how does it all work
here we show you a flow of transformations and actions
which you will try in the upcoming reading and hands - on exercises on spark streaming
spark streaming reads
streaming data and converts it into micro batches
which we call dstreams which is short for discretized stream
in this example a 10 second stream gets converted
into five rdds using a batch length of 2 seconds
similar to other rdds transformations such as map reduce
and filter can be applied to dstreams
dstreams can be aggregated
into windows allowing you to apply computations on sliding window of data
in this example the window size is 4 seconds and
the sliding interval is 2 seconds
in summary spark streaming is spark library to work with
streaming data in near real time
dstreams can be used just like any other rdd and
can go through the same transformation as batch datasets
dstreams can create a sliding window to perform calculations on a window of time
now that we know what machine learning is and have seen some examples of it
let talk about how we do machine learning
in this lecture we will get an overview of the main categories of machine learning
techniques
after this video you will be able to
describe the main categories of machine learning techniques and
summarize how supervised learning differs from unsupervised learning
there are different categories of machine learning techniques for
different types of problems
the main categories are listed here
they are classification regression cluster analysis and
association analysis
we will cover each one in detail in the following slides
in classification the goal is to predict the category of the input data
an example of this is predicting the weather as being sunny rainy windy or
cloudy
the input data in this case would be sensor data specifying the temperature
relative humidity atmospheric pressure wind speed wind direction etc
the target or what you are trying to predict would be the different weather
categories sunny windy rainy and cloudy
another example is to classify a tumor as either benign or malignant
in this case the classification is referred to as
binary classification since there are only two categories
but you can have many categories as well
as the weather prediction problem shown here
another example is to identify hand written digits as being in one of ten
categories zero to nine
some more examples of classification are classifying a tumor from a medical
image as being benign or malignant
predicting whether it will rain the next day
determining if a loan application is high - risk medium - risk or low - risk
identifying the sentiment of a tweet or
review as being positive negative or neutral
when your model has to predict a numeric value instead of a category
then the task becomes a regression problem
an example of regression is to predict the price of a stock
the stock price is a numeric value not a category
so this is a regression task instead of a classification task
if you were to predict whether the stock price will rise or
fall then that would be a classification problem
but if you are predicting the actual price of the stock
then that is a regression problem
that is the main difference between classification and regression
in classification you are predicting a category and
in regression you are predicting a numeric value
some other examples of regression are estimating the demand of a product
based on time or season of the year
predicting a score on a test
determining the likelihood of how effective a drug will be for
a particular patient predicting the amount of rain for a region
in cluster analysis
the goal is to organize similar items in your data set into groups
a very common application of cluster analysis is referred to as
customer segmentation
this means that you are separating your customer base into different groups or
segments based on customer types
for example it would be very beneficial to segment your customers into seniors
adults and teenagers
these groups have different likes and dislikes and
have different purchasing behaviors
by segmenting your customers to different groups you can more effectively provide
marketing adds targeted for each groups particular interests
note that cluster analysis is also referred to as clustering
some other examples of cluster analysis are identifying areas of
similar topography such as desert region grassy areas mountains etc
categorizing different types of tissues from medical images
determining different groups of weather patterns such as snowy dry monsoon
and discovering hot spots for different types of crime from police reports
the goal in association analysis is to come up with a set of rules to
capture associations between items or events
the rules are used to determine when items or events occur together
a common application of association analysis is known as market
basket analysis
which is used to understand customer purchasing behavior
for example association analysis can reveal that banking customers who have
cds or certificates of deposits also tend to be interested in
other investment vehicles such as money market accounts
this information can be used for cross selling
if you advertise money market accounts to your customers with cds they are likely to
open such an account
according to data mining folklore a supermarket chain used association
analysis to discover a connection between two seemingly unrelated products
they discovered that many customers who go to the store
late on sunday night to buy diapers also tend to buy beer
this information was then used to place beer and
diapers close together and they saw a jump in sales of both items
this is the famous diaper beer connection
some other applications of association analysis are recommending similar
items based on the purchasing behavior or browsing histories of customers
finding items that are often purchased together such as garden hose and
potting soil and
offer sales on these related items at the same time to drive sales of both items
identifying web pages that are often accessed together so
that you can more efficiently offer up these related web pages at the same time
we have now looked at the different categories of machine learning techniques
they are classification regression cluster analysis and
association analysis
we have also seen some examples of each category
there is also another categorization of machine learning techniques and
that is supervised versus unsupervised approaches
in supervised approaches the target
which is what the model is predicting is provided
this is referred to as having labeled data because the target is labeled for
every sample that you have in your data set
referring back to our example of predicting a weather category of sunny
windy rainy or cloudy
every sample in the data set is labeled as being one of these four categories
so the data is labeled and predicting the weather categories is a supervised task
in general classification and regression are supervised approaches
in unsupervised approaches on the other hand
the target that the model is predicting is unknown or unavailable
this means that you have unlabeled data
going back to our cluster analysis example of segmenting customers into
different groups
the samples in your data are not labeled with the correct group
instead the segmentation is performed using a clustering technique to group
items based on characteristics that they have in common
thus the data is unlabeled and
the task of grouping customers into different segments is an unsupervised one
in general cluster analysis and
association analysis are unsupervised approaches
in summary
in this lecture we looked at the different categories of machine learning techniques
we discussed classification regression cluster analysis and association analysis
we also defined what supervised and
unsupervised approaches are in machine learning
in this lecture we will review each of the steps in
the machine learning process in greater detail
after this video you will be able to explain the goals of each step in
the machine learning process and list key activities in each step in the process
this is the machine learning process that we saw in the last lecture
in this lecture we will cover each step in more detail
we will describe the goals of each step and
the key activities performed in each step
the first step in the data science process is to acquire the data
the goal of the step is to identify and
obtain all data related to the problem at hand
first we need to identify all related data and the sources
keep in mind that data can come from different sources such as files
databases the internet mobile devices
so remember to include all data related to the problem you are addressing
after you have identified your data and data sources
the next step is to collect the data and integrate data from the different sources
this may require conversion as data can come in different formats
and it may also require aligning the data
as data from different sources may have different time or spacial resolutions
once you ve collected and integrated your data you now have a coherent data set for
your analysis
the next step after acquiring data is to prepare it to make it suitable for
analysis
there are two parts to this step explore data and preprocess data
we will discuss data exploration first
in data exploration you want to do some preliminary investigation
in order to gain a better understanding of the specific characteristics of your data
this in turn will guide the rest of the process
with data exploration you will want to look for
things like correlations general trends outliers etc
correlations provide information about the relationship
between variables in your data
trends in your data will reveal if the variable is moving in a certain direction
such as transaction volume increasing throughout the year
outliers indicate potential problems with the data or
may indicate an interesting data point that needs further examination
without this data exploration activity
you will not be able to use your data effectively
one way to explore your data is to calculate summary statistics
to numerically describe the data
summary statistics are quantities that capture various characteristics
of a set of values with a single number or a small set of numbers
some basic summary statistics that you should compute for your data set are mean
median mode range and standard deviation
mean and median are measures of the location of a set of values
mode is the value that occurs most frequently in your data set and
range and standard deviation are measures of spread in your data
looking at these measures will give you an idea of the nature of your data
they can tell you if there something wrong with your data
for example if the range of the values for age in your data
includes negative numbers or a number much greater than a hundred
there something suspicious in the data that needs to be examined
visualization techniques also provide quick and
effective ways to explore your data
some examples are a histogram
such as the plot shown here shows the distribution of the data and
can show skewness or unusual dispersion in outliers
a line plot like the one in the lower left can be used to look at trends in
the data such as the change in the price of a stock
a heat map can give you an idea of where the hot spots are
a scatter plot effectively shows correlation between two variables
overall there are many types of plots to visualize data
they are very useful in helping you understand the data you have
the second part of the prepare step is preprocess
so after we have explored the data we need to preprocess the data to prepare it for
analysis
the goal here is to create the data that will be used for analysis
the main activities on this part are to clean the data
select the appropriate variables to use and transform the data as needed
a very important part of data preparation is to
clean the data to address quality issues
real world data is nothing
there are many examples of quality issues with data from real applications including
missing values such as income in a survey duplicate data
such as two different records for the same customer with different addresses
inconsistent or invalid data such as a six digit zip code
noise in the collection of data that distorts the true values
outliers such as a number much larger than 100 for someone age
it is essential to detect and
address these issues that can negatively affect the quality of the data
other activities in data preprocessing can be broadly categorized as
feature selection and feature transformation
feature selection refers to choosing the set of features to
use that is appropriate for the application
feature selection can involve removing redundant or
irrelevant features combining features or creating new features
during the exploring data step
you may have discovered that two features are very correlated
in that case one of these features can be removed
without negatively effecting the analysis results
for example the purchase price of a product and
the amount of sales tax pain are very likely to be correlated
eliminating the sales tax amount then will be beneficial
removing redundant or irrelevant features will make the subsequent analysis simpler
you may also want to combine features or create new ones
for example adding the applicants education level
as a feature to a loan approval application would make sense
there are also algorithms to automatically determine the most relevant
features based on various mathematical properties
feature transformation maps the data from one format to another
various transformation operations exist
for example scaling maps the data values to a specified
range to prevent any one feature from dominating the analysis results
filtering or aggregation can be used to reduce noise and variability in the data
dimensionality reduction maps the data to a smaller subset of dimensions
to simplify the subsequent analysis
we will discuss techniques to prepare data in more detail later in this course
after preparing the data to address data quality issues and
preprocess it to get it in the appropriate format
the next step in the machine learning process is to analyze the data
the goals of the staff are to build a machine learning model
to analyze the data and to evaluate the results that you get from the model
the analyze steps starts with this determining the type of problem you have
you begin by selecting appropriate machine learning techniques to analyze the data
then you construct the model using the data that you have prepared
once the model is built you will want to apply it to new data samples
to evaluate how well the model performs
thus data analysis involves selecting the appropriate technique for
your problem building the model then evaluating the results
as there are a different types of problems
there are also different types of analysis techniques
we will cover algorithms for
building machine learning models in a much more detail in week three of this course
the next step in the machine learning process is reporting results from your
analysis
in reporting your results it is important to communicate your insights and
make a case for what actions should follow
in reporting your results
you will want to think about what to present as well as how to present
in deciding what to present you should consider what the main results are
what insights were gained from your analysis and
what added value do these insights bring to the application
keep in mind that even negative results are valuable lessons learned and
suggest further avenues for additional analysis
remember that all findings must be presented so
that informs decisions can be made for next steps
in deciding how to present
remember that visualization is an important tool in presenting your results
plots and summary statistics discussing the explore step
can be used effectively here as well
you should also have tables with details from your analysis as backup
if someone wants to take a deeper dive into the results
in summary you want to report your findings by presenting your results and
the value added with graphs using visualization tools
the final step in the machine loading process
is to determine what action should be taken based on the insights gained
what action should be taken based on the results of your analysis
should you market certain products to a specific customer segment to
increase sales
what inefficiency is can be removed from your process
what incentives would be effective in attracting new customers
once a specific action has been determined
the next step is to implement the action
things to consider here include how can the action be added to your application
how will end users be affected
assessing the impact of the implemented action is then necessary to evaluate
the benefits gained
the results of this assessment determine next steps
which could suggest additional analysis or further opportunities
which would begin another cycle of the machine learning process
in summary we have looked at the steps in the machine learning process in detail
the goals or main activities of each step were discussed in this lecture
remember that this is an iterative process
in which each step can be repeated more than once and findings from
each step may require a previous step to be repeated with new information
hello everyone you have probably heard of machine
learning before enough to grab your attention and bring you to this class
however you might be wondering what machine learning is
we will talk about that in this lecture and
discuss how we can see machine learning in action in our day - to - day life
after this video you will be able to explain what machine learning is
and list three applications of machine learning encountered in everyday life
since this course is about machine learning lets define what that means
we hear this term a lot these days used in many contexts
so it good to start out with a solid definition of what machine learning means
machine learning is the field of study that focuses on computer systems that can
learn from data
that is the system often called models can learn to perform a specific
task by analyzing lots of examples for a particular problem
for example a machine learning model can learn to recognize
an image of a cat by being shown lots and lots of images of cats
this notion of learning from data means that a machine learning
model can learn a specific task without being explicitly programmed
in other words the machine learning model is not given the step
by step instructions on how to recognize the image of a cat
instead the model learns what features are important
in determining whether it picture contains a cat from the data that has analyzed
because the model learns to perform this task from data
it good to know that the amount and quality of data available for
building the model are important factors in how well the model learns the task
because machine learning models can learn from data
that can be used to discover hidden patterns and trends in the data
these patterns and trends lead to valuable insights into the data
thus the use of machine learning allows for data driven decisions to be made for
a particular problem
so to summarize the field of machine learning focuses on the study and
construction of computer systems that can learn from data
without being explicitly programmed
machine learning algorithms and
techniques are used to build models to discover hidden patterns and
trends in the data allowing for data - driven decisions to be made
you may have heard that machine learning is an inter - disciplinary field
this is very true
machine learning combines concepts and methods from many disciplines including
math statistics computer science artificial intelligence and optimization
in applying machine learning to a problem
domain knowledge is essential to the success of end results
by domain knowledge we mean an understanding of the application or
business domain
knowledge about the application the data related to the application and
how the outcomes will be used are crucial to driving the process of building
the machine learning model
so domain knowledge is also an integral part of a machine learning solution
machine learning has been used in many different learning application many of
which you will probably encounter in your daily life perhaps without realizing it
one application of machine learning that you likely used this past weekend or
even just today is credit card fraud detection
every time you use your credit card the current purchase is analyzed
against your history of credit card transactions to determine if the current
purchase is a legitimate transaction or a potentially fraudulent one
if the purchase is very different from your past purchases such as for
a big ticket item in a category that you had never shown an interest in or
when the point of sales location is from another country
then it will be flagged as a suspicious activity
in that case the transaction may be denied
or you may get a call from your credit card company to confirm that
the purchase was indeed made by you
this is a very common use of machine learning that is encountered in
everyday life
another example application of machine learning encountered in daily life is
handwritten digit recognition
when you deposit a hand - written check into an atm a machine learning process is used
to read the numbers written on the check to determine the amount of the deposit
handwritten digits are trickier to decipher than typed digits
due to the many variations in people handwriting
a machine learning system can sift through the different variations to find similar
patterns to distinguish a one from a nine for example
recommendations in what sites is another example application of
machine learning that most people have experienced first hand
after you buy an item on a website you will often get a list of related items
often this will be displayed as customers who bought this
item also bought these items or you may also like
these related items have been associated with the item you purchased by
a machine learning model and
are now being shown to you since you may also be interested in them
this is a common application of machine learning used often in
sales and marketing
here are some other examples of where machine learning has been used
like targeted ads on mobile devices
sentiment analysis of social media data
climate monitoring to detect seasonal patterns crime pattern detection and
a healthiness analysis of drugs among many other applications
as you can see from this short list
machine learning has been used in various applications including science
medicine retail law enforcement education and many others
let take a few minutes to discuss the different terms which refer to this field
the term we are using for this course is machine learning but you may have heard
other terms such as data mining predictive analytics and data slangs
so what is the difference between these different terms
as we have discussed machine learning has its roots since statistics
artificial intelligence and computer science among other fields
machine learning encompasses the algorithms and
techniques used to learn from data
the term data mining became popular around the time that the use
databases became common place
so data mining was used to refer to activities related to finding patterns in
databases and data warehouses
there are some practical data management aspects to data mining related to
accessing data from databases
but the process of finding patterns in data is similar and
can use the same algorithms and techniques as machine learning
predictive analytics refers to analyzing data in order to predict future outcomes
this term is usually used in the business context to describe activities such as
sales forecasting or predicting the purchasing behavior of a customer
but again the techniques used to make these predictions are the same techniques
from machine learning
data science is a new term that is used to describe processing and
analyzing data to extract meaning
again machine learning techniques can also be used here
because the term data science became popular at the same time that big
data began appearing data science usually refers to extracting meaning from big data
and so includes approaches for collecting storing and managing big data
these terms evolved at different times and
may have encompassed different sets of activities
but there have always been more similarities than differences between
them
now they are often used interchangeably and
have come to mean essentially the same thing
the process of extracting valuable insight from data the core algorithms and
techniques for doing this do not change with different terms
to summarize in this lecture we have discussed what machine learning is and
how it is being used
machine learning models learn from data to perform a task without being explicitly
programmed
they are used to discover patterns and trends in the data
and a lab for data driven decisions to be made for the problems being studied
we also discuss in this lecture examples of how machine learning is being used
we see how the example applications that machine learning can be applied
to many different areas
what are the steps in the machine learning process
we will discuss those in this lecture
after this video you will be able to identify the steps in the machine
learning process and discuss why the machine learning process is iterative
this diagram illustrates the steps in the machine learning process
in this lecture we will cover an overview of these steps
in the next lecture we will cover each step in more detail
it should be kept in mind that all of these steps need to be carried out with
a clear purpose in mind
that is the problem or opportunity that is being addressed must be defined with
clearly stated goals and objectives
for example
the purpose of a project may be to study customer purchasing behavior to come up
with a more effective marketing strategy in order to increase sales revenue
the purpose behind the project will drive the machine learning process
the first step in the machine learning process is to get
all available data related to the problem at hand
here we need to identify all data sources collect the data and
finally integrate data from these multiple sources
the next step in the machine learning process is to prepare the data
this step is further divided into two parts explore data and pre - process data
the first part of data preparation involves preliminary exploration
of the data to understand the nature of the data that we have to work with
things we want to understand about the data are its characteristics format
and quality
a good understanding of the data leads to a more informed analysis and
a more successful outcome
once we know more about the data through exploratory analysis
the next part is pre - processing of the data for analysis
this includes cleaning data selecting the variables to use and
transforming data to make the data more suitable for analysis in the next step
the prepared data then would be passed on to the analysis step
this step involves selecting the analytical techniques to use
building a model using the data and assessing the results
step four in the machine learning process it to communicate results
this includes evaluating the results with respect to the goal set for the project
presenting the results in a easy to understand way and
communicating the results to others
the last step is to apply the results
this brings us back to the purpose of the project
how can the insights from our analysis be used to provide effective marketing
to increase sales revenue
determining actions from insights gained
from analysis is the main focus of the act step
note that the machine learning process is a very iterative one
findings from one step may require a previous step to be repeated
with new information
for example during the prepare step we may find some data quality issues that may
require us to go back to the acquire step to address some issues with data
collection or to get additional data that we did not include in the first go around
each step may also require several iterations
for example it is common to try different analysis techniques in the analyze step
in order to get reasonable results from the model
so it is important to recognize that this is a highly iterative process and
not a linear one
now that maya has explained the basics of machine learning
let remember how big data influences analytical applications
and how we can take advantage of the existing big data tools and
techniques in machine learning
how can machine learning algorithms be scaled up
to process large volumes of data
let talk about that now
after this video you will be able to
explain how machine learning techniques can scale up to big data
and discuss the role of distributed computing platforms like hadoop and
spark in applying machine learning to big data
with the massive amounts of data that need to be processed for
applications such as drug effectiveness analysis
climate monitoring and website recommendations to name a few
we need to be able to add scalability to machine learning techniques
how do we apply machine learning at scale
one way is to scale up by adding more memory processors
and storage to our system so that it can store and process more data
this is not the big data approach
specialized hardware such as graphical processing units or
gpus for short can also be added to speed up the miracle
operations common in machine learning algorithms
although this is a good approach this is also not the big data approach
as we learned in our introductory course one problem with this approach
is that larger specialized hardware can be very costly
another problem is that we eventually will hit a limit
there only so much hardware you can add to a machine
an alternative approach is to scale out
this means using many local commodity distribution systems together
data is distributed over these systems to gain processing speed up
as shown in this illustration the idea is to divide the data into smaller subsets
the same processing is applied to each subset or map and the results
are merged at the end to come up with the overall results for the original dataset
let consider an example where we want to apply the same operation
to all the samples in a dataset of n samples
in this case n is four
if it takes t time units to perform this
operation on each sample then with sequential processing
the time to apply that operation to all samples is n times t
if we have a cluster of four processors
we can distribute the data across the four processors
each process performs the operation on the dataset subset of n over four samples
processing of the four subsets of the data is done in parallel
that is the subsets are processed at the same time
the processing time for the distributed approach is approximately n over 4 times t
plus any overhead required to merge the subset results and maybe shuffle them
this is a speedup of nearly four times over the sequential approach
on a distributed computing platform such as spark or hadoop
scalable machine learning algorithms use the same scale out approach
data is distributed across different processors
which operate on the data subsets in parallel using map reduce and
other distributed parallel transformations
this allows for
machine learning techniques to be applied to large volumes of data
in this course we will use spark and its scalable machine learning library
mlf to show you how machine learning can be applied to big data
and do not forget
this is the processing of the machine learning on where the data resides
and we call this the big data approach
however you can also imagine a scenario where you also
update the machine learning algorithms to scale up
so you can paralyze the machine learning algorithms themselves
and also use processing of big data together with this approach
in this video we will provide you with a quick summary of the main points
from our first three courses to recall what you have learned
if you have just completed our third course and do not need a refresher
you might skip to the next lecture
we started our first course explaining how a new torrent of big data
combined with cloud computing capabilities to process data anytime and
anywhere has been at the core of the launch of the big data era
such capabilities enable or present opportunities for
many dynamic data - driven applications including energy management
smart cities precision medicine and smart manufacturing
these applications are increasingly more data - driven dynamic and
heterogeneous in terms of their technology needs
they are also more process - driven and
need to be tackled using a collaborative approach by a team that
puts value on accountability and reproducibility of the results
overall by modeling managing integrating diverse
data streams we add value to our big data and
improve our business even more before we start analyzing it
a part of modeling and
managing big data is focusing on the dimensions of the scalability and
considering the challenges associated with these dimensions to pick the right tools
we also talked about characteristics of big data referring to some vs
like volume variety velocity veracity and valence
each week presents a challenging dimension of big data
namely size complexity speed quality and connectedness
we also added a sixth v
value referring to the real reason we are interested in big data
to turn it into an advantage in the context of a problem using data science
techniques big data needs to be analyzed
we explained a five steps process for data science that includes data acquisition
modeling management integration and analysis
the influence of big data pushes for
alternative scalability approaches at each step of the process
if we just focus on the scalability challenges related to the three vs
we can say big data has varying volume and
velocity requiring dynamic and scalable batch and stream processing
big data has variety requiring management of data in many different data systems
and integration of it at scale
in our introduction to the big data course
we talked about the version of a layer diagram for the tools in the hadoop
ecosystem organized vertically based on the interface
low level interfaces for storage and scheduling on the bottom
and high level languages and interactivity at the top
most of the tools in the hadoop ecosystem were initially built to compliment
the capabilities of hadoop for distributed file system management using hdfs
data processing using the mapreduce engine and
resource scheduling and negotiation using the yarn engine
over time a number of new projects were built
either to add to these complementary tools or to handle additional types of
big data management and processing not available in hadoop just like spark
arguably the most important change to hadoop over time
was the separation of yarn from the mapreduce programming model
to solely handle resource management concerns
this allowed for hadoop to be extensible to different programming models and enable
the development of a number of processing engines for batch and stream processing
another way to look at the vast number of tools that have been added to the hadoop
ecosystem is from the point of view of their functionality
in the big data processing pipeline
simply put these are associated with three distinct layers for
data management and storage for data processing and
for resource coordination and workflow management
in our second course we talked in detail about the bottom layer in this diagram
namely data management and storage
while this layer includes hadoop hdfs there are a number of other systems
that rely on hdfs as a file system or implement their own no - sql storage option
as big data can have a variety of structured semi - structured and
unstructured formats and gets analyzed through a variety of tools
many tools were introduced to fit this variety of needs
we call these big data management systems
we reviewed redis and aerospike as
key value stores where each data item is identified with a unique key
we also got some practical experience with lucene and
gephi as vector and graph - stores respectively
we also talked about vertica as a column - store database where
information is stored in columns rather than rows
cassandra and hbase are also in this category
finally we introduced solr and asterisk db for managing unstructured and
semi - structured text and mongodb as a document store
the processing layer is where all these different types
of data get retrieved integrated and analyzed
which was the primary focus of our third course
in the integration and processing layer
we roughly refer to the tools that are built on top of htfs and yarn
although some of them were with other storage and file systems
yarn is a significant enable of many of these tools making a number of batch and
stream processing engines like storm spark flink and beam possible
this layer also includes tools like hive and spark sql for
bringing a query interface on top of the storage layer pig for
scripting simple big data pipelines using the mapreduce framework and
a number of specialized analytical libraries
formation learning and graph analytics
giraph and graphx of spark are examples of such libraries for graph processing
mahout on top of the hadoop stack and
mllib of spark are two options for machine learning
although we had a basic overview of graph processing and
machine learning for big data analytics earlier in our second and
third courses we have not gone into the details there
in this course we will use spark mllib as one of our two main tools
providing a deeper introduction to the machine learning library of spark
the third and top layer in our diagram is the coordination and management layer
this is where integrations scheduling coordination and
monitoring of applications across many tools in the bottom two layers take place
this layer is also where the results of the big data analysis get communicated
to other programs websites visualization tools and business intelligence tools
workflow management systems help to develop automated solutions that
can manage and coordinate the process of combining data management and
analytical tasks in a big data pipeline as a configurable structured set of steps
workflow driven thinking also matches
this basic process of data science that we overviewed before
oozie is an example workflow scheduler that can interact with
many of the tools in the integration and processing layer
zookeeper is the resource coordination tool which monitors and
manages and coordinates all these tools and named after animal
now that we have reviewed all three layers we are ready to come back to
the integration and processing layer but now in the context of machine learning
in which we will use machine learning techniques to
apply to our five step data science process and analyze big data
just a simple google search for big data processing pipelines will bring
a vast number of pipelines with a large number of technologies
that support scalable data cleaning preparation and analysis
how do we make sense of all of it to make sure we use the right tools for
our application
how do we pick the right pre - processing and
machine learning techniques to start doing predictive modeling
over the next few weeks dr mei will walk you through some of the most
fundamental machine learning techniques along with introductory hands
on exercises we designed for you to ease you into the world of machine learning
let get started
let go through an overview of the tools we will be using in this course
after this video you will be able to describe what knime is
describe what spark mllib is and contrast knime and mllib as machine learning tools
the machine learning tools that we will be using in this course are knime and
spark mllib
these are both open source tools
this lecture will introduce these tools to you
you will need to use them for the hands on activities in this course
knime analytics is a platform for data analytics reporting and visualization
the knime platform uses a graphical user interface based approach with drag and
drop features to facilitate constructing an analytic solution
the basic components in knime are referred to as nodes
each node provides a specific functionalities
such as reading in a file
creating a specific type of machine running model and generating a plot
nodes can be connected to create machine running workflows or pipelines
knime stands for konstanz information miner
the konstanz is for the university of konstanz in germany
and note that the k in knime is silent in the pronunciation
in knime you assemble the steps that need to be performed in a machine
learning process by connecting nodes to create a workflow
to create a workflow the user chooses the appropriate nodes
from the node repository and assembles them into a workflow
the workflow can then be executed in the knime work bench
a node implements a specific operation in a workflow
in this screenshot we see two nodes
the file reader node is used to read data from a text file or
a url or a web address
the decision tree learner node builds a decision tree model
each node can have input and output ports and can be connected to other nodes
when a node is executed it takes data from its input port
performs some operations on the data and writes the results to the output port
data is transferred between nodes that are connected
a node can be configured by opening up its configuration dialog
this is where the parameters for the node can be set
the node repository is where you will find all the nodes available in your knime
installation
the nodes are organized by categories
knime provides an array of nodes to perform operations for data access
data manipulation analysis visualization and reporting
as you can see knime provides a visual approach to machine learning
it gui - based drag - and - drop approach provides an easy way to create and
execute a machine learning workflow
the open source version of knime however is limited in how large of a dataset
it can handle
there are commercial extensions to knime to manage large datasets and
offer other extra functionalities but these extensions are not open source
now let talk about spark mllib
you have worked with spark before if you took the third course in this
specialization on big data
spark is a distributed computing platform
mllib is a scalable machine learning library that runs on top of spark
it provides distributed implementations of commonly used machine learning algorithms
and utilities
the ml and mllib of course stands for machine learning
to implement machine learning operations in spark mllib you need to write code
so mllib is not a gui - based approach
this segment of code reads and parses data from a file
then builds a decision tree classification model
mllib as with the base spark core provides an application programming
interface or api for java python scala and r
this means that you can write code in these programming languages to execute
the base operations provided in spark
spark mllib runs on a distributed platform
it provides machine learning algorithms and
techniques that are implemented using distributed processing
so mllib is used for processing and analyzing large datasets
and as we have discussed writing code is required to implement operations in mllib
in summary knime is a gui - based machine learning tool while spark mllib provides
a programming - based scalable platform for processing very large datasets
you will be using both spark mllib and knime throughout this course
we have readings and hands - on exercises to help you get familiar with these popular
open source tools for machine learning
i think you will find it very informative and fun to work with these tools
welcome to course four of the big data specialization
i am ilkay altintas for the new learners i am the chief data science officer
at the san diego supercomputer center at the university of california san diego
i feel honored to teach you the basics of big data modeling
management and analysis in this specialization
and to work with dr mai nguyen on this class
and i am mai nguyen while most of you might be familiar with ilkay
i am a new face
i am excited to be here to teach you what i love doing machine learning
i received my phd in computer science with a focus on machine learning
from the university of california in san diego
since then i have worked as a data scientist
and instructor of machine learning in various venues
i am the lead for data analytics at sdfc
in this role i work on data science projects doing research
on scalability on machine learning methods to big data
we are really happy to have you in this course to develop your understanding and
skills in machine learning
and give you an introductory level experience
with application of machine learning to big data
by now you might have just finished our first three courses and
learned the basics of big data modeling management integration and processing
if you have not it not required
but for those with less background in big data management and
systems you might find it valuable
we understand that you may not even have heard anything on
machine learning yet
that why we will start by discussing what machine learning is
describing some sample applications and presenting the typical process
of a machine learning project to give you a sense of what machine learning is
then we will delve into some commonly used machine learning
techniques like classification and clustering
we are also going to show you how to explore your data prepare it for
analysis and evaluate the results you get with your machine learning model
these are all necessary steps for a successful machine learning solution
as you know for many data science applications
one has to use many different tools and methods to analyze data
in fact keeping up with the rapid development of new tools is
one of the challenges of today big data environment
in this course we will introduce you to two different types of machine learning
tools namely nime and spark mnl
nime is a graphical user interface based tool that requires no programming
and as representative of a set of tools used in visual
workflow approach to machine learning
you will have hand on practice with nime as you go through the exercises in
this course
we are also excited to show you examples of data processing
using sparks machine learning library and owlweb
our goal here is to provide you
with simple hands - on exercises that require introductory level programming
to inspire you on how big data machine learning tools can be operated
we wish you a fun time learning and
hope to hear from you in the discussion forums and learner stories as always
we have suggested time estimates each week for the course
but feel free to take the course at a faster or slower pace
and do not forget to connect to other learners through the forums to
enhance your learning experience
happy learning
in the last lecture we discussed data quality issues
we will now discuss some common techniques for addressing those quality issues
after this video you will be able to define what imputation means
illustrate three ways to handle missing values and
describe the role of domain knowledge in addressing data quality issues
as we discussed in the last lecture real world data is messy
some data quality issues that you can find in your data are missing values
duplicate data invalid data noise and outliers
you will need to clean your data if you want to perform any meaningful analysis
on that data
recall that missing data occurs when you do not have a value for
certain variables in some samples
a simple way to handle missing data is to simply drop any samples with missing
values or nas
all machine learning tools provide a mechanism or command for
filtering out rows with any missing values
the advantage of this approach is that it is very simple
the caveat is that you are removing data when you filter out examples
if the number of samples dropped is large then you end up losing a lot of your data
an alternative to dropping samples with missing data is to
impute the missing values
imputing means to replace the missing values with some reasonable values
the advantage of this approach is that you are making use of all your data
oc course imputing is more complicated than simply dropping samples
there are several ways to impute missing values
one strategy is to replace the missing values with the mean or
median value of the variable
for example a missing value for years of employment can be replaced by the mean or
median value for years of employment for all current employees
another approach is to use the most frequent value
in place of the missing value
for example the most frequently recorded age of customers
associated with the specific item can be used if that value is missing
alternatively a sensible value can be derived as a replacement for
a missing value
for example a missing value for income can be set to zero for
customers less then 18 years old or
it can be replaced with an average value based on occupation and location
note that this approach requires knowledge about the application and
the variable with missing values in order to make reasonable choices
about what valuables would be sensible to replace the missing values
in the case of duplicate data one approach is to delete the older record
another approach is to merge duplicate records
this often requires a way to determine how to resolve conflicting values
for example in the case of multiple addresses for the same customer
some logic for determining similarities between addresses might be necessary
for example st period is the same as street
to address invalid data consulting another data source may be necessary
for example an invalid zip code can be corrected
by looking up the correct zip code based on city and state
a best estimate for a reasonable value can also be used as a replacement
for example for a missing age value for an employee
a reasonable value can be estimated based on the employee length of employment
noise that distorts the data values can be addressed by
filtering out the source of the noise
for example filtering out the frequency of a constant background noise
will remove that noise component from a recording
this filtering must be done with care however
as it can also remove some components of the true data in the process
outliers can be detected through the use of summary statistics and
plots of the data
outliers can significantly skew the distribution of your data and
thus the results of your analysis
in cases where outliers are not the focus of your analysis
you will want to remove these outlier samples from your data set
for example when a thermostat malfunctions and
causes values to fluctuate wildly or to be much higher or
lower than normal these samples should be filtered out
in some applications however outliers are exactly what you are looking for
so when you detect outliers you do not want to throw them out
instead you want to examine them more closely
a classic example of this is in fraud detection where outliers represent
potential fraudulent use and those samples should be analyzed closely
in order to address data quality issues effectively
knowledge about the application is crucial
things such as how the data was collected
the user population the intended use of the application etc are important
this domain knowledge is essential to making informed decisions on how
to best impute missing values how to handle duplicate records and
invalid data and what to do about noise and outliers in your data
this activity we will be exploring weather data in spark
first we will load weather data from a csv file into a spark dataframe
next we will examine the columns and schema of the dataframe
we will then view the summary statistics and drop rows with missing values
finally we will compute the correlation between two columns
let begin
first we will create a new jupyter python notebook
you do this by clicking on new and choosing python 3
next we will import sql context
this is done by entering from
pyspark sql import sqlcontext
next we will create an instance of the sqlcontext
we will enter sqlcontext = sqlcontext sc
now let read our weather data into a dataframe
we will call the dataframe df and we will read it using the sqlcontext
we will enter sqlcontext read load
the first argument is the url of the file
that file : home cloudera downloads big - data - -
4 daily weather csv
the second argument specifies the format of how to read the file
in this case we are going to use the spark csv package from databricks to load
the csv directly into the dataframe
we need to use this because the cloudera image only has spark 1
in spark 2 and later this package is included so
we do not have to use this argument
we will enter format = and
the name of the package is com databricks spark csv
the next argument specifies that the first line in the csv file is the header
header = true
the last argument tells spark to try to infer the schema
from the csv header inferschema = true
run this
now let look at our dataframe
we can run a df columns to see the names of all the columns
we can also run df printschema to see the schema of the dataframe
next let look at the summary statistics for the data
we can do this using the describe method
we will run df describe show
this shows summary statistics for all the columns in the dataframe
there a lot of information here so lets just choose one column
let look at air pressure at 9 am
we can see the summary statistics for air pressure 9 am by running
df describe air pressure 9am show
there are five statistics in this output the count the number of rows
the mean the standard deviation and the min and max values
we can see the total number of columns in the dataframe by running len df columns
we can also see the total number of rows in the dataframe by writing df count
this says that there are 1 095 rows in the dataframe
however the summary statistics for air pressure 9am
we see the count is 1 092
summary statistics do not include rows of missing values
this means that there are three rows in the air pressure 9am column that have
missing values
we can drop these missing values
let create a new dataframe where we have dropped these missing values
we will call the new dataframe df2
to drop the missing values we will enter
df na drop subset = air pressure 9am
we can then count the total number of rows in the new dataframe df2 count
we see this value agrees with our earlier value of 1092
next let compute the correlation between two columns in the dataframe
we will compute the correlation between rain accumulation and rain duration
to do this we will enter df2 stat corr and
then the names of the two columns
rain accumulation 9am and rain duration 9am
visualizing your data is a very effective way to explore your data
we will look at different ways to visualize your data in this lecture
after this video
you will be able to discuss how plots can be useful in exploring data
describe how you would use a scatter plot and summarize what a boxplot shows
visualizing data that is looking at data graphically
is a great way to explore your data set
data visualization is a nice complement to using summary statistics for
exploring data
we will cover several ways to visualize your data in this lecture
there are several types of plots that you can use to visualize your data
we will go over histogram line plot scatter plot bar plot and box plot
these are the most commonly used plots but there are many others as well
a histogram is used to display the distribution of a variable
the range of values for the variable is divided into the number of bins and
the number of values that fall into each bin is counted
which determines the height of each bin
a histogram can reveal many things about a variable in your data for
example you can usually determine the central tendency of a variable
that is where the majority of the values lie
you can also see the most frequent value of values for that variable
a histogram also shows whether the values for that variable are skewed and
whether the skewness is to the left towards smaller values or
to the right towards larger values
you can also pick outliers in the histogram as shown on the bottom plot
a line plot shows how data values change over time
the values of a variable or variables are shown on the y axis and
the x axis shows the motion of time
the resulting line displays the data values over time
a line plot can show patterns in your variables
for example a cyclical pattern can be detected as in this plot
where the values start high then decrease and go back up again
trends can also be detected as shown in the upper - right plot
where the values fluctuate but show a general upward trend over time
it is also easy to compare how multiple variables change over time on a single
line plot as displayed in the center bottom plot
a scatter plot is a great way to visualize the relationship between two variables
one variable is on the x axis
the other variable is on the y axis each sample is
a product using the values of the 2 variables aspects and y coordinates
the resulting plot shows how one variable changes as the other is changed
a scatter plot can be used to display the correlation between 2 variables
for example 2 variables such as the high temperature of the day and
the low temperature of the day
can have a positive correlation as shown in this plot
a positive correlation means that as the value of one variable increases
the value of the other variable also increases by a similar amount
the upper right scatter plot shows a negative correlation between two
variables
this means that as the value of one variable increases
there is a corresponding decrease in the other variable two variables
can also have a non - linear correlation as shown in the lower left plot
this means that a change in one variable will not
always correspond to the same change in the other variable
this is indicated by the curve in the scatter plot as opposed to something
closer to a straight line for linear correlation
there can also be no correlation between two variables
in this case you will see something like randomly placed dots as
displayed in the lower right plot indicating no
relationship between how the two variables change with respect to each other
a bar plot is used to show the distribution of categorical variables
recall that a histogram is also used to look at the distribution of the values
of the variable
the difference is that in general a histogram is used for
numeric variables whereas a bar plot is used for categorical variables
in a bar chart the different categories of a categorical variable is shown along
the x - axis and the count of instances for each category is displayed on the y - axis
this is an effective way to compare the different categories
for example the most frequent category can be easily determined
a bar plot is also a great way to compare two categorical variables
for example this plot compares two categorical variables
one in blue and the other in orange each with three different categories
here you can see that for the first category
the blue variable has the higher count
while the orange variable has a higher count for the second and third category
this type of bar plot is called a grouped bar chart
and the different variables of products side by side
a different kind of comparison can be performed using a stacked bar chart
as seen in a lower right quad
here the accounts for the two variables are stacked on top of each other for
each category
with this bar chart you can determine that the combined count for
the first category is about equal to the combine count for the second category
while the compliant count for the third category is much larger
a box plot is another plot that shows the distribution of a numeric variable
it shows the distribution in a different format than the histogram however
this is how a box plot displays the distribution of values for
a variable the gray portion in the figure is the box part
the lower and upper boundaries of the box represent the 25th and
75th percentiles respectively
this means that the box represents the middle 50 of the data
the median is the 50th percentile meaning that 50 of
the data is greater than its value and 50 of the data is less than this value
the top and bottom lines are the whiskers and represent the 10th and
90th percentiles respectively
so 80 of the data are in the region indicated by the upper extreme and
lower extreme
any data values outside of this region are outliers and
are indicated as single point on the box plot
note that there are different variations of the box plot
with the whiskers representing different types of extreme values
box plots provide a compact way to show how variables are distributed so
they are often used to compare variables
the box plot on the left for
example compares the base salary for two different roles
this plot can quickly provide information regarding the median value the range and
the spread of the two different variables
we can quickly see that the median salary for
the marketing role is higher than the research role
we can also see that the variation or spread of the values for
marketing is greater than for research due to the larger area of the purple box
a box plot can also show you if the distribution of the data values is
symmetrical positively skewed or negatively skewed
here we see that a box plot can also be displayed on its side
a symmetric distribution is indicated if the line in the box
which specifies the median is in the center of the box
a negative skew is indicated when the median is to the right
of the center of the box
this means that there are more values that are less than the median
than there are values greater than the median
similarly a positive skew is indicated when the median is to the left
of the center of the box
to summarize data visualization provides a quick and
intuitive way to examine your data
data visualization should be used in conjunction with summary
statistics that we discussed in the last lecture to explore data
the different types of plots that we have covered in this lecture will also be very
helpful in communicating your results throughout your machine learning project
let look at how we can use summary statistics to explore data in more detail
after this video you will be able to define what a summary statistic is
list three common summary statistics and
explain how summary statistics are useful in exploring data
summary statistics are quantities that describe a set of data values
summary statistics provide a simple and quick way to summarize a dataset
we will discuss three main categories of summary statistics
measures of location or centrality measures of spread and measures of shape
measures of location are summary statistics that describe the central or
typical value in your dataset
these statistics give a sense of the middle or center of the dataset
examples of these are mean median and mode
the mean is just the average of the values in a dataset
the median is the value in the middle if you sorted the values in your dataset
in a sorted list half of the values will be less than the median and
half will be greater than the median
if the number of data values is even
then the median is the mean of the two middle values
the mode is a value that is repeated more often than any other value
in this example we have a dataset with ten values
for this dataset
the mean is 51 1 which is the number of all the values divided by 10
the median is 46 if you sort these numbers the middle numbers are 42 and 50
the average of these two numbers is 46
there are two modes for the this dataset 42 and 78
since each occurs twice more than any other value in the dataset
measures of spread describe how dispersed or varied your dataset is
common measures of spread are minimum maximum range
standard deviation and variance
minimum and maximum are of course the smallest and
largest values in your dataset respectively
the range is simply the difference between the maximum and minimum and
tells you how spread out your data is
standard deviation describes the amount of variation in your dataset
a low standard deviation value means that the samples in your dataset
tend to be close to the mean
and a high standard deviation value means that the data samples are spread out
variance is closely related to standard deviation
in fact the variance is the square of the standard deviation
so it also indicates how spread out the data samples are from the mean
for the same dataset the range is 66 which is a difference between the largest
number which is 87 and the smallest number which is 21
the variance is 548 767
you can calculate this using a calculator or a spreadsheet
and the standard deviation is 23 426 which is the square root of the variance
measures of shape describe the shape of the distribution of a set of values
common members of shape are skewness and kurtosis
skewness indicates whether the data values are asymmetrically distributed
a skewness value of around zero indicates that the data distribution
is approximately normal as shown in the middle figure in the top diagram
a negative skewness value indicates that the distribution is skewed to the left
as indicated in the left figure in the top diagram
a positive skewness value on the other hand
indicates that the data distribution is skewed to the right
kurtosis measures the tailedness of the data distribution or
how heavy or fat the tails of the distribution are
a high kurtosis value describes a distribution with longer and fatter tails
and a higher and sharper central peak indicating the presence of outliers
a low kurtosis value on the other hand
describes a distribution with shorter and lighter tails and lower and
broader central peak suggesting the lack of outliers
in our age example the skewness is about 0 3 indicating a slight positive skew
and the kurtosis is - 1 2 indicating a distribution with a low and
broad central peak and shorter and lighter tails
measures of dependence determine if any relationship exists between variables
pairwise correlation is a commonly used measure of dependence
this is a table that shows pairwise correlation for a set of variables
note that correlation applies only to numerical variables
correlations is between zero and one with zero indicating no correlation
and one indicating a one to one correlation
so a correlation of 0 89 is very strong and
this is expected since a person height and weight should be very correlated
the summary statistics we just covered are useful for numerical variables
for categorical variables we want to look at statistics that describe the number of
categories and the frequency of each category
this is done using a contingency table
here an example that shows a distribution of people pets and
their colors
we can see the most common pet is a dog and least common a fish
similarly black is the most common color and orange the least common
the contingency table also shows the distribution between the categories
for example only fish are orange while most of the brown pets are dogs
in addition to looking at the traditional summary statistics for
numerical variables and category count for categorical variables
for machine learning problems
we also want to examine some additional statistics to quickly validate the data
one of the first things to check is the number of rows and
the number of columns in your dataset
does the number of rows match the expected number of samples
does the number of columns match the expected number of variables
these should be very quick and easy checks
another easy data validation check is to look at the values in the first and
last few samples in your dataset to see if they are reasonable
for example do the temperature values looks to be in the right units of measure
do the values for rainfall look correct or
are there some values that look out of place
are the data types for your variables correct for example
is the date field captured as dates or timestamp
or is it capture as a string or numerical value
these will have consequences in how these fields should be processed
another important step is to check for missing values
you need to determine the number of samples with missing values
you also need to determine if there are any variables
with a high percentage of missing values
handling missing values is a very important step in data preparation
which we will cover in the next module
having this information will be very helpful in determining how missing values
should be handled in data preparation
we covered several types of summary statistics useful for exploring data and
machine learning
the statistics provide useful information about your dataset and should be
thoroughly examine if you want to get a better understanding of your data
now that we are familiar with some commonly use terms to describe data
let look at what data exploration is and why it important
after this video you will be able to explain why data
exploration is necessary articulate the objectives of data exploration
list the categories of techniques for exploring data
data exploration means doing some preliminary
investigation of your data set
the goal is to gain a better understanding of the data that you have to work with
if you understand the characteristics of your data you can make optimal use of it
in whatever subsequent processing and analysis you do with the data
note that data exploration is also called exploratory data analysis or
eda for short
how do you go about exploring data
there are two main categories of techniques to explore your data
one based on summary statistics and the other based on visualization methods
summary statistics provide important information that summarizes a set
of data values
there are many such statistics
many of them you have probably heard of before
such as mean median and standard deviation
these are some very commonly used summary statistics
a summary statistic provides a single quantity that summarizes some aspects of
the dataset
for example the mean is a single value that describes the average value
of the dataset no matter how large that dataset is
you can think of the mean as an indicator of where your dataset is centrally located
on a number line thus summary statistics provide a simple and
quick way to summarize a dataset
data visualization techniques allow you to look at your data graphically
there are several types of plots that you can use to visualize your data
some examples are histogram line plot and scatter plot
each type of plot serves a different purpose we will cover the use of plots to
visualize your data in an upcoming lecture
what should you look for when exploring your data
you use statistics and visual methods to summarize and
describe your dataset and some of the things you will want to look for
are correlations general trends and outliers
correlations provide information about the relation took between
variables in your data
by looking at correlations
you may be able to determine that two variables are very correlated
this means they provide the same or similar information about your data
since this contain redundant information this suggest that you may want to
remove one of the variables to make the analysis simpler
trends in your data will reveal characteristics in your data
for example you can see where the majority of the data values lie
whether your data is skilled or
not what the most frequent value or values are in a date set etc
looking at trends in your data can also reveal that a variable is moving in
a certain direction such as sales revenue increasing or decreasing over the years
calculating the minimum the maximum and
range of the data values are basic steps in exploring your data
determining outliers is a also very important
outliers indicate potential problems with the data and
may need to be eliminated in some applications
in other applications
outliers represent interesting data points that should be looked at more closely
in either case outliers usually require further examination
in summary what you get by exploring your data is a better understanding of
the complexity of the data so you can work with it more effectively
better understanding in turn will guide the rest of the process and
lead to more informed analysis
summary statistics and
visualization techniques are essential in exploring your data
this should be used together to examined a dataset
in the next two lectures
we will look at a specific methods that you can apply to explore your data
in this lesson you will learn how to prepare data for analysis
after this video you will be able to articulate the importance of data
preparation define the objectives of data preparation and
list some activities in preparing data
the raw data that you get directly from your sources is rarely in the format
that you can use to perform analysis on
the goal of data preparation is to create the data that will be used for analysis
this means cleaning the data and putting the data in the right format for analysis
the latter generally involves selecting the appropriate features to use and
transforming the data as needed
the data that you have acquired will likely have many problems
an important part of data preparation is to clean the data that you have to work
with to address what are referred to as data quality issues
there are many types of data quality issues
including missing values duplicate data
inconsistent or invalid data noise and outliers
the problems listed here can negatively affect the quality of the data and
compromise the analysis process and results
so it is very important to detect and address these data quality issues
some techniques to address data quality issues include removing data records
with missing values merging duplicate records
generating a best or at most reasonable estimate for invalid values
we will discuss these techniques in more detail in the next lecture
since the goal of the step of data preparation is cleaning the data
it is referred to as data cleaning or data cleansing
after the data has been cleaned another goal of data preparation is to
get the data into the format needed for the analysis
this step is referred to by many names data munching data wrangling and
data preprocessing
the two broad categories of data wrangling are feature selection and
feature transformation
feature selection involves deciding on which features
to use from the existing ones available in your data
features can be removed added or combined
feature transformation involves changing the format of the data
in some way to reduce noise or variability or make the data easier to analyze
two common feature transformations are scaling the data so
that all features have the same value range and reducing the dimensionality
which is effectively the number of features of the data
we will discuss these techniques later in this lesson
data preparation is a very important part of the machine learning process
it can be a tedious process but it is a crucial step
if you do not spend the time and effort to create good data for
the analysis you will not get good results
no matter how sophisticated the analysis technique you are using is
always remember garbage in garbage out
so take the time to prepare your data if you want good analysis results
a very important part of data preparation is to assess the quality of your data
we will look at some common data quality issues in this lecture
after this video you will be able to describe three data quality issues
name three reasons for poor data quality and
explain why data quality issues need to be addressed
real world data is often very messy so
it a given fact that you will need to clean your data by identifying and
addressing many issues that affect the quality of your data
let take a closer look at what these data quality issues are
a very common data quality issue is missing data
recall that a sample in your dataset typically contains several variables or
features like name age and income
for some samples some of these variables may not have a value
these are referred to as missing values in the data
missing values are also referred to as n a for not available
so you will see n a and missing values used interchangeably
you may have missing values in your data if you have an optional field in your
data set
for example the field age is often an optional field on a survey
also many people may choose not to provide a response for income
and so you will end up with missing values for the variable income in your data set
in some cases a variable may not be applicable to all cases
for example income may not be applicable to people who are retired or
unemployed or to children
so you will not have an entry for income in all of your samples
you can also have missing values due to a data collecting device that malfunctions
a network problem that affects how the data was transmitted or
something else that goes wrong during the data collection process itself or
the process of transmitting the data or storing the data
duplicate data occurs when your data set has data objects that are duplicates or
new duplicates of one another
an example of this is when there are two different records for
the same customer with different addresses
this can come about for example
if a customer address has changed but the second address was simply
added to this customer records instead of used to update the first address
duplicate data can occur when merging data from multiple sources
invalid or
inconsistent data occurs when you have an impossible value for a variable
some common examples are when you have a six digit zip code the letters ab for
state abbreviations or a negative numbers for age
these invalid data values can come about when there is a data
entry error during data collection
for example if you allow people to type in their zip code and
someone accidentally includes an extra digit to their five digit zip code
then you will end up with an invalid six digit zipcode
noise refers to anything that can distort your data
noise can be introduced during the data collection process or
data transmission process
an example is buzzing in the background when an audio message is recorded
due to background noise or a faulty microphone
another example is an overly bright image due to an incorrect light
exposure setting
an outlier is a data sample with values that are considerably different
than the rest of the other data samples in a data set
an example scenario that can create outliers is when there a sense of
failure that causes values being recorded to be much higher or lower than normal
in this case you want to remove the outliers from your data
in other applications however such as fraud detection
outliers are the important samples that should be examined more closely
so depending on the application outliers may need to be removed or
be kept for further analysis
if you simply ignore these data quality issues
any analysis that is performed will produce misleading results
in addition some implementations of analysis techniques
cannot handle some of these problems such as missing values
so problems that we have discussed in this lecture need to be
addressed before any meaningful analysis can be performed
we will discuss some techniques for
handling data quality issues in the next lecture
if you have been in a conversation on machine learning
you have probably heard terms like feature sample and variable
we will be defining some of those terms in this lecture
after this video you will be able to describe what a feature is and
how it relates to a sample
name some alternative terms for feature
summarize how a categorical feature differs from a numerical feature
before we delve into the methods for processing and
analyzing data let first start with defining some term used to describe data
starting with sample and variable
a sample is an instance or example of an entity in your data
this is typically a row in your dataset
this figure shows part of a dataset of values related to weather
each row is a sample representing weather data for particular day
the table in the figure shows four samples of weather data each for different day
in this table each sample has five values associated with it
these values are different information pieces about the sample
such as the sample id sample date
minimum temperature maximum temperature and rainfall on that day
we call these different values variables of the sample
there are many names for sample and variable
some other terms for sample that you might hear in a machine learning
context include record example row instance and observation
it is helpful to realize that all of these terms mean the same thing in
machine learning
that is they all refer to a specific example of an entity in your dataset
there are also many names for the term variable such as feature column
dimension attribute and field
all of these terms refer to specific characteristics for
each sample in your dataset
an important point to emphasize about variable is that
they are additional values with a data type
each variable has a data type associated with it
the most common data types are numeric and categorical
there are other data types as well such as string and date but
we will focus on two of the more common data types numeric and categorical
as the name implies numeric variables are variables that take on number values
numeric variables can be measured and their values can be sorted in some way
note that a numeric variable can take on just integer values or
be continuous valued
it can also have just positive numbers negative numbers or both
let go over some examples of various numeric variables
a person height is a positive continuous valued number
the score in an exam is a positive number that range between zero and a 100
the number of transactions per hour is a positive integer
whereas the change in a stock price can be either positive or negative
a variable with labels names or categories for
values instead of numbers are called categorical variables
for example a variable that describes the color of an item such as the color of
a car can have values such as red silver blue white and black
these are non - numeric values that describes some quality or
characteristic of an entity
these values can be thought of as names or labels that can be sorted into categories
therefore categorical variables are also referred to as qualitative variables or
nominal variables
some examples of categorical variables are gender marital status
type of customer for example teenager adult senior
product categories for example electronics kitchen bathroom and
color of an item
to summarize a sample is an instance or example of an entity in your data
a variable captures a specific characteristic of each entity
so a sample has many variables to describe it
data from real applications are often multidimensional
meaning that there are many dimensions or variables describing each sample
each variable has a data type associated with it
the most common data types are numeric and categorical
note that there are many terms to describe these data related concepts
the data used in machine learning processes often have many variables
this is what we call highly dimensional data
most of these dimensions may or may not matter in the context of our application
with the questions we are asking
reducing such high dimensions to a more manageable set of related and
useful variables improves the performance and accuracy of our analysis
after this video you will be able to explain what dimensionality reduction is
discuss the benefits of dimensionality reduction and
describe how pca transforms your data
the number of features or variables you have in your data set determines
the number of dimensions or dimensionality of your data
if your dataset has two features than it is two dimensional data
if it has three features than it has three features and so on
you want to use as many features as possible to capture the characteristics of
your data but
you also do not want the dimension audio of your data to be too high
as the dimensionality increases the problem spaces you are looking at increases
requiring substantially more instances to adequately sample of that space
so as the dimensionality increases
the space that you are looking at grows exponentially
as the space grows data becomes increasingly sparse
in this diagram we see how the problem space grows as
the dimensionality increases from 1 to 2 to 3
in the left plot we have a one dimensional space partitioned into four
regions each with size of 5 units
the middle plot shows a two dimensional space with 5x5 regions
the number of regions has now going from 4 to 16
in the third plot the problem space is three dimensional with 5x5x5 regions
the number of regions increased even more to 64
we see that as the number of dimensions increases the number of regions
increases exponentially and the data becomes increasingly sparse
with a small dataset relative to the problem space analysis results degrade
in addition certain calculations used in analysis become much more difficult to
define and calculate effectively
for example distances between samples are harder to compare since all samples
are far away from each other
all of these challenges represent the difficulty of dealing with high
dimensional data and as referred to as the curse of dimensionality
to avoid the curse of dimensionality
you want to reduce the dimensionality of your data
this means finding a smaller subset of features that can effectively capture
the characteristics of your data
recall from the lecture on feature selection part of data preparation is to
select the features to use
for example you can a feature that is very correlated with another feature
using feature selection techniques to select assessitive
features is one approach to dimensionality reduction
another approach to dimensionality reduction is to mathematically determine
the most important dimension to keep and ignore the rest
the idea is to find a smallest subset of dimensions that
capture the most variation in your data
this reduces the dimensions of the data while eliminating the relevant features
making the subsequent analysis simple
a technique commonly use to find the subset of most important dimensions is
called principal component analysis or pca for short
the goal of pca is to map the data from the original high dimensional space
to a lower dimensional space that captures as much of the variation in
the data as possible
in other words
pca aims to find the most useful subset of dimensions to summarize the data
this plot illustrates the idea behind pca
here we have data samples in a two dimensional space that is defined
by the x axis and the y axis
you can see that most of the variation in the data lies along the red diagonal line
this means that the dat samples are best differentiated along this dimension
because they are spread out not clumped together along this dimension
this dimension indicated by the red line is the first principle component
labelled as pc1 in the part
it captures the large amount of variance along a single dimension in data
pc1 indicated by the red line does not correspond to either axis
the next principle component is determined by looking in the direction that is
orthogonal in other words perpendicular to the first principle component which
captures the next largest amount of variance in the data
this is the second principal component pc2 and
it indicated by the green line in the plot
this process can be repeated to find as many principal components as desired
note that the principal components do not align with either the x - axis or
the y - axis
and that they are orthogonal in other words perpendicular to each other
this is what pca does
it finds the underlined dimensions the principal
components that capture as much of the variation in the data as possible
these principal components form a new coordinates system to transform
the data to instead of the conventional dimensions like x y and z
so how does pca help with dimensionality reduction
let look again in this plot with the first principle component
since the first principle component captures most of the variations in
the data the original data sample can be mapped to this dimension indicated by
the red line with minimum loss of information
in this case then we map a two - dimensional dataset to
a one - dimensional space while keeping as much information as possible
here are some main points about principal components analysis
pca finds a new coordinate system for your data
such that the first coordinate defined by the first principal
component captures the greatest variance in your data
the second coordinate defined by the second principal component captures
the second greatest variance in a data etc
the first few principle components that capture most of the variance in a data
can be used to define a lower - dimensional space for your data
pca can be a very useful technique for dimensionality reduction
especially when working with high - dimensional data
while pca is a useful technique for reducing the dimensionality of your
data which can help with the downstream analysis
it can also make the resulting analysis models more difficult to interpret
the original features in your data set have specific meanings such as income
age and occupation
by mapping the data to a new coordinate system defined by principal components
the dimensions in your transformed data no longer have natural meanings
this should be kept in mind when using pca for dimensionality reduction
in this activity we will use knime to perform data exploration of weather data
first we will create a new knime workflow
we will then input the weather data
next we will create a histogram of air temperature
create a scatter plot between two variables
create a bar chart to show the distribution of a categorical variable
and finally create a box plot to compare two different distributions
let begin
first we will create a new workflow in knime
to do this we go to the file menu
select new select new knime workflow and click on next
then we type the name of the workflow we want to create
we will call this one plots
click on finish
next we want to load weather data into knime
to do this we will use a file reader node
to add this node go to the bottom left node repository
and in the box type in file reader
drag file reader to the canvas
next double click on file reader to configure it with the weather data
click on the browse button
we will choose the weather file
that daily weather csv
we can see preview of the data at the bottom half
of the file reader configure dialog
you can see values for each column in the csv file
click ok to close the dialog
next we want to create a histogram of air temperature
we will add the histogram node to the workflow
again we go to the node repository and type in histogram
we will drag and drop histogram to the workflow and
we will connect file reader to histogram
we will click and hold on output to file reader and
drag to the input of histogram and release
before we configure the histogram node we need to run the file reader node
we can do that by selecting the file reader and
either clicking on the green arrow at the top or
right clicking and choosing execute here
once we have done that double - click on histogram
we will select error temp 9am as the biding column and
also add error temp 9am to the aggregation column
we will leave the default number of bins as ten
click on ok
now we will run the workflow
you can click on the two arrow green button at the top to run all the nodes
now let view the histogram
right click on the histogram node
and choose view histogram view
the x - axis shows the value for each bin in the histogram
and the y - axis is the count or frequency
we can see the most frequent values are between 60 and 73
on the right we also see that there some with missing values
next close the window
now let create a scatter plot to show the relationship between two variables
first we will add the scatter plot node to the work flow
we will connect the the output of file reader to the input of scatter plot
execute the workflow right - click on
scatter plot and choose view scatter plot
we will click on the column selection and choose air temp 9am for the x column
and for the y column choose relative humidity 9 am
in this plot
we can see a negative correlation between temperature and humidity
as the temperature increases the humidity goes down
we will close this window
next we will create a bar chart to show the distribution of a categorical variable
we will visualize the wind direction at 9 am
we will begin by creating the categorical variable by using the numeric binner node
let add numeric binner to the work flow
we will connect the output of file reader to the input of numeric binner
double - click on numeric binner to configure it
select max wind direction 9am and
click on add five times to add five bins
now let give a name for each of these bins
select a bin and now choose a name
the first will be for the north direction
so we will call that 1 - n
next 2 - e for east 3 - s for
south 4 - w for west and
finally 1 - n for north again
now we need to specify the values for each of these bins
we will select the first one and set the endpoint to be 45 degrees
next choose east and set that maximum to be 135
select the third one and choose the max to be 225
finally select the fourth one and select the max to be 315
next click on a pin new column
set the name for categorical variable to be categorical underscore max underscore
wind direction 9am
click ok
now add a histogram note to the work flow
connect the output of numeric binner to histogram
double - click on histogram to configure it
make sure they binning column is categorical max wind direction 9am
and also there are no aggregation columns
click ok and execute the work flow
let view the chart
right click on histogram and choose view histogram view
this tells us that most of the wind comes from the east and the south
and not many measurements from the north
next close this
now lets create a box plot to compare two different distributions
we w will examine the distribution air pressure for
low humidity days versus normal or high humidity days
to do this we will first need to creat a categorical variable for humidity
lets add another numeric binner actor to the workflow
connect the output a file reader to this actor
double click to configure
select relative humidity 9 am
and click on add twice to add two bins
select the first bin and we will call that humidity low
select the second bin and we will call that humidity not low
select the first bin and
we will set the maximum value to 25
check append new column
and set the name to low humidity day click on ok
next add the conditional box plot node to the workflow
right click on conditional box plot to configure it
make sure the nominal column is low humidity day and
the numeric column is air pressure 9am
click ok
run the workflow
right click on conditional box plot and choose few additional box plot
and the x axis we see the two values or a categorical variable humidity low and
humidity not low
the y axis shows the air pressure values
i can see that on average lower humidity means higher air pressure
close this
finally save the workflow when we are done by clicking on the disk
at the top left of the toolbar
in addition to cleaning your data to address data quality issues
data preparation also includes selecting features to use for analysis
after this video you will be able to explain what feature selection involves
discuss the goal of feature selection and list three approaches for
selecting features
feature selection refers to choosing the set of features to
use that is appropriate for the subsequent analysis
the goal of feature selection is to come up with the smallest set of features
that best captures the characteristics of the problem being addressed
the smaller the number of features used the simpler the analysis will be
but of course
the set of features used must include all features relevant to the problem
so there must be a balance between expressiveness and
compactness of the feature set
there are several methods to consider in selecting features
new features can be added
some features can be removed features can be re - coded or features can be combined
all these operations affect the final set of features that will be used for
analysis
of course some features can be kept as is as well
new features can be derived from existing features
for example a new feature to specify whether a student is in state or
out of state can be added based on the student state of residence
for an application such as college admissions
this new feature represents an important aspect of an application and so
would be very helpful as a separate feature
another example is adding a feature to indicate the color of a vehicle
which can play an important role in an auto insurance application
features can also be removed candidates for
removal are features that are very correlated
during data exploration you may have discovered that
two features are very correlated that is they change in very similar ways
for example the purchase price of a product and
the amount of sales tax paid are likely to be very correlated
the higher the purchase price the higher the sales tax
in this case you might want to drop one of these features
since these features have essentially duplicate information
and keeping both features makes the feature set larger and
the analysis unnecessarily more complex
features with a high percentage of missing values may also be good
candidates for removal
the validity and
usefulness of features with a lot of missing values are in question
so removing may not result in any loss of information
again these features would have been discovered during the data
exploration step
irrelevant features should also be removed from the data set
irrelevant features are those that contain no information that is useful for
the analysis task
an example of this is employee id in predicting income
other fields used simply for identification such as row number
person id etc are good candidates for removal
features can also be combined if the new feature presents important information
that is not represented by looking at the original features individually
for example bmi which is body mass index is an indicator of
whether a person is underweight average weight or overweight
this is an important feature to have for a weight loss application
it represents information about how much a person weighs relative to their height
that is not available by looking at just the person height or weight alone
a feature can be re - coded as appropriate for the application
a common example of this is when you want to turn a continuous feature in to
a categorical one
for example for a marketing application you might want to re - code customer age
into customer categories such as teenager young adult adult and senior citizen
so you would map ages 13 to 19 to teenager ages 20 to 25 to young adult
26 to 55 as adult and over 55 as senior
for some applications you may want to make use of finery features
as an example you might want a feature to capture whether a customer tends to buy
expensive items or not
in this case you would want a feature that maps to one for a customer with
an average purchase price over a certain amount and maps to zero otherwise
re - coding features can also result in breaking one feature
into multiple features
a common example of this is to separate an address feature
into its constituent parts street address city state and zip code
this way you can more easily group records by state for
example to provide a state by state analysis
future selection aims to select the smallest set of features to best
capture the characteristics of the data for your application
know from the examples represented that domain knowledge once again place
a key role in choosing the appropriate features to use
good understanding of the application is essential in deciding which features to
add drop or modify
it should also be noted that feature selection can be referred to as feature
engineering since what you are doing here is to engineer the best feature set for
your application
let now discuss what feature transformation is
after this video you will be able to articulate the purpose of
feature transformation list three feature transformation operations and
discuss when scaling is important
in addition to feature selection
data pre - processing can also include feature transformation
feature transformation involves mapping a set of values for
the feature to a new set of values to make the representation of the data more
suitable or easier to process for the downstream analysis
a common feature transformation operation is scaling
this involves changing the range of values for
a feature of features to another specified range
this is done to avoid allowing features with large values to
dominate the analysis results
for example if your dataset has both width and height as features
the magnitude of the weight values which are in pounds will be much
larger than the magnitude of the height values which are in feet and inches
so scaling both features to a common value range
will make the contributions from both weight and height equal
one way to perform scaling is to map all values of a feature to a specific range
such as between zero and one
for example let say you have a feature for
income that ranges from 30 000 to 100 000
and you have another feature for years of employment that ranges from 0 to 50
these features have very different scales
if you want both features to have equal weighting when you compare the data
samples then you can scale the range of both features to be between 0 and 1
that way the income feature which is on much largest scale than the years
of employment feature will not dominate the compares result
alternatively scaling can be perform by transforming the features such that
the results have zero mean and unit standard deviation
the steps to perform the scaling is to first calculate the mean and
standard deviation values for the feature to be scaled
then for each value for this feature
subtract the mean value from that value and divide by the standard deviation
the transformed feature will end up with a mean value of zero and
standard deviation of one
this effectively removes the units of the features and
converts each future value to number of standard deviations from the mean
this scaling method is used when the min and max values are known
this is also useful when there are outliers which will skew the calculation
for the range as the max value is determined by the furthest outlier
this scaling operation is often referred to as zero - normalization or
as standardization
filtering is another feature transformation operation
this is commonly applied to time series data such as speech or audio signals
a low pass filter can be used to filter out noise
which usually manifests as the high frequency component in the signal
a low pass filter removes components above a certain frequency
allowing the rest to pass through unaltered
filtering can also be used to remove noise in images
noise in an image is random variation in intensity or color in the pixels
for example a noise can cause an image to appear grainy
a mean or median filter can be used to replace the pixel value with the mean or
median value of its neighboring pixels
this has the effect of smoothing out the image
removing the noise that causes the graininess in the image
aggregation combines values for a feature in order to summarize data or
reduce variability
aggregation combines values for a feature in order to summarize the data or
to reduce variability
aggregation is done by summing or averaging data values at a higher level
for example hourly values can be aggregated to the daily level
or values within a city region can be aggregated to a state level
these plots show the results of aggregation
the left plot shows the wind speed values in miles per hour
averaged every 10 minutes over a period of seven days
notice that there a lot of variability that is the values fluctuate a lot
the right plot shows wind speed values averaged every hour so
every 60 minutes instead of every 10 minutes
notice that the line is much smoother here because the values are aggregated at
a higher time scale level
so aggregation can have the effect of removing noise
to provide a clear representation of the structure of your data
another example is tracking stock prices
hourly deviations of a stock may be difficult to track but
aggregated daily changes may better reveal any upward or downward trend of the stock
in summary feature transformation involves mapping the set of values for
a feature to a new set of values to make the representation of the data
more suitable for the downstream analysis
feature transformation should be used with cautions since they change the nature of
the data and unintentionally remove some important characteristics of the data
so it important to look at the effects of the transformation you are applying
to your data to make certain that it has the intended consequences
in this activity we will be using knime to handle missing data
first we will create new workflow and import our weather data
next we will remove missing values for specific measurement in the data
we will then impute missing values with the mean
and finally remove all the rows with missing values
let begin first let create a new workflow in knime
we will name it handling missing values
next let import the weather data using the file reader node
we will add the file reader node to the canvas
we will configure file reader to read daily weather csv
next we will connect the histogram node to file reader
before we configure the histogram node we need to run the file reader node
we can do this by clicking on file reader and
clicking on the green arrow in the toolbar
next double - click on histogram to configure it
we will set both the binning column and aggregation columns to air temp 9am
next we will add a missing value node
we will connect this to the file reader node
double click on missing value to configuring it
go to column settings
select air temp 9am and click on add
we will then choose remove row
this will remove the measurements of air temp 9am that had missing values
click ok
next we will add another histogram node to the output of missing value
we can do this easily by copying and pasting the existing histogram node
now let run the workflow by clicking on the double green arrows
let view the output in the histogram nodes before and
after we remove missing values
in this histogram view we can see that there are missing values
if we go and look at the second histogram node
the one after we removed the missing values
we can see that there are no missing values in this chart
next instead of removing missing values let impute the values to the mean
we could do this by configuring the missing value node
and instead of remove row change that to mean
click ok and rerun the work flow
we could see the difference by comparing the graphs and the two histogram nodes
if we go to visualization settings
and change labels to all elements we will see the number of elements in each band
in the histogram before we removed the missing values
we can see the fifth column has 216 measurements in it
where as the fifth column after we imputed the missing values has 221 values in it
let close these
next let remove all the rows that have missing values in the data
we can do this by double clicking on missing value
removing air temp 9am
clicking on the default tab
changing this to remove row
i will click ok now we rerun the workflow
again we will look at the histograms before and after we remove the missing values
again we will go to visualization settings and change the labels to all elements so
we can see the number of elements in each bin
we can see the number of elements in each bin in the different histograms
has changed
in this activity we will see how to handle missing values in spark
first we will load weather data into a spark dataframe
we will then examine the summary statistics for air temperature remove
the rows with missing values and finally impute missing values with the mean
let begin
first we will open the notebook called handling missing values
the first cell creates an sqlcontext and
then loads the weather data csv into a data frame
let execute this we can view the summary statistics for
the dataframe by running df describe show
let just look at the summary statistics for the air temperature
we will run
df describe air score 9am show
this says that there are 1090 rows
this does not include the rows of missing values for the air temperature
we can count the total number of rows in the dataframe by running df count
since there are 1095 total rows in the dataframe but
only 1090 in the air temp column
that means there are five rows in air temp that have missing values
next let remove all the rows in the dataframe that have missing values
we will put these in a new data frame called removealldf
to drop the missing values we will run df na drop
let look at the summary statistics for
air temp 9am with the missing values dropped
we will run removealldf describe air temp 9am show
we can see that the mean and standard deviation values
are close to the original values before we removed the rows with missing values
additionally the count of the number of rows is 1064
we can verify that this is the total number of rows in the new dataframe by
running removealldf count
next let impute the missing values with the mean
instead of removing them from the dataframe
first we will need to load the average function from pyspark
we will do this by running from pyspark sql functions import avg
next we will create a copy of the dataframe in which we will input the missing values
we will call the new dataframe imputedf
to impute the missing values we will iterate through each column of
the original dataframe first computing the mean value for that column and
then replacing the missing values in that column with the mean value
to move through the columns in the data frame
we will enter for x in imputedf columns : next
we will compute the mean value for that column
we will use the data frame in which we removed all the missing values
we will call the agg function to compute an aggregate
and the argument that we give it is avg
the argument avg is x which is the column we are trying to compute the average of
the agg function returns to dataframe and
we want to get the first row of that data frame
we can do this by calling first and then you get the first value in
this row or say 0
next let print the column name in mean value
print x meanvalue
now let update our new dataframe
replacing the missing values with the mean value
imputedf = imputedf na fill meanvalue x
let run this
we can see that the mean value for
air temp 9am matches the mean value computed in the summary statistics of
the data frame where the missing values were removed
finally let print the imputed data summary statistics
first we will show the summary statistics for the original dataframe
and then the summary statistics for the imputed dataframe
we will enter df describe air temp 9am show and
imputedf describe air temp 9am sho - w
run this
we can see that the number of rows in the imputed dataframe is larger
than the number of rows in the original dataframe
there were five rows in the original dataframe with missing values
and these have now been replaced with the mean
let talk about what it means to build a classification model and
how building a model differs from applying a model
after this video
you will be able to discuss what building a classification model means
explain the difference between building and applying a model
and summarize why the parameters of a model needs to be adjusted
a machine learning model is a mathematical model
in the general sense this means that the model has parameters and uses
equations to determine the relationship between its inputs and outputs
the parameters are used by the model to modify the inputs to generate the outputs
the model adjusts its parameters in order to correct or
refine this input output relationship
here an example of a simple model
this mathematical model represents a line
y is the output x is the input m determines the slope of the line and
b determines the y - intercept or where the line crosses the y - axis
m and b are the model parameters
given a specific value for
x the model uses as parameters along with x to determine y
by adjusting the values for the parameters m and b
the model can adjust how the input x matched to the output y
here we see how the output y changes for
the same value of input x when parameter b changes
recall that b is the y - intercept or where the line crosses the y - axis
the value of b is + 1 for the red line and - 1 for the blue line
for the input x = 1 the value of y is 3 for
the red line as indicated by the red arrow
for the blue line when the parameter b changes from + 1 to - 1
for x = 1 the value of y is 1 as indicated by the blue arrow
so we see that with just a simple change in one model parameter
the input to output mapping changes
a machine learning model works in a similar way
it maps input values to output values
and it adjusts the parameters in order to correct or
refine this input - output mapping
the parameters of a machine learning model are adjusted or
estimated from the data using a learning algorithm
this in essence is what is involved in building a model
this process is referred to by many terms such as model building
model creation model training and model fitting
in building a model
we want to adjust the parameters in order to reduce the model error
in the case of supervised tasks such as classification this means getting
the model outputs to match the targets or desired outputs as much as possible
since the classification task is to predict the correct category or
class given the input variables
you can think of the classification problem visually as carving out the input
space as regions corresponding to the different class labels
in this diagram for example the classification model needs to form
the boundaries to define the regions separating red triangles
from blue diamonds from green circles from yellow squares
in this example if a sample falls within the region in the upper right corner
it will be classified as a blue diamond
classification decisions are based on these regions and the regions are defined
by the boundaries as indicated by the dashed lines in the diagram
so these boundaries are referred to as decision boundaries
building a classification then means using the data to adjust the model parameters
in order to form decision boundaries to separate the target classes
note that the term classifier is often used to mean classification model
in general building a classification model
as well as other machine learning models involves two phases
the first is the training phase in which the model is constructed and
its parameters adjusted using as what referred to as training data
training data is the data set used to train or create a model
the second is the testing phase
this is where the learned model is applied to new data
that is data not used in training the model
here another way to look at the two phases
in a training phase the learning algorithm uses the training data
to adjust the model parameters to minimize errors
at the end of the training phase you get the trained model
in the testing phase the trained model is applied to test data
test data is separate from training data and is previously unseen by the model
the model is then evaluated on how it performs on the test data
the goal in building a classifier model is to have the model
perform well on training as well as test data
we will discuss in more detail the use of training and
test data sets in the next module when we discuss model evaluation
to adjust a model parameters we need to apply a learning algorithm
we will discuss the specific algorithms to build a classification model in
the next few lectures
in this video we will outline some commonly used algorithms for
building a classification model
after this video you will be able to describe the goal of
a classification algorithm and name some common algorithms for classification
recall that a classification task is to predict the category from the input
variables
a classification model processes the input data it receives and provides an output
since classification is a supervised task a target or
desired output is provided for each sample
the goal is to get the model outputs to match the targets as much as possible
a classification model adjusts its parameters
to get its outputs to match the targets
to adjust a model parameters a learning algorithm is applied
this occurs in a training phase when the model is constructed
there are many algorithms to build a classification model
in this course we will cover the algorithms listed here
knn or k nearest neighbors decision tree and naive bayes
knn stands for k nearest neighbors
this technique relies on the notion that samples with similar characteristics
that is samples with similar values for input likely belong to the same class
so classification of a sample is dependent
on the target values of the neighboring points
another classification technique is referred to as decision tree
a decision tree is a classification model that uses a treelike structure
to represent multiple decision paths
traversing each path leads to a different way to classify an input sample
a naive bayes model uses a probabilistic approach to classification
baye theorem is used to capture the relationship between the input data and
the output class
simply put the baye theorem compares the probability of an event
in the presence of another event
we see here the probability of a if b is present
for example probability of having a fire if the weather is hot
you can imagine event b depending on more than one variable
for example weather is hot and windy
we will cover knn decision tree and naive bayes in detail in the next few lectures
there are many other classification techniques but we will focus on these
since they are fundamental algorithms that are commonly used and
form the basis of other algorithms for classification
in this activity we will perform classification in spark is in
decision tree
first we will load weather data into dataframe and
drop unused and missing data
we will then create a categorical variable for
low humidity days and aggregate features used to make predictions
we will then split our data into training and test sets
and then create and train the decision tree
finally we will save our predictions to a csv file
let begin first we will open the notebook called classification
the first cell contains the classes we need to load to run this exercise
let run this
next we create sql context and load the weather data csv into a data frame
the second cell also prints all the columns in this data frame
run this
the third cell defines the columns in the weather data we will use for
the decision tree classifier
let run it
we will now use the column name number
so let drop that from the data frame df = df drop number
now let revolve the rows with missing data df = df na drop
now let print the number of rows and columns in our resulting data frame
df count len df columns
next let create a categorical variable to denote if the humidity is low
we will enter binarizer = binarizer
the first argument specifies a threshold value for the variable
we want the categorical variable to be 1 if the humidity is greater than 25
so we will enter a threshold = 24 9999
the next argument specifies the column to use to create the categorical variable
we will input inputcol = relative humidity 3pm
the final argument specifies the new column name outputcol = label
now let create a new data frame with this categorical variable
binarizereddf = binarizer transform df
let run this
let look at the first four rows in this new data frame
we will run binarizeddf select are lative humidity 3pm
label show 4
the relative humidity in the first row is greater than 25 and the label is 1
the relative humidity in the second third and fourth rows are less than 25
and the label is 0
next let aggregate the features we will use to make predictions into a single col
assembler = vectorassember
the first argument is a list of the columns to be aggregated
inputcols = featurecolumns and the second argument is the name
of the new column containing the aggregated features outputcol = features
we can create the new data frame by running
assembled = assembler transform binarizeddf
let run this
next we will split our data set into two parts one for
training data and one for test data
you can do this by entering training
data testdata = assembled randomsplit 0 8
0 2 seed = 13234
we can see the size of the two sets by running count
trainingdata count testdata count
next let create and train the decision tree
we will enter dt = decisiontreeclassifier
the first argument is the column we are trying to predict labelcol = label
the second argument is the name of the column containing your
aggregated features featurescol = features
the third argument is the stopping criteria for
tree induction based on the maximum depth of the tree maxdepth = 5
the fourth argument is the stopping criteria for tree induction based
on the minimum number of samples in a node mininstancespernode = 20
and finally the last argument specifies the impurity measure
used to split the nodes impurity = gini let run this
next we can create a model by training the decision tree
we will do this by executing it in a pipeline
we will enter pipeline = pipeline stages = dt
we will create them all by putting a training data model =
pipeline fit trainingdata
let run this now we can make predictions using our test data
we will enter predictions = model transform testdata
you can look at the first 10 rows of the prediction by running
predictions select prediction label show 10
you can see in the first ten rows the prediction matches the label
now let save our predictions to a csv file
in the next spark hands - on activity we will evaluate the accuracy
you can save it by running predictions select prediction
label write save path = file file :
home cloudera downloads big - data - 4 predic - tions csv
we will specify the format to use spark csv
format = com databricks spark csv
finally we will enter header = true
run this to save the predictions to a csv file
in this activity we will be performing classification in knime
first we will create a new workflow and import our weather data
next we will remove the missing data and then create a categorical value for
the humidity measurements
we will then examine summary statistics of the data before and
after the missing data was removed and finally build a decision tree workflow
let begin
first let create a new workflow
we will call it classification
next we will import the daily weather data using the file reader node
configure the file reader node to use daily weather csv
next we will add a missing value node
to remove the missing values in the daily weather data
we will configure missing value to remove all the missing values
next we will use a numeric binner node to create a categorical variable for
the humidity at 3pm
we will add the numeric binner node we will connect it to missing value
we will select the relative humidity 3pm column
we will create two bins the first bin we will call humidity low
and that value will go up to 25
the second bin we will
call humidity not low
we will check the append new column and
we will call the new column low humidity day
next we will examine some summary statistics both before and
after we have removed the missing values
we will add the statistics node to the canvas
we will connect the first one to the output of the file reader actor
we will add another one to the output of numeric binner
we will change the name of the first one to be before filtering
and change the name of the second one to after filtering
lets configure the first one
we will change the maximum number of possible values per column to 1500
we will also add all the columns
let configure the second statistics now
again we will change the maximum number of possible values per column to 1500 and
we will add all the columns
now let run our workflow
let view both statistic nodes to compare the outputs
in the before filtering statistics we can see that there are missing values
however there are no missing values in the after filtering statistics
we can also compare the summary statistics for different measurements
to see that they are similar values
for example let take a look at air temp 9am
we could see that most of the statistics are the same
as well as the distribution of values
in the after filtering statistics click on the nominal tab
and we will look at the low humidity day categorical variable we created
we can see that the samples are equally distributed between the two values
let close these statistics views
next let add a column filter node
we will connect this to the output of numeric binner
double - click to configure the node
and we will exclude relative humidity 9am and
relative humidity 3pm columns click ok
next we will add a color manager node to the canvas
will connect this to the output of column filter double - click to configure it
we will make sure the humidly low is red and humidity not low is blue
click ok to close
next we will add the partitioning node to the campus
we will connect this to the output of color manager
double - click to configure
we want to split the data into two partitions
the first partition should have 80 of the data
the second partition should have 20
to do this click on relative and change this to 80
we will make sure draw randomly is selected
and check use random seed and change the seed to 12345
normally we would not specific the random seed
however since we want repeatable results we use a specific seed value here
click ok to continue
next we will add a decision tree learner to the work flow
we will connect this to the top output of the partitioning node
double - click to configure and
change the min number of records per node to 20
click ok
next we will add a decision tree predictor node to the canvas and we will connect
the bottom output of partitioning to the bottom input of the predictor
next we will connect the output of decision tree learner
to the top input of decision tree predictor
now let execute our workflow
we can view the resulting classification rules
by right clicking on decision tree predictor
and choosing either view : decision tree view or view : decision tree view simple
let do the first one
this shows the first two splits in our decision tree
we can expand each branch by clicking on the plus
let close this
now let look at the simplified view
again we can expand the branches to see the splits in the decision tree
close this finally let save this workflow
we will analyze the results of the decision tree model in the next knime hands on
save the workflow by clicking on the disk icon
welcome back we already discussing classification models and techniques for
next few lectures
let first define what the classification task is
after this video you will be able to define what classification is
explain whether classification is supervised or unsupervised and
describe how binomial classification differs from multinomial classification
classification is one type of machine learning problems
in the classification problem the input data is presented to the machine learning
model and the task is to predict the target corresponding to the input data
the target is a categorical variable so the classification task is
to predict the category or label of the target given the input data
for example the classification problem illustrated in this image
is to predict the type of weather
the target that the model has to predict is the weather and the possible values for
weather in this case is sunny windy rainy or cloudy
the input data can consist of measurements like temperature relative humidity
atmospheric pressure wind speed wind direction etc
so given specific values for temperature relative humidity atmospheric pressure
etc the task for the model is to predict if the weather will be sunny
windy rainy or cloudy for the day
this is what the data set might look like for the weather classification problem
each row is a sample with input variables temperature humidity and
pressure and target variable weather
each row has specific values for the input variables and
a corresponding value for the target variable
the classification task is to predict the value of the target variable
from the values of the input variables
since a target is provided we have labeled data and so
classification is a supervised task
recall that in a supervised task the target or
desired output for each sample is given
note that the target variable goes by many names such as target
label output class variable category and class
a classification problem can be binary or multi - class with binary
classification the target variable has two possible values for example yes and no
with multi - class classification the target variable has more than
two possible values
for example the target can be short medium and tall
multi - class classification is also referred to multinomial or
multi - label classification
remember though that the target is always a categorical variable in classification
some examples of binary classification are predicting
whether it will rain tomorrow or not here there are two possible outcomes
yes it will rain tomorrow or no it will not rain tomorrow
identifying whether a credit card transaction is legitimate or fraudulent
again there are only two possible values for the target legitimate or fraudulent
some examples of multi - class classification include
predicting what type of product that a customer will buy
the possible values for the target variables would be product
categories such as kitchen electronics clothes etc
there is more than one category of products so
this is a multi - class classification problem
another example is categorizing a tweet as having a positive negative or
neutral sentiment again the number of possible values for
the target is more than two here
so this is also a multi - class classification task
to summarize in classification
the model has to predict the category corresponding to the input data
since the target is provided for each sample classification is a supervised
task the target variable is always categorical in classification
in this lecture
we will look at the decision tree model a popular method used for classification
after this video you will be able to explain how a decision tree is used for
classification
describe the process of constructing a decision tree for classification
and interpret how a decision tree comes up with a classification decision
the idea behind decision trees for classification is to split the data
into subsets where each subset belongs to only one class
this is accomplished by dividing the input space into pure regions
that is regions with samples from only one class
with real data completely pure subsets may not be possible
so the goal is to divide the data into subsets that are as pure as possible
that is each subset contains as many samples as possible from a single class
graphically this is equivalent to dividing the input space into regions that are as
pure as possible
boundaries separating these regions are called decision boundaries
and the decision tree model makes classification decisions
based on these decision boundaries
a decision tree is a hierarchical structure with nodes and directed edges
the node at the top is called the root node
the nodes at the bottom are called the leaf nodes
nodes that are neither the root node or the leaf nodes are called internal nodes
the root and internal nodes have test conditions
each leaf node has a class label associated with it
a classification decision is made by traversing the decision tree
starting with the root node
at each node the answer to the test condition determines which
branch to traverse to
when a leaf node is reached the category at the leaf node
determines the classification decision
the depth of a node is the number of edges from the root node to that node
the depth of the root node is 0
the depth of a decision tree is the number of edges
in the longest path from the root node to the leaf node
the size of a decision tree is the number of nodes in the tree
this is an example of a decision tree
it can be used to classify an animal as a mammal or not a mammal
according to this decision tree if an animal is warm - blooded
gives live birth and is a vertebrate then it is a mammal
if an animal does not have all of these three characteristics
then it is not a mammal
a decision tree is built by starting with all samples at a single node
the root node
additional nodes are added when the data is split into subsets
at a high level constructing a decision tree consists of the following steps
start with all samples and a node
partition the samples into subsets based in the input variables
the goal is to create subsets of records that are purest that is
each subset contains as many samples as possible belonging to just one class
another way to say this is that the subsets should be as homogeneous or
as pure as possible
repeatedly partition data into successively purer subsets
until some stopping criterion is satisfied
an algorithm for
constructing a decision tree model is referred to as an induction algorithm
so you may hear the term tree induction used to describe the process of
building a decision tree
note that at each split the induction algorithm
only considers the best way to split that particular portion of the data
this is referred to as a greedy approach
greedy algorithms solve a subset of the problem at a time and
as a necessary approach when solving the entire problem is not feasible
this is the case with decision trees
it is not feasible to determine the best tree given a data set so
the tree has to be built in piecemeal fashion
by determining the best way to split the current node at each step
and combining these decisions together to form the final decision tree
in constructing a decision tree how is the data partitioned
how does a decision tree determine the best way to split
the set of samples at a node
again the goal is to partition data at a node into subsets that are as
pure as possible
in this example
the partition shown on the right results in more homogeneous subsets
since these subsets contain more samples belonging to a single class
than the resulting subsets shown on the left
so the partition on the right results in purer subsets and
is the preferred partition
therefore we need a way to measure the purity of a split
in order to compare different ways to partition a set of data
it turns out that it works out better mathematically if we measure the impurity
rather than the purity of a split
so the impurity measure of a node
specifies how mixed the resulting subsets are
since we want the resulting subsets to have homogeneous class labels
not mixed class labels we want the split that minimizes the impurity measure
a common impurity measure used for
determining the best split is the gini index
the lower the gini index the higher the purity of the split
so the decision tree will select the split that minimizes the gini index
besides the gini index other impurity measures include entropy or
information gain and misclassification rate
the other factor in determining the best way to partition a node
is which variable to split on
the decision tree will test all variables to determine the best way to split a node
using a purity measure such as the gini index to compare the various
possibilities
recall that the tree induction algorithm repeatedly splits nodes to get more and
more homogeneous subsets
so when does this process stop
when does the algorithm stop growing the tree
there several criteria that can be used to determine when a node should no longer
be split into subsets
the induction algorithm can stop expanding a node when
all samples in the node have the same class label
this means that this set of data is as pure as possible and
further splitting will not result in any better partition of the data
since getting completely pure subsets is difficult to achieve with real data
this stopping criterion can be modified
to when a certain percentage of the samples in the node say 90 for
example have the same class labels
the algorithm can stop expanding a node when the number of samples in the node
falls below a certain minimum value
a this point the number of samples is too small to make
much difference in the classification results with the further splitting
the induction algorithm can stop expanding a node when the improvement in impurity
measure is too small to make much of a difference in classification results
the algorithm can stop expanding a node when the maximum tree depth is reached
this is to control the complexity of the resulting tree
there can be other criteria that can be used to determine when tree induction
should stop
let take a look at an example to illustrate the tree induction process
let say that we want to classify loan applicants as being likely to repay a loan
or not likely to repay a loan based on their income and
amount of debt they already have
building a decision tree for
this classification problem could proceed as follows
consider the input space of this problem as shown in the left figure
one way to split this data set into homogeneous
subsets is to consider the decision boundary where income equals t1
to the right of this decision boundary are mostly red samples and
to the left are mostly blue samples
the subsets are not completely homogeneous but
that is the best way to split the original data set based on the variable income
this decision boundary is represented in the decision tree by the condition
income is greater than t1 at the root node
this is the condition used to split the original data set
samples with income greater than the threshold value
of t1 are placed in the right subset and samples with income less than or
equal to t1 are placed in the left subset just as shown in the right diagram
the right subset is now labeled as red
meaning that the loan applicant is likely to be paid alone
the second step then is to determine how to split the region outlined in red
as shown in the left diagram in input space the best way to split this data
is specified by the second decision boundary with debt equals t2
this is represented in the decision tree on the right
with the addition of the node with condition debt greater than t2
samples with the value of debt greater than t2 are shown in the region
above the decision boundary
this region contains all blue samples and so the corresponding node is labeled blue
meaning that the loan applicant is not likely to repay the loan
the third and final split looks at how to split the region outlined in red
in the left diagram
the best split is specified by the boundary with income equals t3
this splits the red region into two pure subsets
this split is represented in the decision tree by adding a node with condition
income is greater than t3
the left resulting node is labeled blue and
the right resulting node is labeled red
corresponding to the resulting subsets within the red border in the left diagram
we end with the final decision tree on the right
which implements the decision boundaries shown as dash lines in the left diagram
these decision boundaries partition the data set as shown
the label for each region is determined by the label of the majority of the samples
these labels are reflected in the leaf nodes of the decision tree
shown on the right
you may have noticed that the decision boundaries of a decision tree are parallel
to the axes formed by the variables this is referred to as being rectilinear
the boundaries are rectilinear because each split considers only
a single variable
there are variance of the tree induction algorithm that consider more than one
attribute when splitting a note
however each split has to consider all combinations of combined variables and
so such induction algorithms are much more computationally expensive
there are a few important things to note about the decision tree classifier
the resulting tree is often simple to understand and interpret
this is one of the biggest advantages of decision trees for classification
it is often possible to look at the resulting tree to see
which variables are important to the classification problem and
understand how the classification is performed
for this reason many people will start out with the decision tree classifier
to get a feel for the classification problem
even if they end up using more sophisticated models later on
the tree induction algorithm as described in this lesson
is relatively computationally inexpensive
so training a decision tree for classification can be relatively fast
the greedy approach used by tree induction algorithm determines the best way to split
the portion of the data at a node but
does not guarantee the best solution overall for the entire data set
decision boundaries are rectilinear
this can limit the expressiveness of the resulting model which means
that it may not be able to solve complicated classification problems that
require more complex decision boundaries to be formed
in summary the decision tree classifier uses a tree like structure to specify
a series of conditions that are tested to determine the class label for a sample
the decision tree is constructed by repeatedly splitting a data partition
into successively more homogeneous subsets
the resulting tree can often be easy to interpret
we will start with a very simple classification technique called k - nearest
neighbors
after this video you will be able to describe how knn is used for
classification
discuss the assumption behind knn and explain what the k stands for in knn
knn stands for k - nearest neighbors
this is one of the simplest techniques to build a classification model
the basic idea is to classify a sample based on its neighbors
so when you get a new sample as shown by the green circle in the figure the class
label for that sample is determined by looking at the labels of its neighbors
knn relies on the notion of the so - called duck test
that is if it looks like a duck swims like a duck and quacks like a duck
then it probably is a duck
in the classification context
this means that samples with similar input values likely belong to the same class
so samples with similar input values should be labeled with the same
target label
this means that classification of a sample is dependent
on the target labels of the neighboring points
in more detail then this is how knn works
given a new sample look for
the samples in the training data that are closest to the new sample
these are the neighbors
use the labels of this neighboring points to determine the label for the new sample
this figure illustrate how knn works
the problem here is to determine if a sample should be classified as
a blue square or red triangle
the green circle is the new sample
to determine a class label for this new sample look at its closest neighbors
these neighbors are the samples within the dashed circle
two blue squares and one red triangle
the class labels of the neighboring samples determine the label for
the new sample
the value of k determines the number of nearest neighbor to consider
so if k equals 1 then only the closest neighbor is examined
to determine the class of the new sample as shown in the left figure
if k equals 2
then the 2 nearest neighbors are considered as seen in the middle figure
if k equal 3 then the 3 nearest neighbors are considered as
in the right figure and so on
if k equal 1 and only 1 neighbor is used then the label for
the new sample is simpler the label of the neighbor
this is shown in the left figure
the label of the new sample is then a
since that is the label of its one nearest neighbor
when multiple neighbors are considered then a voting scheme is used
majority of vote is commonly used so the label associated with
the majority of the neighbors is used as the label of the new sample
this is what we see in the right figure
with k equals 3 3 nearest neighbors are considered
with two neighbors labeled as a and one as b
the majority of vote determines that the new sample should be labeled as a
in case of a tie which could be possible if the value of k is even
then some tight breaking rule is needed
for example the label of the closer neighbor is used or
the label is chosen randomly among the neighbors
this is seen in the middle figure
with two nearest neighbors and each with a different class label the label for
the new sample is randomly chosen here to be b
with knn some measure of similarity is needed to determine how
close two samples are together
this is necessary to determine which samples are the nearest neighbors
distance measures such as distance are commonly used
other distance measures that can be used include manhattan and hemming distance
to summarize knn is a very simple classification technique
note that there is no separate training phase
there is no separate part where a model is constructed and its parameter is adjusted
this is unlike most other classification algorithms
knn can generate complex decision boundaries allowing for
complex classification decisions to be made
it can be susceptible to noise however
because classification decisions are made using only information about
a few neighboring points instead of the entire dataset
knn can be slow however since the distance between a new sample and
all sample points in the data must be calculated in order to determine
the k - nearest neighbors
in this lecture we will discuss the naive bayes classifier
after this video you will be able to discuss how a naive bayes model
works fro classification define the components of bayes rule and
explain what the naive means in naive bayes
a naive bayes classification model uses a probabilistic approach to classification
what this means is that the relationships between the input features and
the class is expressed as probabilities
so given the input features for a sample the probability for
each class is estimated
the class with the highest probability then determines the label for the sample
in addition to using a probabilistic framework for classification
the naive bayes classifier also uses what is known as bayes theorem
the application of bayes theorem makes estimating the probabilities easier
in addition naive bayes assumes that the input features are statistically
independent of one another
this means that for a given class
the value of one feature does not affect the value of any other feature
this independence assumption is an oversimplified one that does not always
hold true and so is considered a naive assumption
the naive independence assumption and
the use of bayes theorem gives this classification model its name
we will cover bayes theorem and
the independence assumption in more detail in this lecture
before we look at naive bayes in more detail
let first start with some background on probability
probability is the measure of how likely an event is
the probability of an event a occurring is denoted p and in parenthesis a
it is calculated by dividing the number of ways event a can occur
by the total number of possible outcomes
for example what is the probability of rolling a die and getting six
when you roll a die you can get a number from one to six so
the number of possible outcomes is six
the number of ways fro getting six is one
since the way you can get six is if the die shows six when it stops rolling
that means that the probability of getting the number six when you roll a die
is one over six
this is denoted p of six and that equal to one over six and
is read as probability of six is one over six
there also a joint probability the joint probability specifies
the probability of event a and event b occurring together
in this diagram the probability of event a occurring is shown as the blue circle
and the probability of event b occurring is shown as the green circle
then the joint probability that is the probability of a and
b occurring together is shown as the overlap of these two circles
the joint probability of a and b is denoted
p a b for
an example of joint probability let consider rolling 2 dice together
what is the probability in getting 2 sixes or a six from each die
if the two events are independent then the joint probability is simply the result
of multiplying the probabilities of the individual events together
in this case then we have the probability of rolling a six for
each die is one over six so the joint probability is one over 36
this leads us to conditional probability
the conditional probability is the probability of event a occurring
given that event b has already occurred
another way to say this is that event a is conditioned on event b
the conditional probability is the noted p and in parentheses a
vertical line b and is read as probability of a given b
this diagram gives a graphical definition of conditional probability
as before the blue circle is the probability of event a occurring
the green circle is the probability of event b occurring
the overlap is a joint probability of a and b
the conditional probability p a given b then is
calculated as the join probability divided by the probability of b
the conditional probability is an important concept in classification
as we will see later
it provides the means to specify the probability of a class label
given the input values
the relationship between conditional probabilities p of b given a and
p of a given b can be expressed through bayes theorem
this theorem is named after a reverend named thomas bayes who lived in the 1700s
it is a way to look at how the probability of a hypothesis is affected by
new evidence gathered from data
bayes theorem expresses the relationship between probability of b
given a and probability of a given b as shown in this equation
bayes theorem is also known as bayes rule or bayes law
now that we have reviewed some background on probability
let see how all this relates to the classification problem
with the probabilistic framework the classification task is defined as follows
capital x is the set of values for the input features in the sample
given a sample with features x predict the corresponding class c
another way to state this is what is the class label associated with
the feature vector x or how should the feature vector x be classified
to find the class label c we need to calculate the conditional probability of
class c given x for all classes and
select a class with the highest probability
so for classification
we want to find the value of c that maximizes the probability of c given x
the problem is that it is difficult to estimate this probability
because we would need to enumerate every possible combination of feature values and
to know the conditional probability
for each class given every possible feature combination and
here is where bayes theorem comes into play
the classification problem can be reformulated using bayes theorem
to simplify the classification problem
specifically using bayes theorem the probability of c given x can be expressed
using other probability quantities which can be estimated from the data
here bayes theorem again but some additional terms defined
probability of c i x is referred to as the posterior probability since
it is the probability of the class label being c after observing input features x
probability of x given c is the probability of
observing input features x given that c is the class label
this is the class conditional probability since it is conditioned on the class
probability of c is the probability of the class label being c
this is the probability of each class prior to observing any input data
and so is referred to as the prior probability
the probability of x is the probability
of observing input features x regardless of what the class label is
so for classification we want to calculate the posterior
probability p c x for each class c
from bayes theorem p c x is related to
the p x c p c and probability of x
probability of x does not depend on the class c therefore
it is a constant value given the input x
since it the same value for all classes the probability
of x can be removed from the calculation of probability of c given x
what is left then are probability of x given c and the probability of c
so estimating the probability of c given x boils down to
estimating the probability of x given c and probability of c
the nice thing is that probability of x given c and
probability of c can be estimated from the data
so now we have a way to calculate probably of c given x which is what we need for
classification
to the estimate the probability of c
which is the probability of the class of c before observing any input data
we simply calculate the fraction of samples with that class label
c in the training data
for this example there are four samples labeled as green circles out of 10
samples so probability of green circle is 4 out of 10 or 0 4
similarly the fraction of samples labeled as red triangles is 6 out of 10 or 0 6
so estimating the prior probabilities is a simple count
of number of samples with each class label
divided by the total number of samples in the training data center
in estimating probability of x given c which is the probability
of observing feature factor x given that the class is c
we can use the independent assumption to simplify the problem
the independence assumption of the naive bayes classifier assumes
that each feature x sub i in the featured vector x
is conditionally independent of every other feature given the class c
this means that we only need to estimate the probability of x
sub i given c instead of having to
estimate the probability of the entire feature x given c
for every combination of values for
the features in x then we would simply multiply these individual probabilities
together to get the probability of the entire feature vector x
given the class c to estimate the probability of x sub i
given c we count up the number of times a particular input
value is observed for the class c in the training data
for example the number of times that we see the value of yes for the future home
owner when the class label is no it three as indicated by the green arrows
this is divided by the number of samples with no as the class label which is seven
this fraction three out of seven
is the probability that home owner is yes given that the class is no
similarly the samples with the value of single for
the feature marital status when it crosses yes are indicated by the red arrows
and the probability that marital status is single
given that the class label is yes is 2 3 or 0 67
some things to know about the naive bayes classification model are it is a fast and
simple algorithm
the algorithm boils down to calculating counts for probabilities and
performing some multiplication so it is very simple to implement
and the probabilities that are needed can be calculated with a single
scan of the data set and stored in a table
either two processing of the data is not necessary as with many other
machine learning algorithms
so model building and testing of both task it scales well
due today independent assumption the probability for
each feature can be independently estimated
these means that featured probability is can be calculated in parallel
this also means that the data set size does not have to grow exponentially
with a number of features
this avoids the many problems associated with the curse of dimensionality
this also means that you do not need a lot of data to build the model
the number of parameters scales linearly with the number of features
the independence assumption does not hold true in many cases
in practice however the naive bayes classifier still tends to perform very
well this is because even though naive bayes may
not provide good estimates of the correct class probabilities
as long as the correct class is more probable than any other class
the correct classification results will be reached
the independence assumption also prevents the naive base classifier to model
interactions between features which limits its classification power
the increased risk of smoking in a history of cancer would not be captured
for example
the naive bays classifier has been applied to many real world problems
including spam filtering document classification and sentiment analysis
to summarize the naive bayes classifier uses a probabilistic framework for
classification
it applies bayes theorem and the feature independence assumption
to simplify the problem of estimating probabilities for the classification task
in addition to the evaluation matrix covered n the last lecture
the performance of a classification model can also be evaluated
using a confusion matrix
we will introduce the confusion matrix in this lecture
after this video you will be able to
describe how a confusion matrix can be used to evaluate a classifier
interpret the confusion matrix of a model
and relate accuracy to values in a confusion matrix
let use our example again of predicting whether a given animal is a mammal or not
recall that this is a binary classification task with the class label
being either yes indicating mammal or no indicating non - mammal
now let review the different types of errors that you can get with
classification
if the true label is yes and
the predicted label is yes then this is a true positive abbreviated as tp
this is a case where the label is correctly predicted as positive
if the true label is no and
the predicted label is no then this is a true negative abbreviated as tn
this is the case where the label is correctly predicted as negative
if the true label is no and
the predicted label is yes then this is a false positive abbreviated as fp
this is the case where the label is incorrectly predicted as positive
when it should be negative
if the true label is yes and the predicted label is no
then this is a false negative abbreviated as fn
this is the case where the label is incorrectly predicted as negative
when it should be positive
a confusion matrix can be used to summarize the different types of
classification errors
the true positive cell corresponds to the samples that are correctly predicted as
positive by the model
the true negative cell corresponds to the samples that are correctly predicted
as negative
the false positive cell corresponds to samples that are incorrectly predicted
as positive
the false negative cell corresponds to samples that are incorrectly predicted
as negative
each cell has the count or percentage of samples with each type of errors
let look at an example to see how a confusion matrix is filled in
the table on the lists true labels along with the models prediction for
a data set of ten samples
we will summarize this results in a confusion matrix
first let figure out the number of true positives
we call that a true positive occurrence when the output is correctly predicted
as positive
in other words the true label is yes and the model prediction is also yes
in this example there are three true positives as indicated by the red arrows
we enter three and the true positive cell in the confusion matrix
now let look at the true negatives
a true negative occurs when the output is correctly predicted as negative
in other words the true label is no and the models prediction is also no
in this example
there are four true negatives as indicated by the green arrows
we enter four in the true negative cell in the confusion matrix
what about false negatives
a false negative occurs when the output is incorrectly predicted as negative
when it should be positive
that is the true label is yes and the model prediction is no
in this example
there are two false negatives as indicated by the purple arrows
we enter two in the false negative cell in the confusion matrix
finally we need to look at false positives
a false positive occurs
when the input is incorrectly predicted as positive when it should be negative
that is the true label is no and models prediction is yes
in this example there is one false positive as indicated by the yellow arrow
we enter one in the false positive cell in the confusion matrix
this is our complete confusion matrix for this example
we see that the sum of the numbers in the cells add up to ten
which is the number of samples in our dataset
note that the diagonal values true positives and
true negatives are samples with correct predictions
in our example these values sum up to 7
meaning that 7 out of 10 samples were correctly predicted by the model
the higher the sum of the diagonal values the better the performance of the model
the off diagonal values capture the misclassified samples
where the model predictions do not match the true labels
in this example these values indicate that there were three misclassifications
smaller values for
the off diagonal cells in the confusion matrix indicate better model performance
note that the diagonal values true positives and
true negatives are samples with correct predictions
in our example these values sum up to 7 meaning
that 7 out of 10 samples were correctly predicted by the model
the higher the sum of the diagonal values the better the performance of the model
you may have noticed that the diagonal values are related to accuracy rate
recall that accuracy is defined as the sum of two positives and
true negatives divided by all samples
the sum of two positives and
two negatives is the sum of the diagonal values in a confusion matrix
the sum of the diagonal values in a confusion matrix
divided by the total number of samples gives you the accuracy rate
similarly the off diagonal values are related to the error rate
recall that the error rate is the opposite of the accuracy rate
the sum of the off diagonal values in a confusion matrix
divided by the total number of samples gives you the error rate
looking at the values in the confusion matrix can help you understand
the kind of misclassifications that your model is making
a high value for this cell indicated by the yellow arrow
means that classifying the positive class is problematic for the model
a high value for the cell indicated by the orange arrow on the other hand
means that classifying the negative class is problematic for the model
in summary the confusion matrix is a table
used to summarize the different types of errors for a classifier
the values in a confusion matrix can be used to evaluate the performance of
a classifier and are related to evaluation metrics such as accuracy and error rates
they also indicate what other types of misclassifications the model is making
note that in some implementations of a confusion matrix the true and
predictive labels are switched
be sure to review the documentation for the software you are using to generate
a confusion matrix to understand what each cell specifies
in this activity we will be evaluating the decision tree model
we created in the knime classification hands - on
first we will create a confusion matrix to determine the accuracy
of the decision tree model
next we will use highlighting and
a scatter plot to analyze the classification errors
let begin
first let open the classification workflow that we built in the previous
hands - on
in the top - left of knime is a knime explorer
double - click on the classification under local
next we will create a confusion matrix to analyze the accuracy
of our decision tree model
to do this we will add the scorer node to the canvas
connect the output of decision tree predictor to the input of scorer
double - click on scorer
we will use the default values so click ok
next run the workflow
now let view the confusion matrix
i can see the accuracy as 80 282
at the top i can see that it accurately predicted 76 values for
humidity low and 95 for humidity not low
it inaccurately predicted 24 values for humidty low and
18 for humidty not low for an error of 19 718
close this
next we use an interactive table to look at the values that were incorrectly
predicted
we will add the interactive table to the canvas
we will connect this to the output of decision tree predictor
run the workflow and view the table
the right two columns have the real value for low humidity and the prediction
for some of these rows we can tell that the prediction was not correct
for example in row ten and in row 17
let leave the table view open and go back to the workflow
next we will add the scatter plot nodes to the workflow
connect this to the output of decision tree predictor
execute the workflow and view the scatter plot
we will select row 17 and choose hilite selected
go back to the scatter plot
and we see this particular value is highlighted in the plot
we could choose another row from the table and
highlight it again to see its place in the plot
let choose row ten
we can do this for values that were incorrectly predicted
to find any patterns for further analysis
in this activity we will use spark to evaluate our decision tree
first we load the classification predictions
created during the last spark hands on activity
we then compute the accuracy of these predictions
and then generate a confusion matrix
let begin
first let open the model evaluation notebook
next let execute the first cell to load the classes
then execute the second cell to load the predictions we saved
during the previous hands on
we could then complete the accuracy of these predictions
by using a multi - class classification evaluator
let enter evaluator = multiclassclassificationevaluator labelco -
l = label predictioncol = prediction and
finally metricname = precision and execute this
we can then compute the accuracy by calling evaluate on the evaluator
we will enter evaluator evaluate predictions
this says that the accuracy is about 81
next let use multi - class metrics to compute a confusion matrix
multi - class metrics takes an rdd of numbers and
our data is currently in a data frame
we can access the rdd of the underlying data frame by using the rdd
attribute of predictions
if we look at predictions rdd take 2 we see the rdd
is the rdd of rows or each row has a prediction and label
however multi - class metrics wants an rdd of numbers
we could do this using a map
we will enter predictions rdd map and we will use a key word
tuple and we will look at the first two elements in this rdd
run this
we can see now this rdd is just numbers
now we will create a new instance of a multiclass metrics using this rdd
metrics = multiclassmetrics predrictions rdd map tu -
ple
we can then display the confusion matrix by running
metrics confusionmatrix toarray trans - pose
we can see these results are similar to the confusion matrix in nine
generalization and overfitting are very important concepts in machine learning
we will cover them in the next three lectures
after this video you will be able to define what overfitting is
describe how overfitting is related to generalization and
explain why overfitting should be avoided
before we look at generalization and overfitting let first define some terms
that we will need to know to discuss errors in classification
recall that a machine learning model maps the input it receives to an output
for a classification model the model output is the predicted class label for
the input variables and the true class label is the target
then if the classifier predicts the correct classes label for
a sample that is a success
if the predicted class label is different from the true class label
then that is an error
the error rate then is the percentage of errors made over the entire data set
that is it is the number of errors divided by the total number of samples
in a data set
error rate is also known as misclassification rate or simply error
in our lesson on classification we discuss that there is a training phase in which
the model is built and a testing phase in which the model is applied to new data
the model is built using training data and evaluated on test data
the training and test data are two different data sets
the goal in building a machine learning model is to have the model perform well
on training as well as test data
error rate or simply error on the training data is refered to as training
error and the error on test data is referred to as test error
the error on the test data is an indication of how well the classifier
will perform on new data
this is known as generalization
generalization refers to how well your model performs on new data
that is data not used to train the model
you want your model to generalize well to new data
if your model generalizes well then it will perform well on data sets that
are similar in structure to the training data but
does not contain exactly the same samples as in the training set
since the test error indicates how well your model generalizes to new data
note that the test error is also called generalization error
a related concept to generalization is overfitting
if your model has very low training error but
high generalization error then it is overfitting
this means that the model has learned to model the noise in the training data
instead of learning the underlying structure of the data
these plots illustrate what happens when a model overfits
training samples are shown as points and
the input to output mapping that the model has learned is indicated as a curve
the plot on the left shows that the model has learned the underlying structure of
the data as the curve follows the trend of the sample point as well
the plot on the right
however shows that the model has learned to model the noise in a data set
the model tries to capture every sample point
instead of the general trend of the samples together
the training error and
the generalization error are plotted together during model training
what is the connection between overfitting and generalization
a model that overfits will not generalize well to new data
so the model will do well on just the data it was trained on but
given a new data set it will perform poorly
a classifier that performs well on just the training data set
will not be very useful
so it is essential that the goal of good generalization performance is kept in mind
when building a model
a problem related to overfitting is underfitting
overfitting occurs when the model is fitting to the noise in the training data
this results in low training error and high test error
underfitting on the other hand
occurs when the model has not learned the structure of the data
this results in high training error and high test error
both are undesirable
since both mean that the model will not generalize well to new data
overfitting generally occurs when a model is too complex that is
it has too many parameters relative to the number of training samples
so to avoid overfitting the model needs to be kept as simple as possible and yet
still solve the input output mapping for the given data set
we will discuss methods for
avoiding overfitting in the next couple of lectures
in summary overfitting is when your model has learned the noise in the training data
instead of the underlying structure of the data
you want to avoid overfitting so that your model will generalize well to new data
how do you evaluate your model performance
in this lecture we will look at different metrics that can be used to
evaluate the performance of your classification model
after this video you will be able to
discuss how performance metrics can be used to evaluate models
name three model evaluation metrics and explain why accuracy may be misleading
for the classification task an error occurs when the model prediction of
the class label is different from the true class label
we can also define the different types of errors in classification depending on
the predicted and true labels
let take the case with the task is to predict whether a given animal is
a mammal or not
this is a binary classification task with the class label being either yes
indicating mammal or no indicating non - mammal
then the different types of errors are as follows
if the true label is yes and the predicted label is yes
then this is a true positive abbreviated as tp
this is the case where the label is correctly predicted as positive
if the true label is no and the predicted label is no
then this is a true negative abbreviated as tn
this is the case where the label is correctly predicted as negative
if the true label is no and the predicted label is yes
then this is a false positive abbreviated as fp
this is the case with the label is incorrectly predicted as positive
when it should be negative
if the true label is yes and
the predicted label is no then this is a false negative abbreviated as fn
this is the case where the label is incorrectly predicted as negative
when it should be positive
these definitions can take a while to sink in so feel free to hit the pause button
and replay button several times here to review this part
these four different types of errors are used in calculating many evaluation
metrics for classifiers
the most commonly used evaluation metric is the accuracy rate or
accuracy for short
for classication accuracy is calculated as the number of
correct predictions divided by the total number of predictions
note that the number of correct predictions is the sum of the true
positives and the true negatives since the true and predicted labels match for
those cases
the accuracy rate is an intuitive way to measure the performance
of a classification model
model performance can also be expressed in terms of error rate
error rate is the opposite of accuracy rate
let look at an example to see how accuracy and error rates are calculated
the table on the left lists the true label along with the model prediction
for a data set of ten samples
first let s figure out the number of true positives
recall that a true positive occurs when the output is correctly predicted as
positive
in other words the true label is yes and the model prediction is yes
in this example there are three true positives as indicated by the red arrows
so tp = 3 remember that value as we will need it later
now let figure out the number of true negatives
a true negative occurs when the output is correctly predicted as negative
in other words the true label is no and the model prediction is no
in this example there are four true negatives as indicated by the green
arrows
so tn = 4 we will need to remember this value as well
now we use the values for tp and tn to calculate the accuracy rate
using the equation for accuracy rate we plug in three for tp and four for tn
we get seven correct predictions for the numerator
the denominator is simply the total number of samples in our data set which is ten
so the accuracy rate for
example is 7 out of 10 which is 0 7 or 70
the error rate is the exact opposite of the accuracy rate
to calculate the error rate we simply subtract the accuracy rate from 1
for our example that is 1 - 0 7 which is 0 3
so the error rate for this example is 0 3 or 30
there a limitation with accuracy and
error rates when you have a class imbalance problem
this is when there are very few samples of the class of interest and
the majority are negative examples
an example of this is identifying if a tumor is cancerous or not
what is of interest is identifying samples with cancerous tumors but
these positive cases where the tumor is cancerous are very rare
so you end up with a very small fraction of positive samples and
most of the samples are negative
thus the name class imbalance problem
what could be the problem with using accuracy for a class imbalance problem
consider the situation where only 3 of the cases are cancerous tumors
if the classification model always predicts non - cancer
it will have an accuracy rate of 97
since 97 of the samples will have non - cancerous tumors
but note that in this case the model fails to detect any cancer cases at all
so the accuracy rate is very misleading here
you may think that your model is performing very well with such
a high accuracy rate
but in fact it cannot identify any of the cases in the class of interest
in these cases we need evaluation metrics that can capture how
well the model classifies positive versus negative classes
a pair of evaluations metrics that are commonly used when there is a class
imbalance are precision and recall
precision is defined as the number of true positives divided by the sum of
true positives and false positives
in other words it is the number of true positives divided by the total number
of samples predicted as being positive
recall is defined as the number of true positives divided by the sum of
true positives and false negatives
it is the number of true positives divided by the total number of samples
actually belonging to the true class
here an illustration that shows precision and recall
the selected elements indicated by the green half circle are the true positives
that is samples predicted as positive and are actually positive
the relevant elements indicated by the green half circle and
the green half rectangle are the true positives plus the false negatives
that is samples that are actually positive but some are correctly predicted
as positive and some are incorrectly predicted as negative
recall then is the number of samples correctly predicted as positive
divided by all samples that are actually positive
the entire circle indicated by the green half circle and
the pink half circle are the true positives plus the false positives
that is samples that were predicted as positive
although some were actually positive and some were actually negative
then precision is the number of samples correctly predicted as positive
divided by the number of all samples predicted as positive
precision is considered a measure of exactness because it calculates
the percentage of samples predicted as positive
which are actually in a positive class
recall is considered a measure of completeness because it calculates
the percentage of positive samples that the model correctly identified
there is a trade off between precision and recall
a perfect precision score of one for a class c means that every sample
predicted as belonging to class c does indeed belong to class c
but this says nothing about the number of samples from class c that were predicted
incorrectly
a perfect recall score of one for
a class c means that every sample from class c was correctly labeled
but this does not say anything about how many other samples were
incorrectly labeled as belonging to class c
so they are used together
for example precision values can be compared for a fixed value of recall or
vice versa
the goal for classification is to maximize both precision and recall
precision and recall can be combined into a single metric called the f - measure
the equation for that is 2 times the product of precision and
recall divided by their sum
there are different versions of the f - measure
the equation on this side is for
the f1 measure which is the most commonly used variant of the f measure
with the f1 measure precision and recall are equally weighted
the f2 measure weights recall higher than precision
and the f0 5 measure weights precision higher than recall
the value for the f1 measure ranges from zero to one
with higher values giving better classification performance
in summary there are several metrics for
evaluating the performance of a classification model
they are defined in terms of the types of errors you can get in
a classification problem
we covered some of the most commonly used evaluation metrics in this lecture
namely accuracy and error rates precision and recall and f1 measure
in this lecture we will discuss how overfitting occurs with decision trees and
how it can be avoided
after this video
you will be able to discuss overfitting in the context of decision tree models
explain how overfitting is addressed in decision tree induction
define pre - pruning and post - pruning
in our lecture on decision trees we discussed that during the construction of
a decision tree also referred to as tree induction the tree repeatedly
splits the data in a node in order to get successively paired subsets of data
note that a decision tree classifier can potentially expand its nodes until it can
perfectly classify samples in the training data
but if the tree grows nodes to fit the noise in the training data
then it will not classify a new sample well
this is because the tree has partitioned the input space according to the noise in
the data instead of to the true structure of a data
in other words it has overfit
how can overfitting be avoided in decision trees
there are two ways
one is to stop growing the tree before the tree is fully grown
to perfectly fit the training data
this is referred to as pre - pruning
the other way to avoid overfitting in decision trees is to grow the tree to its
maximum size and then prune the tree back by removing parts of the tree
this is referred to as post - pruning
in general overfitting occurs because the model is too complex
for a decision tree model
model complexity is determined by the number of nodes in the tree
addressing overfitting in decision trees means controlling the number of nodes
both methods of pruning control the growth of the tree and consequently
the complexity of the resulting model
with pre - pruning the idea is to stop tree induction before a fully grown tree is
built that perfectly fits the training data
to do this restrictive stopping conditions for growing nodes must be used
for example a nose stops expanding if the number of samples in the node is less
than some minimum threshold
another example is to stop expanding a note if the improvement in the impurity
measure falls below a certain threshold
in post - pruning the tree is grown to its maximum size
then the tree is pruned by removing nodes using a bottom up approach
that is the tree is trimmed starting with the leaf nodes
the pruning is done by replacing a subtree with a leaf node if
this improves the generalization error or if there is no
change to the generalization error with this replacement
in other words if removing a subtree does not have a negative effect
on the generalization error then the nodes in that subtree only
add to the complexity of the tree and not to its overall performance
so those nodes should be removed
in practice post - pruning tends to give better results
this is because pruning decisions are based on information from the full tree
pre - pruning on the other hand may stop the tree growing process prematurely
however post - pruning is more computationally expensive since the tree
has to be expanded to its full size
in summary to address overfitting in decision trees tree pruning is used
there are two pruning methods pre - pruning and post - pruning
both methods control the complexity of the tree model
in this lecture we will discuss what a validation set is and
how it relates to overfitting and model performance evaluation
after this video you will be able to describe how validation sets can be
used to avoid overfitting
articulate how training validation and test sets are used
and list three ways that validation can be performed
in our lesson on classification
we discussed that there is a training phase in which the model is built and
a testing phase in which the model is applied to new data
the model is built using training data and evaluated on test data
the training and test data are two different datasets
the goal in building a machine learning model is to have the model perform well
on the training set as well as generalize well on new data in the test set
recall that a model that overfits does not generalize well to new data
recall also that overfitting generally occurs when a model is too complex
so to have a model with good generalization performance
model training has to stop before the model gets too complex
how do you determine when this should occur
a validation set can be used to guide the training process to avoid overfitting and
deliver good generalization performance
we have discussed having a training set and a separate test set
the training set is used to build a model and
the test set is used to see how the model performs a new data
now we want to further divide up the training data into a training set and
a validation set
the training set is used to train the model as before and
the validation set is used to determine when to stop training the model
to avoid overfitting in order to get the best generalization performance
the idea is to look at the errors on both training set and
validation set during model training as shown here
the orange solid line on the plot is the training error and
the green line is the validation error
we see that as model building progresses along the x - axis
the number of nodes increases
that is the complexity of the model increases
we can see that as the model complexity increases the training error decreases
on the other hand the validation error initially decreases but
then starts to increase
when the validation error increases this indicates that the model is overfitting
resulting in decreased generalization performance
this can be used to determine when to stop training
where validation error starts to increase is when you get the best generalization
performance so training should stop there
this method of using a validation set to determine when to stop training
is referred to as model selection
since you are selecting one from many of varying complexities
note that this was illustrated for a decision tree classifier but
the same method can be applied to any type of machine learning model
there are several ways to create and use the validation set to avoid overfitting
the different methods are holdout method
random subsampling k - fold cross - validation
and leave - one - out cross - validation
the first way to use a validation set is the holdout method
this describes the scenario that we have been discussing
where part of the training data is reserved as a validation set
the validation set is then the holdout set
errors on the training set and the holdout set are calculated at each step
during model training and plotted together as we have seen before
and the lowest error on the holdout set is when training should stop
this is the just the process that we have described here before
there some limitations to the holdout method however
first since some samples are reserved for the holdout validation set
the training set now has less data than it originally started out with
secondly if the training and holdout sets do not have the same data distributions
then the results will be misleading
for example if the training data has many more samples of one class and
the holdout dataset has many more samples of another class
the next method for using a validation set is repeated holdout
as the name implies
this is essentially repeating the holdout method several times
with each iteration samples are randomly selected from the original training data
to create the holdout validation set
this is repeated several times with different training and validation sets
then the iterates on the holdout set for the different iterations
are averaged together to get the overall iterate for model selection
a potential problem with repeated holdout is that you could end up with some samples
being used more than others for training
since a sample can be used for either testing or training any number of times
some samples may be put in the training set more times than other samples
so you might end up with some samples being overrepresented while
other samples are underrepresented in training or testing
a way to improve on the repeated holdout method is use cross - validation
cross - validation works as follows
segment the data into k number of disjoint partitions
during each iteration one partition is used as the validation set
repeat the process k times
each time using a different partition for validation
so each partition is used for validation exactly once
this is illustrated in this figure
in the fist iteration the first partition specified in green is used for
validation
in the second iteration the second partition is used for
validation and so on
the overall validation error is calculated by averaging the validation errors for
all k iterations
the model with the smallest average validation error then is selected
the process we just described is referred to as k - fold cross - validation
this is a very commonly used approach to model selection in practice
this approach gives you a more structured way to divide available data up between
training and validation datasets and provides a way to overcome the variability
in performance that you can get when using a single partitioning of the data
leave - one - out cross - validation is a special case of k - fold
cross - validation where k equals n where n is the size of your dataset
here for each iteration the validation set has exactly one sample
so the model is trained to using n minus one samples and
is validated on the remaining sample
the rest of the process works the same way as regular k - fold cross - validation
note that cross - validation is often abbreviated cv and leave - one - out
cross - validation is in abbreviated l - o - o - c - v and pronounced loocv
we have described several ways to use a validation set to address overfitting
error on the validation set is used to determine when to stop training so
that the model does not overfit
note that the validation error that comes out of this process can also be used
to estimate generalization performance of the model
in other words
the error on the validation set provides an estimate of the error on the test set
with the addition of the validation set
you really need three distinct datasets when you build a model
let review these datasets
the training dataset is used to train the model that is to adjust the parameters of
the model to learn the input to output mapping
the validation dataset is used to determine when training should stop
in order to avoid overfitting
the test data set is used to evaluate the performance of the model on new data
note that the test data set should never ever be used in any way to create or
tune the model
it should not be used for
example in a cross - validation process to determine when to stop training
the test dataset must always remain independent from model training and
remain untouched until the very end when all training has been completed
note that in sampling the original dataset to create the training validation and
test sets all datasets must contain the same distribution of the target classes
for example if in the original dataset 70 of the samples belong to one class and
30 to the other class then this same distribution should approximately
be present in each of the training validation and test sets
otherwise analysis results will be misleading
to summarize we have discuss the need for
three different datasets in building model
a training set to train the model a validation set to determine when to stop
training and a test to evaluate performance on new data
we learned how a validation set can be used to avoid overfitting and
in the process provide an estimate of generalization performance
and we covered different ways to create and
use a validation set such as k - fold cross - validation
now that we have seen what association analysis is
let go over the association analysis process in more detail
after this video you will be able to define the terms support and
confidence describe the steps in association analysis and
explain how association rules are formed from item sets
let review the set in association analysis
they are create item the sets then identify the frequent item sets
finally generate the rules
we will continue with this example dataset
there are five transactions in the dataset
each with a set of items purchased together
the goal is to come up with rules describing associations between items
the first step is to create item sets
item sets have different sizes which need to be created
we will color code the items so
that each one is easier to pick out from the transactions table
we start out with just 1 - item sets that is sets with just one item
the left table is the dataset of transactions
the right table contains the 1 - item sets that can be created from this dataset
as each item set is created we also need to keep track of the frequency at which
these item set occurs in the dataset
this is referred to support for the item set and
is calculated by dividing the number of times the item set occurs in the dataset
by the total number of transactions
this is what is in the support column in the right table
for example eggs the last item in the right table occurs
just occurs just once in the dataset in the transaction two
so if support is 1 5 or one fifth the item set with
diaper occurs in all transactions so if support is 5 5 or 1
the support for each item set will be used to identify frequent item sets
in the next step specifically the support issues to prune or
remove item sets that do not occur frequently
the support of each item set will be used to identify
frequent item sets in the next step
specifically the support is used to prune or
remove item sets that do not occur frequently
for example the minimum support threshold is set to 3 5
so looking at the 1 - item sets table we can remove any item set with
the support of less than 3 5
these item sets are highlighted in pink they will be removed before the sets for
two items are created
the final one item sets are then the item sets with bread milk beer and diaper
we only consider items that were in the one item sets that were not pruned
the two item sets are shown in the right table
we again need to keep track of the support for
these item sets just as we did with the one item sets
for example for the last item set with beer and
diaper we see by looking at the left table that beer and
diaper occur together three times in transactions two three and four
so with support is 3 5
again we need to prune item sets with low support
the ones highlighted in pink in the two item sets table
those would be the item set with bread and beer and the item set with milk and beer
the remaining two items that end
one item such or then use to create the three item sets
let look now at creating three item sets
the only three item sets that has a support value greater than minimum support
is the one shown in the right table
namely the items start with bread milk and diaper
the second step in association analysis is to identify the frequent item sets
but note that the process that we just described for
creating item sets already identifies frequent item sets
a frequent item set is one whose support is greater than or
equal to the minimum support
so by keeping track of the support of each item set as it is being created and
removing item sets with low support
we are already identifying frequent item sets
for our example the frequent one two and three item sets are shown here
now that we identified the frequent item sets the last step is to
generate the rules to capture associations that we see in the data
let first define some terms we will need to discuss association rules
the format of an association rule is shown at the top
it written as x arrow y and is read as if x then y
the x part is called the antecedent and
the y part is called the consequent of the rule
x and y are item sets
an important term in rule generation is the rule confidence
this is to find as a support for x and
y together divided by the support for x only
so rule confidence calculates the frequency of
instances to which the rule applies
recall that the support for x is the frequency of item set x and
is defined as the number of transactions containing items in x
divided by the total number of transactions
the rule confidence measures how frequently items in
y appear in the transaction that contain x
in other words the confidence measures the reliability of the rule by determining
how often if x and y is found to be true in the data
how is rule confidence used in rule generation
association rules are generated from the frequent item sets created from the data
each item in an item set can be used as a part of the antecedent or
consequent of the rule
and you can have many ways to combine items to form the antecedent and
consequent
so if we just simply generate rules from each frequent item set
we would end up with lots and lots of rules
each item set with k items can generate 2 to the k - 2 rules
that a lot of rules
and the majority of those rules would not be found in the data
this is where rule confidence comes in
we can use rule confidence to constrain the number of rules to keep
specifically a minimum confidence threshold is set and
only rules with confidence greater than or
equal to the minimum confidence are significant and only those will be kept
let look at how this works with our example dataset
we call that only one three item set was created from the transactions
that three items that contains items bread milk and
diaper as shown at the top
with these three item set let see how we can generate rules from it and
determine which rules to keep and which one to prune
let set the minimum confidence to 0 95
and here again is the definition for confidence
for candidate rule if bread and milk then diaper
we can calculate it confidence as follows the support for
both antecedent and consequent is the number of times we see bread milk and
diaper together in the data divided by the total number of transactions
items bread milk and diaper appear together in transaction 1 4 and
5 so the support is 3 5
the support for just the antecedent is the number of times we see bread and
milk together divided by the total number of transactions
items bread and milk appear together also in transactions 1 4 and 5
so the support is 3 5
the confidence of this rule is then 1 or 100
this means that the rule is correct 100
every time bread and milk are bought together diaper is bought as well
for candidate rule if bread and
diaper than milk we calculate its confidence the same way
the support for bread diaper and milk is 3 5 as before
items bread and diaper are paired together in transactions 1 2 4 and 5
so the support for the items set with bread and milk is 4 5
then the confidence with this rule is 0 75 or 75
since the minimum confidence is 0 95 or 95
the first rule is kept and the second rule is removed from consideration
there are several algorithms for association analysis
each uses a different set of methods to make frequent items set creation and
rule generation efficient
the more popular algorithms are apriori fp growth and eclat
as a summary we just looked at the steps in association analysis in more detail
we saw how items sets can be created from a dataset how frequent items sets can be
identified and how association rules can be created from frequent item sets and
pruned using rule confidence
we have looked at classification regression and cluster analysis
let now discuss association analysis as a machine learning task
after this video you will be able to explain what association analysis entails
list some applications of association analysis define what an item set is
in association analysis the goal is to come up with a set of rules to capture
associations between items or events
the rules are used to determine when items or events occur together
you may remember seeing these images earlier in the course where we introduced
the different categories of machine learning tasks and techniques
but do you remember what the association is between these items
well let recap that story in case you do not remember
the story goes like this
a supermarket chain used association analysis to discover
a connection between two seemingly unrelated products
they discovered that many customers who go to the store
late on sunday night to buy diapers also tend to buy beer
this information was then used to place beer and diapers close together
and they saw a jump in sales of both items
this illustrates that you can uncover unexpected and
useful relationships with association analysis
this diaper and beer story has become part of the data mining folklore
it unclear how much of it true but it has become the prime example of what you
can discover with association analysis and machine learning in general
a common application of association analysis is referred to as
market basket analysis
this is used to understand the purchasing behavior of customers
the idea is that you are looking into the shopping basket of customers
when they are at the market and
analyzing that data to understand what items are purchased together
this information can be used to place related items together or
to have sales on items that are often purchased together
another application of association analysis is to recommend items that
a customer may be interested in based on their purchasing or browsing history
this is very commonly used on companies websites
to get customers to buy more items
there are medical applications as well
analysis of patients and treatments may reveal associations to identify effective
treatments for patients with certain medical histories
this diagram illustrates how association analysis works
the data set is a collection of transactions
each transaction contains one or more items
this is referred to as the item set
from the given items sets
generate association rules that capture which item tend occur together
in our example the data set consists of five transactions
in the first transaction the items are diaper bread and milk
the second transaction has items bread diaper beer and eggs and so on
rules that could be generated from this data set are shown at the bottom
for example the first rule states that if bread and
milk are bought together then diaper is also bought
the second rule state that if milk is bought then bread is also bought
the association analysis process consist of the following steps
the first step is to create item sets
item sets are generated for sets with one item two items three items and so on
then frequent item sets are identified
frequent item sets are those that occur at least a minimum number of times
from the frequent item sets association rules are generated
we will take a more detailed look at these steps in the next lecture
some things to note about association analysis
like cluster analysis each transaction does not have a label to specify which
item set or rule it belongs to
so association analysis is an unsupervised task
you may end up with many rules at the end of the analysis
but whether those rules are interesting useful
or applicable requires interpretation using domain knowledge of the application
in addition
the association analysis process will not tell you how to apply the rules
this also requires knowledge of the application
so as with cluster analysis interpretation and analysis are required
to make sense of the resulting rules that you get from association analysis
in summary
association analysis finds rules to capture associations between items
the association rules have intuitive appeal because they are in the form of
if this then that which is easy to understand
the results of association analysis require analysis and
interpretation using domain knowledge to determine the usefulness and
applicability of the resulting rules
next we will cover the steps in the association analysis process in
more detail
in this activity we will use spark to perform cluster analysis
first we will load the minute weather data
next we will remove the unused and missing data and
then scale the data so that the mean is zero
we will then create an elbow plot a subset of the data
to determine the optimal number of clusters
and then cluster the full data set using k - means
finally we will generate parallel plots to analyze the individual clusters
let begin
first let open the clustering notebook
execute the first cell to load the libraries
execute the second cell to load the data set
this data set contains weather station measurements that were taken every minute
so there a lot of measurements
we can count how many rows there are in the data frame by running df count
this says that there are over 1 5 million rows in the data frame
clustering this much data on a single cloudera vm can take a lot of time
so let only work with one - tenth of the data
let subset the data into the new data frame
we will enter filtereddf
= df filter df rowid
10 = = 0
we then count the rows of the new data frame by calling filtereddf count
the new data frame has one - tenth as many rows as the original data set
let compute the summary statistics using describe
filtereddf describe and to display it nicely
we will enter topandas transpose
run this
these weather measurements were taken during the period of a long drought
as we can see from the mean values of the two rain measurements
rain accumulation the rain duration the measurements are close to zero
let count how many rain values are equal to 0
filterdf filter filterdf rain accumulation = =
0 0 count
now let do rain duration
filtereddf filter filtereddf rain duration = =
0 0 count
we can see from these counts that most in these two measurements are zero
so let remove them from our data frame
workingdf = filterdf drop rain accumulation drop -
rain duration
and we will also drop the column called hpwren timestamp
since we will not use it
so drop hpwren timestamp
next let drop rows with missing values and count how many rows were dropped
before = workingdf count workingdf =
workingdf na drop after = workingdf count
and finally we will print the difference before - after
so only 46 rows had missing values and were dropped
next let scale the data so that each feature will have a value of 0 for
the mean and a value of 1 for the standard deviation
first we need to combine the columns into a single vector column
we can look at the existing columns by entering workingdf columns
we do not want to include rowid since it is a row number
additionally the minimum wind measurements have a high correlation
to the average wind measurements so we will not include this either
let create an array of the columns we want to combine and
then use vector assembler to create the vector column
featuresused =
now let copy and paste the columns we want to use
assembler = vectorassembler inputcols = featuresused
outputcol = features unscaled
and finally assembled = assembler transform workingdf
run this
now we will use standard scaler to scale the data
scaler = standard scaler inputcol = features unscaler
outputcol = features withstd = true
withmean = true scalermodel = scaler fit assembled
scaleddata = scalermodel transform assembled
next we will create an elbow plot to determine the value k for
the number of clusters
to create the elbow plot we will calculate the within cluster
sum of squared error or wsse for different values of k
so since some valves running k - means many times let do it for
a smaller subset of the data since it will be faster
first let choose the data to work with
let subset the data
so scaleddata = scaleddata select features rowid
elbowset = scaleddata filter scaleddata rowid
3 = = 0 select features
and finally we will call the persist method on elbowset
persist will keep it in memory and make the calculations faster
run this
now let compute the wsse values for different values of k
we will do for k 2 to 30
clusters equals range 2 31
wsselist = utils elbow elbowset clusters
run this this will print out the value of wsse for each value of k
as you can tell this will take some time to run let skip to the end
now let display the plot of our data
utils elbow plot wsselist clusters
the x axis is k the number of clusters and the y axis is the wsse value
you can see that the graph flattens out between 10 and 15 for k
so let choose k equals 12 as the midpoint for our number of clusters
we will now cluster the data into 12 clusters using k - means
first let select the data we want to cluster
scaleddatafeat = scaleddata select features
scaleddatafeat persist
now i will perform the clustering using kmeans
kmeans = kmeans k = 12 seed = 1
model = kmeans fit scaleddatafeat and finally
transformed = model transform scaledatafeat
run this
we can now see the centre measurement of each
cluster by calling model clustercenters
it is difficult to compare the cluster centers just by looking at these numbers
so let use parallel plots to visualize them
p = utils pd centers featuresused
model clustercenters
let show the clusters for
dry days where the weather samples have low relative humidity
utils parallel plot p p are lative humidi - ty
< - 0 5 p
the x axis of this chart shows the different measurement types
the y values show the standard deviations with zero being the mean
each line is a different cluster and there are five clusters in this graph
we can see that they all have a low relative humidity
notice that cluster four the red one has a high average wind speed and
a high maximum wind speed
additionally it has a low average wind direction
which means it was coming from the north and northeast directions
so this cluster probably represents santa ana conditions
next let show the plot for warm days
the weather samples with high air temperature
utils parallel plot p p air temp
0 5 p
other clusters in this plot have air temperature greater than 0 5 standard
deviations away from the mean
however they have different values for the other features
now let show the clusters for cool days
weather samples with high relative humidity and low air temperatures
utils parallel plot p p are lative humidi - ty
0 5 p air temp
< 0 5 p
all the clusters in this plot have relative humidity greater than 0 5
standard deviations and air temp less than 0 5 standard deviations
these clusters represent cool temperature with high humidity and
possibly rainy weather patterns
so far we have seen all the clusters except two
since it is not falling to any other categories let plot this cluster
utils parallel plot p iloc 2
p
cluster two captures days with mild weather
in addition to classification and regression machine learning tasks and
techniques can also fall into another category known as cluster analysis
after this video you will be able to articulate the goal of cluster analysis
discuss whether cluster analysis is supervised or unsupervised and
list some ways that cluster results can be applied
in cluster analysis
the goal is to organize similar items in your data set into groups or clusters
by segmenting your data into clusters you can analyze each cluster more carefully
note that cluster analysis is also referred to as clustering
a very common application of cluster analysis that we have discussed before is
to divide your customer base into segments based on their purchasing histories
for example you can segment customers into those who have purchased science
fiction books and videos versus those who tend to buy nonfiction books
versus those who have bought many children books
this way you can provide more targeted suggestions to each different group
some other examples of cluster analysis are characterizing different weather
patterns for a region grouping the latest news articles into
topics to identify the trending topics of the day and
discovering hot spots for different types of crime from police reports
in order to provide sufficient police presence for problem areas
cluster analysis divides all the samples in a data set into groups
in this diagram we see that the red green and
purple data points are clustered together
which group a sample is placed in is based on some measure of similarity
the goal of cluster analysis is to segment data so that differences between samples
in the same cluster are minimized as shown by the yellow arrow and differences
between samples of different clusters are maximized as shown by the orange arrow
visually you can think of this as getting samples in
each cluster to be as close together as possible and
the samples from different clusters to be as far apart as possible
cluster analysis requires some sort of metric to
measure similarity between two samples
some common similarity measures are euclidean distance which is the distance
along a straight line between two points a and b as shown in this plot
manhattan distance which is calculated on a strictly horizontal and
vertical path as shown in the right plot
to go from point a to point b you can only step along either the x - axis or
the y - axis in a two - dimensional case
so the path to calculate the manhattan distance consists of segments
along the axes instead of along a diagonal path as with euclidean distance
cosine similarity measures the cosine of the angle between points a and
b as shown in the bottom plot
since distance measures such as euclidean distance are often used to measure
similarity between samples in clustering algorithms
note that it may be necessary to normalize the input variables so
that no one value dominates the similarity calculation
we discussed scaling and
normalizing variables in the lecture on feature transformation
normalizing is one method to scale variables
essentially scaling the input variables puts the variables on the same scale so
that all variables have equal weighting in the calculation
to determine similarity between samples
scaling is necessary when you have variables that have very different scales
such as weight and height
the magnitude of the height values which are in feet and inches
will be much smaller than the magnitude of the weight values which are in pounds
so scaling both variables to a common value range will
make the contributions from both weight and height equal
here are some things to note about cluster analysis
first unlike classification or regression in general
cluster analysis is an unsupervised task
this means that there is no target label for any sample in the data set
in general there is no correct clustering results
the best set of clusters is highly dependent
on how the resulting clusters will be used
there are numerical measures to compare two different clusters but
since there are no labels to determine whether a sample has
been correctly clustered there is no ground truth
to determine if a set of clustering results are truly correct or incorrect
clusters do not come with labels
you may end up with five different clusters at the end of a cluster
analysis process but you do not know what each cluster represents
only by analyzing the samples in each cluster
can you come out with reasonable labels for your clusters
given all this it is important to keep in mind that interpretation and
analysis of the clusters are required to make sense of and
make use of the results of cluster analysis
there are several ways that the results of cluster analysis can be used
the most obvious is data segmentation and the benefits that come from that
if you segment your customer base into different types of readers
the resulting insights can be used to provide more effective marketing
to the different customer groups based on their preferences
for example analyzing each segment separately can provide valuable insights
into each group likes dislikes and purchasing behavior just like we see
science fiction non - fiction and children books preferences here
clusters can also be used to classify new data samples
when a new sample is received
like the orange sample here compute the similarity measure between it and
the centers of all clusters and assign a new sample to the closest cluster
the label of that cluster
manually determined through analysis is then used to classify the new sample
in our book buyers preferences example a new customer can be classified as being
either a science fiction non - fiction or children books customer
depending on which cluster the new customer is most similar to
once cluster labels have been determined
samples in each cluster can be used as labeled data for a classification task
the samples would be the input to the classification model
and the cluster label would be the target class for each sample
this process can be used to provide much needed labeled data for classification
yet another use of cluster results is as a basis for anomaly detection
if a sample is very far away or
very different from any of the cluster centers like the yellow sample here
then that sample is a cluster outlier and can be flagged as an anomaly
however these anomalies require further analysis
depending on the application these anomalies can be considered noise and
should be removed from the data set
an example of this would be a sample with a value of 150 for age
for other cases these anomalous cases should be studied more carefully
examples of this are in a credit card fraud detection or
a network intrusion detection application
in these applications examples outside of the norm are the interesting cases
that should be looked at to determine if they represent potential problems
to summarize cluster analysis is used to organize similar data items into groups or
clusters
analyzing the resulting clusters often leads to useful insights
about the characteristics of each group
as well as the underlying structure of the entire data set
clusters require analysis and
interpretation to make sense of the results
since there are no labels associated with samples or clusters in a clustering task
in the next lecture we will discuss a specific algorithm for cluster analysis
k - means clustering is a simple yet effective algorithm for
cluster analysis that is commonly used in practice
after this video
you will be able to describe the steps in the k - means algorithm
explain what the k stands for in k - means and define what a cluster centroid is
recall a cluster analysis divides samples in a data set into groups or clusters
the idea is to group similar items in the same cluster where similar is defined
by some metric that measures similarity between data samples
so the goal of cluster analysis is to divide data sample
such that sample within a cluster are as close together as possible
and samples from different clusters are as far apart as possible
k - means is a classic algorithm used for cluster analysis
the algorithm is very simple
the first step is to select k initial centroids
a centroid is simply the center of a cluster as you see in the diagram here
next assign each sample in a dataset to the closest centroid
this means you calculate the distance between the sample and
each cluster center and assign a sample to the cluster with the closest centroid
then you calculate the mean
or average of each cluster to determine a new centroid
these two steps are then repeated until some stopping criterion are reached
here an illustration of how k - means works
a shows the original data set with some samples
and b illustrates centroids initially selected
c shows the first iteration
here samples are assigned to the closest centroid
in d the centroids are recalculated
e shows the second iteration
samples are assigned to the closer centroid
note that some samples changed their cluster assignments
and in f the centroids are recalculated again
cluster assignments and
centroid calculations are repeated until some stopping criteria is reached
and you get your final clusters as shown in f
how are the initial centroids selected
the issue is that the final cluster results are sensitive
to initial centroids
this means that cluster results with one set of initial centroids can be
very different from results with another set of initial centroids
there are many approaches to selecting the initial centroids for
k - means varying in levels of sophistication
the easiest and most widely used approach is to apply k - means several times
with different initial centroids randomly chosen to cluster you dataset
and then select the centroids that give the best clustering results
to evaluate the cluster results an error measure
known as the within cluster sum of squared error can be used
the error associated with a sample
within a cluster is the distance between the sample and the cluster centroid
the squared error of the sample then is the squared of that distance
we sum up all the squared errors for all samples for
a cluster to the get the squared error for that cluster
we then do the same thing for all clusters to get the final calculation for
the within - cluster sum of squared error for
all clusters in the results of a cluster analysis run
given two clustering results the one with the smaller within - cluster sum of squared
error or wsse for short provides the better solution numerically
however as we have discussed before there is no ground truth
to mathematically determine which set of clusters is more correct than the other
in addition note that increasing the number of clusters
that is increasing the value for k always reduces wsse
so wsse should be used with caution
it only makes sense to use wsse to compare two sets of clusters
with the same value for k and generate it from the same dataset
also the set of clusters with the smallest wsse may not
always be the best solution for the application at hand
again interpretation and
domain knowledge about what the cluster should represent and how they will be used
are crucial in determining which cluster results are best
now that there are several metrics that are used to evaluate cluster results as well
choosing the optimal value for k is always a big question in using k - means
there are several methods to determine the value for k
we will discuss a few here
visualization techniques can be used to determine the dataset to see if
there are natural groupings of the samples
scatter plots and
the use of dimensionality reduction are useful here to visualize the data
a good value for k is application - dependent
so domain knowledge of the application can drive the selection for the value of k
for example
if you want to cluster the types of products customers are purchasing
a natural choice for k might be the number of product categories that you offer
or k might be selected to represent the geographical locations of respondents to
a survey
in which case a good value for
k would be the number of regions your interested in analyzing
there are also data - driven method for determining the value of k
these methods calculate symmetric for
different values of k to determine the best selections of k
one such method is the elbow method
the elbow method for determining the value of k is shown on this plot
as we saw in the previous slide
wsse or within - cluster sum of squared error measures how much
data samples deviate from their respective centroids in a set of clustering results
if we plot wsse for different values for k we can see how this
error measure changes as a value of k changes as seen in the plot
the bend in this error curve indicates a drop in gain by adding more clusters
so this elbow in the curve provides a suggestion for a good value of k
note that the elbow can not always be unambiguously determined especially for
complex data
and in many cases the error curve will not have a clear suggestion for
one value but for multiple values
this can be used as a guideline for the range of values to try for k
we have discussed choosing the initial centroids and
looked at ways to select a value for k the number of clusters
let now look at when to stop
how do you know when to stop iterating when using k - means
one obviously stopping criterion is when there are no changes to the centroids
this means that no samples would change cluster assignments
and recalculating the centroids will not result in any changes
so additional iterations will not bring about any more changes
to the cluster results
the stopping criterion can be relaxed to the second stopping criterion listed here
which is when the number of sample changing clusters is below
a certain threshold say 1 for example
at this point the clusters are changing by only a few samples
resulting in only minimal changes to the final cluster results
so the algorithm can be stopped here
at the end of k - means we have a set of clusters each with a centroid
each centroid is the mean of the samples assigned to that cluster
you can think of the centroid as a representative sample for that cluster
so to interpret the cluster analysis results
we can examine the cluster centroids
comparing the values of the variables between the centroids will reveal
how different or alike clusters are and
provide insights into what each cluster represents
for example if the value for age is different for different customer clusters
this indicates that the clusters are encoding different
customer segments by age among other variables
in summary k - means is a classic algorithm for performing cluster analysis
it is an algorithm that is simple to understand and implement and
is also efficient
the value of k the number of clusters must be specified
and final clusters are sensitive to initial centroids
linear regression is a very common algorithm to build regression models
after this video you will be able to describe how linear regression works
discuss how least squares is used in linear regression define simple and
multiple linear regression
a linear regression model captures the relationship between a numerical output
and the input variables
the relationship is modeled as a linear relationship hence the linear
in linear regression
to see how linear regression works let take a look at an example from the iris
flower dataset which is a commonly used dataset for machine learning
this dataset has samples of different species of iris flowers
along with measurements such as petal width and petal length
here we have a plot with petal width measurements in centimeters on the x axis
and petal length measurements on the y axis
let say that we want to predict petal length based on petal width
then the regression task is this given a measurement for
petal width predict the petal length
we can build a linear regression model to capture this linear relationship between
the input petal width and the output petal length
the linear relationship for this samples is shown as the red line on the plot
from this example we see that linear regression works by finding the best
fitting straight line through the samples
this is called the regression line
in the simple case with just one input variable
the regression line is simply a line
the equation for a line is y = mx + b
where m determines the slope of the line and
b is the y intercept or where the line crosses the y axis
m and b are the parameters of the model
training a linear regression model means adjusting these parameters to
fit the regression line to the samples
the regression line can be determined using what is referred to
as the least squares method
this plot illustrates how the least squares method works
the yellow dots are the data samples
the red line is the regression line
the straight line that goes through the samples
this line represents the model prediction of the output given the input
each green line indicates the distance of each sample from the regression line
so the green line represents the error between the prediction
which is the value of the red regression line and the actual value of the sample
the square of this distance is referred to as the residual
associated with that sample
the least squares method finds the regression line
that makes the sum of the residuals as small as possible
in other words we want to find the line that minimizes the sum
of the squared errors of prediction
the goal of linear regression then is to find the best fitting straight line
through the samples using the least squares method
once the regression model is built we can use it to make predictions
for example given a measurement of 1 5 centimeters for
petal width the model will predict a value of 4 5 centimeters for
petal length base on the regression line that it has constructed
in linear regression if there is only one input variable then the task is
referred to as simple linear regression
in cases with more than one input variables
then it is referred to as multiple linear regression
to summarize linear regression captures the linear relationship
between a numerical output and the input variables
the least squares method can be used to build a linear regression model
by finding the best fitting line through the samples
we studied the machine learning process applied techniques to explore and
prepare data discussed the different categories of machine learning tasks
looked at metrics and methods for evaluating a model
learned how to use scalable machine learning algorithms for big data problems
and worked with two widely used tools to construct the machine learning models
i hope that the lectures along with the hands - on activities have given you
a sound and practical introduction to machine learning tools and techniques
i also hope that the course piqued your interest in the exiting and
rapidly developing field of machine learning for big data
keep in mind that the best way to learn machine learning
is to do machine learning
so i encourage you to go out and find a problem or data set that interest you
apply the techniques you have learned in this course to it and start analyzing
thank you for your time and effort on this course happy machine learning
if you recall we have previously discussed that the main categories of
machine learning tasks are classification regression
cluster analysis and association analysis
we have discussed classification in detail
now let look at the other categories starting with regression
after this video you will be able to define what regression is
explain the difference between regression and classification and
name some applications of regression
before we talk about regression let review classification
in a classification problem the input data is presented to the machine learning
model and the task is to predict the target corresponding to the input data
the target is a categorical variable
so the classification task is to predict the category or label of
the target given the input data
the classification example shown here is one we have seen before
the input variables are measurements such as temperature relative humidity
atmospheric pressure wind speed wind direction etc
the task for
the model is to predict the weather category associated with the input data
the possible values for
the weather category is sunny windy rainy or cloudy
since we are predicting the category this is a classification task
with that context in mind let now discuss regression
when the model has to predict a numeric value instead of a category
then the task becomes a regression problem
an example of regression is to predict the price of a stock
the stock price is a numeric value not a category
so this is a regression task instead of a classification task
note that if you were to predict not the actual price of the stock but whether
the stock price will go up or go down then that would be a classification task
that is the main difference between classification and regression
in classification you are predicting a category and
in regression you are predicting a numeric value
here are some examples where regression can be used
forecast the high temperature for the next day estimate the average housing price
for a particular region determine the demand for a new product a new book for
example based on similar existing products predict the power usage for
a particular power grid
this is what the data set might look like for
the regression task of predicting tomorrow high temperature
the input variables could be the high temperature for
today the low temperature for today and the month
and the target is the high temperature for tomorrow
the model has to predict this target value for each sample
recall that in a supervised task the target is provided
well for an unsupervised task the target is not available or not known
since the target label is provided for each sample here
the regression task is a supervised one similar to classification
as with classification building a regression model also involve two phases
a training phase in which the model is built and
a testing phase in which the model is applied to new data
the model is built using training data and evaluated on test data
similar to classification the goal in building a regression model is also to
have a model perform well on training data as well as generalize to new data
the use of three different datasets that we have previously discussed
also apply to regression
recall that the three datasets are used as follows
the training dataset is used to train the model that is to adjust the parameters of
the model to learn the input to output mapping
the validation dataset is used to determine when training should stop
in order to avoid over fitting
and the test dataset is used to evaluate the performance of the model on new data
in summary in regression the model needs to predict the numeric value
corresponding to the input data
since a target is provided for each sample regression is a supervised task
the target is always a numerical variable in regression
in the next lecture
we will discuss a specific algorithm to build a regression model
hello
welcome to the graph analytics module in the big data specialization
i am amarnath gupta a research scientist at the san diego supercomputer center
what do i do research on
well a number of different areas all generally related to data engineering
but the area i am recently very excited about has to do with graphs
now graphs or networks has many people call them
are about studying relationships and relationship patterns on objects
i became interested in graphs when i was a graduate student and
the professor in our artificial intelligence class showed us how a part of
human knowledge can be represented as a kind of graphs called semantic networks
she showed us how even very simple things like
relationships somewhere in a family can be represented and viewed as graphs
represent your knowledge huh
now that got me really excited
someday i thought this will be a really interesting topic to research on
what i did not realize then is that in just a few years graphs and
the need to model and analyze them would become so dominant in both academia and
industry that graphs will be found everywhere today
now we look at facebook linkedin twitter and many
many more companies that are thriving in the market with data
that are represented modeled and processed as graphs
now even the entire world wide web if you think about it
is a giant graph that people analyze
and that brings us to this course
now in this course i will introduce you to the wonderful world of graph analytics
specifically i would like to show how different
kinds of real world data science problems can be viewed and modeled as graphs
and how the process of solving them can apply analytical
techniques that used graph based methods that is algorithms
this course would have four models
in model one we will introduce graphs and different applications that use graphs
in model two we will cover a number of common techniques
mathematical and algorithm techniques that are used in graph analytics
in module three we will look at a graph database
and through some sort of a hands on guidance
we will show you how to store and query graph data with the database
in module four we will cover some strategies of handling very large
graphs and discuss how existing tools that are currently used by
the community are actually prints
thank you for joining this course and
i sincerely hope that you will find it both exciting and useful
happy learning
as we saw in these four examples what graphs are used for
are kind of different but they all show
different viewpoints from which you can use graphs for your analysis
since this course focuses on graph analytics
i would like to briefly recap what the term means
analytics is the ability to discover meaningful patterns and
interesting insights into data using mathematical properties of data
it covers the process of computing with mathematical properties and
accessing the data itself efficiently
further it involves the ability to represent and
work with domain knowledge as we saw in use case two with biology
finally analytics often involves statistical modeling techniques for
drawing inferences and making predictions on data
with analytics we should be able to achieve the goals shown here
take a minute to read
therefore graph analytics is a special case of analytics where
the underlying data can be modeled as a set of graphs
so in this video we will going to talk about graph analytics
within the context of this big data specialization
so in the previous courses you know about the three important v of big data
so the three well - known v are volume velocity and variety
we will also talk about a lesser - known v which is called valence
okay what we want to talk about is
what impact these things have on graph data
so for volume let take a dataset like
the load network of the united states
well that a pretty large graph
so when we say volume i mean that the size of the graph
is much larger than what you might have
in the memory of a reasonable computer or real computing infrastructure
now we will see what impact the size
of the graph has on analytic operations
what we mean by velocity when it comes to graphs
well think of facebook again
so these little graphs are updates
so you write a post then like somebody else post and make a comment
that a bunch of updates
that comes and adds to your graph
well then ten minutes later you do something similar and
that also comes and adds to the graph
then your friend does the same thing it adds to your graph
so as time goes by you are sending more edges to your graph
and the speed at which you are doing this for
at least like facebook can be really really high
so the rate of update in facebook is really high
this is what is called streaming edges into graphs
and there can be multiple streams for various reasons
what do we mean by variety
for graphs it means that the graph is collecting data from various places
and all these different places are giving different kinds of information to
the graph
so in the end the graph has more non - uniform and
complex information potentially coming from multiple sources
that what we mean by variety when we refer to graphs
that picture there by the way is different kinds of protein interactions
the next one the less - known one is valence
now if you remember your chemistry this comes from valence electrons
which are electrons in an atom which are used for bonding
the other electrons are called core electrons
so the idea is if we increase the valence of the graphs
you increase the connectiveness of the graph
how we will see
now graph size clearly impacts analytics
why a it takes more space but more importantly it increases the algorithmic
complexity of any operation that you want it to on the graph
now we will see an example of that but what happens as
a result is that the data - to - analysis time becomes high
so i put in some data and i wanted to do this analysis
but there is so much data that my analysis takes way longer than it should
let give a simple example an example we have seen before
remember we had this little graph from our biological example where we
were asking find a simple path between alzheimer disease and colorectal cancer
and in this case the result is obvious
now let pause and ask
there are two nodes that i mentioned in this case
my colorectal cancer and alzheimer disease nodes
and we are asking is there a simple path connecting them
this is called a decision problem
i give you a data and i am asking does such a simple path exist or not exist
but this is actually a very hard decision problem
and the computer scientists will tell you that this is a very complicated problem
because it has a very high complexity
let ask another question
well how many simple paths now i want to count
how many simple paths exist between these two nodes
indeed it is another hard computing problem
and if you really want to know the size of the result
in the worst case is exponential in the number of nodes
so if we increase the number of nodes and edges if we increase the size of
the graph such a seemingly simple question can take a very very very long time
so that it almost practically impossible to compute it for
a really large graph if we have no other information supporting
that the worst case
but when we say algorithmic complexity increases that what we mean
let talk about velocity and i said our favorite example is facebook
so we are adding a bunch of updates which means we are adding a bunch of edges
we are streaming the edges into the data and we want to compute a metric
we want to see what is the shortest distance
between person a and person b or item a and item b
or i want to know that facebook has communities
twitter has communities like we saw
and how many people out there in these communities and
how many such communities are there like a facebook group
now if you want to compute this metric and you get this
edges very fast it is very difficult to know when you have the answer
because you are going to get an increasing number of edges in the system
and you keep computing this metric that you want to find the answer for and
it will turn out that your continuous stream does not fit in memory
because your memory is limited compared to the amount of
edges or edge updates you are streaming into the system
so that what is happened when you have high velocity information
very soon your memory runs out and you want to compute
your answer right now from the data that you have
okay let look at variety also known as heterogeneity
there are two aspects of heterogeneity
one we have already mentioned graph data is often created through integration
like we saw in the case of the biology
and therefore the variety comes because the nature of data is very different
also they may not be all the same kind of data
for example the data may come from a relational database
it may come from an xml database
it may come from another graph
it may come from a document
it may even come from complex things like social networks
like citation networks between papers or patents between interaction networks
between web entities which are connected through links
and from human knowledge that has been represented as graphs through ontologists
so all of these graphs the nodes and the edges do not mean the same thing
and somehow in there you need to capture what it means to have
an edge because that will determine what you can do with the edge
a simple example in an ontology
is something that says a is a b and b is a c so a is a c
the a is a c is an inference that you do given the other two relationships
what would be an example
my pet is a dog and the dog is a mammal therefore my pet is a mammal
you want to do inferences for some edges likes is a
now you need to know this
you do not do this with the biology example where you are looking at genes and
proteins because that operation does not make sense when you have genes and
proteins
so therefore every graph may have a different semantics
and what happens with variety is the number of sub - semantics and
the number of valid operations that you can do
that changes and that becomes more complex
now valence i said is about connectedness
it is also about interdependency among data
so if i have a higher valence which means i have more data elements that
are more strongly related and these relationships can be exploited
in most cases the part where valence becomes important
is that it increases over time which means parts of the graph becomes denser
and the average distance between node pairs decreases
let me show you here is my gmail
and i have plotted my gmail graphs from 2006 to about two months back
when i first started using it i had these users
a very few users and they are not really related
now with time more and
more people started communicating with me through gmail
and more and more of these people were also talking amongst themselves and
copying me and responding to me
by the end you would see that you can find dense groups
within my gmail because the information and
the connectedness between people have evolved and become more dense over time
this is the phenomenon of valence and this is very important to study because
you want to study things like what parts of the graph have become more dense
and why have they become more dense
maybe something was going on
maybe there was an event that brought these people together
and you want to analyze that and find that out from your graph analytics
that why you want to understand the effect of valence
you also want to understand what do i do if the graph becomes very very dense
in a place so that finding a path through that dense space becomes very hard
you will see in a later video that when this happens the computer system
that is trying to process these graphs in a parallel and distributed way has to do
something special to handle these increasing density in parts of the graph
so before we go into graph analytics the first question we want to ask is
what is a graph
let see
this is a plot of the sales of some items against time and
it gives you a nice visual representation of the data but is it a graph
while you think about it let try another one
this is another common visual representation of data
if you go to google and type pie graph
you will see many results that look like this
but is this a graph
in our research this is not a graph
we call it a chart
yes you guessed it right this time
this too is a chart and not a graph
so why do people call them graphs then
in a sense they are abbreviating
a chart depicts what is called a graph of a function
let me explain
look at the two column table on the right
the first column has information about product category
with values like furniture office supplies and technology
the second column represents another set of values called total containing 1724
4610 and 2065
now we can define our mapping option
which means a correspondence from product category to total
so we map furniture to the value 1 724
office supplies to the value 4 610 and so forth
if we visually portray this
we can represent it like a bar chart or a pie chart
this is why both the previous diagram and this diagram are charts and not graphs
graph analytics has its basis in a brand of mathematics called graph theory
what is more interesting
however is that graph theory was born out of a very practical problem
the problem started in a very old city in prussia which is now in russia
called konigsberg
even if we look at in in google maps it would sort of look like this
one of the interesting features of konigsberg is that it has two islands and
these islands are connected by seven bridges
back in 1736 the city wanted to create a walkway and the criteria was
this walkway would traverse all seven bridges such that somebody
wanting to go from one part of the city to another can cross a bridge only once
now this is sort of an urban planning problem right
well in fact it required a mathematician to solve the problem
the mathematician named euler shown on the left looked at this and
figured out that you really cannot create such a walk
why
he said it cannot be done because there are an odd number of bridges and
proved it mathematically
from this problem the whole field called graph theory emerged
on the right you can see edsger dijkstra a well - known computer scientist who has
developed graph algorithms one of which we will study later in the course
his work has had far further impact on both the theoretical computer science and
practical applications
what is the difference between the mathematics view and
the computer science view
let try to define the mathematical view of graphs
we start with a set of vertices
here we have a set of six nodes or vertices
now i will add another set
i will call this the set of edges
in our diagram there are only four edges but
there something special about these edges
each edge is just not an ordinary atomic object
an edge like e1 actually is one term from v and then a second term from v
so this edge e1 goes from v1 to v5
pictorially we can draw and arrow from v1 to v5
now if i had said v5 to v1 the arrow would be reversed
so what do we have so far
we have a set of vertices and a set of edges
that is the mathematical definition of a graph
what about the computer scientist definition
of course a computer scientist needs to adhere to the mathematical definition but
they want to represent and manipulate the same information
so they need a data structure
in other words something they can operate on
so what kind of operations would they do
well with a graph
they can say add edge or add a new vertex find the nearest neighbors of
the vertex where the term neighbor refers to the nodes connected to the vertex
we said a computer scientist needs to represent graphs using data structures
here is one that you should recognize
it a matrix called the adjacency matrix of a graph
both the rows and columns of this matrix represent notes
if i go from v1 one along the row i see that there one at v3
which means there is an edge from v1 to v3
similarly there is another from v1 to v5
let look at some operation
let say i first want to add an edge from v3 to v2
what should i do
i will start from the row v3
go up to the column v2 and add a 1 in that set
so i have added an edge which is an operation on the matrix
another operation
i want to get the neighbors a v3
this will be a little more complicated
i look at the row v3 and paint that row and
i will also look at the column v3 and paint that column
if we go down the row of v3 we will get v2 so v2 is neighbor
and if we go down the column of v3 we will get v1 and v6
so v1 and v6 have alternators
what is the difference
since the matrix has the from along the rows and the tos along the columns
following the row v3 gives us the edges outgoing from v3
and following the column v3 gives us the edges coming into v3
is this the only representation of the graph
no it not
here is another one
in this representation there are two kinds of data objects
no data which are the blue rectangles and edge data which are the triangles
to get a sense of this representation look at the note v1 and
follow the top yellow line
it will reach v3
so this link structure directly captures the graph diagram we created before
now start from v1 again and follow the blue link and
it will reach e1 and then v3
so that tells you that e1 is an edge object between v1 and v3
next let stand on the edge triangle e1 and follow the red
dashed line to get to e2 which is the next edge from the same starting node
is this possibly too complex
yes it is
however as we will see down the road many graph database systems are using this kind
of data structure internally so that the database operations become more efficient
in the first example of graph analytics for
big data we will consider the social media called twitter
and graphs representing tweets
what types of objects and relationships does a tweet have
well in fact tweets consist of many of the same elements and
relationships as the facebook posts
tweets have users they contain text
tweets can point to one another or to url they have hashtags they can
include reference to various other types of media but what about relationships
well much like facebook relationships and
tweets are more reflective of what the users do with tweets
for example people create tweets they respond to tweets
they mention other users and so forth
let look at these relationships in detail
in this graph all of the light blue notes are tweets and
all of the purple notes are users
when a specific user creates a specific tweet
an entity is created in the graph as a result
we will come back to this graph in the next few slides
so what we want to do with it
well to be very specific
this graph was created from tweets of a bunch of online gamers
in this case we were monitoring the tweets of all people
who played particular online video game
typically gamers are very excited about their video games
they are exited about their characters of the video games and they want to
discuss the video games they are excited about when new versions are released
so what are the data science questions here
people who look at these things such as behavioral psychologists want to know
if you are a war game user or if you play any other violent game where
there is a lot of fighting online do these people also show violent behavior
maybe they do maybe they do not
they also want to know whether as a result of looking at somebody tweets and
following them over time they can tell if the person is addicted to the game or not
so why use graphs for that
one of the things you could do is what we showed here
from the graphs you can extract certain elements like conversations
if you look at it you will see all of them have somebody posting something
somebody responding to the post and the first person responding to the response
they are retweeting and they are responding and so forth
you would see a conversation chain going on which can be short or long
like you see and other people would join in
we do not know if it violent or not but
at least there is a lively conversation going on about something
using graphs we could find some meaningful parts of a graph
that we can further analyze using techniques like text analytics
another kind of thing people would like to identify
is which players are interacting with which other players
who are these people
do they form a close community
can anybody join in
are there groups what are the groups
if you find a group who are the most influential users
who are the people that everybody refers to listens to and so on
graph analytics is used to answer all these questions about a conversation
that going on live in social media stream
let look at our next example
our second use case is about biology
interactions arise naturally in biology
genes produce proteins proteins regulate the functions of other proteins
cells transmit signals to other cells
these functional genes lead to pathological conditions that
present themselves as observable phenotypes
some of these interactions that are observed and measured by experiment lists
another class of graph relations represent human knowledge
for example an edge may denote an anatomical association such as
the nucleuses inside a cell part of the cerebral cortex is part of the brain
similarly one can encode different
classifications of entities like both humans and dogs and mammals
researchers also find these relationships from literature
or by computational techniques like bioinformatics algorithms
there are many bioinformatics algorithms that find statistical correlations between
genes and proteins
many biological networks are created by creating edges between entities because
they are strongly correlated based on measurements like gene expression level
yet a third category of computed relationships
associates terms by mining scientific literature
if two entities are co - mentioned in scientific articles very often
then there is a likelihood that these two entities are related
in this case the edge between them does not depict a specific relationship but
the fact they are associated
all these interactions can be assembled into networks of graphs where the nodes
are biological entities and edges represent different categories of
molecular interactions associations between diseases and
now there are two issues i would like you to understand
first graphs like the one we saw are assembled
that is integrated from many data sources produced by many independent science
groups who have different research goals use different scientific techniques
but the underlying biological entities are common across many groups
it is the commonality that helps us stitch together these logic graphs
second as more results get linked and integrated the size of the networks grow
leading to big data problems and the need for big data technology
now let ask the same question
why graphs
in bio medicine people are always trying to discover new science for
instance they want to discover unknown relationships
for example they can take two diseases very different diseases colorectal
cancer and alzheimers disease and they might want to ask are they related
if so can you connect the dots and
find out what the intervening network between them is
it turns out as you can see there are several genes that directly or
indirectly connect these two diseases
thus we can use path finding techniques like this to discover previously
unknown connections in a network
in addition
researchers sometimes think to explore the networks to help their discovery process
i have collaborated with a group that is using graph exploration techniques
to figure out how phenotypes of undiagnosed diseases all fit together
our third use case is about the human information network
that means a personal information network
the graphic you see there is my linkedin network
everybody who is on my linkedin is a node
and if they know each other there an edge between them
you can possibly see some groups or clusters there
one analytical question we will explore in module two
is how to discover these groups automatically
now of course with linkedin we only have professional information
but it is prudent to ask whether
one can integrate the professional network with other forms of personal information
this would be other social media data like my friendship network from facebook or
google or it could be information like my outlook email network
one can add even more information and put that interpersonal relationships
for example professor norman who is on my contact list is my director
and if we add my calendar to this
one can find events that i will be attending and people that i will be meeting
taking it even further for
special applications you might actually include financial and
business transactions or performance in activities
or fitness information or the location from my gps
now if you add all of these questions we should ask what we do with these things
let see
one use of this kind of information is matching
for example matching people with jobs is not just a matter of screening
series based on job descriptions or evaluating their job experience
to recruit for high level positions like the board of directors of a company
you need to evaluate the network of the candidate to determine their relationships
with important organizations groups and individuals
for some tasks like choosing a surgeon
you might also want inspect their social media ratings
in other classic applications we might want to look for
people who can influence a human network
suppose we are in an election campaign team and
need our message to get to as many people as possible in a city
we can not go door to door ourselves we need to go to some people and
these people will reach others on our behalf
graph analytic techniques may help identify the fewest number of people
who will have maximal reach into most of the potential voters in the city
a third category of application is threat detection
this network is created by groups who study news
for example they collect information about all
the militant groups in different countries and all the reported acts of terrorism
this creates a network as you can see
we show only a part of the network
in this graph view the green notes are groups and
the pink notes are deemed individuals
it should be clear that some of these individuals and
groups are more closely associated than others
discovering and tracking these groups their current activities
together with an analysis of details of the events they are associated with might
help analysts to get deeper insight into the networks and
perhaps anticipate their future activities
our fourth and last use case has to do with smart cities
now a city is a geographically bounded space and
contains many different networks operating within the same spatial domain
what kind of networks
let see
it has transportation networks
water and sewage networks power transmission networks
your ip broadband networks
some of these networks have multiple subtypes for
example transportation networks include the bus networks the subway network
the surface street network and the railway network and so on
these networks form a physical infrastructure and therefore
can be represented as graphs where each node has a geographic coordinate
but some of these networks can also be thought of as a commodity flow network
people flow through transportation networks
sewage material flows through a sewage network and so on
for many of these networks
a city planner would like to make sure that they cover the entire city
that commute time is optimized traffic congestions are well planned
to accomplish this they would need to create what is called a network model
for example urban planners develop city traffic model servicing
a traffic model will use both the geographic layout and
connectivity of the network along with the flow parameters like
the number of commuters getting on board at any station
well if we are planning to create a smart hub
we need to make sure that all the right things happen at the same place
people who come out of a metro station find nearby businesses
they find nearby facilities
those facilities should have broadband network for
people who are going to go on their mobile phones
the same places need to have a water supply network and
you have to plan it in such a way that all these networks
who exist within a certain distance of each other
and all the facilities can be planned accordingly
beyond normal operations
we also need to model what would happen if the network gets disrupted
what are the kinds of congestion or traffic that might disturb the network
therefore these graphs are no longer just structures but they represent things like
congestions things like people behavior and materials behavior over the network
one should also compute energy use patterns for
the busy parts of the network in order to figure out how the network structure or
the network flow can be altered to enable energy optimal operations
as we saw in these four examples
what graphs are used for are kind of different but
they all show different view points from which you can use graphs for analysis
so this course focuses on graph analytics
i would like to briefly recap what the term means
analytics is the ability to discover meaningful patterns and
interesting insights into data using mathematical properties of data
it covers a process of computing with mathematical properties and
accessing the data itself efficiently
further it involves the ability to represent and
work with domain knowledge as we saw in use case two with biology
finally analytics often involves statistical modeling techniques for
drawing inferences and making predictions on data
with analytics we should be able to achieve the goals shown here
therefore graph analytics is a special piece of
analytics where the underlying data can be modeled as a set of graphs
in the previous video we learned what a graph is
we gained insight into both the mathematician view and
the computer scientist view
now we want to look at the big picture of graph analytics
why are we doing what we are doing and
why do i need a graph representation on graph analytics
let start with a graph network which you may already be familiar with facebook
here is my facebook page
let look at it and consider some of the elements it contains
there is a primary user and that me
there are my friends
and typically there are some posts some of which may have media in them
such as video
what else does it have
well let consider what is inside a post
the post contains text
it has tags
i tag some people some people comment on my post
if somebody commenting
then that means there must be a commenter who is also a user in the facebook
other people like my post or
they like a comment and they also respond to some of the comments
many posts have locations associated with them as well
when we consider all of these together do you see the graph
well if not we will show you
here we see very much the same types of information but now they are in a graph
first notice me on the far left
if you look carefully at this graph you will also notice there are relations labeled
friend - of and created post and parts of the post and everything that you saw
before that are now organized in terms of objects and relationship speaking objects
the objects here on the post comments on the post replies to the comments and so
forth and the relationships also include tagged in or refers to
so this is sort of the big picture right
next we will look at 4 specific use cases in four different disciplines
the first one will be on social media
the second one will be on biology where we will look at genes and diseases
the third one will be human information network which means personal information
and the fourth one will be on smart cities
let go through these examples one by one
we will go over the logic of dijkstra algorithm without writing code
if you are an advanced student and
know the algorithm you can skip to the next lecture
the basic plan is to start from node i and
progressively traverse a sequence of notes
when the method attempts to choose the next node to traverse to
it chooses a node for which the total rate of the path to that node is the lowest
in the beginning the algorithm is on the start node i
the distance from i to i is 0
and the distance to all other nodes is infinity
because the system does not know them yet
a second table called a priority queue
is currently exactly the same as the distance row of the first array
the system starts with processing node i the source node
that means it finds the nodes that can reach from i f and j
note that the respective total weights that is 5 for f
and 15 for j to get to these nodes in the distance row
then it marks i as done
we have made the node i agree because the node is processed
next it looks at row d to find the least distance which is 5
the corresponding vertex is f
so next the method traverses to f
now the algorithm on node f and has determined that out of its possible
destinations e g and j j is the least expensive
the total path that is the weight of the path to j is 10
5 from i to f plus 5 from f to j
this diagram shows that the priority is now shorter because it has
popped out the already processed load i
at step three we are processing node j but face the following situation
we can go back to f from j but
that will cost 10 plus 15 that is 25
25 is worse than the cost of the current path to f which is 5 directly from i
thus we do not go from f to j and do not update the distance shown
the other option is to go from j to g which incurs a cost of 10 plus 5 15
hm this does not improve the current cost to reach g through f
which is now at 15 already
therefore we do not update the distance for g
so at this point we see that while j is processed
it had no impact on the traversal process
we consider the distance row again and find that the next node to expand is g
which is reached through f
continuing as before g processed
it opens up the possibility of diverging to c at a cost of 35
or to d at the cost of 25
but wait we have an issue there are two competing nodes
e coming form f or d coming from g that are both expansion candidates
at this point
the algorithm can make a random choice because there is no other information
let say we make an arbitrary choice we expand to e next
in an optional video we will see
how we can use the additional information to make a more informed decision
after expanding to e
we can find that we have already reached the node b so we are done
the other choice that is to go to d from g costs less than the path through b but
it does not matter now because the destination is reached
just for the sake of completeness if we did let the algorithm continue to operate
it will terminate when all reachable nodes are reached
we say all reachable nodes become some nodes like h
are not reachable because it has no incoming edge
such a node as we said before is called the root node of the graph
in general a graph can have more than one root node
now that we have reached our destination we need to construct the shortest path
we start by taking the destination b and find its predecessor e
then we find the node e and check its predecessor which is f
finally we find the predecessor of f to obtain i
which is a source node for the task
so these nodes can then be stretched together in reverse
thus building i to f to e to b which is highlighted in the film
so how well does this algorithm work for big graphs
actually not very well
we often measure the performance of an algorithm
in terms of the size of the data
so we saw that the dijkstra algorithm has a very high worst case complexity
despite the high complexity of the algorithm there are several
practical improvements that will enhance the performance of the method
one of them is bi - directional dijkstra algorithm
the idea is very simple we will go forward from the source now and
backward from the target node and stop when the two expanding frontiers meet
we will briefly illustrate the process without going deep into
the details of every step
so the technique starts just like the regular method
the control moves from i to f at a cost of 5
but then it switches and
starts from the target and moves backward along the edges
so from a it comes to d or c
we will chose d because an ad is a least weight part
now the forward step is performed again and we traverse from f to g
we are skipping the expansion to j because as we saw before
it does not contribute to the path
so the total rate of the ifg path is 15
the backward process then reaches g through d
the cost of the ifg is 15
and the cost of adg is also 15
we stop because a common node is reached
we need to ensure that the weight of the forward path and
that of the reverse path are added and the total combined rate is minimal
at this point we can concatenate the partial paths
to construct the full shortest path which is ifgda
now one point to remember is that the length of the smallest weight path
can be longer than the shortest hop path
here the fca path has 2 hops but a weight of 20
but the weight of the 3 hop path fgda is 15
so just remember that
the final type of analytics we will discuss in this module
is called centrality analysis
we call something central if it in the middle of a larger entity
we also call something central if it important and vital
for graphs we will identify important notes by looking at how central they are
in the graph
look at the the six node graph you do not have to know a lot
to figure out that the orange node is pretty important why
well one reason could be it the most vulnerable node
if you remove it the graph will fall apart
because this is clearly one way to look at the centrality of the node
but it not the only way
another way of looking at the orange node
is that it can reach all other nodes quicker than any other node
so this is the idea behind influences
people in a social network who are connected enough to reach out and
possibly influence a lot more people than others will be able to
if the little graph represents a transportation network
and you were asked to build a restaurant somewhere around this network
you will possibly choose an area near the central node
because more traffic will flow through this node than other nodes
and some of them will get out at the station and
bring business to your restaurant
we can give many more examples
in biological networks house - keeping genes are genes needed for
the maintenance of basic cellular function and
are expressed in all cells of an organism under normal and
abnormal conditions these genes are central because they are vital and
they are connected to many other nodes in the biological network
so much so that they need to be taken out of the network so
that the rest of the network can be studied
out of all these examples we will focus on a kind of problem
researchers have called the key player problem
the problem comes in two flavors
now take a little time to read the two examples
the first is sort of a negative piece
we have a network and we are trying to find a small subset of people
who removal will maximally disrupt the network
the key operative word here is maximally
so if there is a node which removal breaks the network into two parts
it is not what we want if there another two nodes
whose removal will break the network into ten parts
the second case however is a lot more conventional
the goal is to find a small set of nodes with maximal combined reachability
to other nodes
that means taken together these nodes should reach almost all other nodes
you should know that people use two terms to
characterize a general concept of network centrality
the first one centrality is about a node
it measures how central the node is with respect to the network
so the orange node in the left graph has high centrality and
the blue nodes have low centrality
the second term centralization is about the network
now look at the graph on the right
where the dark orange node is still very central for the light orange node and
between the other nodes and therefore has reasonable centrality
as more nodes start having higher centrality
the centralization of the network drops
because there is less variation in the centrality values of the network
so for each type of centrality that we discuss next we can compute the network
centralization by considering the sum of the difference between the maximum
centrality and the centrality of the node divided by the maximum centrality
there are thirty different measures of centrality
we will consider only a few of them and
explore the conceptual principles supported here
the first and the most intuitive measure is degree centrality
quick measures the degree of a node divided by the possible edges it
could have if it connected to each of the other n - 1 nodes in the graph
now we have seen this before
this measure gives us a sense of the hubness of the node
the higher the number is the more hub - like the node is
thinking of our second key player problem
one way to approach this is to find a hub - like measure for
a group with multiple nodes
instead of measuring the degree centrality of individual nodes
the measure simply counts the number of edges coming into the group as a whole
compared to the number of outsiders
in our example two red nodes here together connect to all blue nodes
although there is just one node neighboring both of them
closeness centrality takes a different approach to the centrality problem
it acts the shortest distance of a node to all other nodes and
divides it by a minus one
so in our graph a node like i which is on the periphery of the graph
will be quite far from all nodes in general and
therefore will have a very high closeness centrality value
on the other hand nodes like f c and h are much closer to all other nodes
know that we define this measure in terms of shortest paths
so if a moving object like information flows to the shortest path
in the network f is more likely to receive them earlier than other nodes
and therefore can process into other nodes more quickly
therefore
if we look to inject a new piece of information into the network with the idea
that it should read every other node quickly i should possibly inject it at f
recall however that node information flow is two shortest routes
an example is gossip that tends to travel through centrality nodes
closeness centrality does not work well for these types of information nodes
another very popular centrality measure is called betweenness centrality
for any node it measures the fraction of shortest paths flowing through that node
compared to the number of shortest paths in the graph
since b is at one end its between a centrality is 0
but let look at a
a is in the path from b to e
so is d
therefore a score for the b to e path is 0 5
similarly its score for the c to e path is also 0 5 making the total score 1
e is in the path from a to d for there is one more
path from a to do through c so e score is 0 5
now can you verify why c score is 3 5
betweenness centrality is typically used for
problem where a commodity is flowing through the network
as in the case of closeness centrality
any quantity that does not flow in shortest path channels like infection or
rumor on the internet does not work well with betweeness centrality
this lesson on graph analytics is about identifying and
tracking groups of interacting entities in a network
we call these groups communities
let try to provide a more concrete definition of communities in a network
we multiply the definition by this diagram
showing a research study on the santa fe institute
a theoretical research institute located in santa fe new mexico us
they performed multidisciplinary studies on fundamental principles
of complex adaptive systems
the nodes in the graph are researchers
and an edge exists between two researchers
if they collaborate with each other
as you can see there are distinct groups among researchers
a mathematically college researcher
does not collaborate with researchers who work on structure of the rna
so the graph is essentially a set of separate groups
thinly connected through a handful of cross - disciplinary researchers
who collaborate across groups
these groups are then the communities in this collaboration graph
what does this tell us
it tells us that communities are highly interacting clusters in a graph
that is they form pockets of denser subgraphs that are more
connected to each other than to members of the other clusters
communities of humans or otherwise are interesting things to study
because it gives us an insight into the interaction patterns
and how they change with time
here are some analytics questions about communities
we have divided them into three categories
analytics questions that do not depend on time are called static
here we ask questions about the composition of the community
how tight - knit members are connected and so forth
in the second category we involve the formation and evolution of the community
communities can form temporal for example
around an event like a school shooting
or some communities despite the comings and
goings of members sustain themselves well
a facebook group a political party fans of a music band
are likely to continue over time and hence are non - transient
one can also be interested in the history of formation of a community
like a criminal network
the third category is about predictions
analysts would like to predict how a community would grow
whether it composition of members might change
or whether there are emerging power shifts within the community
now before we ask these questions however
we need to first identify communities in a large network
to find communities we need to formalize the idea that there are more
connections within the community and fewer connections between two communities
one way to achieve this is to think of dividing the degree of a node
into an internal and an external component
the internal component is the count of edges within community
and the external degree is the count of edges outside the community
an example
will be to consider that my community is where i live that is san diego
and then count the number of my friends within san diego versus outside san diego
in the figure the highlighted node has four internal connections and
one external connection
the next step would be to think of the internal degree and
the external degree of an entire cluster
we can sum up the internal degrees of all nodes in a cluster
and call it the internal degree of the whole cluster
and similarly sum the external degrees of the nodes
to compute the external degree of the cluster
now we can define intra - cluster
density to be the ratio of the number of internal edges of the cluster
divided by the number of possible connections inside the box
the denominator is n cues 2
which is the number of pairwise combination of nodes within the cluster
we call this delta int
similarly inter - cluster density delta x is the number
of inter - cluster edges divided by the possible pairings between nc
a node in the cluster to n - nc the number of nodes outside the cluster
there are two kinds of methods used for finding communities in the network
one of them focuses on local properties that is
properties for which one only looks at a node and its neighbor
for the most ideal community in a network is a subgraph
where every node is connected to every other node in the subgraph
such a structure is called a clique
to find a perfect community structure as a clique
one can try to find the largest clique within a graph return cell
that is a computationally challenging problem
it much simpler to find cliques if we know the value of k
that means the number of members in the clique
we are going to show a simple version of this in model three
the more general problem has been solved by complex algorithms
that are beyond the scope of this course
in the real world perfect cliques larger than three or four are harder to find
so we need to relax the definition of it
now there are two types of relaxations
those based on distance and those based on density
two distance based definitions are n - clique and n - plan
we will illustrate this over a friendship graph shown here
n - clique is a subgraph
such that the distance between each node pair in that subgraph is n or less
by this definition holly paul and gary form a two clique
that a little awkward is not it
yeah
they are within two distance of each other
but the two clique does not include intermediate nodes that
connect the member nodes
so mike is not in the two clique
this situation is corrected in n - clan
where to belong to the n - clan the shortest part between any members
without involving outsiders is n or less
now holly mike
bill don harry and gary form a two - clan
clearly this group is more cohesive than the two - clique we saw before
n - clique and n - clan are distance based measures for
finding cohesive groups of communities
k - core is a density based method for finding communities
let look at the dark orange subgraph
every node is connected to at least three other nodes within the subgraph
they form a 3 - core
let include the medium light orange nodes in the subgraph now
each node is connected to at least two other members within the subgraph
they form a 2 - core
relaxing further we can add the light orange nodes and the graph as a 1 - core
we have already defined the degree of the node
as the number of edges connected to it
thus specifying if a node is more connected than another
looking closer we can separate out
that two components denotes degrees into in degree and out
which are the counts of the incident and the outgoing edges of a node respectively
in the example graph g has an indegree and
outdegree of three making the total degree equal to six
we first construct this degree table for each node
it a simple procedure where we count the number of nodes with degree
0 1 2 and so forth
the degree versus count table is a degree histogram of the graph
we can compare two graphs by computing the vector distance between them
one simplistic measure is just the euclidean distance
for our case the degree histogram based on comparisons of
the histograms find the graphs to be very similar
the more sophisticated methods are available but
are outside the scope of this course
we can also compute histograms of just the in degree or
just the out degree of the graph
but perhaps more interesting is the joint two dimensional histogram of the graph
the colorful histogram of the graph can be interpreted here as follows
the graph has a maximum in degree of three and a maximum out degree of three
this creates a two - dimensional histogram with four times four
equal to 16 different joined values
the actual value for any combination is computed from the graph and
color coded in the ratings
for example there is no node with in degree 0 and out degree 0
so the lower - left square of the graph has value zero and color - coded blue
on the other hand there are two nodes with in - degree three and out - degree three
thus the top - right corner has the value twp which is 20 of the nodes
color coded as light green
the 2d histogram provides an interesting insight
the nodes with more incident edges than outgoing edges
represent entities that take in more than they put out
in a social networking setting they represent members who are listeners
they receive a lot of posts but send much fewer posts
on the opposite side of the spectrum
there are talkers whose out - degrees exceed their in - degrees
the entities that are in between we have both large values of in - degree and
out - degree
these are communicators
in this graph there seems to be more talkers than listeners
not surprising though
my social media friends show similar statistics
in this video we will explore
another fundamental property of graphs called connectivity
we list two important kinds of graph analytic questions
that are based on connectivity
in the first case we are asking about the robustness of the network
suppose we have a computer network with many servers and
a hacker is trying to bring the system down
you set a small set of servers that the hacker can target to disrupt the network
what we mean by disrupt is to disconnect a part of the network from the rest
a similar problem may occur in the power distribution network
in that case an attacker may be able to attack one or two central components so
that large portions of the network loses power
i have a geneticist colleague at tech graduate institute who studied
the robustness of biological networks
he told me that many biological networks have built in redundancy so
that even if you disrupt one important gene there are other genes in the network
which will support the biological function possibly through other routes
therefore a network is robust if removing one or
more edges or nodes still keeps it connected
the second category is about network comparison in terms of their
overall connectivity
the two graphs shown here are very different in their structure
what are some parameters by which we can compare them
that to talk about connectivity we must first define the concept of connectivity
very simple
a graph is connected if we can reach any node from any other node
let look at the crypto graph in the picture clearly we cannot
reach from all nodes to all nodes here because this graph is not connected
however we can identify four parts of the graph that are themselves connected
these islands of connected parts are called components or
connected components of a graph
for directed graphs we need to be a little more specific about connectivity
we say that the directed graph is strongly connected if we follow the direction of
the edges and still reach every node from every other node
a weaker form of connectivity is if we do not care about the direction of the arrows
and can reach every node from every other node
another way of saying it is that the undirected version of the graph
is connected this is called weak connected
look at the graph that we have seen so many times in this course
is it strongly connected or weakly connected
this leads to some big graph challenge
given an arbitrarily large graph
can i find the connected components of the graph efficiently
second given an arbitrarily large graph
can we find its sub graphs that are strongly connected
we will touch upon these questions in module four
so there are two ways to break a graph
identifying the smallest node set which if removed will disconnect the graph
here if we remove f d and
h or h f g we have disconnected the graph
so the separating set is either h f and g or h f and d
so the connectivity is three
similarly removing c - f d - g d - f and
h - e edges will also disconnect the graph
therefore the edge connectivity is four
so this is how network robustness is defined
now let ask is this network robust
suppose the attacker removed node f
why remove f
because f is the most connected node
that is f has the highest degree
if we remove f five paths are disrupted
for example there is no way to go from c to g or
from i to e because these paths went through f
let try this exercise
suppose the attacker has already removed f
and would like to cause more damage to the rest of the network
which node should be targeted next
the answer is c because c is the next most connected node
higher degree nodes make the network more vulnerable
so far the centrality of a node is defined using the degree and
the shortest distance to other nodes
now we introduce a different idea
we would like to say that if you are important and
i am connected to you then i must be somewhat important too
in other words my centrality
is proportional to the combined centrality values of my neighbors
now if we write that down mathematically it would look like the top formula
the centrality of vi is the sum of its neighbors
now we can write that as an equation
where lambda is a proportionality constant
the resulting equation looks exactly like the eigenvector equation we have
seen before
now again you really do not have to understand how it works
it fine to know that if we solve that equation
we will get the eigen values lambda
now let take the largest lambda and
find the corresponding eigenvector which will give you the centrality of each note
notice the difference between the degree centrality and
the eigenvector centrality in the same graph
the yellow node in the middle has a low degree centrality
compared to its neighbors
however with the eigenvector centrality the node becomes comparably more important
because the neighbor centrality status boost some of the centrality of this node
in contrast consider the second highlighted note
it had the same on normalize degree centrality as the previous node
but because the neighbors are low centrality nodes
the eigenvector centrality goes down
so this is the intended consequence of the eigenvector centrality measure
speaking of consequences eigenvector centrality essentially says
if you know the right people your importance will go up
well that kind of risky proposition
here is me in a social network and let say i am connected to
this somewhat dubious character and i think it does not really matter
what i do not know is that my connection has it own set of connections and
look at who they are
so on the one hand these shady characters that are now connected to
indirectly does raise my eigenvector centrality but
it also has quite a damaging effect on my reputation
my ev centrality almost makes me look like a suspect
now think about that
now brin and page the founders of google
had an interesting way to think about the eigenvector centrality
they thought about a server
well no not that kind of server
this kind of server
the kind that surfs the web
but this is a special web surfer called a random surfer
and here is what he does he picks a web page and looks at the links
then he chooses a random link goes to that page and does the same thing again
except sometimes when you kind of get bored and goes to totally new page
how often does he do this random jump
let say there always sort of a 15 chance that he will
or more generally with the probability of 1 minus alpha
so page and brin idea was to figure out
that this surfer will visit a page with a high chance if the page is central
they came up with a measure for
this stationary probability of a page being visited by the random surfer
they did not call it centrality they called it pagerank
let see a youtube video to understand how pagerank behaves
okay now we are talking about the world wide web which is a huge graph
how do we of such a graph
the answer is iteratively using a method called power iteration
this method can be used because we are looking for the largest eigenvalue
let me show you
let take a small graph
let initialize the still unknown page rank as zero for all nodes
now page rank a is a 0 15 chance that i was at a already
and 0 85 chance that i come to a from b or i come to a from c
however at this point the page rank of b and c are at zero
so in the first iteration page rank of a is 0 15
now for b i can only come to b from a but we cannot claim all of pagerank of a
because there is always a half chance that the surfer will come to b
from a because he could also get to here from c
this plus the 0 15 chance that the surfer is already at b
makes bs pagerank 0 21
now after doing a few rounds of this computation between 50 and 100 iteration
let say
the values will converge
now this computation has been demonstrated to perform well
in the mapreduce framework
in module four we will talk about another way of computing this metric
welcome back to the second module of the course
in this module we will cover a number of basic principles and
techniques of graph analytics
as we mentioned in the last module the goal of graph analytics
is to utilize the mathematical properties of data and provide
efficient algorithmic solutions for large and complex graph structure problems
as i said in this module we will learn a number of basic graph analytic techniques
after this module you will be able to identify the right
class of techniques to apply for a graph analytics problem
to be more specific in this module we will consider
the mathematical and algorithmic aspects and not so
much the computing frameworks to implement these methods
in modules 3 and 4 we will look at two different kinds of computing
platforms that are used for implementing the techniques discussed in this module
here is the lesson plan for the module
first we will discuss a few basic terms and
their definition which we will use for the rest of the course
of course they are not the only terms and concepts we will learn
as we go through each technique we will add more terms and
definitions in our vocabulary
now following these definitions we will consider four categories of
graph analytic procedures
the first called path analytics is centered around the analytic techniques
where the primary objective involves traversing to the nodes and
edges of the ground
the second analytic technique inquires and
explores the connectivity pattern of the gaps
where the term connectivity pattern refers to the structure and
organizations of the edges of the graph
the third analytics category involves the discovery and
behavior of communities which are closely interacting entities in a network
the fourth category termed centrality analytics detects and characterizes
significant nodes of a network with respect to a specific analysis problem
of course there are many more types of graph analytic techniques that we will cover
in the course
we will provide some additional reading material for those who are interested
but we start by recapitulating our definition of graphs
as a collection of vertices and edges which represent ordered pairs of nodes
while this mathematical definition is indeed correct
in practice it needs to be extended to give you other information elements
let us consider a single tweet
as we have mentioned previously a tweet is a complex information output
because it is a graph in itself with several nodes and edges
but over and about the structure a tweet
actually contains much more information and code inside the nodes and edges
first there several kinds of nodes in a tweet
for example it has a tweet node a user node a media node
a url node a hashtag node and so forth
this assignment of kinds or labels to nodes is often called node typing
every graph application will have its own set of types
and it will assign one or more types to a node but it is not mandatory for
an application to use node types
mathematically we can extend our original definition with two more elements
the set of node types and the mapping function that assigns types to nodes
that means it associates a type to every node
however not all nodes need to have a type but in many applications they do
in addition to types a node also has attributes and values
in our tweet example
text is the name of an attribute that refers to the textual body of the tweet
whose value is a character string written by the author of the tweet
for a specific kind of data like a tweet
one has a fixed set of attributes as decided by twitter
this collection of attributes is called a node schema
for a general graph
a node schema may have an arbitrary number of attribute value pairs
we will revisit this in module 3 when we discuss graphing the models
similarly at edge of a graph we have an edge type also called an edge label
also just like a node
an edge may have an edge schema consisting of attribute value pierce
here interaction type is an attribute in our biological
network that describes the modality of interaction between a pair of genes
for the specific edge we have highlighted
the genes interact through biochemical activity
because they are party to some biochemical process
clearly there are different kinds of interaction between these
genes or proteins
that means an attribute called interaction type can have a set of
possible values like physical genetic and so on
this set of possible values is called the domain of the attribute
putting these elements back into our mathematical model
we get a more concrete specification of what a real live graph would contain
we have already discussed edge types as well as node and edge properties
take a minute to look through this again
whenever you consider an application that needs graph analytics the first task
should be to determine the informational model of the graph your application needs
it always a good exercise to document the information model
in terms of the elements described on the slide
let see a little more on the topic of edge properties
many application encode different kids of numeric knowledge
into edges of a graph in the form of edge points
if we do not put weights in an adjacency metrics
an edge is just represented by placing a one in the appropriate cell
however if we do use a weight
the weight value can be placed in the adjacency matrix to facilitate
down stream computation as we will show in the next lesson
what do the weights mean
that depends on the application
let see some examples
the most obvious example is a road map where the nodes are road intersections and
the edges represent stretches of the street or
highway between these intersections
the edge weight can represent the distance of a particular segment of the road
in a personal communication network for example an email network
we can count the average number of emails per week sent from john to jill and
use it as a proxy for the strength of their connection
so more emails means a stronger connection
in a biological network one often has to assess whether an interaction that
can occur is actually likely to occur given the concentration of the reactants
the chemical environment at the site of the reaction and so forth
this is represented as a weight that designates the likelihood of interaction
finally consider a knowledge network
where nodes represent entities like people places and events
and edges represent relationships like a person visited a place or
movie actor tom is dating movie actress kim
now this kind of information may be important for some news media
however if the information does not come from an authentic source
itself it is more prudent to put a certainty value on it
this certainty value may be treated as a weight on the edge
moving on from the information model of the graph
the structure of the graph often contains valuable insights to a graph
many of the graph analytic techniques we will discuss in this section
will consider these structural properties of graphs
one such structure is a loop which is an edge from a node to itself
in the example here
you can see that a protein can interact with another protein of the same kind
many other examples abound
people send emails to themselves
a road segment circles back to the same intersection
a website has a link to its own url
the existence of loops and the nodes that have such loops can be very informative
in some applications and can be problematic for other applications
another structure property of a graph is the occurrence of multiple
edges between the same node pair
the graphs with this feature are called multi - graphs
in this example the two map kinase genes have five edges between them
why multiple edges
it because each edge has a different information content
in this case
these two genes can have five different types of interactions between them
where each interaction has a different value for the attribute interaction type
we see this all the time in human networks too
a person can be my spouse a co - performer in music and
my financial adviser all at the same time
many analytics algorithms are not natively designed for
multigraphs and often need a little customization to handle them
we will mention some of these customizations as we go forward and walk
through the different kinds of analytics applications preformed on graphs
so we talked about local properties
in this lecture
we will cover a global property based method of inaudible finding
the specific property we focus on is called modularity
it tries to estimate the quality of clusters of
communities in the inaudible
the intuition is as follows
if we consider the edges in a group and
try to see whether it different from what you would see if the edges
were assigned randomly with some probability distribution
if there is a community there will be more edges than would happen at random
if there is no community in some part of the graph the number of edges in
that part will either be close to the random case or even lower than that
the modularity measure thus estimates the quality of the clusters in
the graph by evaluating this difference of the actual minus the random edge fraction
so this is the mathematical formulation of what i just described
the adjacency matrix a gives us the actual edges
the pij provides a probability of a random edge
the m in the denominator gives us the fractional edges
and the delta function task is to evaluate if i and
j should be in the same cluster
if they are the contribution will be added to q
the quality metric which is multi - layered
well we have not defined what the probability model looks like
there are many ways to figure out what pij should look like
one simple model says that the chance that there is an edge between nodes i and
j is proportional to the degree of node i times the degree of node j
that means if nodes i and
j are already well connected there is a high chance that they share an edge
so if you are a mathematical person you might be thinking okay
let find clusters in the graph so that q is maximum and then we are done
well sadly maximizing q is very hard
so we need to find an approximate solution
so we will illustrate a very
popular method of finding this modularity based community detection
well the best way to describe this is through a youtube video
that the url
now the next slide and the following slide
describes it but i think it better to explain the method
through screenshots off the video as it happens
we will show you some snapshots of this video
there are 309 nodes in this graph
initially they all have different colors
that is they belong to different communities
this screenshot shows the graph at iteration 144 of the algorithm
the number of communities now is 286
the chart on the right side plots time on the x - axis and modularity on the y - axis
as you see the modularity on the rights
roughly at each iteration
the system is trying to change the color of a node to that of its neighbors
but it actually changes the color only if the modularity value of
the whole graph changes as a result of that color change
after a few more iterations the number of communities has become 241
the three arrows show some parts of the graph where the nodes have changed colors
modularity is on the rise
after 1 437 iterations the modularity of the graph is still going up
now there are 113 communities
the errors show some new areas where the neighboring nodes have the same color
at 1 842 iterations the modulary gains slows down
meanwhile the number of communities have reduced to 75
at 4 179 iterations the modularity growth has started becoming flat
but in the meantime the number of colors that is communities has reduced to 48
at around 5 196 iterations the algorithm decides that there is not enough
reduction in the number of communities
which is reduced to only 45 in the last 1 000 iterations or so
now it collapses each community that is clustered to a single node and
creates a cluster to cluster edges
the orange box an arrow shows this contraction
now compared to the previous slide this collapsing or
contraction of the plastic creates a skeleton of the original draft
now the algorithm starts again with this reduced graph
you will find many graph analysis software
where you can run the louvain method of community detection
inaudible
i took my linked - in network which has me at the center and
all my connections as nodes
if two of my contacts are also connected in linked - in
there is an edge between them
this kind of mean - centric network is often called an ego network
when i inaudible the community direction algorithm here i found six communities
with one set of parameters and seven communities with another
i could clearly see my connections in san diego
my connections in my professional network my friends in india and so forth
there always one false community which stands for
others nodes that do not clearly belong to any specific group
perhaps more interesting and important than the static
analysis of communities is to track communities over a length of time
and determine how they evolve and why
there are six large categories of evolution steps
that can happen within a community
a community like a new facebook group can be born
a community like a group of people who gathered for an event
would dissolve because the event and the mutual interest around it has ended
a community can grow because the members rally around a common cause
typically new cross - community edges start getting
formed before the communities actually merge
the communities can shrink like my book club
where do you see this in real life
well how about company mergers
surely enough the inaudible results will happen when a community splits
going along with the previous example
a closely working group in a company may at some point create their own product and
form a new company with very little ties to the old company
one standard symptom of a group splitting is that the nodes in the subgroup
show an increase in the number of edges just amongst themselves
so far we have seen two versions of the dijkstra algorithm
both these versions assume that the edge weights provided by the network
must be used as is
now that can lead to some interesting problems
we saw one such problem before
remember we were trying to decide whether we should go from g to d or
from f to e because both options had the same total weight
now had we chosen to go from g to d
it would take us a few extra steps to arrive at correct solution
one way of handling this problem is to use additional knowledge
so intuitively we want to say that we know that we want to go to b
so traversing through d is not a good idea
because it will take us away from b
in other words we use the knowledge of the destination of b location
to steer the direction of search
this variant is called goal - directed dijkstra algorithm because
it is using the information about the target known at any point in the search
the trick to use this information is to change the edge weights as we diverse
how do we change the weight
we use a formula where the new weight
is the original weight together with a function called the potential function
now we will show this in our example
since our graph is a proxy for
a road network we can assume that we know the coordinates of every node
therefore we can compute the distance between any two nodes
in practice we will choose a few nodes so
that we can compute the distance of every other node from these chosen nodes
these chosen nodes are called landmarks
let assume b which is our target is a landmark node and
let rewind to the state where we are trying to choose between
the gd expansion or the fe expansion
so we calculate the distance of f g and e from b
bf is 20 bg is 80 and be is 15
now we will apply the formula like this
for the fg case we subtract the bf distance
from the weight and add the bd distance to the weight
this gives us 70 because g is far from b
similarly for the fe case we subtract the bf distance and
add the be distance to the weight and it gives us 15
now with these modified weights we choose the fe expansion
in practice this significantly improves the actual performance of the algorithm
so this technique is used by many online mapping services when they give you
directions
so now let bring back the constraints that we have ignored so far
there are two constraints here parts of the graph to include and
parts of the graph to exclude
in this example we have to go to b but
we should go to j first and then travel from b to j
also we cannot use any of the paths through e
this really means two things
first we split the problem into two independent shortest path problems
that we can solve in parallel if needed
second when we go from j to b we need to extract
the useful subgraph that we need to consider
for a large network and a complex exclusion condition
we will essentially operate over a smaller graph
thereby reducing the effective size of the problem
as we will see in module three this kind of subgraph extraction operation
can be done effectively and efficiently with a graph database system
this concludes our short tour of path analytics
so in this optional module we will look at the two key player problems again
the goal of the first problem is to identify a small set of nodes
whose removal will create maximum disruption
now in this case a traditional centrality algorithm may not work
because the optimization goal is to break up the network
so we need a quantitive measure of the breakage
if dij is the distance between nodes i and
j then 1 over dij is the closeness of these two nodes
if we add the closeness of all nodes and normalize it by the number of node pairs
we will get a measure of cohesiveness as a fraction
so 1 minus this value is a measure of fragmentation
our goal is to maximize this fragmentation metric
in the model terrorist network shown here removing the red nodes a
b and c will break up the network into seven components
with f reaching a value of 0 59
the second key player problem is trying to find a group of s influencers
which can reach a maximum number of nodes within k steps
the number of unique nodes reachable from a starting node is called the reach
of the starting node
for this we need to adapt the concept of reach to limit it to k steps
we also need to adapt it to measure the distance of an arbitrary node
from a group of nodes between our influences
the distance from one node to a group of nodes can be defined as a maximum
or average or minimum distance of the node from the members of the group
often the minimum distance is a good choice
so the distance we could reach
can then be through of as the proportion of all nodes reached by the group
where the nodes are weighted by the distance from the set
and only nodes at distance 1 are given full rate
hence a distance we could reach that use a maximum value of 1
where every outside node is adjacent to at least one member of the set of influences
in the network shown just three nodes a c and d
are sufficient to reach every other member within just four steps
now this concludes this module where we looked at several analytic techniques and
measures to extract different kinds of insights from a network
we saw how a community in a graph can evolve
to track the nature of evolution
we need to measure how the community changes over time
so here are three cases
one two and three of a community changing between two observation points
the goal is to figure out whether these are normal fluctuations in the network or
are more drastic changes occurring
look at them for a second
just visually the first case seems to show just minor changes
whereas case two shows a merger and case three shows a split
now to come up with a quantitative measure of change over time we need to
take two observations from two consecutive time points and fuse the graph
if you do it for case one you will find one new node
one living node and the rest will come on over time
for case two you will see that two previous communities
colored differently are internally connected the same way as before
but some members of the two communities have created new crosslinks
now can you tell me what you observe in case three
well i see one join node color purple
apart from it there are just two edges connecting the two groups
now with these observations we can now compute the autocorrelation
between the graphs across time t and t plus 1
this is just a measure of the number of common nodes
divided by the number of nodes in the combined graph
if the community does not change at all this number is 1
if a community has only a few connection the number is lower
after computing autocorrelation over every pair of time steps
we can then compute stationarity
which measures the overall change in the autocorrelation over a period of time
so if we measure over 100 time steps
we will add the 99 correlation values from the steps and then divide it by 99
this will tell us what fraction of members remain unchanged
on an average over these 100 time steps
therefore the 1 minus zeta tells us the average ratio of members
that are changed in a time step
let take three cases
in the first plot the size of the graph is small and
nothing much is happening here
a note occasionally joins or leaves keeping the stationarity pretty flat
in the second case the graph is small but there are a lot of changes especially
at time step seven a whole bunch of purple nodes have joined and then they went away
the size of the graph clearly reflects this
with a purple spike that you see on the size versus the time graph
this spike on the time series by the way is called a burst
the third plot shows a large graph with many nodes joining and leaving
the stationarity of this graph will be quite low given the abrupt changes we
observe over time
in this video we will discuss what paths are and
how to find your way as it travels along the nodes and edges of the graph
let start with an example
for this example
we will consider an edge weighted graph with no loops as shown here
term edge weighted means the edges have weights
the weight of the edge i to j is 15
we can think of this graph as a small road network where the nodes are cities and
the edge weights are highway distances between them
to walk or traverse through this graph we will define what a walk is
a walk is an arbitrary sequence of nodes and
edges that starts from some node and ends on some node
here we can go from h to f
to g to c to
f to e to b
notice that in this walk we went through the node f twice
in many applications we do not want to consider arbitrary walks but
consider a walk where we do not repeat nodes
unless we need to come back to the starting point
such a constrained walk is called a path
the green arrows indicate a path from j to b
we said on the last slide that a path can start from a node and end on it
such a path is called a cycle when the path has a three or more nodes
the j g c
f j is a four node cycle sometimes called a four cycle
c f e is a three cycle
however although there is an edge from f to j and another from j back to f
this two node path is not a cycle by our definition
a network with no cycles is called acyclic
a graph that is both directed and
acyclic is called a directed acyclic graph in short a deck
a trail is a concept similar to a path it is a walk with no repeating edges
in the graph shown in the walk h f g c f e
c f j is not a trail
because c f is traversed twice
remember the seven bridges of the konigsberg problem that we described
in module one
in that problem
we had the constraint that one cannot cross the same bridge twice
often we see such constraints in path planning problems
a common notion in directive graphs is called reachability
if there is a path from node u to node v v is reachable from u
reachability is not symmetric
even if v is reachable from u u may or may not be reachable from v
as we can see in this graph i is not reachable from a
look at a more carefully
there is no outgoing edge from a at all
so no node in this graph is reachable from a
a is a terminal a leaf node of the graph
where do we see this in real life
think of road network with one way streets and road blocks through the construction
this can make some areas unreachable by cars
in biology there are gene regulation networks
in which the nodes represent genes and
edges represent the fact that gene a regulates gene b and not visa verse
this makes it a directed graph
we can easily think of a case where a regulates b and b regulates c but
c does not regulate b or a
that making a unreachable from c
the final concept you will explore in this graph
in this lecture is that of a graph diameter
the diameter of a graph measures the maximum number of steps also called hops
want us to traverse to go to the most distant node in the graph
that means if you go from an arbitrary node
to any other arbitrary node in the graph following only the shortest paths roots
what is the maximum number of steps you have to take
let see how this is computed
for this task we will create a matrix called the shortest hop distance matrix
just like the adjacency matrix the rows and columns here represent graph nodes
and each cell contains the distance from the i eighth node
to the g eighth node via the shortest path
the distance from any node to itself is zero
so all diagonal elements of the matrix are zero
if a node i cannot reach node j through any path
the distance is marked as infinity
thus the distance from b to c is infinity
you can go from e to f in two steps e to c to f
therefore the wait at the c cell is two
if you fill this matrix you will notice that the largest reachable value
is 4 in doing the infinite distance
thus the diameter of this graph is 4 where it represents the part from i
to a through j g and d
there are a few noteworthy items in this distance matrix
the row of a has a value of 0 with itself and infinity for every other node
this happens because a is a leaf node
similarly except for the 0 distance with itself
the h column has infinity for all of the nodes
this happens because h has no incoming edges and
therefore no other node can reach h
so we have seen how to compute degree histograms of a graph
while degree histograms are useful to characterize a graph
it is usually a means to an end
it a known practice in statistics to compute a mathematical expression for
a statistical distribution using histograms
for graphs we often look for a function to describe the degree distribution
but this is expressed as a distribution of the probability
that a random vertex will have exactly k neighbors
now this problem has been investigated by many
one popular well known model is a power law
a graph follows a power law if the best probability is given by k
erased to a negative exponent called alpha
the value of alpha for many practical networks is between two and three
more recently
people have suggested other distributions that look like the power law graph
one of them is a log - normal graph
here the logarithm of k has a gaussian distribution
so this log - normal distribution seems to have the better fit to
natural graphs that are observed
so why are power law graphs important
interestingly many very
very different real life graphs in the world seem to follow the power law
if a graph does follow the power law it would have one large connected component
with a very high proportion of notes connected to it in a power law graph
most nodes have a low degree and some nodes will be disconnected
the low degree nodes belong to a very dense sub graphs and
those sub graphs are connected to each other through hubs
in the center of the graph has a high density
power law graphs can be difficult to compute with
for example the shortest path algorithm operating in the dense part
will possibly be very inefficient not because of the size of the network but
because there are too many paths to explore inside the denser pieces
the more interesting reason why people study power - law graphs
is because power - law graphs are supposed to be robust
so in nature all biological networks show power - law graphs because
it gives you a high rate of redundancy against failure and attacks
the most primitive path analytics question one can ask is to find the best
path from node one to node two
what does best mean
well that depends on the actual needs of the application
but in general to specify the best path
we need to define when one path is better than another
this is usually expressed in terms of an optimization problem
where we need to minimize and maximize our subfunction subject to constraints
what kind of constraints
two common criteria for graphs are inclusion and exclusion conditions
inclusion criteria may specify which nodes we have to include in the path
and exclusion criteria specifies which nodes and
edges should be excluded from the path
in addition one specify a preference criteria
that act as a softer or less strict constraint
for example we would like to minimize highways on my trip
or avoid condition
these are soft because although the users would like to have them
enforced completely it is all right if they are not fully enforced
a good practical use case occurs when i am trying to drive to work in the morning
ideally i would like to take a path having the shortest distance from my home
for example node i to my workplace which is node b in the graph
but i have to drop off my son at school
so my path must include his school the j here
however i would like to avoid roads around the new construction that
happening about five miles from my workplace like the node e in the graph
because there is usually a huge traffic delay around that construction site
i could also add a preference criteria like
i do not prefer to drive on the highway
but for this discussion we will skip the preference idea
too complicated
okay let start with a simpler problem
to start with let drop the constraints and look at the problem with just
the optimization part of the problem having a single variable
in our case that variable is the sum of edge weights from the source
that is the starting node i to the target which is b
this problem is handled by all mapping and road direction software
here is a google map screenshot in which i am trying to go from my home
in north san diego to a collision center in a nearby city
google maps shows three different routes and
highlights one as a preferred solution
you should readily see that the real shortest path of 26 6 miles
will take the longest time at the time of the day when i was looking at the map
so this means the weights here are not raw distances but estimated travel time
you should also notice the blue red and
orange segments in the preferred path are presented by google
the orange and red street segments clearly represent congestion areas and
therefore have higher weight than the blue segments
therefore the weights of the street segments are not really static but
change with many other factors like weather or the time of the day
this is why the least weight path problem is an important problem to solve for
the benefit of the commuter
a widely applied algorithm that is applied for
shortest path problems is called dijkstra algorithm
originally dijkstra considered a variant of the problem where the task is
to find the shortest path from a single source node to all other nodes
we will go through the algorithm here
however there are many good online resources including tutorials and
youtube videos describing the algorithm
for our discussion we will confine ourselves to the case where both
the source and the target nodes are known in advance
as you probably already know cypher is the scripting language used in neo4j and
it what we have been using already in the previous lectures
in this lecture we are going to go through a series of basic queries using cypher
with the focus on the data sets that we have already been using
here a listing of the basic queries we will go through step by step
so let get started
to keep things simple we will be using a text file containing the basic queries and
we will make this file available for download as a reading in the module
i will briefly review the queries and
then we will toggle to the browser to view the results of the queries in neo4j
neo4j has a very nice feature which allows us to retain individual queries
in multiple panels as we are going through the process of exploring each query
so for the first few queries we will be using the simple road network data set
that we used in previous demonstrations
and here we have already loaded the data set into neo4j
so let look at our first query
our first query is a very a simple one
in which we are counting the number of nodes in the network
so the first line of code simply matches all of the nodes with the label mynode and
it returns a count of those nodes
so let look at the results
the results are very simple the value of eleven
and we can visually confirm this by inspecting the graph itself and
see it has 11 nodes and we can see that up here
the next query is almost as simple we want to count the number of edges
now first thing to keep in mind is in order to count edges
we also need to declare nodes that are associated with those edges
so this first line of codes includes a declaration
of the nodes associated with the edges
here we are identifying with thevariable r and
then we are returning a count of those edges
so let take a look in neo4j and the results of this query are a value of 14
and once again we can confirm this visually by looking at our network and
counting the number of edges
the next query involves finding all of the leaf nodes in the network
now as you may remember from a previous lecture
leaf nodes are defined as those nodes which have no outgoing edges
notice that we are returning the node represented by the variable m
which is the target node in this query
so here we are matching all nodes associated with edges having the label two
and we want to place a constraint on those nodes
such that they have no outgoing edges
and then we return all those nodes
so let take a look at the results
we are going to see a single node returned the node with the label p
and if we inspect our graph we can see over here on the right the node p
and sure enough it has no outgoing edges only one incoming edge
the next query is also similar
we are looking for root nodes instead of leaf notes
and as you may also remember
root nodes are defined as a node which has no incoming edges
you may notice that this segment of the first line of code is sort of a mirror
image of the same segment in the first line of code from the previous query
we also want to place the constraint on the nodes that we want to return
by specifying that they can have no incoming edges
and then we return all of those nodes when we look at our results in neo4j
once again
we see we only get a single node return it the node with the label h
and if we inspect our graph we see over here the node h and
sure enough it has no incoming edges
only a single outgoing edge which means it a root node of the network
the next query can be described as a pattern matching query
we are looking for a pattern that we are describing as triangles
this is a pattern that a bit more complex than
the patterns we have been looking for in our previous queries
a triangle can also be described as a three cycle consisting of three nodes and
three edges where the beginning and end node are the same
so here we are matching a node a which goes through an edge to node b
which goes through a second edge to a second node c and
through a third edge back to the original node a
and then we return all of those notes
let look at our results
and here we see we have five distinct nodes returned
and we have two triangles or two three cycles
from d to e to g and from d to c to b
finally the last query we are going to execute with this data set
is going to explore the neighborhood of a particular node
in this case the node with the label d
and we are going to be looking for what we are calling second neighbors of d
this means nodes that are two nodes away from d
so the first line of code matches all nodes that are two nodes away
from a specific node
and then the second line of codes specifies the actual node that we
we want to consider by constraining its name to have the label d
and then we return those nodes
and here we are using the command distinct
because we want to make sure that we do not return any duplicate nodes
all of our nodes must be unique
so let look at the results
and here we have a network that consists of nine nodes and 11 edges and
we can see that each node is two nodes away from the node d
some nodes appear to be only one node away from the node d but
we can get to those nodes indirectly through another node which means that
they are not only a first neighbor but they are also a second neighbor
so we encourage you to play around with these queries
and make minor changes with them and see what the results might be
for our next three queries we are going to switch to the terrorist
data set that we had used in our previous demonstration
our first query involves finding the types of a particular node
so as you may recall in the terrorist data set there were node types
corresponding to a country
so in this case we want to match all nodes
where the name is equal to afghanistan
and we will return the labels for that particular match
and the results for this query are relatively simple
the label for the node named afghanistan is country as you might expect
next we are going to do something similar but with an edge
in this case we want to find the label
of a edge associated with a node named afghanistan
and also if you can recall from that particular network the label for
an edge associated with a country named afghanistan would be an is from label
and the final query we would like to demonstrate with this terrorist data set
involves finding all of the properties of a node
now based on how we defined our data import script
we defined all of our nodes to be of type actor
so in this query we are going to search for all nodes of type actor and
then we are going to return all of the properties associated with those nodes
but since there are thousands of nodes
we are going to limit the results to the first 20
so let go ahead and submit our query
and here are the results
each node represents a terrorist and if we look at the rows data
behind the scenes we can see the various properties associated with each node
each node has a name
each node has aliases one or more aliases
and they have a type property
now depending on how we defined our import script in the first place
these nodes could have different types of properties
in this case we only defined them to have three different properties
for our next two queries we are going to use a different data set
it a biological data set consisting of genetics data representing
interactions between genes
we will be providing the data for you to download
in fact there are two separate data sets
one is a complete data set consisting of 250 000 rows
and the other data set consists of the first 50 000 rows
and that what we will be using for this demonstration
so let take a look at a small sample of the data
here you see a graph network in which each node is a gene
and each edge represents the association between genes
to load this data set this is the smaller
data set required 1446 seconds
and it consists of 9656 labels and
46621 relationships
so the first query involves finding loops in the data which represent genes
that have associations with there own types
so it a very simple query in which the source node and
the target node are the same and we will be returning those along the edges and
we will limit our results to the first ten
so here are the results of our query
we can see a few different loops
if we look at the rows our query returned not only the node but the edge type
so on the left we see the particular gene and on the right
we see the type of association
and there are a range of different types
so this data set also contains multigraphs
if you recall from a previous lecture the definition of a multigraph
is any two nodes which have two or more edges between them
so in this case we will be matching two separate node edge relationships
and we will apply a constraint in which the edges must be different for
the same pairs of nodes
and then we will return those nodes and those edges
we will limit our results to the first ten
and here the results
here we see a set of four genes and there are two pairs that have three
edges between them and another pair that has four edges between them
our final query addresses something that is not necessarily been fully covered
in previous lectures but it is useful enough to address here and
you will get an understanding of it by going through this query example
we are going to essentially extract a subset of nodes and
edges from the graph that we have been working with
and this is called an induced subgraph
in which if we provide a set of nodes we want to return
the network that consists only of those nodes and their associated edges
so my first line of code is very familiar we are matching nodes and
edges it a very basic node and edge match
the second line of code is where the constraints are explicitly stated
a resulting network must consist of edges in which the source node
must be constrained to this subset of node labels
and the target node must also be constrained to be a part of the subset of
nodes with just these labels
and then we return the nodes and the edges
so let see the resulting graph
and here it is
so as we would expect
we are seeing the five nodes that were defined in our query constraints
and the edges corresponding to them retain the network structure
so this concludes our review of some of the basic queries you can do
with neo4j using the cipher scripting language
next we will talk about connectivity analytics with cypher
if you remember in module two
we talked about connectivity analytics in terms of network robustness
in other words a measure of how resistant a graph network is to being disconnected
specifically we used two kinds of methods
one computed the eigenvalues and the second computed the degree distribution
for these examples we are going to use the second one degree distributions
and we will use the same graph network we have used previously
a simple graph representing a road network
and here a listing of the query examples we are going to be applying to our network
my first query example finds all of the outdegrees of all nodes
now if you will notice this query consists of two parts because there a specific
type of node a leaf node which does not conform to this particular constraint
so our first match statement finds all nodes with outgoing edges
as you can see here this is a directed edge
and then we returns the names of the nodes and
the count as the variable outdegree
and for convenience we order by outdegree
and we need to combine that with a specific query dealing with leaf nodes
we are familiar with how to do that from past examples
and so we will match all leaf nodes and return the name and
the value zero for its outdegree
so when we submit this query we get this listing right here
the node p has 0 for its outdegree and all of the other nodes are as we might
expect and they are ordered by their value of outdegree
our next query finds the indegree of all nodes
which is very similar to our previous example
but in this case as you might expect
we are going to take into account root nodes instead of leaf nodes
and so our match involves incoming edges
indegree is a measure of all nodes connected to a specific node with
incoming edges
and we return similar results and
we union that with the specific query commands to find all of the root nodes
and then we return those names and 0 as the value of indegree
so when we submit this query here our results as we might expect
in this case h is our only root node
so it has a value of 0 for indegree and
all the other nodes are as we might expect
and our third query example finds the degree of all nodes
which is a combination of outdegree and indegree
so in this case we are not including any specific direction in our match statement
and we are returning the name and the count for all of our edges
but we are using the distinct statement
otherwise we would be counting some nodes twice
and then for convenience we order this by the value of degree
and when we submit this query we get the results as shown here
we have 1 column with the name and the other column with the degree and
the values are as we would expect we have a leaf node p with the degree of 1 and
a root node h with a degree of 1
our next query example generates a degree histogram of the graph since we are able to
calculate the degree of each node we can sort those into actual values of degree
so if we look at the distribution of degree among our nodes
we see there 2 nodes with the degree 1 there 3 nodes with degree 2
there 4 nodes with degree 3 and there 2 nodes with degree 4
so we are going to group those in the form of a histogram
so when we submit this query we get this table
the first column list the degree value in ascending order and
the second column list the counts of the nodes that have that degree value
so for those of you who are familiar with sql you might recognize this as similar
to the group by command it performs a similar function
our next query example saves the degree of the node as a new node property
this provides an added convenience so that we do not have to calculate the degree of
a node every time we are performing some sort of analysis
so we match all nodes with edges and
there no direction in this particular edge definition
and then we return distinct counts of each node degree and
then we create a new property called deg and assign the value of degree to it
then we return the names and the degree values and so
when we submit this query we see this distribution right here
with the names in the left column and the values of degree in the right column
and we can verify that if we issue a command to return all of the properties of
the specific node
so in this case i issued a command to match the node named d and
return all of its properties
and sure enough we see that it has a property name and a property degree
before we go to the last two examples
there a philosophical issue that we need to remember with all databases
every database will allow you some analytical computation and the remainder
of the analytical computations must be done outside of the database
however it is always a judicious idea to get the database to
achieve an intermediate result formatted in a way that you would need for
the next computation
and then you use that intermediate result as the input to the next computation
we have seen that a number of computations in graph analytics
start with the adjacency matrix
so we should be able to force cypher to produce an adjacency matrix
and this is what we are doing here
so think of a matrix as a three column table in which here one column
here another column and the third column will be the values that we
are calculating when we determine whether two nodes have an edge between them
and we are introducing a new construct in cypher called case
this allows us to evaluate conditions and return one result or
a different result depending on the condition
here we are specifying that when there is an edge between nodes n and
m then we return a value of 1 otherwise return a value of 0
and we will output those results as a value
and so when we submit this query we get our three column table in which
the first column is the name of our first node
the second column is the name of our second node and the value is either a 1 or
a 1 depending on whether the nodes have an edge between them
so in this case we see node a and c have an edge
a and l have an edge and so on as we would expect
so if we can calculate the adjacency matrix then we can calculate any matrix
you might remember from our module two lecture where we
learned about this complex structure called the normalized laplacian matrix
so let go ahead and calculate that
we will perform something very similar to what we did in the previous example
we will match all nodes for the first column and all nodes for
the second column
we will return the names of those nodes and then we will use the case structure again
to compare the names of each node and determine whether we have the same node
if we do have the same node then that is a diagonal of the matrix and
should get a value of 1
if they are different nodes and contain an edge between them
then we calculate the normalized laplacian with this equation here
and you will also want to notice that here we are using the actual degree property
that we assigned to the nodes in a previous example
this is an example of how that can become a convenient option
so when the calculation is performed the value would be returned
if there no edge between the 2 nodes then the value of 0 will be returned
and these values will end up in the value column
so when we submit this query here the table that get returned
this is the first column with the source node
the second column with the target node and the values
so in the first row the first node is p and the second node is p so
it identical which means it on the diagonal of the matrix
likewise for a in this row down here
and then the first value of the laplacian is calculated between nodes a and
c and so on
so that concludes our examples of how to perform connectivity analytics
in neo4j with cypher
hello everyone and welcome to a series of lessons on graph analytics with neo4j
in this first tutorial we are going to go briefly through the process of downloading
and installing neo4j and then we will go ahead and run neo4j and
provide a brief review of the neo4j graphical interface
so let get started
to download neo4j you will want to browse to neo4j com and
once you are at that url you should see a webpage similar to this
neo4j typically will detect which operating system you are running but
if you want to download other versions of neo4j
click this link in the upper right - hand corner to download neo4j
we are going to use the community edition so we will click this link right here
but if you would like to explore other releases
you can click the link down here
when we click the download community edition link
neo4j should automatically begin the download
there are versions of neo4j for windows mac and linux
neo4j is developed with the java programming language so
you will want to be sure you have the minimum system requirements to run neo4j
we will provide a link to those system requirements in the resources of
this video
this example is with the mac os x operating system
and we have downloaded the dmg file and we can click to open that
and as is the case with the mac applications to install is very
straightforward
we will just click and drag this icon into the applications folder and
that should automatically install
once the application is installed
we should see it listed in the applications folder
so let go ahead and run neo4j
to run neo4j you will just double - click on the application icon
neo4j is browser - based so it launches a web server and
it launches a url specific to neo4j
so to activate that server we will click the start button
if it your first time using neo4j then you probably wo not have any graph
databases available to open so neo4j makes it easy for
you by providing a default graph database of movie data
to run neo4j you click this link and that should launch your default browser
installation on windows should be just as straightforward as os x
you will click the same download neo4j button and
when the download page opens you will click download community edition
neo4j should recognize you are running windows and should download an executable
once that downloads we can run it and we will step through the same steps
which are typical for a windows operating system
now i already have neo4j installed in my windows system so
i will be updating my existing installation
and neo4j downloads a java jar file
once the application installed it will open the dialog box and
we can start up our web server
and the same url is available and when we click that our default
browser should be launched and we should see the same interface we see in os x
you should be able to subsequently run neo4j by accessing the executable
in the windows start menu
so let take a look at the neo4j interface
as i mentioned previously neo4j is a browser - based application
so once the application launches it should open your default browser and
in my case i am using the chrome browser
and you should see a url like this in the address bar
most browsers provide a full - screen viewing mode so i am going to go ahead and
activate that in this case what chrome calls presentation mode
the interface for neo4j consists of three main areas
there the command line along the top where you can issue commands and you can
paste content into the command line and execute multiple lines at one time
you can specify these commands to be one of your favorites
you can clear the command box
and you can run or execute the commands with the play button
on the left - hand side is an expandable and collapsible panel that provides
supplementary information about the database you are currently working with
there an option to list your favorites and
neo4j provides an initial default listing of favorites
and there supplementary information and links to references and
examples and tutorials and so on
you can also modify the configuration of your neo4j installation for
your particular user
and there additional information about the application
the third area is the main panel in the middle where the results of all of
the commands that you execute are displayed
in fact this panel itself has been generated by issuing a command
which is displayed in the very top of the panel
the command is ;play start
in fact if i type that command into my command line i should be able to generate
a duplicate of that panel and sure enough there it is
the upper right - hand corner of these panels i can pin the panel to my webpage
and i can do this with as many panels as i want and
the window will simply allow me to scroll up and down
i can view this particular panel full screen
or it can cancel or close it which is what i am going to do
now you can see neo4j makes it very easy to learn all about graph analytics
so let go ahead and get started with learning how to create and
modify our first graph network
next we are going to get started with neo4j by creating our first graph network
to do this first we will review a graphical or
a diagrammatic representation of a graph network
then we will introduce you to an equivalent text representation of that network
then we will build on those text representations in the form of pseudocode
with the ultimate goal being to develop an actual script
to create our network in neo4j
then we will go ahead and run the script to create the network and we will explore it
and confirm it structure and content
you are looking at a simple graph network consisting of five nodes and five edges
each node represents a person an individual
and the edges represent relationships between those people
each node has a number associate with it n1 through n5
and each edge has a corresponding number associated with it e1 through e5
edges are relationships such as harry is known by tom
or julian is coworker of harry
we could have more or less edges but we wanted to keep things relatively simple
while still maintaining a reasonable degree of complexity
what we want is a script that we can
process with neo4j in order to create an actual graph network
so let look at a text representation of this network
so here we list our five nodes and five edges and we are going to begin
the process of extending the text descriptions of our graph network
i am going to scroll down briefly and just show you the end result so
you have a better idea of what the final goal is going to be
this is the actual code that we are going to submit to neo4j in order to create
our network
but we are going to back up a little bit and
look at some simplified versions of this syntax so
we can better understand how simple the graph network relationships really are
here we list the five nodes and five edges as you saw just a moment ago
and down below we have a simple notation structure
which attempts to describe the five edge relationships
the first line represents the edge e1
we can see that the nodes n1 and n2 are included
because harry is known by tom and tom is node n1 and harry is node n2
the same goes for the second line the relationship between julian and harry
julian is co - worker of harry and so on
so let take this a step further by defining our graph network
so that each node is a particular type of node
in this case we are going to define a node type as what we are calling a toynode
as we introduce each node and its relationship with other nodes
we will define the node to be of type toynode
so on this first line n1 goes through e1 to n2
and both of those are introduced for the first time so
we will define them as type toynode
but on the next line since we already introduced n2 as type toynode
we do not need to repeat that statement
and so we continue in the same manner with the remaining edge relationships
taking this even further we will apply a similar kind of constraint to our edges
in this case we will define our network such that each edge is a particular type
which we are calling toyrelation
next we are going to add properties to our nodes and edges
our nodes can have properties such as name or job
so in this case our first node n1 will have the name tom
and the appropriate syntax for this includes curly braces surrounding the key
value pairs a colon separating the key value pairs and
the values defined within single quotes
likewise each edge may have a specific type of relationship
including co - worker wife and friend
so finally this brings us to the actual code we are going to use to create our
graph network
so let go ahead and copy this and paste it into neo4j so
we can take a look at our network
here we are running neo4j in our browser
so i am going to paste the code that i just copied from my text file
into the command line in the neo4j interface
and i will click the play button to execute those commands and
we will see the results returned in this newly displayed panel
we can see that we have 5 labels added 5 nodes were created 13 properties were
set 5 relationships were created and the entire process required 31 milliseconds
however we still cannot actually view our graph unless we issue yet another command
so let shuffle to our text file and take a look at that command
what this command does is it tries to identify a match
in which a particular node has a relationship with any other node
and then we will return those nodes and relationships
so we will go ahead and copy this and
we will paste it in to our command line and we will execute
and there our graph
when we mouse over the nodes we can see information displayed on the bottom
and when we select those nodes that information is displayed permanently along
the bottom likewise with edge relationships
so we would expect to see things such as michelle is the wife of harry
julian is a co - worker of harry and so on
so it looks like our network has been created successfully
we can also display information in a tabular format
by clicking the rows icon on the left
and we will see that this information is not constrained by the directed
nature of our graph
for example we see that harry has a relationship with tom
in which harry knows tom
but likewise down here tom has a relationship with harry
in which tom knows harry
next we are going to learn how to add to this graph and
modify some of the properties of the nodes and edges
in this segment we are going to learn how to import data into neo4j
we will begin by using a fairly simple spreadsheet consisting of only a few
rows and three columns in a format that fairly typical for
importing into a graph database
we will review the neo4j cypher script used to perform this import
and then we will run the script and validate the resulting graph
then we will demonstrate a similar process but
with a more challenging dataset consisting of terrorist network data
we will review this dataset and
the script commands necessary for performing the import
and we will run the script and explore the resulting graph
and finally we will review a third dataset that you will use yourself to
perform similar data inport operations
first let take a look at our sample dataset
this spreadsheet consists of just a few rows and three columns
each column has a heading
the first column heading is source the second column heading is target and
the third column heading is distance
you can imagine that this might represent data from a simple road network in which
the source and target values represent towns and
the distance values represent the actual distance in miles between the towns
so let take a look at the neo4j cypher script and
see what we will need to do to import our spreadsheet data
the first line of code performs the actual import
the other three lines of code provide constraints to the formatting
of that data
since our data file is a comma separated values or
csv file we will need to specify that in our code
our file also contains headers
and if you are using a windows operating system
your file path will look something like this
since we are running neo4j in a browser the file path needs
to conform to the http address conventions of the word file
followed by a colon followed by three forward slashes and
then the hard disk letter where the file is located plus the path to that file
if you are using mac osx your command will be similar but
the file path will probably look something more like this
the next three lines specify which nodes will be the source nodes and
which nodes will be the target nodes
and the properties will attach to them as well as defining the relationships and
the properties we will attach to the relationships
as we read each line of data n we are going to use keyword line
to specify the individual line we are currently working on
we use that here at the end of our load command and so
we will have to continue to use it in the subsequent merge commands
our source node variable is going to be n and
we will use the mynode type which we have made up ourselves
we are going to add a name property to each of our source nodes
and we are going to attach the value in the source column to that particular node
likewise for our target nodes we will use a variable m
we will define them as the same type mynode
we will give them a name and we will extract that name from the target column
on the particular line we are working with
finally we need to define our edge relationships
we are going to give each edge a label of the word to
and we are going to add a property called dist which represents the distance
and we will attach the values in the distance column
from the particular line we are currently working on
so let go ahead and copy this code and paste it into neo4j and see what happens
now i am working on a mac osx machine so
i am going to copy this code down here and perform the import operation
so i have pasted the line of code into neo4j and
i will click execute
and it takes a few moments to run
there not too much data so it should not take more than just a few seconds
and now we get the results in which 11 labels 11 nodes have been added
25 properties have been set and 14 relationships have been created
so let take a look at this graph network
we can see that the nodes are listed all as mynode and there our graph
the edge relationships should all have different distance values and
each node should be named a different letter
okay so let try a more difficult dataset
here is the spreadsheet containing terrorist data
the spreadsheet consists of seven columns with headings such as country
actorname actortype affiliationto affiliationstartdate
affiliationenddate and any aliases associated with that particular terrorist
this dataset consists of over 100 000 rows of data
since that could take a very long time to load into neo4j we will be
working with a subset of this dataset consisting of the first 1 000 rows
that much data will still include three countries
which should be plenty of data for our purposes
so here is the script we are going to use to import the subset of terrorist data
which shares similarities with the script we used previously
but since there are more columns in our dataset
we are going to include some additional properties into our graph network
the first line of code is very similar
to the load command we have used in previous datasets
the second line of code will use a variable c and a label country for
the particular nodes representing the individual countries in the dataset
in this particular case we are going to use the keyword row instead of line to
read our data n but it really does not matter
we could use either word as long we are consistent from command to command
so we are using the term row and associating the value in the country
column with the node that we are working on in that particular row
we will do something similar with nodes that are intended to represent
the actors or the actual individual terrorists
we are going to use a variable a and we will associate a property
called name and associate the actorname with that property
we will also associate a property named aliases and
associate the value in the aliases column with that property
and finally we will define a property called type and
associate the values in the actortype column with that property
we are going to create nodes representing organizations as well and
we will use the variable o and the label organization for those nodes
we will attach a single property to these nodes called name and
we will assign the values in the affiliationto column to that property
then we are going to define relationships between the actors and
the organizations they are affiliated with
the relationship label is going to be affiliated to and
we will define a property called start
and we will assign the values in the affiliationstartdate with that property
likewise we will define a property called end and
assign the values in the affiliationenddate with that property
and finally we are going to create relationships between the countries and
the actors
in this case we will define relationships with the label is from that will
describe the fact that a particular actor is from a particular country
so if all this makes sense let go ahead and copy this script and
paste it into neo4j and see the results
so here we are in neo4j and i am going to go ahead and
paste that script into the command line and we will execute it
we loaded 1 000 rows of data which consists of 658 labels and 658 nodes
3 464 properties and 1 403 relationships and
it took about two and a half seconds
so let look at a small subset of this network
here we see the equivalent of the first 25 rows of the dataset
there only enough data such that 1 country
8 actors and 15 organizations are visible
let go ahead and change this command to 250
by clicking on the line of code in the top of our panel
it automatically gets pasted into the command line above
so all we need to do is add a zero on the end of our command and execute that again
now we have a much larger more complex graph
but we still only have one country
in order to see more than one country
we will need to render the entire 1 000 rows of our terrorist data subset
but in so doing we will have a difficult time viewing the entire graph
the community edition of neo4j is limited in its ability to
navigate a graph network
but i am going to show you a little trick by editing
the html behind the scenes to scale the view of our graph
so let go ahead and render all 1 000 rows
so most recent versions of the major browsers provide the ability to go behind
the scenes and edit the html
so the trick is to find a place on the viewing panel that does not have
any objects
so that when you right - click and inspect the element
you will be inspecting the viewing area
neo4j uses svg graphics or
scalable vector graphics to render its graph networks
and svg uses a g element which can be seen here on the right
so in order to change the scale of our view we simply need to double - click and
add scale open parentheses and the scale factor that we would like
we hit return and the graph network now is zoomed out
i am going to try to position it so we can see at least two countries
and i will close my html panel
and so now we can view two countries
we can see albania in the upper region and afghanistan in the lower right
and we can see that there are actors and
organizations that have relationships with both countries
now there are add ons to neo4j that make navigating a graph network a little
easier but
this trick is convenient for those of you who have not added any neo4j extensions
the last thing that we are going to do is take a look at the sample dataset of
gene - disease associations and give you an idea what is going to be expected of
you in the accompanying assignment for this module
this data consists of information associating
different genes with different diseases
the spreadsheet consists of columns with headings for geneid
genesymbol genename diseaseid
the diseasename the score that represents the extent to which that gene
is associated with that particular disease
the numberofpubmed articles containing that information
the associationtypes
there are up to three different types of associations between a gene and a disease
and then the sources of data and
information that confirm this gene disease relationship
now this dataset contains over 400 000 rows of data
so if you have difficulty importing this entire dataset
then you will be better off extracting the first few thousand rows
so you are goal will be to define the load statement
which includes a csv with headers that will allow you to import enough
data into neo4j to give you an idea that you have done it successfully
we have already learned a little about the neo4j interface
and we have learned how to create a relatively simple graph with it
in this lecture
we are going to learn how to add another node and an edge to the graph
we will also go through the process of adding a node and
edge incorrectly to the graph
and we will learn how to correct that mistake
and finally we will learn how to modify an existing node information
okay so here our network that we created in the previous lecture
the first modification that we want to make
is adding a single node to the network
so let say that julian has a fiance and
her name is joyce and she works as a store clerk
so let look at the code that we are going to use to make that modification
so this process involves two steps or two separate commands
first command requires you to find the node that you want to add the new node to
so we use the match command and we specify the toynode named julian
once that command is issued then we will use the merge command and
define the relation between julian and the new node
and it going to be fiancee
and then the new node will also be a toynode
and the name is joyce and her job is store clerk
so let go ahead and copy both these lines of code
and we will paste them into our command line and we will run these commands
and the results that are returned look good
neo4j says that it has added 1 label created 1 node set 3 properties
created 1 relationship and it required 55 milliseconds to execute
so let look at that network
maybe the easiest way to view an existing network
if it the only one you are working on and you know the constraints involved
just toynodes is to expand the panel on the left and just click the toynode node
and you will easily see the new network
and we can confirm that joyce has been successfully added and
when we select that we can see that her job is store clerk
the command that was issued automatically by clicking the toynode button in
the panel is a little different than what we have been using to view our networks
but they both work essentially the same with this particular network
so next let see what happens if we do something incorrectly and
how to correct the mistake
so to do this
we will need to get back to our original network without the added node
and maybe the easiest way to do this is to delete everything and
recreate our original network
so first i am going to copy and
paste command to delete all of the nodes and edges
you will find this command in the getting started video supplementary resources
it involves the match command and i am matching all nodes and
all relationships and i am deleting those nodes and relationships
so let issue that command which should say it deleted 6 nodes and
6 relationships and sure enough
neo4j command line has a nice feature of maintaining a history of the commands and
so in osx we can use the command + up arrow to cycle through the commands and
find the original create command that created our network
on windows it a ctrl + up arrow command
so here i have found that command and i am going to re - execute it
and we have our original network back again
let view that network
and there it is
so let say for whatever reason i am not quite fully understanding how to add
an additional node to an existing network and i want to use the create command
for example i might be thinking that
this statement right here will accomplish the same kind of thing
by using the create command and by specifying a toynode named julian
well if we go ahead and give that a try let see what happens
so i will copy this command and i will paste it into my command line and execute it
and it says it added 2 labels and created 2 nodes and set 4 properties
and if we look at this we
see we have actually got another node named julian who has a relationship with joyce
so that much is correct but it not the same julian from the original network
so how do we undo this
well we will need to specify the julian that has a relationship with joyce and
delete both the julian and the joyce notes
so here we will use the match command once again
and we will identify the node the toynode with the name joyce and any relationship
she has with any other node should be deleted in addition to that other node
let go ahead and copy this
and we will paste it into our command line and execute
and it says it deleted 2 nodes and deleted 1 relationship
let view our network again
and it back to normal
so that one example of how you can intuitively figure out how to correct
certain mistakes
next we are going to modify information of an existing node
so if you remember when we first created our network harry did not have a job
so let go ahead and add a job to harry
first of all
we will need to actually select the node by using the match command
so we will issue that here and
we will specify that that node name must be equal to harry
and then we are going to use the set command and
specify that job will be equal to drummer
so let go ahead and copy that
and we will paste it and execute it
and the results that are returned says that one property has been set
but let say that harry does more than just play drums
let say that he can also play lead guitar
so in this case we will be adding an additional property
to a property that already exists and we will see how neo4j handles that
it a relatively simple modification we make in which we are setting
the job key equal to the existing job key
+ an additional value to that key in this case lead guitarist
so let copy that statement
and we will paste it and execute it
and we get a similar result returned and then let look at our network
and when we select harry sure enough now we see that he has two jobs
they are separated by a comma
one is drummer and one is lead guitarist
there much more you can do with neo4j but
we will want to move on and learn some more advanced capabilities
that work us closer towards managing our big data challenges
next we will talk about path analytics using cypher
the query language for neo4j
here the listing of the various queries we will be demonstrating
there are some things that cypher is capable of doing very well
and there are other things that require a little bit of creativity
in order to get the results that you are looking for
and we will show you some examples of that
it also important to keep in mind that because we are working with paths
which are an official structure in graph networks
each one of these examples includes a new variable
which in this case we are using the letter p to represent for
the actual path objects that we are going to be returning
you may also see the complete word path instead of just the single letter
p to represent these objects
we are going to continue to use the data set of a simple road network that we have
already been using in previous demonstrations that contains 11 nodes and
14 edges
so the first query we are going to demonstrate
is finding a path between specific nodes
so this would be very much like trying to find a root between two different
locations in our road network
in this case we are going to find a path between the node named h and
the node named p
to do this we will use the match command and
we will say match p which is a variable we are using to represent our path
= node a going through an edge to node c
there something slightly different about this edge and that is that we are using
a star to represent an arbitrary number of edges in sequence between a and c and
we will be returning all of those edges that are necessary to complete the path
and in this case we only want to return a single path
so when we submit this query we see this path
it consists of eight nodes and seven edges
and it begins with h and ends with p
now another common function we will use frequently with paths
is finding the length between two specific nodes
so we will issue the same two lines of code and then we will use this new command
length to return an actual value
we want to be returning an actual path
and we just want a single value
and when we submit this query we get the result seven
and we can see that by visually inspecting the graph or our seven edges
but because most networks are much more complex than this
we would need to understand the necessary query to return the length
and ideally in the case of our road network
we would want to find the shortest path between those two nodes
so in this case we are introducing yet
another new command specific to paths called shortestpath
we will use the same variable key and
the same descriptions in our syntax in connecting node a with node c
and in this case were going to look for the shortest path between node a and
node p and we are going to return that path as well as the length of that path
and we are just going to return a single path
and when we submit this query we get a path that five nodes and
four edges long and if we look at the text results that are returned
we will see a length displayed in the length column
and that value is 4 and we can see that by visually inspecting our graph
the next query we are going to demonstrate is intended to illustrate that
there may be more than one shortest path
and so we may want to know all of the possible shortest paths in order to make
a choice between which one we prefer
so we will be using a command that is built into neo4j called allshortestpaths
we will be issuing a similar query to what we issued previously
we are going to try to find all of the shortest paths between node a and node p
and instead of the letters a and c we are using the terms source and destination
but the results that we are going to return will actually be in the form of an array
we are using a new term extract which is based on the following
assuming we have matched our path p we want to identify
all of the nodes in p and extract their names
and we will return these names as a listing which we will call the variable paths
if there more than one shortest path we will get multiple listings of node names
so when we submit this query the results are listed in the rows display and
we see there are actually two shortest paths
they each have five nodes and four edges
now we may want to issue a query that finds the shortest path but
with particular constraints or conditions that we place on them
so in this case we still want to find the shortest path but
in this case we may want to constrain the path length to be greater
than a particular value in this case 5
and then we want to return essentially the same results that we returned in
the previous query
but we will also want to return the length of the resulting path just so
we have that information conveniently
so when we issue this command
we get a path with length six between node a and node p
so it clearly longer than the shortest path that we had found earlier
now that we are somewhat familiar with the two shortest path commands
the shortest path or a single path and
the all shortest paths command or multiple shortest paths we are going to use
that in a little bit of a creative way to return the diameter of the graph
and if you remember from a previous lecture
the definition of the diameter of the graph
is actually the longest continuous path between two nodes in the graph
so by using the shortest path command but returning all possible shortest paths
we are actually going to get the longest path included in those results returned
now if we look carefully at this script
it is a little different than our previous scripts
in this case our match command is matching all nodes of type mynode
we will assign those to the variable end
we are also matching the all nodes of type mynode and assigning that to variable m
so these matches are the same
but we want to place a constraint such that the nodes in n are not
the same as the nodes in m and
then we want to find all of the shortest paths between unique nodes in n and m
and return the names of those nodes as well as the length of that resulting path
and the trick is to use the command order by
and so for those of you who are familiar already with sql query language
you will recognize order by
you will also recognize the descend command
so if we order the resulting paths by their length in descending order
and only return 1 that path should actually be the longest path
and that equal to the diameter of the graph
so when we submit this query here the results that we get
we get a path between node e and node l with length severn
or maybe it occurs to you that maybe this is not the only diameter of the graph
the only path with length of seven
so we can modify our query just a little bit and change the limit from one to five
and we will see the results
and sure enough we actually get five paths
and 3 of those have length 7
so there are actually three distinct paths which qualify as
a diameter of this particular graph
so up until now we have been calculating path length
based on the number of hops between our beginning node and our end node
this is roughly equivalent to counting the number of towns between one town and
another town
but it does not really get at the value that is usually of
greatest importance to us
and that is the actual distance between one location and another location
which is found in the values that we have assigned to the edges between the nodes
so in this next example we are going to perform that kind of a calculation
so the first two lines of code we are already fairly familiar with
we are matching a path between node a and node c
where the first node is h and the second node is p
and this third line of code is also fairly familiar
we are extracting the names of the nodes and the path that been returned and
we are returning a listing of those names as well as a length of the path
all of that is being returned as the variable pathlength
we have added a third element to our return statement and
that is using the reduce statement
so what we are doing here is the purpose of the reduce statement
takes a set of values and reduces them down to a single value
so in this line of code we begin by setting a variable s equal to 0
and then we define a variable e which represents the set of relationships in
a path that returned or in other words the edges
and we pass that into this variable s and add to it
the value of the distance that we have assigned to that edge
so we are performing an aggregate calculation
and returning the final results to a variable called pathdist
and we are limiting that results to a single value
and so when we do this we should get a value that is more indicative
of the actual distance between our source and our destination
and so here the results
the path itself as we know begins in h and ends in p
and it has a pathlength of 7 but it has a pathdist of 39
so we could interpret this to mean that even though there are 6 towns
between the source town and the destination town or
a pathlength of 7 the actual distance in miles would be a value of 39
so with that we can apply dijkstra algorithm
so here i am going to match the node with the name a and the node with the name p
and we are going to find the shortest path in terms of hops from a to p
and we will set that equal to the variable path
then we will perform a reduce command and set the variable dist = 0
and we will go through and
sum all of the distances of each of the edges in our shortest path
and return that value as a distance
and we will also return the path variable
so remember this is not the path in our network with the least weights
it is the weight of the shortest path based on numbers of hops
now that an inherent feature of the shortest path command in cipher
so here is the path that returned
it a five node path with four edges and
the total sum of the weights of those edges sums to a value of 22
so in our previous query we specified that we wanted a match for
the source node and the destination node
but if i do not specify my destination node i can apply dijkstra single
source shortest path algorithm from node a to any other node
so when we apply this query the results displayed consist of
the actual original path from a to p with a distance of 22
and we will see a display of all of the intermediate paths generated in
the process all the way down to a single edge path between a and c
so just to reiterate what we have calculated is the shortest hop path
with the weights added the sum of the weights of the edges in that path
this is not the least weight path of the entire network
okay so let switch gears for a moment
as we learned in one of our previous lectures we can extract a subset
of nodes and edges from a particular graph for various reasons
let say for example that we want to avoid a particular town or
a particular area where there might be congestion
and this would be represented by one of our nodes
so we are going to perform a similar match as we have done in the past
where we are going to match any node n with any node m with a two edge between them
but we want to apply an additional constrained in which none of the n nodes
are going to include the node d
and none of the m nodes are going to include the node d as well
and then we will return the resulting graph
so when we do that we get a graph but looks very much as we might expect
very similar to our previous graph but it is missing node d so
it only has ten nodes and it now been reduced to ten edges
so now let say we want to calculate the shortest path over there graph that we
just returned in the previous query
so in this case we are going to match the shortest path between node a and node p
but in the second line we want to issue sort of a negative statement
in which the resulting list of node names that we extract using
the extract statement cannot contain the node d
and then we will return that path and the length of that path
so when we issue this command here our resulting path
it a five node path of length four
as we recall from one of our earlier queries where we were trying to calculate
all of the shortest paths we returned two paths
one path that contained d and this is the second path which did not contain d
so we can make this a little complicated
instead of avoiding a single node in our resulting path we are looking for
a graph that does not contain the immediate neighborhood of a specific node
this means all of the nearest or the first neighbors of a specific node
so in this case we are going to match the same node d and
all edges between d and any other node
and then we are going to issue a collect command to collect all of
the distinct neighbors of d
and we will apply a constraint to that in which the returned
list of neighbors cannot contain the node with the name d
likewise the neighbors list for
the target nodes can also not contain the node d
and when we submit this command we see a network that looks like this
five nodes and four edges
and that seems to makes sense
node d is not in the network nor are its first neighbors
but if you recall the original network
there may be a peculiar result that you might find a little bit disconcerting
so let look at our original network
now here the node d and here are all it nearest neighbors
so these are the forbidden neighbors that we want to
remove from our resulting graph
and we seemed to have done that successfully
these are the five nodes that are retained in the resulting graph but
there a node out here
the node p which seems to be neglected or not handled in the results
it not a first neighbor of d
so it in some ways arguably should be returned in our results but
it not part of the connected graph that we saw returned
this is one area in which cipher does not handle these situations by default
so we will need to supplement our query with an additional query
in this case the node p was a leaf node so we want to make sure that
not only matching the nodes that conform to these constraints above
but we also want to include the node or any nodes which are leaf nodes
which may also be arguably part of the results that you expect to be returned
now in our network we do have one root node
but it does not impact the results in this particular query
in the interests of being complete for
any network most networks being much more complex than the one we are working with
we would want to take into account not only those leaf nodes that might be left out
but also any root notes that might be left out
and finally our last query example extends the previous query
to find the graph which does not contain a selective neighborhood
in this case the two neighborhood of a particular node
in this example we are going to use the node f
and we want to eliminate all of the second neighbors of that node
so initially we match all of those nodes that are second neighbors of f
including f itself
and we will place those in a variable called mylist
then we go back through the network and match all of the nodes and
edges where the source nodes are not part of the nodes in the mylist and
the target nodes are not contained in mylist
and then we return those nodes and edges
and here the resulting graph
it does not contain f or its first or second neighbors
if we scroll down to look at the original graph here node f nodes h
j c a and l are all the first and second neighbors of f
so those should be eliminated from the graph that gets returned from our results
and sure enough
this subset of nodes represents the results that were returned from our query
it consists of nodes b d e g and p
and so this concludes our review of some of the more advanced
path analytics queries
we were using a simple network but
we are providing additional data sets that are much larger and
present a more realistic challenge in applying pathanalythics queries
hello everyone and welcome to this week module on graph analytics with neo4j
using the cypher query language
i am jeff sale and i will be your instructor for this series of lessons
i have been an instructional designer at the san diego supercomputer center for
more than ten years but i have also had a passion for scientific visualization and
visual analytics in one form or another for over two decades
and i am very excited about this opportunity to introduce you to this
free and very powerful graph analytics tool called neo4j
first we realized that many of you may not have the systems capable of
pushing the boundaries of neo4j performance limits
plus the fact that many of you are fitting this course into your already busy
schedules means we will be working with data sets which will load into neo4j and can
be analyze in a reasonable length of time on the order of minutes not hours or days
however you can be sure that neo4j is capable of processing and
analyzing extremely complex graph networks consisting of millions of nodes and
relationships
this module consists of a series of hands - on demonstrations with neo4j
which begin with examples of some basic cypher queries
that soon progress to some of the more advanced cypher queries
we will begin by using a relatively simple graph representing a road network but
we will also use much larger and more complex data sets
including sociological data on global terrorist groups and
genetics data on associations and interactions between genes
these data sets are in fact sub sets of much larger data sets and
we are making both of the sub sets and complete data sets available for download
once you become comfortable working with the smaller data sets
we encourage you to explore the larger sets on your own
finally you will notice that each video is accompanied by a text file
containing all of the code used in the video demonstrations
these files include dozens of sample scripts written in cypher designed to
make it easy for you to learn not only basic cypher cards but also queries which
focus on more advanced methods such pathenoids and connectivity analytics
when you are finished with this module you will be able to write cypher scripts to
import and analyze your own data using neo4j
so thank you for enrolling in this course and let get
started doing some real graph analytics with neo4j and the cypher query language
a parallel computation is at the heart of big data computing
however to specify what becomes parallel we usually think of a conceptual model
of parallel computation often called a programming model
a parallel programming model is a way to specify abstractly
how a parallel program will run
naturally for a program to be parallel
there must be a number of concurrently operating processes
but how do these processes communicate and exchange data
how do they decide when to communicate with each other
further what exactly is done in parallel
to think of the first question
two processes communicate data by sharing memory
indeed there are architectures in which all memory in multiple machines can be
made to virtually look like one large addressable memory space
however two processes
we also communicate by passing messages to one another
either directly from one process to another or
through a common message carrying pipe often called a message bus
the second question can also have multiple answers
two of the most common ways of achieving parallelism are pass parallelism and
data parallels
in task parallelism a large task can be decomposed into multiple sub - tasks
each of which can be run concurrently
in data parallelism the data can be partitioned into many smaller fragments
and operation can run on each partition independent of the others
typically these partial operations have then synchronized and
partially process data combined to produce a full answer
many parallel data management systems
operate a partition due to parallel manner
we need to remember that task parallelism is somewhat independent of
data parallelism
and it is possible to have both problems of parallelism in a programming model
it is important to emphasize the issue of a programming model
should be not be confused with the issue of a programming language
a programming language is independent of the programming model
and therefore a programming model can be implemented
in several different languages
as i mentioned the programming model we are going to consider is bsp
bsp was not initially created for graph computation
it was thought of as a parallel computing model
that will bridge the gap between software models of parallel computation and
hardware capabilities for supporting parallelism
the basic idea of bsp is as follows
there are number of processors
each processor can perform local computation using its own local memory
there a router which can serve to pass a message from any processor to any other
when one pair of nodes are exchanging messages
another third node can still perform computation
there a facility that can synchronize the state of
all auto - substative processes
this synchronize may either happen periodically
at intervals of l time units or there may be another way of specifying
when this synchronization is going to happen
but when it does all processors affected by it will come to a consistent state
when synchronization is performed a fresh round of computation can start
we call this
synchronization point
barrier synchronization
because all executed processes must reach this barrier point
before the next step of processing can continue
a bsp program is broken up into a sequence stop supersteps
in each superstep each processor will get the data if needed
performance computation if needed and
then exchange data with the right partner
once all the nodes are done the system helps to synchronize
then the next round starts
each processor can determine if it needs to compute or exchange data
if not it will make itself inactive
if required later a processor can be woken up to be active again
when all processors are inactive the computation stops
in applying bsp model to graphs we make a few assumptions
we assume that a processor is synonymous with a vertex
so for a processor can only send messages to or
receive from its neighboring processes
we also assume a vertex has an id and possibly a complex value
and an edge we also have an idea and fact
each vertex knows which edges it connected to
we cannot think of a computation as a vertex centered task
we shall inaudible what this means
in a now famous paper from google
this programming model was called think like a vertex
well to think like a vertex we need to know what a vertex can do
here a list of actions a vertex can take
the first one is easy
a vertex can find its own identifier
the second operation is to get or set the value of the node
this operation may be a little involved if the value is a complex data object
for our purposes we will assume the value is a scalar
next a node can ask for
its own edges the result of the operation is a set of edge objects
a node may also count its edges
since we are referring to outgoing edges throughout
this is the out degree of the vertex
recognize that
this means a vertex does not natively have access to its incident notes
however it does have control of the outgoing edges
so it can get inside the edge values
there may be two different ways of specifying an edge
the edge we have an id that the node can get
passively more commonly an edge is identified the vertex of targets
so in our diagram v1 lasts for the edge targeting v4
so in the situation like v3 and v5 we are there are multiple edges between v3 and
v5 the source v3 can ask for the values of all edges going to v5
the operate operation can add or remove an edge of a vertex
finally since the vertices are processes they can start or stop computing
typically a node wakes up if it receives a message from another node
now in comparison to a vertex an edge can do far less
it can get its own id if the system allows edge id it can set and
retrieve its own values and it can get the id of the node its pointing to
that it
now we still have not defined how to think like a vertex
that what we will do next
using an example that we have seen several times before
it dijkstra single source shortest path sssp algorithm
we have seen this algorithm before
but now we will show how to compute it in a parallel setting using bsp
here is the edge value that the weight of the edge
this is known before the algorithm starts
each vertex runs the exact same routine concurrently
each vertex asks
1 is it super step zero
2 if yes
then if this is a source vertex it sets the value to zero
else it sets the value to infinity which is a large number
the source vertex
propagates its edge value to the nodes at the other end of the edges
just the source vertex
all other vertices are quiet
the propagation process works like this
a vertex gets its own value which for the source vertex is zero
it gets its edges for each edge it gets the value of the edge
adds it to its own value and sends the result to the end point of the edge
the blue numbers indicate that the messages are sent
all vertices go to halt
that is they now have hit a synchronization barrier
notice that the receiving nodes do not look at the messages yet
it the system job to ensure that the messages are available to these nodes
at the next superstep
all nodes who have received messages wake up and read the messages
if a node receives multiple messages it picks the minimum
in our case the two active nodes have received only one value each
we have for the sake of convenience colored the processed edges in yellow
this is just for visualization purposes in this example
now it compares this band for a minimum value to its own value
and if its own value is greater it sets its own value with the minimum value
in our case both notes set their value to that of the incoming message
the same propagation routine works again
so each note completes the new distance
and sends the message along an edge to the other endpoint then halts
the same step is repeated in the next superstep
at this point the nodes have updated their values
the node with the value 6
has received our message just along one of the three edges on it
continuing
at the end of superstep 2
all nodes are ready to receive messages from all their incident edges
the node with a value 6 received a value which is lower than its current value
now the active nodes have no more messages to send
so each vertex votes to halt
the vertex id and the value are read out from each vertex and
then the process starts
if these nodes are in different machines of a cluster
the system will rely on the underlying platform like yarn
or sparks underlying infrastructure to ensure
that the edges going across machines can send and receive messages effectively
this should give you a sense of the speed of this process for a large scale network
as we said earlier while the giraph paradigm implements bsb
it must also be pragmatic
one such point of pragmatism is the computation of aggregate values
in the think like a vertex paradigm
operations local to a vertex can be performed in parallel and
each vertex only has to work with its immediate neighborhood
this is very useful but it is not sufficient at times
for example we need to know and use the total number of edges in the graph
this will be computed by adding edges connected to each vertex but
once aggregated it does not belong to any specific vertex
so whom does this vertex send the aggregate to
also suppose a vertex creates some edges as part of its compute step
when does this information get sent out
let answer the first question first
the class in charge of these aggregates is called the defaultmastercompute class
this class specializes mastercompute
how does the defaultmastercompute relate to the basic vertex computation
we have seen that all vertex programs are created by first defining a vertex class
this class has a compute function that performs like the think like a vertex
logic
now let add to it a basic vertex function and an aggregate function
now this function for
our example of all the total number of aggregate edges looks like this
the name of the function is aggregate
as you can see in yellow it just gets the number of edges off this vertex
what is a little strange is that the first argument of this aggregation has
an id of something whose name is total number edges
what really happens is as follows
the defaltmastercompute class which is in charge of this global aggregate
operations is specialized by your aggregate class
this class has an id and
the aggregator gets registered with giraph defaultmastercompute class
the id we saw before refers to your registered aggregator classes id
the mastercompute class performs the centralized computation between
supersteps
this class is initiated on the master node and
will run every superstep before the workers do
communication with the workers should be performed via aggregators
the values of the aggregators are broadcast to the workers before
the vertex compute is called
and collected by the master before the master compute is called
this means the aggregator values used by the workers are consistent
with the aggregator values from the master from the same superstep
and the aggregator used by the master are consistent
with the aggregator values from the workers from the previous superstep
now let go back to the big picture for a second
giraph is a big data software
why not implement the giraph system with a set of mapreduce jobs
too much disk requirement
no in - memory caching
every superstep becomes a job
so all intermediate steps are written to files and
that is not a very scalable solution for iterative operations
however it will be incorrect to think that giraph works
only in an in memory process
it can always have less memory than it needs
there are two broad categories of what is called out - of - core computation
the first situation occurs when the graph is really large compared to the capacity
of the cluster it running on
each worker stores the vertices assigned to it inside a set of partitions
inside a partition are a subset of vertices together with their data
during a superstep the worker node
processes multiple partitions concurrently one per thread
if a graph is large then not all partitions are stored in memory
typically only n partitions are kept in memory at all times and
the rest of the partitions are swapped into disk
the second situation occurs when the number of messages becomes high
normally vertices are processed in the order of their ids
a large number of messages is handled by creating
temporary message stores which are sorted by their destination ids
all messages going to the same vertex are placed together
to do this messages are sorted in memory periodically
the message store files are accessed based on
which vertices are being processed at this moment
this whole system is managed by giraph out of core message processor
in this lesson we will talk about two dominant systems developed for
large scale graph processing
the first one called giraph is from apache and
implements a bsp model on hadoop
the second system is called graphx is developed on the spark platform
which as you know emphasizes on interactive in memory computations
while bsp is a popular graph processing model
the actual implementation of bsp in an infrastructure needs
additional programmability beyond what we have discussed so far
in giraph several additional capabilities are added to make it more practical
a thorough coverage of the giraph platform is beyond the scoop of these lectures
however we will touch upon a few of these capabilities
we will first consider graph io that is how graphs can come into a system
represented inside the system and when completed are written out
next we will describe how giraph interacts with external data sources
some of these data sources use a different data model
other sources include databases
once a graph is imported
it is important to make sure that the system runs efficiently
we will look at a method that uses a special kind of global aggregate operation
which saves time by reducing the amount of messaging
to compute aggregate functions like sum and products
finally we will recognize that even if giraph is designed for
performing iterative in memory computation
there are times where it is absolutely necessary to store data on disk
we will briefly touch upon giraph ability to handle out of core graphs and
out of core messages
a graph can be written in many ways
for neo4j we saw how graphs can be important to the database from a csv file
in giraph two of the most common input formats are adjacency list and edge list
for an adjacency list each line has the node id a node value
which is a single number here and a list of destination weight pairs
thus in line one a has a value of 10 and 2 neighbors b and
f with edge weights 2 and 5 respectively
since g has no outgoing edge the adjacency list is empty
the current way of representing graphs is in terms of triplets
containing the source and destination nodes followed by an inaudible
notice the way we have shown it here
and the node values is not represented
let us simplify the adjacency list representation of it
we remove the colons commas braces and
parenthesis and get a space separated set of lines
one line for each vertex
we further replace the node ids a b c etc with 1 2 3 etc
so that these ids are integers
so what do we need to specify to parse this for giraph
one the graph is a text subject and not let say a database subject
two it is a vertex based representation each line is a vertex
this splitter here is a space
the idea of the node is a first value for each line
the value is a second token
the next pair of items you find an edge with the target and the weight
respectively
and lastly there is a list of these pairs until the end of the line
therefore each line would typically lead to the creation of both notes and
a set of edges
this shows a typical reader formula decency matrix written in java
again you do not have to know java to get the elements of this program
our reader is clearly customized for your specific input
very often the starting point is a basic reader provided by giraph
like the reader that knows how to read vertices from each line of a text swipe
to customize it you extend it and create your own version
now you need to define how to get the id and
value of the vertex by writing separate message for them
notice that the id comes from the zeroth item of each line after
the split by white space and the value comes from the next open
the second term marked by 1 for the 0 base of the light
the next code element is this block here
this specifies how to create edges by iterating through every line
to keep the short we will remove the part that gets the edges here
as giraph as mature it has included many specialized
to interoperate with compatible resources
this diagram is from giraph where the show some of these sources
we can group them into three different categories
group one interoperates with hive and hbase
you possibly remember these systems from a prior course
these systems are designed to give a higher level of data access on
interface on top of mapreduce
group two accesses relational systems like mysql and cassandra
but these systems have accessed indirectly through a software module called gora
gora uses a json schema to map the relation schema of the sql database
to a structure that giraph can read
group three accesses graph databases like neo4j and dex
which is now called sparksee
these systems are all taxes indirectly
using the inaudible service of tinkerpop
which is a graph api layer that can use
many different giraph stores including inaudible graph and titan
consider a relational table stored in hive
the table shown here is extracted from the bio grid data source that
we mentioned in module two
each row of the table represents a molecule interaction
we can create a network from here just by considering the first two columns
the first column represents the source node of an edge colored red
and the second column represents the target node of the edge colored blue
the label on the edge comes from the fifth column of the table
which is a black bold font
let assume that these predict items
these are items that we want to pick up from the hive table
the simplest way to get a record from hive
to giraph is to extend the class called simplehiverowtoedge
for this class we need to specify the source node the target node and
the edge value using three methods as shown here
my extension is called myhiverowtoedge
it shows the implementation of these methods where we just pick up the first
second and fifth columns as we described before
now as mentioned before giraph interacts with neo4j through
the gremlin api provided by tinkerpop
one can think of gremlin as a traversal api which means
it allows one to start from some node and walk the graph step by step
to show this consider disease gene graph on the right
let call this graph g
so g v represents all the vertices of g
therefore g v has name mc4r selects the node that
has a property called name whose value is mc4r
let add to this path the condition out
which chooses the out edges of the mc4r node and
then traverses the associatedwith edge to the orange node called obesity
for this call returns the vertex only
now adding the path to values means gives us obesity
we can also expand differently from the obesity node
when we say inv we refer to all nodes that have
incoming edges to the current node
in this case there is only one
the lepr node
to this we add the traversal out beam and
thus we get back the out going edge from the lepr node highlighted in together
we can also look at the giraph gremlin near project connection
from tinkerpop viewpoint
tinkerpop is trying to create a standard language for graph reversal
just like neo4j is trying to create open cypher as a standard query language for
graph databases
in trying to create the standard tinkerpop recognizes that the actual
storage management for graph databases should be provided by another vendor
the vendor needs to implement the gremlin api for access
similarly for graphic processing including expensive analytic operations
should be performed by what they call a graph computer
this is the role played by giraph as well as spark
both of which interface with tinkerpop
next we will count the number of vertices and edges define a min and
max function for spark reduce method computer the min and max degrees
and compute the histogram data of the degree of connectedness
in this hands on we will cover the degree distribution of
the metros graph from the first hands on exercise
this will help you practice finding the degrees of connectedness in a graph
these numbers will be used for
plotting the visualizations in the next hands on exercises
the degree of a vertex is the number of edges or
connections the vertex has to other vertices in the graph
in directed graphs each vertex has an in degree
the number of edges directed to the vertex
in and out degree the number of edges directed away from the vertex
the metros graph is an example of a directed graph
each metropolis vertex has one outgoing edge to a country vertex
each country vertex has one or more incoming edges from metropolis vertices
this will be a quiz question
starting again where we left off from the previous hands - on exercise first
ensure your cloudera vm is started and
that you downloaded the dataset examples of analytics
the link is in the content for this week
use the numedges attribute to print the number of edges in metrosgraph
as you can see the result is 65
which matches the number of lines in metro country csv
now use the numvertices attribute to print the number
of vertices in metrosgraph
as you can see the result is 93 which matches the number of
lines in metro csv65 plus the number of lines in country csv 28
define the max and the min reduce operation to compute the highest and
lowest degree vertex
let us find the vertex with the most outgoing edges or
the vertex with the largest out degree by passing the max
function to a reduced operation on the out degrees of metrosgraph
the result in this case is vertex id five with one outgoing edge
the result could have been any metropolis because every metropolis in this graph
has one outgoing edge to its country
let us find the vertex with the most incoming edges or
the vertex with the largest indegree
this is done the same way as the previous example
except you will run the reduce operation on the indegrees of metrosgraph
the result is vertexid 108 with 14 incoming edges
apply a filter to the metrosgraph vertices to find out which vertex is 108
the answer is the united states
this means that the united states has 14 metropolises in the metros csvfile
we can also compute how many vertices have one out going edge by applying a filter of
one to the outgoing degrees and counting the results
the result is 65 because there are 65 metropolises with one outgoing degree
none of the countries have any outgoing degrees
let us ignore whether or not the edge is in or out and
just find which vertex has the most edges
again we will run the reduce operation with the max function
but this time we will run it on metrosgraph degrees attribute
the result is 108 again with 14 connections
this means that the united states is the most connected vertex in metrosgraph
finally let us calculate the histogram data of the degrees for
the countries in metrosgraph
first create a map that only includes countries
so create a filter to only include the vertices with the vertex id that is
greater than or equal to 100
then you will group the map by the size of the degree and
sort the map from lowest to highest degree
the output shows six pairs in an array
the first number is the number of edges and
the second number is the number of vertices that have that number of edges
in other words the result of the query shows that there are 18
countries with 1 metropolis 4 countries with 2 metropolises
2 countries with 3 metropolises 2 countries with 5 metropolises
1 country with 9 metropolises and 1 country with 14 metropolises
next we will import the graphx libraries import the vertices import the edges
create a graph and use spark filter method to return vertices in the graph
hi this is cristine kirkpatrick division director for
information technology systems and
services at the san diego super computer center
i will guide you through the hands - on exercises
i recommend you follow along with the video once
then either using the video or
the hands - on reading go through the hands - on exercise on your own computer
this hands - on exercise will show you how to build a graph using graphx
spark api for graphs and graph - parallel computation
we will start with importing the data and then build a simple graph
note that the first four hands on assignments are meant to be completed
sequentially
that is you will need to have your cloudera vm running continuously
if you must shut down your vm and
restart you will need to run the commands from this first hands on assignment again
otherwise you may receive error messages because the data has not been imported
the data references metro areas
in an effort to disambiguate or distinguish between metropolitan areas and
an english word also used to refer to a train or
light rail when we mean metro area we will say metropolis
first ensure your cloudera vm is started and
that you have downloaded the data set examples of analytics
the link is in the content for this week
the download process might name the zip file something very long
copy the examples of analytics zip file to the cloudera home folder
if the zip file is on the desktop
simply drag it to the cloudera home folder on the desktop
if the file is saved elsewhere then you will need to navigate
to the folder where it is saved before dragging it to the cloudera home folder
open the terminal window by clicking the terminal icon at the top of the screen
use the unzip command to extract the zip file to the cloudera home directory
you can copy and paste the name of the zip file
let it extract with the default name examplesofanalytics
go into the examplesofanalytics directory and
list the contents of the eoa data directory
you should see five csv files and one txt file
in order to access the csv and txt files we have to first copy the files to hdfs
rally hdfs foot command to copy the eoa data directory to hdfs
then less the contents of the eoa data directory on hdfs
start the spark shell and include the graph stream and breeze fizz libraries
do not worry about copying the full command from the video
a text version will be included within the course reading that contains the full
command for you to copy and paste
import the log for j classes and suppress the notice in info messages
import sparks graphx and rdd classes along with scala source class
the data set we are going to use in this hands on is from three files
the metro csv file and the country csv file contain the vertices for
the graph and metro underscore country csv
contains the edges that make up the relationships between the metro areas and
the country they belong too
before importing any of the csv files we are going to list the first five lines of
each file to verify that they are indeed csv files
notice that the metric csv contains an id the metropolis name and the population
the country csv file contains only an id and the country name
the metro country csv file contains the metro id and
the id of the country that the metropolis belongs to
create a class called placenode to store the information about the vertices
then extend the placenode class with case classes specifically for
the metro and the countries vertices
create attributes for
the metro class to store the name and the population from the csv file
the country class only needs an attribute to store the name
to import the metro csv file create a spark resilient distributive data set or
rdd named metros made up of a vertex id in the metro class
an rdd represents an immutable partition collection
of elements that can be operated on in parallel
when the contents of the csv files printed
the line with the column names started with the symbol
so create a filter to ignore any line that starts with a so
that the column names do not import into the rdd
the csv files being imported contain values separated by commas
so you will need to split each line in the metro csv file into rows
by using a comma as a delimiter
map the first row to the vertex id
the second row is the metro name attribute and
the third row is the population attribute
you are going to import the country csv feed file the same way as the metro csv
feed file
however this time since the ids in both the metro csv file and the country csv
file start with one you will add 100 to the vertex id of the countries
so that the vertex ids are unique between both data sets
if the ids are not unique that will prevent us from
creating an accurate graph
this will be on the quiz
import the edges into an rdd named mclinks
this is done the same way as the previous two examples
remember to add 100 to the countries vertex id
concatenate the metros and countries vertices into a single variable and
use graphx graph function to create a graph of the metros and
countries vertices with the mc links edges
let us take a look at what is in the graph
use the vertices and edges attributes to print five vertices and
five edges from the metros graph
query the graph to find how the metropolises and
the countries are related
let us find which country tokyo is in
tokyo has a vertex id of 1
use rdd filter method to filter all of the edges in metro graph
that have a source for text id of one and create a map of destination vertex id
the result is 101 which is japan
you can verify this by looking at the metro csv and country csv files
remember we added 100 to the ids in country csv
now let us do the opposite and
find all of the metropolises that are in china which has a vertex id of 103
this time we are going to filter all of the edges in metro graph
that have a vertex id of 103 and create a map of all of the source ids
the result is 3 4 7 24 and 34
you can look in metrostats csv and verify that those metropolises are in china
next we will create a new dataset join two datasets with joinvertices
join two datasets with outerjoinvertices and create a new return type for
the joined vertices
in this hands - on exercise
we will create a new graph made up of five airline flights
the vertices will represent the airports
and the edges will represent the departures and the arrivals
once the graph has been created we will add a second dataset
with additional airport information and
practice using graphx join methods to create new graphs by joining the datasets
we will start a new spark shell session so
we will be opening a new terminal window
open the new terminal window by clicking the terminal icon at the top
of the screen
start the spark shell
import the log for j classes and suppress the notice and info messages
import sparks graphics and rdd classes
now we will create the vertices ourselves from a list
the list will contain the vertex id and the name of the airport
now we will create the edges
the edges will represent a flight departing from one airport and
arriving at another
we will set the edge property to a fake flight number
create the flights graph by joining the vertices and
the edges using graph flexes graph functions
let us explore the graph so far
look through each triplet in flights graph and print the contents of the graph
we will specify which airport the flight departs from
which airport the flight arrives at and the flight number
you will just put all of the vertices in the graph
now we are willing to create an additional dataset to store additional information
about each airport
first we will create a case class called airport information with the city and
airport code properties
then we are going to create the airport information vertices from a list
as we did earlier
we will make sure the vertex id for
the airport information matches the vertex id of the airport defined earlier
note there does not have to be a one to one relationship between the airport
vertices and the airport information vertices
los angeles international airport is present in the airport vertices but
it is missing from the airport information vertices
the airport information vertices contains information about airports in london and
hong kong
but we do not have any flights departing or arriving from those airports
let us complete our first join
a mapping function has to be defined in order to join vertices with graphics join
vertices method
we are going to define a map function that will join the name of the airport from
the airport vertices with the city name from the airport information vertices
in order to create a new graph with the vertices that has the airport name
colon city name
after the map function in defined
then we will use the joined vertices method to create the new graph
vertices without a matching value in the rdd retain their original value
now print out the vertices of the new graph
notice all of the vertices contain the airport and city names
except los angeles international airport which retained its original value
now we will join the vertices using graphx outerjoinvertices method
outerjoinvertices is similar to joinvertices
except that the user - defined map function is applied to all vertices and
it can change the vertex property type
here we are using the outerjoinvertices method to create a new graph where
the vertices contain a property with the name of the airport and
a property makeup of the airport information class
print the vertices once the new graph is made
notice that the type of the second vertex property is sum
this is because los angeles international airport
does not have a corresponding vertex in airport information
therefore graphx assigned all of the properties the sum type so
that all of the vertex property types are the same
we can use the get or
else method to assign a default value if one does not exist
now let us rerun the outer join vertices but
this time use the get get or else method to create an airport
information class with na as the values for the city and the airport code
print the vertices once the new graph is made
now the type of the second vertex property is airport information in
los angeles international airport airport information class
has the properties na and na
finally in this last exercise we will create a new case class called airport
that contains property for the name city and code of the airport
first we will define the new airport case class with the name city and
code properties
then use the outer join vertices method to join the data sets and
create the new graph
create a mapping so if the airport has an airport information vertex the city and
code are taken from the instance of the airport information class
otherwise only include the airport name
finally print the vertices of the new graph
the new graph has only one vertex property which is an instance of the airport class
graphx has lots of methods for joining graph datasets
this hands on example only scratched the surface of graphx power
next we will create a new graph by adding the continents dataset
import the graphstream library
import the countriesgraph into a graphstream singlegraph
visualize the countriesgraph and visualize the facebook graph
in this hands - on exercise we will use the graphstream library
to visualize countries graph
the metros graph that we have been working with in the previous exercises
this time with the continent vertices and edges added
starting again where we left off from the previous hands - on exercise
ensure your inaudible has started and that you have imported the data
first in order to make the graph more interesting
we are going to import additional vertices from the continent csv and
additional edges from country continent csv to create
a relationship between the country and the continent it belongs to
we will show the steps for importing the datasets but
we do not cover the steps in detail
if you are not sure how to import a dataset go back and
view the video called hands - on building a graph
now we are going to concatenate the metros countries and continents vertices
into a single variable and concatenate the metros to countries edges and
countries to continent edges into another single variable
finally you will create a new graph called countriesgraph
now import the graphstream library
we will not go over in detail how to use the graphstream library
you can review its documentation and
other online resources on your own if you are interested
first create a new instance of graphstreams singlegraph class
using the countriesgraph
next we will set some attributes for the graph we are going to visualize
including setting a style for the graph
graphstream uses cascading style sheets or
css just like ordinary web pages to control the appearance of the graph
the zip file that you downloaded from coursera contain the css file that we will
use in this hands - on exercise
now load the countries graph vertices into the visualization
using graphstreams add node method
notice that we are setting the style ui class of each vertex
depending on if the vertex is an instance of the metro country or continent class
add the edges of country graph to the visualization using graphstreams
add edge method
finally call the display method to visualize the graph
the graph will look similar to this
the small blue dots are the metropolises the medium sized red dots
are the countries and the large green dots are the continents
by looking at the clusters you can easily identify which
continent in the visualization is antarctica
it is the green dot that has no connections or
it is the least connected cluster in the network
i hope your paying attention because this will be on the quiz
the large cluster of dots at the bottom is asia because it has the most countries and
metropolises in the graph
the asia cluster is the most connected cluster in the network
can you identify which clusters are the other continents
by looking at the visualization
let look at the visualization of a much larger dataset
the facebook dataset with 90 000 vertices
you have seen these techniques before with the metro dataset but
that graph had only around 90 vertices
because we want you to learn the concepts not be bogged down with repetitive tasks
we have supplied this cloudera file in order to create the visualization of the graph
all you need to do is open a new terminal window
go into the examples of analytic directory and
run the spark shell with the facebook cloudera file
do not worry about copying the full command from the video
a text version will be included within the course reading
that contains the full command for you to copy and paste
what do you see
my first reaction is that it looks like broccoli
a green vegetable reviled by many american children unjustly
social networks are made up of several clusters of communities or
pockets of people who interact densely
that are brought together by people who are members of multiple communities
this interlinking of clusters gives the social network
a broccoli like shape when visualized
i hope you heard the last thing i said because that will be on the quiz
next we will import the breezeviz library define a function to calculate the degree
histogram calculate the probability distribution for the degree histogram and
graph the results
in this hands on exercise we will plot the degree histogram created
in the previous hands on exercise using the breezeviz library
starting again where we left off in the previous hands - on exercise
ensure your is started
first we will import the breezeviz library
next we will define a function to calculate the degree histogram of metro
graph so we can plot it with breezeviz
the definition of the degree histogram function is nearly identical
to the code from the previous exercise that helped us create
the histogram data array
now we will calculate the probability distribution of the vertex degrees over
the whole graph by normalizing the vertex degree by the total number of vertices so
that the degree probabilities add up to 1
the output of the first command is 28 the number of countries in country csv
the output of the second command is an array of numbered pairs
the first number is the vertex degree
and the second number is the probability distribution
notice that the sum of all the probability distributions equals one
now we will plot two graphs to visualize the degree histogram
the first graph will be a line graph of the degree histogram and
the second will be the degree histogram itself
we will not go over in detail how to use the breezeviz library to create graphs
the project is well documented and there are many resources online if you want to
explore the breezeviz library on your own
for the first graph we will define the x axis as the vertex degree and
the y axis as the degree probability
for the second graph we will just pass the metro graph
degree attribute to breezeviz histogram function
you should see two graphical representations of the data
the bottom one is the histogram
the top shows the degrees distribution plotting the histogram
as we saw in the previous exercise array most countries have one metropolis
welcome back to the fourth and final module of the course
in this module we will cover the underlying principles of large scale graph processing
and the software infrastructure that supports it
so in this module you will learn a programming model for
graph computation and systems that implement this model
after this model you will be able to formulate graph analytics computations
in terms of the programming model
this module will consist of three lessons
the first lesson will revisit the concept of the programming model and
introduce a programming model called bulk synchronous parallel or
bsp that is designed specifically for graph oriented computation
i will discuss two well known versions of the central idea pregel from google and
graphlab from carnegie mellon university
the second lesson we will discuss two software systems
giraph that operates on hadoop and graphx that operates on spark
we will compare the basic architecture of these two systems and
point out their differences
the final lesson will show example computations using graphics platform
since graphics come with spark
we have created these examples on the virtual machine which you have access to
the code and some data sets are available for
those who wish to play with the system
now we are going to introduce you to graphx
which we will primarily cover as a hands - on presentation
graphx was developed by the amp lab at uc berkeley and
has now become an apache product
in this brief introduction we are using a few slides from amp lab presentations
like inaudible graphic uses a property graph model
that means both nodes and edges can have attributes and values
in graphx the node properties are stored in a vertex table
and edge properties are stored in an edge table
the connectivity information that is which edge connects to which nodes
is stored separately from the nodes and edge properties
since graphx is based on spark
whose central information representation is based on resilient data sets or rdds
you may recall that rdds are typically in memory information objects
these objects can be used to perform an action which returns a value
or they can perform a transformation which can produce another rdd
graphx is built on special rdds for vertices and edges
note that vertexids are defined to be unique by design
vertexrdd a represents a set of vertices all of which have an attribute called a
the edge class is an object with a source vertex a destination vertex and
edge attribute
the edgerdd extends this basic edge by storing
edges in a columnar format on each partition of performance
very often it easier to operate on a data structure that has both
node properties and edge properties
if you are familiar with this schema you will readily see that this is a three - way
join operation between the node set the edge set and the second node set
finally graphx implements it own version of bsp
this implementation not surprisingly is called pregel
it allows a user to write a vertex program a send message routine
and a message combiner routine just like bsp
however this implementation also performs
vertex partitioning like we saw in graph lab
also similarly to graph lab
it enables the message sending computation to reach the attributes of both vertices
the code limit shown here is written in scala
the hands on code after this you will see are all certain in scatter
will have a notice here in no scatter
we would like to show you here an example which uses
the pregel runtime object in graphx to implement the simple bsp desk
we would like to show here how pregel runtime objects in graphx works
we point out all the functions that are defined by users
in running the pregel operation
the vprogf function which takes a vertex and a message and
returns a new attribute value for that vertex
the sendmsgr function which computes the new message along each edge
the option m construct says that it is optional for a vertex to send the message
that is the system should not show an error
if your message is not sent for the vertex
the combinef function is a message combiner that we
mention in passive for graph
finally the user can also specify the number of reiterations that
the graphx bsp process will run for
in 2010 google
published a paper outlining a system that they had been working on
this publication about a system called pregel has been one of the most
influential publications on large scale graph computing
the pregel system essentially implemented the bsb model that we covered in
the last lecture
to show how the pregel system is programmed
we present the published code of google most famous algorithm the pagerank
recall that pagerank task is to compute note centrality
the basic philosophy of pagerank is that a note that is connected to an more
important note gains more importance
in the filler on the right b is a very important node with a high page rank
because a lot of other nodes directly or indirectly point to it
so c being his direct neighbor that receives an edge from b
also has a high page rank
all the c itself there not have too many incident edges
on the left side we have google published c + + code
that implements pagerank method on the pregel infrastructure
you do not have to know c + + to understand the basic essence of the code
we will explain the basic elements of the vertex program in the next few slides
remember from the last lecture that the vsp technique considers
a vertex to be a process
every vertex implements a method called compute
this method implements the logic of what a vertex should do during the super steps
the program starts by creating a special kind of vertex called the pagerank vertex
for which this compute method is specified
you will notice that the compute method starts by saying what happens
when the super step is one or more
but what happens in super step zero
usually superstep 0 is used for initialization
every vertex initialization pagerank value to a same number
which is one divided by the total number of vertices in the graph
computationally a pagerank of a vertex is a number calculated by adding two terms
the first term depends on the total number of vertices in the graph and
is therefore the same every time
and the second term depends on the page rank of the neighbors of the vertex
how does the vertex compute the second term
it gets the pagerank values of the neighbors in its messages
and adds them up
as we saw for sssp after a vertex computes its value
it goes to the propagate step and sends a message to its outgoing edges
for pagerank the message it sends out
is just computed value divided by the number of outgoing edges
when this is done the node halts for the next superstep and waits for
some other node to wake it up
at this point we have seen two examples of graph analytic operations
executed on the bsb programming model
now we will look at the same problem from a slightly different viewpoint
graphlab originally a project from carnegie mellon university now turned
into a company called dato took a similar yet different approach to the problem
in graphlab any kind of data can be associated with a vertex or an edge
this information is stored in what is called a data graph
let look at the same page like i already did
the syntax is a bit different but the logical blocks are identical
these are the same blocks that we highlighted before
graphlab breaks up these blocks into three different user specified functions
called gather apply scatter or gas for short
okay so what is different
let mention a few important differences
first let consider gather
rather than adopting a message passing or data flow model like pregel
graphlab allows the user defined update function complete freedom to read and
modify any of the data on adjacent vertices edges
in graphlab a receiving vertex has access to the data on adjacent vertices
even if the adjacent vertices did not schedule the current update
in contrast for pregel the control is with descending nodes
an update can happen only when a node sends out messages
for some graph analytics operations like a dynamic version of pagerank
this is very important
further if vertex can update its value asynchronously
that is as soon as it receives an update without having to wait for
all nodes like we do in vsp
this often helps some intuitive algorithms like page rank converge faster
when the graph is large and must be split across machines
bsp cuts the graph along edges as we see on this slide
so every cut edge results in a machine to machine communication
if we increase the number of across machine edges
we increase communication cost
this has an interesting practical consequence
as we have mentioned many graph applications have communities
and central nodes that have high degree
many young people today have over 500 facebook friends
so when an analytical operation like page rank
that goes through multiple iterations until convergence for
these graphs the communication cost can become very high
in the cluster graph shown here every color represents a different machine
let look at that red vertex
what would happen if we split it like this instead
the red node gets split
and different vertices of different machines work with their own copy
of the red vertex
in the diagram the primary red vertex is marked zero and
copies are marked one through five
now the gather phase happens for each copy
followed by a second operation from the copies to the primary red vertex
and this is followed by new user defined operation called merge
that combines the partial results from the copies to the primary vertex
so for pagerank the merge operation boils down to computing the total
summation of the partial summation of the edges computed at the copies
thus in this lesson we have seen two of the most influential
paradigms of large scale graph computation when the number of nodes and
edges run into tens of millions and more